<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <race>
    <name>Fairy (Legacy)</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>The Feywild is home to many fantastic peoples, including fairies. Fairies are a wee folk, but not nearly as much so as their pixie and sprite friends. The first fairies spoke Elvish, Goblin, or Sylvan, and encounters with human visitors prompted many of them to learn Common as well.

Source:	The Wild Beyond The Witchlight p. 12</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Fey Characteristics</name>
      <text>Infused with the magic of the Feywild, fairies share a few commonalities with one another but can differ widely in appearance, behavior, and attitude. Many fairies have a special physical characteristic that sets them apart from other creatures of their kind. For your fairy, roll on the Fey Characteristic table or choose an option from it. The Feywild is a wild place, so come up with your own characteristic if none of these fit your character.

Fey Characteristics:
d8 | Characteristic
1 | Your wings are like those of a bird.
2 | You have shimmering, multicolored skin.
3 | You have exceptionally large ears.
4 | A glittering mist constantly surrounds you.
5 | You have a small spectral horn on your forehead, like a little unicorn horn.
6 | Your legs are insectile.
7 | You smell like fresh brownies.
8 | A noticeable, harmless chill surrounds you</text>
      <roll description="Characteristic">1d8</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different score by 1, or increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Fairies have a life span of about a century.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Fairies can be of any alignment but tend to lean more towards chaotic because of their playful trickster nature.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>You are Small.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Creature Type</name>
      <text>You are a Fey</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Fairy Magic</name>
      <text>You know the Druidcraft cantrip.
	Starting at 3rd level, you can cast the Faerie Fire spell with this trait. Starting at 5th level, you can also cast the Enlarge/Reduce spell with this trait. Once you cast Faerie Fire or Enlarge/Reduce with this trait, you can't cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast either of those spells using any spell slots you have of the appropriate level.
	Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells when you cast them with this trait. (choose when you select this race)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Flight</name>
      <text>Because of your wings, you have a flying speed equal to your walking speed. You can't use this flying speed if you're wearing medium or heavy armor.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and one other language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for the character.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Harengon (Legacy)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <proficiency>Perception</proficiency>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Harengons originated in the Feywild, where they spoke Sylvan and embodied the spirit of freedom and travel. In time, these rabbitfolk hopped into other worlds, bringing the fey realm's exuberance with them and learning new languages as they went.
	Harengons are bipedal, with the characteristic long feet of the rabbits they resemble and fur in a variety of colors. They share the keen senses and powerful legs of leporine creatures and are full of energy, like a wound-up spring. Harengons are blessed with a little fey luck, and they often find themselves a few fortunate feet away from dangers during adventures.

Source:	The Wild Beyond The Witchlight p. 13</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different score by 1, or increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Harengons have a life span of about a century.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Fairies can be of any alignment but tend to lean more towards chaotic because of their playful trickster nature.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>You are Medium or Small. You choose the size when you select this race.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Hare-Trigger</name>
      <text>You can add your proficiency bonus to your initiative rolls.</text>
      <modifier category="bonus">initiative +%0</modifier>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Leporine Senses</name>
      <text>You have proficiency in the Perception skill</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Lucky Footwork</name>
      <text>When you fail a Dexterity saving throw, you can use your reaction to roll a d4 and add it to the save, potentially turning the failure into a success. You can't use this reaction if you're prone or your speed is 0.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Rabbit Hop</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, you can jump a number of feet equal to five times your proficiency bonus, without provoking opportunity attacks. You can use this trait only if your speed is greater than 0. You can use it a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and one other language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for the character.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
</compendium>
