<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <item>
    <name>Chime of Exile</name>
    <detail>very rare</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This silver chime is engraved with delicate magic sigils. While holding the chime, you can use an action to cast the Banishment spell (spell save DC 20). If the target of the spell has 50 hit points or fewer, it automatically fails its saving throw. Once the chime has been used to cast the spell, it can't be used this way again until the next dawn.

Source:	Vecna: Eve of Ruin p. 46</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Crown of Lies</name>
    <detail>artifact (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>After betraying and nearly destroying the lich Vecna, the warrior Kas found himself trapped in the Shadowfell, imprisoned in a Domain of Dread called Tovag. There, he languished as a vampire. In time, the Dark Powers of the Domain of Dread lured Kas to a hidden forge, where he found the Crown of Lies. Once Kas vowed to deliver Vecna into the Dark Powers' clutches and donned the crown, the Dark Powers released Kas. From there, Kas set out to ruin his former master. Should Kas fail, the Dark Powers will reclaim him.
	The crown is made of burnished and entwined metal rods. To attune to it, you must place it on your head and speak a true desire of your heart. You know how to attune to the crown when you touch it.

Random Properties: The Crown of Lies has the following random properties (see the Dungeon Master's Guide for options):

	• 1 minor beneficial property
	• 1 major beneficial property
	• 1 minor detrimental property

Perfect Disguise: While attuned to the crown, you can use an action to transform yourself to look and feel like any creature you've seen at least once and whose size is no more than one size smaller or larger than yours.
	The new form mimics the chosen creature's appearance exactly, including its voice. Your size and speed are replaced by the chosen creature's. You otherwise retain your own game statistics. While in this new form, the crown melds into your person and is undetectable.
	Your new form lasts until you die, your attunement to the crown ends, or you use another action to transform into a different creature or your true form. Interactions with you while you are transformed by the crown reveal no illusory magic, nor do they reveal anything other than details about the creature you're disguised as. You count as the chosen creature for the purposes of spells, traps, and other defenses that wouldn't target the chosen creature.
	While in your disguised form, any lies you tell always seem to be true, no matter what magical or mundane methods are used to try to detect your falsehoods. You are the recipient of Sending spells addressed to you and the creature you are disguised as, and Scrying and similar spells that target the creature you are disguised as actually target you. The only way to reveal your true nature while transformed by the crown is with a Wish spell.
	While wearing this crown in your true form, you can choose for the crown to be visible if you wish.

Destroying the Crown: If a creature wearing the crown is killed by the creature it is disguised as, the crown disintegrates and is destroyed.

Source:	Vecna: Eve of Ruin p. 6</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Rod of Seven Parts</name>
    <detail>artifact (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>RD</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <weight>4</weight>
    <text>Eons ago, a war between the primordials and the gods scarred the planes of existence. A demon lord named Miska the Wolf-Spider eventually pushed the primordials' enemies to the brink of annihilation.

Desperate to save themselves and their allies, powerful elemental beings called the Wind Dukes of Aaqa rose against Miska. Committed to the concept of law, the Wind Dukes descended from a people called the vaati, who once ruled many worlds. Seven Wind Dukes wove their power into an artifact called the Rod of Law. The dukes used the rod to imprison Miska on the plane of Pandemonium. As a result, the rod shattered into seven parts that were scattered throughout the multiverse. The rod thus became known as the Rod of Seven Parts.

Possessing the Broken Rod: The rod can't be attuned to while it is broken. While holding one piece of the broken rod, you know the general location of the next consecutive piece, as the rod yearns to be a complete artifact. Multiple rod pieces can be assembled into one piece or disassembled again, each requiring an action, although a partially complete rod doesn't gain any other abilities.
	Additionally, while holding one piece of the broken rod, you can use an action to cast the spell associated with that piece, as listed on the Rod Pieces table. Once that piece of the rod has been used to cast a spell, it can't be used that way again until the next dawn.

Rod Pieces:
Piece | Spell
First | Commune
Second | Arcane Gate
Third | Reverse Gravity (spell save DC 18)
Fourth | Regenerate
Fifth | Find the Path
Sixth | Mirage Arcane
Seventh | Simulacrum

Possessing the Whole Rod: Once all seven pieces are reassembled, a creature can attune to the Rod of Seven Parts. While attuned to the rod, you gain the following benefits:

Magic Weapon: The Rod of Seven Parts functions for you as a magic quarterstaff that grants a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with it.

Rod Spellcasting: The Rod of Seven Parts has 7 charges and regains 1d4 + 3 expended charges daily at dawn. While holding the rod, you can use an action to expend 1 charge and cast any of the spells in the Rod Pieces table. You can also use an action to cast Detect Evil and Good from the rod without using any charges.

Ultimate Law: If you are not of a lawful alignment, you find your worldview shifting toward keeping a personal code. You are more apt to keep your promises, follow through on your declarations, and adhere to your beliefs.

Destroying the Rod: The only way to destroy the Rod of Seven Parts is to immerse the assembled rod in lava in the Abyss. It must remain in the lava for fifty years before it finally is consumed.
	A piece of the rod may be temporarily destroyed in this way, but each piece re-forms one year after it has succumbed. A re-formed piece teleports to a random place in the multiverse.

Source:	Vecna: Eve of Ruin p. 8</text>
  </item>
</compendium>
