<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Rogue</name>
    <!-- Roguish Archetype: Swashbuckler (UA) -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Roguish Archetype: Swashbuckler (UA)</name>
        <text>You focus your training on the art of the blade, relying on speed, elegance, and charisma in equal parts. While other warriors are brutes clad in heavy armor, your method of fighting looks more like performance. Rakes, duelists, and pirates typically follow this archetype.
	A swashbuckler excels in single combat, and can fight with two weapons while safely darting away from an opponent. Swashbucklers are especially talented at making difficult maneuvers to escape enemies or attack from an unexpected direction.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 3</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Fancy Footwork (Swashbuckler (UA))</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you are a continuous blur of motion in battle as you dart in, attack, and slip away to safety. During your turn, if you make a melee attack against a creature, that creature cannot make opportunity attacks against you for the rest of your turn.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 3</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Toujours l'Audace (Swashbuckler (UA))</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, your unmistakable confidence propels you into battle. You add your Charisma modifier to your initiative rolls.
	In addition, you can use Sneak Attack with any melee attack made against a target that has none of your allies adjacent to it.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 3</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Panache (Swashbuckler (UA))</name>
        <text>At 9th level, your charm becomes as sharp and dangerous as your blade. As an action, you can make a Charisma (Persuasion) check contested by a creature's Wisdom (Insight) check. The creature must be able to hear you, and the two of you must share a language.
	If you succeed on the check and the creature is hostile, it must target you with any attacks it makes and cannot willingly move farther away from you. This effect lasts for 1 minute or until you move more than 60 feet away from the target.
	If you succeed on the check and the creature is not hostile, it is charmed by you for 1 minute. While charmed, it regards you as a friendly acquaintance.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 3</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Elegant Maneuver (Swashbuckler (UA))</name>
        <text>You complete difficult maneuvers with practiced ease. Starting at 13th level, you can use a bonus action to gain advantage on the next Dexterity (Acrobatics) or Strength (Athletics) check you make on your turn.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 3</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Master Duelist (Swashbuckler (UA))</name>
        <text>At 17th level your mastery of the blade lets you turn failure to success in combat. If you miss with an attack, you can choose to roll the attack again with advantage. Once you use this ability, you cannot use it again until you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 3</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
