<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <race>
    <name>Tiefling, Abyssal (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Cha +2, Con +1</ability>
    <spellAbility>Charisma</spellAbility>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>To be greeted with stares and whispers, to suffer violence and insult on the street, to see mistrust and fear in every eye: this is the lot of the tiefling. And to twist the knife, tieflings know that this is because a pact struck generations ago infused the essence of Asmodeus, overlord of the Nine Hells (and many of the other powerful devils serving under him) into their bloodline. Their appearance and their nature are not their fault but the result of an ancient sin, for which they and their children and their children's children will always be held accountable.

All abyssal tieflings trace their bloodline to the demons of the Abyss.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 43,
		Unearthed Arcana 11: That Old Black Magic p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Tieflings mature at the same rate as humans but live a few years longer.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Tieflings might not have an innate tendency toward evil, but many of them end up there. Evil or not, an independent nature inclines many tieflings toward a chaotic alignment.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Tieflings are about the same size and build as humans. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 4 feet + 9 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 110 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Thanks to your abyssal heritage, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Hellish Resistance</name>
      <text>You have resistance to fire damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Abyssal Arcana</name>
      <text>Each time you finish a long rest, you gain the ability to cast cantrips and spells randomly determined from a short list. At 1st level, you can cast a cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can also cast a 1st-level spell. At 5th level, you can cast a 2nd-level spell.
	You can cast a spell gained from this trait only once until you complete your next long rest. You can cast a cantrip gained from this trait at will, as normal. For 1st-level spells whose effect changes if cast using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, you cast the spell as if using a 2nd-level slot. Spells of 2nd level are cast as if using a 2nd-level slot.
	At the end of each long rest, you lose the cantrips and spells previously granted by this feature, even if you did not cast them. You replace those cantrips and spells by rolling for new ones on the Abyssal Arcana Spells table. Roll separately for each cantrip and spell. If you roll the same spell or cantrip you gained at the end of your previous long rest, roll again until you get a different result.

Abyssal Arcana Spells:
d6 | 1st Level | 3rd Level | 5th Level
1 | Dancing Lights | Burning Hands | Alter Self
2 | True Strike | Charm Person | Darkness
3 | Light | Magic Missile | Invisibility
4 | Message | Cure Wounds | Levitate
5 | Spare the Dying | Tasha's Hideous Laughter | Mirror Image
6 | Prestidigitation | Thunderwave | Spider Climb</text>
      <roll description="1st">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Abyssal Fortitude</name>
      <text>Your hit point maximum increases by half your level (minimum 1).</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Variant: Appearance</name>
      <text>Your tiefling might not look like other tieflings. Rather than having the physical characteristics described in the Player's Handbook, choose 1d4 + 1 of the following features:

Small horns;
Fangs or sharp teeth;
A forked tongue;
Catlike eye;
Six fingers on each hand;
Goatlike legs;
Cloven hoofs;
A forked tail;
Leathery or scaly skin;
Red or dark blue skin;
Cast no shadow or reflection;
Exude a smell of brimstone.</text>
      <roll description="Appearance">1d4+1</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Infernal.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Tiefling, Infernal (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Cha +2, Int +1</ability>
    <spellAbility>Charisma</spellAbility>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>To be greeted with stares and whispers, to suffer violence and insult on the street, to see mistrust and fear in every eye: this is the lot of the tiefling. And to twist the knife, tieflings know that this is because a pact struck generations ago infused the essence of Asmodeus, overlord of the Nine Hells (and many of the other powerful devils serving under him) into their bloodline. Their appearance and their nature are not their fault but the result of an ancient sin, for which they and their children and their children's children will always be held accountable.

An infernal tiefling draws upon the power of the Nine Hells and its diabolic masters.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 43,
		Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 118,
		Unearthed Arcana: That Old Black Magic p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Tieflings mature at the same rate as humans but live a few years longer.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Tieflings might not have an innate tendency toward evil, but many of them end up there. Evil or not, an independent nature inclines many tieflings toward a chaotic alignment.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Tieflings are about the same size and build as humans. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 4 feet + 9 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 110 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Height Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Thanks to your infernal heritage, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Hellish Resistance</name>
      <text>You have resistance to fire damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Infernal Legacy</name>
      <text>You know the thaumaturgy cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the hellish rebuke spell as a 2nd-level spell once with this trait and regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest. When you reach 5th level, you can cast the darkness spell once with this trait and regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Variant: Appearance</name>
      <text>Your tiefling might not look like other tieflings. Rather than having the physical characteristics described in the Player's Handbook, choose 1d4 + 1 of the following features:

Small horns;
Fangs or sharp teeth;
A forked tongue;
Catlike eye;
Six fingers on each hand;
Goatlike legs;
Cloven hoofs;
A forked tail;
Leathery or scaly skin;
Red or dark blue skin;
Cast no shadow or reflection;
Exude a smell of brimstone.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Variant: Devil's Tongue</name>
      <text>You know the vicious mockery cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the charm person spell as a 2nd-level spell once with this trait. When you reach 5th level, you can cast the enthrall spell once with this trait. You must finish a long rest to cast these spells once again with this trait. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for them. This trait replaces the Infernal Legacy trait.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Variant: Hellfire</name>
      <text>Once you reach 3rd level, you can cast the burning hands spell once as a 2nd-level spell. This trait replaces the hellish rebuke spell of the Infernal Legacy trait.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Variant: Winged</name>
      <text>You have bat-like wings sprouting from your shoulder blades. You have a flying speed of 30 feet while you aren't wearing heavy armor. This replaces the Infernal Legacy trait.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Infernal.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
</compendium>
