<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <feat>
    <name>Gift of the Chromatic Dragon</name>
    <text>You've manifested some of the power of chromatic dragons, granting you the following benefits:

Chromatic Infusion: As a bonus action, you can touch a simple or martial weapon and infuse it with one of the following damage types: acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison. For the next minute, the weapon deals an extra 1d4 damage of the chosen type when it hits. After you use this bonus action, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest.

Reactive Resistance: When you take acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison damage, you can use your reaction to give yourself resistance to that instance of damage. You can use this reaction a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 17</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Gift of the Gem Dragon (Charisma)</name>
    <text>You've manifested some of the power of gem dragons, granting you the following benefits:

Ability Score Increase: Increase your Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20.

Telekinetic Reprisal: When you take damage from a creature that is within 10 feet of you, you can use your reaction to emanate telekinetic energy. The creature that dealt damage to you must make a Strength saving throw (DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + Charisma). On a failed save, the creature takes 2d8 force damage and is pushed up to 10 feet away from you. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage and isn't pushed. You can use this reaction a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 17</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">charisma +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Gift of the Gem Dragon (Intelligence)</name>
    <text>You've manifested some of the power of gem dragons, granting you the following benefits:

Ability Score Increase: Increase your Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20.

Telekinetic Reprisal: When you take damage from a creature that is within 10 feet of you, you can use your reaction to emanate telekinetic energy. The creature that dealt damage to you must make a Strength saving throw (DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + Intelligence). On a failed save, the creature takes 2d8 force damage and is pushed up to 10 feet away from you. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage and isn't pushed. You can use this reaction a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 17</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">intelligence +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Gift of the Gem Dragon (Wisdom)</name>
    <text>You've manifested some of the power of gem dragons, granting you the following benefits:

Ability Score Increase: Increase your Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20.

Telekinetic Reprisal: When you take damage from a creature that is within 10 feet of you, you can use your reaction to emanate telekinetic energy. The creature that dealt damage to you must make a Strength saving throw (DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + Wisdom). On a failed save, the creature takes 2d8 force damage and is pushed up to 10 feet away from you. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage and isn't pushed. You can use this reaction a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 17</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">wisdom +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Gift of the Metallic Dragon</name>
    <text>You've manifested some of the power of metallic dragons, granting you the following benefits:

Draconic Healing: You learn the cure wounds spell. You can cast this spell without expending a spell slot. Once you cast this spell in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast this spell using spell slots you have. The spell's spellcasting ability is Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma when you cast it with this feat (choose when you gain the feat).

Protective Wings: You can manifest protective wings that can shield you or others. When you or another creature you can see within 5 feet of you is hit by an attack roll, you can use your reaction to manifest spectral wings from your back for a moment. You grant a bonus to the target's AC equal to your proficiency bonus against that attack roll, potentially causing it to miss. You can use this reaction a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 17</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Draconic Gift: Draconic Familiar</name>
    <prerequisite>Wyrmling Dragon Heir or Killer (Uncommon)</prerequisite>
    <text>You gain the aid of a draconic familiar, which might be a splinter of the consciousness of a dragon that invested you with power.
	You can cast the find familiar spell as a ritual without using any material components. When you cast the spell in this way, your familiar always takes the form of a pseudodragon.
	Additionally, when you take the Attack action on your turn, you can forgo one of your own attacks to allow your pseudodragon familiar to make one attack of its own with its reaction.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 28</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Draconic Gift: Draconic Rebirth</name>
    <prerequisite>Wyrmling Dragon Heir or Killer (Uncommon)</prerequisite>
    <text>You become a dragonborn. You replace the racial traits of your original race with the traits of a chromatic, gem, or metallic dragonborn (detailed in this book). The kind of dragonborn you become matches the family of the dragon that is the source of this gift. You can keep any skill proficiencies you gained from your previous race, or you gain proficiency in two skills of your choice.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 28</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Draconic Gift: Draconic Senses</name>
    <prerequisite>Young Dragon Heir or Killer (Rare)</prerequisite>
    <text>You gain keen senses like a dragon's.

Blindsight: You have blindsight to a range of 10 feet. Within that range, you can effectively see anything that isn't behind total cover, even if you're blinded or in darkness. Moreover, you can see invisible creatures within that range, unless the creatures successfully hide from you.

Keen Senses: You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 28</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Draconic Gift: Echo of Dragonsight</name>
    <prerequisite>Adult Dragon Heir or Killer (Very Rare)</prerequisite>
    <text>You have begun to extend your awareness beyond the single world of the Material Plane that is your home.
	You can cast contact other plane as a ritual. The entity you contact is a dragon on another world in the Material Plane, so its knowledge of your world might be limited. Also, this dragon is an echo of the dragon who is the source of the gift, which might affect its attitude and behavior toward you.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 28</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Draconic Gift: Frightful Presence</name>
    <prerequisite>Adult Dragon Heir or Killer (Very Rare)</prerequisite>
    <text>Echoes of a dragon's might linger around you. and you can call on them to inspire fear in those who stand against you.
	As a bonus action, you can manifest your frightful presence. Each creature of your choice that is within 120 feet of you and aware of you must make a Wisdom saving throw against a DC equal to 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Charisma modifier. A creature that fails becomes frightened of you for 1 minute. The creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.
	Once you use this ability a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 28</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Draconic Gift: Psionic Reach</name>
    <prerequisite>Adult Dragon Heir or Killer (Very Rare)</prerequisite>
    <text>The psionic energy of a gem dragon empowers your mind. You gain resistance to psychic damage.
	In addition, you learn the telekinesis spell. You can cast this spell without expending a spell slot. Once you cast this spell in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast this spell using spell slots you have of the appropriate level. The spellcasting ability is Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma when you cast the spell with this gift (choose when you gain the gift).

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 28</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Draconic Gift: Scaled Toughness</name>
    <prerequisite>Ancient Dragon Heir or Killer (Legendary)</prerequisite>
    <text>Your skin toughens, making you resistant to certain types of physical harm. You gain resistance to piercing and slashing damage.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 29</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Draconic Gift: Tongue of the Dragon</name>
    <prerequisite>Wyrmling Dragon Heir or Killer (Uncommon)</prerequisite>
    <text>You gain some of the majestic presence of a dragon.

Dragon's Speech: You can speak, read, and write Draconic.

Dragon's Voice: As a bonus action, you can make your voice audible up to 300 feet away for 1 minute.

Dragon's Wiles: You have advantage on Charisma (Persuasion) checks.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 29</text>
  </feat>
</compendium>
