<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <item>
    <name>Amethyst Lodestone</name>
    <detail>very rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This fist-sized chunk of amethyst is infused with an amethyst dragon's ability to bend gravitational forces. While you are carrying the lodestone, you have advantage on Strength saving throws.
	The lodestone has 6 charges for the following properties, which you can use while you are holding the stone. The stone regains 1d6 expended charges daily at dawn.

Flight: As a bonus action, you can expend 1 charge to gain the power of flight for 10 minutes. For the duration, you gain a flying speed equal to your walking speed, and you can hover.

Gravitational Thrust: As an action, you can expend 1 charge to focus gravity around a creature you can see within 60 feet of you. The target must succeed on a DC 18 Strength saving throw or be pushed up to 20 feet in a direction of your choice.

Reverse Gravity: As an action, you can expend 3 charges to cast reverse gravity from the stone (save DC 18).

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 22</text>
    <roll>1d6</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Dragon Vessel</name>
    <detail>varies (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This vessel can be a potion bottle, drinking horn, or other container meant to hold a liquid.

Slumbering (Uncommon): As a bonus action, if the vessel is empty, you can speak the command word to fill the vessel with one of the following (your choice): ale, olive oil, a potion of healing, or a potion of climbing. Once this property is used, it can't be used until the next dawn. A potion you create in this way loses its magical properties if it isn't imbibed within 24 hours.

Stirring (Rare): In addition to the options for a Slumbering vessel, you can fill a Stirring vessel with mead, a potion of fire breath, or a potion of healing (greater).

Wakened (Very Rare): In addition to the options for a Slumbering or Stirring vessel, you can fill a Wakened vessel with wine, a potion of flying, or a potion of healing (superior).

Ascendant (Legendary): In addition to the options for other states, you can fill an Ascendant vessel with whiskey, a potion of healing (supreme), or a potion of dragon's majesty.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 27</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Dragon-Touched Focus</name>
    <detail>spellcasting focus, varies (requires attunement by a spellcaster)</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This wondrous item can be a scepter, an orb, an amulet, a crystal, or another finely crafted object. It typically incorporates imagery of dragons' wings, claws, teeth, or scales.

Slumbering (Uncommon): You have advantage on initiative rolls. While you are holding the focus, it can function as a spellcasting focus for all your spells.

Stirring (Rare): The Stirring focus has the Slumbering property, and it gains an additional property determined by the family of the dragon in whose hoard it became Stirring:

	• Chromatic: Whenever you use a spell slot to cast a spell that deals acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison damage, roll a d6, and you gain a bonus equal to the number rolled to one of the spell's damage rolls.

	• Gem: Whenever you use a spell slot to cast a spell, you can immediately teleport to an unoccupied space you can see within 15 feet of you.

	• Metallic: When a creature you can see within 30 feet of you makes a saving throw, you can use your reaction to give that creature advantage on the saving throw.

Wakened (Very Rare): The Wakened focus has the Slumbering and Stirring properties, and while you are holding a Wakened focus, you can use it to cast certain spells. Once the item is used to cast a given spell, it can't be used to cast that spell again until the next dawn. The spells are determined by the family of the dragon in whose hoard it became Wakened. An asterisk indicates a new spell that appears earlier in this chapter.

	• Chromatic: Hold monster, Rime's binding ice*
	• Gem: Rary's telepathic bond, Raulothim's psychic lance*
	• Metallic: Fizban's platinum shield,* legend lore

Ascendant (Legendary): The Ascendant focus has the Slumbering, Stirring, and Wakened properties. In addition, when you cast a spell of 1st level or higher while holding this focus, you can treat the spell as if it were cast using a 9th-level spell slot. Once this property is used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.

Arcane Focus: An arcane focus is a special item designed to channel the power of arcane spells. A sorcerer, warlock, or wizard can use such an item as a spellcasting focus.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 26</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Dragonhide Belt</name>
    <detail>varies (requires attunement by a monk)</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This finely detailed belt is made of dragonhide. While wearing it, you gain a bonus to the saving throw DCs of your ki features. The bonus is determined by the belt's rarity.
	In addition, you can use an action to regain ki points equal to a roll of your Martial Arts die. You can't use this action again until the next dawn.

Rarity | Bonus
Uncommon | +1
Rare | +2
Very Rare | +3

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 23</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Emerald Pen</name>
    <detail>uncommon</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This pen is tipped with an emerald nib and requires no ink to write. While holding this pen, you can cast illusory script at will, requiring no material components.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 23</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Flail of Tiamat</name>
    <detail>legendary (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>M</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <weight>2</weight>
    <property>M</property>
    <dmg1>1d8</dmg1>
    <dmgType>B</dmgType>
    <text>This magic flail is made in the image of Tiamat, with five jagged heads shaped like the heads of five different chromatic dragons. You gain a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with this flail. When you hit with an attack roll using it, the target takes an extra 5d4 damage of your choice of one of the following damage types: acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison.
	While holding the flail, you can use an action and speak a command word to cause the heads to breathe multicolored flames in a 90-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, it takes 14d6 damage of one of the following damage types (your choice): acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison. On a successful save, it takes half as much damage. Once this action is used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.

Proficiency: martial, flail
Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 23</text>
    <modifier category="bonus">melee attacks +3</modifier>
    <modifier category="bonus">melee damage +3</modifier>
    <roll>5d4</roll>
    <roll>14d6</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Gold Canary Figurine of Wondrous Power</name>
    <detail>legendary</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This gold statuette is carved in the likeness of a canary and is small enough to fit in a pocket. If you use an action to speak the command word and throw the figurine to a point on the ground within 60 feet of you, the figurine becomes a living creature in one of two forms (you choose). If there isn't enough space for the creature where it would appear, the figurine doesn't become a creature. The two forms are as follows:

Giant Canary Form: The figurine becomes a giant canary for up to 8 hours and can be ridden as a mount. Once the figurine has become a giant canary, it can't be used this way again until the next dawn.

Gold Dragon Form: While you are missing half or more of your hit points, you can speak a different command word and the figurine becomes an adult gold dragon (see its stat block in the Monster Manual) for up to 1 hour. The dragon can't use any legendary actions or lair actions. Once the figurine has become an adult gold dragon, it can't be used this way again until 1 year has passed.

In either form, the creature is friendly to you and your companions. It understands your languages and obeys your spoken commands. If you issue no commands, the creature defends itself but takes no other actions.
	The creature exists for a duration specific to each form. At the end of the duration, the creature reverts to its figurine form. It reverts to a figurine early if it drops to 0 hit points or if you use an action to speak the command word again while touching it. When the creature becomes a figurine again, its property can't be used again until a certain amount of time has passed, as specified in the description.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 23</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Platinum Scarf</name>
    <detail>legendary (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This scarf is made of sturdy cloth and covered in platinum-colored scales.
	As an action, you can pull a scale from the scarf and speak a command word. When you do so, choose one of the following effects:

Breath of Life: The scale disappears, and you or a creature you touch regains 10d4 hit points.

Platinum Shield: For 1 hour or until you dismiss it (no action required), the scale becomes a +1 shield, which you or another creature can use. A creature wielding the shield has immunity to radiant damage.

Radiant Hammer: For 1 hour or until you dismiss it (no action required), the scale becomes a magic light hammer, which you or another creature can use. The weapon deals 2d4 radiant damage, instead of the bludgeoning damage normal for a light hammer. It deals an extra 2d4 radiant damage to chromatic dragons.

Once three scales have been pulled from the scarf, no more scales can be removed until the next dawn, when all the missing scales grow back. If you pull off a scale but don't speak a command word, it disappears after 1 minute.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 24</text>
    <roll description="Heal">10d4</roll>
    <roll description="Radiant Damage">2d4</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Potion of Dragon's Majesty</name>
    <detail>legendary</detail>
    <type>P</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This potion looks like liquid gold, with a single scale from a chromatic, gem, or metallic dragon suspended in it. When you drink this potion, you transform into an adult dragon of the same kind as the dragon the scale came from. The transformation lasts for 1 hour. Any equipment you are wearing or carrying melds into your new form or falls to the ground (your choice). For the duration, you use the game statistics of the adult dragon instead of your own, but you retain your languages, personality, and memories. You can't use a dragon's Change Shape or its legendary or lair actions.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 24</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Ruby Weave Gem</name>
    <detail>legendary (requires attunement by a spellcaster)</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>While you are holding this gem, you can use it as a spellcasting focus for your spells.
	The gem has 3 charges and regains all expended charges daily at dawn. When you cast a spell while holding this gem, you can expend up to 3 charges to ignore the spell's material components with a gold piece cost, up to 500 gp per charge expended.
	When you finish a long rest, choose a spell from any class list. The spell you choose must be of a level you can cast. You know the chosen spell and can cast it with your spell slots of the appropriate level until the end of your next long rest.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 24</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Sapphire Buckler</name>
    <detail>very rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>S</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <weight>6</weight>
    <ac>2</ac>
    <text>This crystalline blue shield is fashioned from a sapphire dragon's scale and is created to aid in rooting out the influence of Aberrations. While wielding the shield, you have resistance to psychic and thunder damage. Also, when you take damage from a creature that is within 5 feet of you, you can use your reaction to deal 2d6 thunder damage to that creature.
	As an action, you can use the shield to help you locate Aberrations until the end of your next turn. If any Aberrations are within 1 mile of you, the shield emits a low humming tone for a moment, and you know the direction of all Aberrations within that range. Once this property is used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 24</text>
    <roll description="Thunder Damage">2d6</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Scaled Ornament</name>
    <detail>varies (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This ornament can be jewelry, a cloak, or another wearable accessory. It appears to be fashioned from a dragon's scale, tooth, or claw, or it incorporates images in those shapes.

Slumbering (Uncommon): You have advantage on saving throws you make to avoid being charmed or frightened or to end those conditions on you.

Stirring (Rare): You gain a +1 bonus to AC, and you can't be charmed or frightened. Moreover, each creature of your choice within 30 feet of you has advantage on saving throws it makes to avoid being charmed or frightened or to end those conditions on itself.

Wakened (Very Rare): The Wakened ornament has the Stirring property. In addition, when you would take damage of the type dealt by the breath of the dragon in whose hoard the ornament became Wakened, you can use your reaction to take no damage instead, and you regain hit points equal to the damage you would have taken. Once this property is used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.

Ascendant (Legendary): The Ascendant ornament has the Stirring and Wakened properties. In addition, while you are wearing the ornament, you gain a flying speed equal to your walking speed and can hover. While you are flying using this speed, spectral dragon wings appear on your back.

Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 27</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Topaz Annihilator</name>
    <detail>firearm, legendary (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>R</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <property>2H</property>
    <dmg1>2d6</dmg1>
    <dmgType>N</dmgType>
    <range>100/300</range>
    <text>This magic ranged weapon resembles a musket, but in lieu of any ammunition, it holds a glowing yellow scale from a topaz dragon in its heart.
	The weapon has a normal range of 100 feet and a long range of 300 feet, and it has the two-handed property. It deals 2d6 necrotic damage on a hit. If this damage reduces a creature or object to 0 hit points, the target is reduced to dust. A creature reduced to dust can be restored to life only by a true resurrection or wish spell.
	While the weapon is on your person, you can use an action to cast the disintegrate spell (save DC 18). Once this property is used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.

Range: A weapon that can be used to make a ranged attack has a range shown in parentheses after the ammunition or thrown property. The range lists two numbers. The first is the weapon's normal range in feet, and the second indicates the weapon's maximum range. When attacking a target beyond normal range, you have disadvantage on the attack roll. You can't attack a target beyond the weapon's long range.

Two-Handed: This weapon requires two hands when you attack with it.

Proficiency: firearms
Source:	Fizban's Treasury of Dragons p. 24</text>
  </item>
</compendium>
