<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <spell>
    <name>Trick Shot: Bullying Shot</name>
    <level>1</level>
    <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger): Trick Shots</classes>
    <text>You can use the powerful blast and thundering sound of your firearm to shake the resolve of a creature. When making a Charisma (Intimidation) check, you can expend one grit point to gain advantage on the roll.

Source:	Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Trick Shot: Dazing Shot</name>
    <level>1</level>
    <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger): Trick Shots</classes>
    <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to dizzy your opponent.
	On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and must make a Constitution saving throw or suffer disadvantage on attacks until the end of their next turn.

Source:	Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Trick Shot: Deadeye Shot</name>
    <level>1</level>
    <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger): Trick Shots</classes>
    <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to gain advantage on the attack roll.

Source:	Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Trick Shot: Disarming Shot</name>
    <level>1</level>
    <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger): Trick Shots</classes>
    <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to shoot an object from their hands.
	On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and must succeed on a Strength saving throw or drop 1 held object of your choice and have that object be pushed 10 feet away from you.

Source:	Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Trick Shot: Forceful Shot</name>
    <level>1</level>
    <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger): Trick Shots</classes>
    <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to trip them up and force them back.
	On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be pushed 15 feet away from you.

Source:	Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Trick Shot: Piercing Shot</name>
    <level>1</level>
    <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger): Trick Shots</classes>
    <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to fire through multiple opponents.
	The initial attack gains a +1 to the firearm's misfire score. On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and you make an attack roll with disadvantage against every creature in a line directly behind the target within your first range increment.
	Only the initial attack can misfire.

Source:	Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Trick Shot: Violent Shot</name>
    <level>1</level>
    <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger): Trick Shots</classes>
    <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one or more grit points to enhance the volatility of the attack. For each grit point expended, the attack gains a +2 to the firearm's misfire score. If the attack hits, you can roll one additional weapon damage die per grit point spent when determining the damage.

Source:	Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Trick Shot: Winging Shot</name>
    <level>1</level>
    <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger): Trick Shots</classes>
    <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to topple a moving target.
	On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and must make a Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.

Source:	Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
  </spell>
</compendium>
