<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <monster>
    <name>Adult Time Dragon</name>
    <sortname>Time Dragon, Adult</sortname>
    <ancestry>Time Dragon</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>dragon</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>250 (20d12+120)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft., climb 40 ft., fly 80 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>23</con>
    <int>23</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>20</cha>
    <save>Wis +9, Con +12, Dex +8, Cha +11</save>
    <skill>Stealth +14, Arcana +12, History +18, Perception +15</skill>
    <passive>25</passive>
    <languages>all</languages>
    <cr>18</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the dragon fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Rreactive</name>
      <text>The dragon can take up to three reactions per round but only one per turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The dragon makes three Rend attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rend</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 14 (2d6 + 7) slashing damage plus 7 (2d6) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Rend|13|2d6+7+2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Time Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The dragon exhales a wave of shimmering light in a 60-foot cone. Nonmagical objects and vegetation in that area that aren't being worn or carried crumble to dust. Each creature in that area must make a DC 20 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 36 (8d8) force damage and is magically weakened as it is desynchronized from the time stream. While the creature is in this state, attack rolls against it have advantage, and it has the poisoned condition. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only. A weakened creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself after it succeeds on three of these saves.</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Reactive Rend</name>
      <text>After using Legendary Resistance or in response to being hit by an attack roll, the dragon makes one Rend attack.</text>
    </reaction>
    <reaction>
      <name>Slow Time</name>
      <text>Immediately after a creature the dragon can see ends its turn, the dragon targets a creature it can see within 60 feet of itself that is weakened by its Time Breath. Until the weakened effect ends on the target, its speed becomes 0, and its speed can't increase.</text>
    </reaction>
    <reaction>
      <name>Time Slip</name>
      <text>The dragon halves the damage it takes from an attack made against it, provided it can see the attacker. The dragon can then immediately teleport, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying, up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space it can see.</text>
    </reaction>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 50,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Ancient Time Dragon</name>
    <sortname>Time Dragon, Ancient</sortname>
    <ancestry>Time Dragon</ancestry>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>dragon</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>22 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>536 (29d20+232)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft., climb 40 ft., fly 80 ft.</speed>
    <str>28</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>26</con>
    <int>27</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>23</cha>
    <save>Wis +12, Con +16, Dex +10, Cha +14</save>
    <skill>Stealth +18, Arcana +16, History +24, Perception +20</skill>
    <passive>30</passive>
    <languages>all</languages>
    <cr>26</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+8</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Cycle of Rebirth</name>
      <text>If the dragon dies, its soul coalesces into a steely egg and teleports to a random plane of existence. The egg is immune to all damage and hatches into a time dragon wyrmling after 1d100 years. The dragon retains all memories and knowledge it gained in its previous life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (5/Day)</name>
      <recharge>5/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the dragon fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Reactive</name>
      <text>The dragon can take up to three reactions per round but only one per turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The dragon makes three Rend attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rend</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +17 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: 22 (3d8 + 9) slashing damage plus 10 (3d6) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Rend|17|3d8+9+3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Time Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The dragon exhales a wave of shimmering light in a 90-foot cone. Nonmagical objects and vegetation in that area that aren't being worn or carried crumble to dust. Each creature in that area must make a DC 24 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 52 (8d12) force damage and is magically weakened as it is desynchronized from the time stream. While the creature is in this state, attack rolls against it have advantage, it has the poisoned condition, and other creatures have resistance to all damage it deals. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage only. A weakened creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself after it succeeds on three of these saves.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Time Gate (1/Day)</name>
      <recharge>1/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The dragon conjures a 20-foot-diameter, circular portal in the space between its horns or in an unoccupied space it can see within 30 feet of itself. The portal links to a precise location on any plane of existence at a point in time up to 8,000 years from the present, whether past or future. The portal lasts for 24 hours or until the dragon's concentration ends (as if concentration on a spell). The portal has a front and a back on each plane where it appears. Travel through the portal is possible only by moving through its front. Anything that does so is transported to the destination, appearing in the unoccupied space nearest to the portal. Deities and other planar rulers can prevent portals created by the dragon from opening in the rulers' presence or anywhere within their domains.</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Reactive Rend</name>
      <text>After using Legendary Resistance or in response to being hit by an attack roll, the dragon makes one Rend attack.</text>
    </reaction>
    <reaction>
      <name>Slow Time</name>
      <text>Immediately after a creature the dragon can see ends its turn, the dragon targets a creature it can see within 90 feet of itself that is weakened by its Time Breath. Until the weakened effect ends on the target, its speed becomes 0, and its speed can't increase.</text>
    </reaction>
    <reaction>
      <name>Time Slip</name>
      <text>The dragon halves the damage it takes from an attack made against it, provided it can see the attacker. The dragon can then immediately teleport, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying, up to 60 feet to an unoccupied space it can see.</text>
    </reaction>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 48,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Athar Null</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>14 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>84 (13d8+26)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Wis +5, Dex +6</save>
    <skill>Stealth +6, Investigation +8, Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common plus two more languages</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Avoidance</name>
      <text>If the null is subjected to an effect that allows it to make a saving throw to take half as much damage, it instead takes no damage if it succeeds on the saving throw, and half as much damage if it fails.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The null makes two Force Dagger attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Force Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. Hit: 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage plus 13 (3d8) force damage. Hit or Miss: The dagger magically returns to the null's hand immediately after a ranged attack.</text>
      <attack>Force Dagger|6|1d4+3+3d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Defier's Whim (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The null takes the Dash, Disengage, or Use an Object action.</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Nullify Spell (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The null utters a magical word of cancelation to interrupt a creature it can see that is casting a spell. If the spell is 3rd level or lower, it fails and has no effect. If the spell is 4th level or higher, the null makes an Intelligence check (DC 10 + the spell's level). On a successful check, the spell fails and has no effect.</text>
    </reaction>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 53,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Aurumach Rilmani</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>285 (30d10+120)</hp>
    <speed>0 ft., fly 40 ft.(hover)</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>21</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>21</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Dex +11, Int +11</save>
    <skill>Arcana +11, History +11, Perception +10</skill>
    <passive>20</passive>
    <languages>all, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>17</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+6</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The aurumach makes three Manifested Blade or Gleaming Ray attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Manifested Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 23 (4d8 + 5) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Manifested Blade|11|4d8+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Gleaming Ray</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +11 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 24 (3d12 + 5) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Gleaming Ray|11|3d12+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The aurumach casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 19):

	• At will: detect magic, detect thoughts
	• 1/Day each: fly, geas (as an action), slow, suggestion</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Aura of Blades (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The aurumach manifests a spectral, golden aura of blades around itself. While this aura is manifested, each creature that starts its turn within 10 feet of the aurumach must make a DC 19 Dexterity saving throw, taking 16 (3d10) force damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. The aura disappears after 1 minute, when the aurumach has the incapacitated condition or dies, or when the aurumach uses a bonus action to end it.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Invoke Weakness (Recharge 5-6) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The aurumach attempts to use its magic to weaken the defenses of a creature it can see within 120 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 19 Wisdom saving throw or become cursed until the end of the aurumach's next turn. The next time the aurumach hits the cursed target with a Manifested Blade or Gleaming Ray attack, the target takes an extra 27 (6d8) force damage.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>detect magic, detect thoughts, fly, geas, slow, suggestion</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 43</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Avoral Guardinal</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral good</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>172 (23d8+69)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., fly 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>19</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>dex +8, cha +8</save>
    <skill>perception +11, religion +7</skill>
    <resist>radiant</resist>
    <vulnerable/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <passive>21</passive>
    <languages>Celestial, Common</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 32, Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands</description>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Dive Attack</name>
      <text>If the avoral is flying, dives at least 30 feet in a straight line toward a Medium or smaller creature, and ends within 5 feet of it, that creature must succeed on a DC 15 Strength saving throw or take 14 (4d6) piercing damage and have the prone condition.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Flyby</name>
      <text>The avoral doesn't provoke an opportunity attack when it flies out of an enemy's reach.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The avoral makes two Talon attacks. It can replace one attack with a use of Spellcasting.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Talon</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage plus 13 (2d12) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Talon|8|2d6+4+2d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The avoral casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Charisma as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 16):

	• 1/Day each: command, hold person</text>
    </action>
    <slots/>
    <spells>command, hold person</spells>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Baernaloth</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>fiend (yugoloth)</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>256 (27d10+108)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>22</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>21</cha>
    <save>Wis +9, Con +10</save>
    <skill>Insight +9, Arcana +12, Perception +9</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>all, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>17</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire, lightning, necrotic, psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>acid, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (4/Day)</name>
      <recharge>4/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the baernaloth fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The baernaloth has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Reactive</name>
      <text>The baernaloth can take up to three reactions per round but only one per turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The baernaloth makes one Anguishing Bite attack and one Claw attack. It can also use Teleport.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Anguishing Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 9 (1d10 + 4) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) psychic damage. If the target is a creature, it can't regain hit points until the start of the baernaloth's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Anguishing Bite|10|1d10+4+3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 11 (2d6 + 4) slashing damage plus 17 (5d6) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|10|2d6+4+5d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Miasma of Discord (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The baernaloth exhales gray vapors that coalesce at a point it can see within 120 feet of itself. The vapors fill a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on that point, then vanish. Each non-yugoloth creature in that area must make a DC 19 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature takes 35 (10d6) psychic damage and has the charmed condition until the end of its next turn. A creature charmed in this way treats its allies as foes, and the colors of its body and equipment become shades of gray. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage only.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The baernaloth casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 20):

	• At will: detect thoughts, phantasmal force, suggestion
	• 1/Day each: cloudkill, plane shift (self only), scrying (as an action)</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Summon Yugoloth (1/Day)</name>
      <recharge>1/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The baernaloth has a 50 percent chance of summoning its choice of 1d4 mezzoloths, 1 arcanaloth, or 1 baernaloth (the mezzoloth and arcanaloth appear in the Monster Manual). A summoned yugoloth appears in an unoccupied space within 60 feet of the baernaloth, acts as an ally of the baernaloth, and can't summon other yugoloths. It remains for 1 minute, until it or the baernaloth dies, or until the baernaloth dismisses it as an action.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Teleport</name>
      <text>The baernaloth teleports, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying, up to 120 feet to an unoccupied space it can see.</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Afflict Despair</name>
      <text>When a creature that the baernaloth can see within 60 feet of itself hits with an attack roll or succeeds on a saving throw, the baernaloth forces the creature to reroll the d20 and use the new result.</text>
    </reaction>
    <reaction>
      <name>Inescapable Pain</name>
      <text>When the baernaloth is damaged by another creature, that creature must make a DC 19 Constitution saving throw, taking 14 (4d6) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
    </reaction>
    <spells>detect thoughts, phantasmal force, suggestion, cloudkill, plane shift, scrying</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 20,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Bariaur Wanderer</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic good</alignment>
    <ac>14 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>71 (11d8+22)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Str +6, Dex +4</save>
    <skill>Survival +6, Stealth +4, Athletics +6, Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Celestial, Common</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Portal Sense</name>
      <text>The bariaur can sense the presence of portals within 30 feet of itself, including inactive portals, and instinctively knows the destination of each one. The bariaur knows the distance and direction to the last portal it used as long as they're on the same plane.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The bariaur makes two Barbed Javelin or Shortbow attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Barbed Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. Hit: 9 (1d10 + 4) piercing damage. If the target is a creature, its speed is reduced by 10 feet until the start of the bariaur's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Barbed Javelin|6|1d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ram</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 8 (1d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage. If the bariaur moved at least 20 feet straight toward the target immediately before the hit, the target takes an extra 10 (3d6) bludgeoning damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 14 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Ram|6|1d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. Hit: 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage, plus 4 (1d8) piercing damage if the target doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|4|1d6+2+1d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The bariaur casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability:

	• At will: dancing lights, druidcraft
	• 1/Day each: goodberry, pass without trace, tongues</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Mighty Leap (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The bariaur jumps a distance up to its walking speed.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>dancing lights, druidcraft, goodberry, pass without trace, tongues</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 21,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Bleak Cabal Void Soother</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (breastplate)</ac>
    <hp>55 (10d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Wis +4, Con +3</save>
    <skill>Medicine +4</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common plus one more language</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The void soother makes two Mace or Void Bolt attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Mace</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 6 (1d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage plus 3 (1d6) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Mace|5|1d6+3+1d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Void Bolt</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +4 to hit, range 90 ft., one target. Hit: 9 (2d8) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Void Bolt|4|2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The void soother casts one of the following spells, using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 12):

	• At will: guidance, light
	• 1/Day each: calm emotions, lesser restoration, remove curse, protection from energy</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Soothing Word (3/Day) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The void soother speaks a magical word of mercy, healing one creature it can see within 60 feet of itself. The target regains 4 (1d4 + 2) hit points.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>guidance, light, calm emotions, lesser restoration, remove curse, protection from energy</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 54,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Cranium Rat Squeaker</name>
    <sortname>Cranium Rat, Squeaker</sortname>
    <ancestry>Cranium Rat</ancestry>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>2 (1d4)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>2</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>4</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>telepathy 30 ft. (emotions only)</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Shared Telepathy</name>
      <text>Any creature touching the cranium rat can use the rat's telepathy if the rat allows it. If the creature knows any language, the creature can use the telepathy to communicate words and emotions.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Telepathic Shroud</name>
      <text>The cranium rat is immune to any effect that would sense its emotions or read its thoughts, as well as to divination spells.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 1 piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|4|1</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Illumination (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The cranium rat sheds dim light from its exposed brain in a 5-foot radius or extinguishes the light.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 22,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Cranium Rat Squeaker Swarm</name>
    <sortname>Cranium Rat, Squeaker Swarm</sortname>
    <ancestry>Cranium Rat</ancestry>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>76 (17d8)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>telepathy 30 ft.</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, prone, restrained, stunned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Psychic Messenger</name>
      <text>The swarm can use its sending spell to target someone familiar to a creature in telepathic contact with the swarm.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Swarm</name>
      <text>The swarm can occupy another creature's space and vice versa, and the swarm can move through any opening large enough for a Tiny rat. The swarm can't regain hit points or gain temporary hit points.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Telepathic Shroud</name>
      <text>The swarm is immune to any effect that would sense its emotions or read its thoughts, as well as to divination spells.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Bites</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 0 ft., one target in the swarm's space. Hit: 14 (4d6) piercing damage, or 7 (2d6) piercing damage if the swarm has half of its hit points or fewer, plus 22 (5d8) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Bites|5|4d6+5d8</attack>
      <attack>Bites (Half HP)|5|2d6+5d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>The swarm casts one of the following spells, requiring no spell components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 13):

	• At will: command*, detect thoughts*, sending*
	• 1/Day each: confusion*, dominate monster*

*To cast this spell, the swarm must have more than half its hit points remaining.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Illumination (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The swarm sheds dim light from its brains in a 5-foot radius, increases the illumination to bright light in a 5- to 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional number of feet equal to the chosen radius, or extinguishes the light.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>command, detect thoughts, sending, confusion, dominate monster</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 22,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Cuprilach Rilmani</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>202 (27d8+81)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>20</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Dex +9, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Stealth +13, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>telepathy 120 ft., any four languages</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>psychic</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The cuprilach makes three Burnished Blade or Bolt attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Burnished Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 8 (1d6 + 5) piercing damage plus 13 (2d12) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Burnished Blade|9|1d6+5+2d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bolt</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d4 + 5) piercing damage plus 13 (2d12) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Bolt|9|1d4+5+2d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The cuprilach casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 15):

	• At will: detect magic, disguise self
	• 1/Day each: alter self, fog cloud, silence</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Assassin's Agility (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The cuprilach takes the Dash or Disengage action, or it makes one Burnished Blade attack.</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Uncanny Dodge</name>
      <text>The cuprilach halves the damage it takes from an attack that hits it, provided it can see the attacker.</text>
    </reaction>
    <spells>detect magic, disguise self, alter self, fog cloud, silence</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 44,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Dabus</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful neutral</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>44 (8d8+8)</hp>
    <speed>20 ft., fly 30 ft.(hover)</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Wis +4, Int +5</save>
    <skill>Insight +4, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>understands all languages but can't speak; communicates via Symbol Speech</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Physical Restraint</name>
      <text>The dabus doesn't make melee attacks or opportunity attacks, even in self-defense.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Symbol Speech</name>
      <text>A dabus communicates by creating illusory symbols and pictures that float in the air in front of itself and disappear a few seconds later. A creature that can see such a message can decipher it with a successful DC 10 Intelligence (Investigation) check (no action required).</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The dabus makes two Flying Brick attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Flying Brick</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +5 to hit, range 90 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d8 + 3) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Flying Brick|5|1d8+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Grasping Ground (Recharge 6)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>The dabus causes a 20-foot-square area of ground it can see within 60 feet of itself to sprout clutching appendages made of stone. Each creature of the dabus's choice in that area must succeed on a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw or take 9 (2d8) bludgeoning damage and have the grappled condition (escape DC 13). While grappled in this way, the creature has the restrained condition. The appendages vanish after 1 minute or if the dabus's concentration ends (as if concentration on a spell).</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 23,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Darkweaver</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>149 (23d8+46)</hp>
    <speed>50 ft., climb 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Wis +6, Dex +7</save>
    <skill>Stealth +7, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Deep Speech, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold</resist>
    <immune>necrotic</immune>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Shadowy Form</name>
      <text>While the darkweaver is in dim light or darkness, attack rolls against it are made with disadvantage unless the darkweaver has the incapacitated condition.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>The darkweaver can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Sunlight Hypersensitivity</name>
      <text>The darkweaver takes 10 radiant damage when it starts its turn in sunlight. While in sunlight, it has disadvantage on attack rolls and ability checks.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The darkweaver makes two Shadow Web attacks and one Bite attack. It can use Reel after any of these attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 13 (3d6 + 3) piercing damage plus 17 (5d6) necrotic damage, and if the target is a creature, the target's hit point maximum is reduced by an amount equal to the necrotic damage taken. This reduction lasts until the target finishes a long rest. The target dies if its hit point maximum is reduced to 0.</text>
      <attack>Bite|7|3d6+3+5d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shadow Web</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 120 ft., one creature. Hit: 16 (3d10) necrotic damage, and the target has the grappled condition (escape DC 15). The shadow web can be attacked and destroyed (AC 16; 20 hit points; vulnerability to radiant damage; immunity to bludgeoning, necrotic, poison, and psychic damage). The darkweaver can grapple up to six creatures at a time using its shadow web.</text>
      <attack>Shadow Web|7|3d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Reel</name>
      <text>The darkweaver pulls each creature it has grappled up to 60 feet toward itself.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 25,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Decaton Modron</name>
    <sortname>Modron, Decaton</sortname>
    <ancestry>Modron</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful neutral</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>144 (17d10+51)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., fly 30 ft.(hover)</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Wis +5, Int +5</save>
    <skill>Perception +8</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages>Modron, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Axiomatic Mind</name>
      <text>The decaton can't be compelled to act in a manner contrary to its nature or its instructions.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Combat Ready</name>
      <text>The decaton has advantage on initiative rolls.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Disintegration</name>
      <text>If the decaton dies, its body disintegrates into dust, leaving behind anything it was carrying.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The decaton makes three Tentacle attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tentacle</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 15 (2d10 + 4) piercing damage, and if the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 14). Until this grapple ends, the decaton can't use this tentacle against other targets. The decaton has ten tentacles, each of which can grapple one target.</text>
      <attack>Tentacle|7|2d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Lightning Rays (Recharge 6)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>The decaton unleashes a barrage of lightning bolts from its eyes. Each creature within 30 feet of the decaton must make a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw, taking 38 (7d10) lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful save.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The decaton casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 13):

	• At will: detect magic, dispel magic, mending (as an action)
	• 1/Day each: plane shift (self only), protection from evil and good</text>
    </action>
    <spells>detect magic, dispel magic, mending, plane shift, protection from evil and good</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 36,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Doomguard Doom Lord</name>
    <sortname>Doomguard, Doom Lord</sortname>
    <ancestry>Doomguard</ancestry>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>202 (27d8+81)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Str +9, Con +7</save>
    <skill>Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Common plus three more languages</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>necrotic</immune>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Aura of Doom</name>
      <text>Any creature that starts its turn within 10 feet of the doom lord must make a DC 16 Constitution saving throw, taking 18 (4d8) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. If the doom lord doesn't have the incapacitated condition, it can suppress or resume this aura at the start of its turn (no action required).</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The doom lord deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The doom lord makes two Entropic Greatsword or Entropic Javelin attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Entropic Greatsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 12 (2d6 + 5) slashing damage plus 10 (3d6) necrotic damage. A creature killed by this attack has its body and everything it is wearing or carrying, except for magic items, reduced to ash.</text>
      <attack>Entropic Greatsword|9|2d6+5+3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Entropic Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. Hit: 8 (1d6 + 5) piercing damage plus 14 (4d6) necrotic damage. A creature killed by this attack has its body and everything it is wearing or carrying, except for magic items, reduced to ash.</text>
      <attack>Entropic Javelin|9|1d6+5+4d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 54,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Doomguard Rot Blade</name>
    <sortname>Doomguard, Rot Blade</sortname>
    <ancestry>Doomguard</ancestry>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>97 (13d8+39)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Str +7, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common plus two more languages</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>necrotic</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The rot blade makes two Entropic Blade or Entropic Javelin attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Entropic Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 9 (1d10 + 4) slashing damage plus 7 (2d6) necrotic damage. A creature killed by this attack has its body and everything it is wearing or carrying, except for magic items, reduced to ash. Hit or Miss: The rot blade can cause the blade to emit a burst of entropic magic in a 10-foot-radius sphere centered on the weapon. Each creature in that area other than the rot blade must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or take 6 (1d12) necrotic damage. The blade can emit entropic magic in this way only once per turn.</text>
      <attack>Entropic Blade|7|1d10+4+2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Entropic Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage plus 13 (2d12) necrotic damage. A creature killed by this attack has its body and everything it is wearing or carrying, except for magic items, reduced to ash.</text>
      <attack>Entropic Javelin|7|1d6+4+2d12</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 56,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Eater of Knowledge</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>102 (12d10+36)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>18</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Str +7, Int +7</save>
    <skill>Arcana +7, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>psychic</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Brains Devoured</name>
      <text>When the eater of knowledge is first encountered, roll 1d10 to determine the number of brains it has already consumed.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The eater of knowledge has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The eater of knowledge makes two Slam attacks. If both attacks hit the same creature and the target is Large or smaller, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 14) and must succeed on a DC 15 Intelligence saving throw or have the stunned condition until the grapple ends.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 11 (2d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|7|2d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Extract Brain</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one Humanoid with the incapacitated condition. Hit: 45 (10d8) piercing damage. If this damage reduces the target to 0 hit points, the eater of knowledge kills the target by extracting and consuming its brain.</text>
      <attack>Extract Brain|7|10d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>The eater of knowledge casts one of the following spells, requiring no spell components and using Intelligence as its spellcasting ability (spell save DC 15). It must have consumed the requisite number of brains to cast the spell, as indicated:

	• 1/Day each: plane shift (self only,  0 brains), detect magic (1 brain), silent image (2 brains), invisibility (3 brains), hypnotic pattern (4 brains), major image (5 brains), telekinesis (6 brains), arcane eye (7 brains), mislead (8 brains), greater invisibility (9 brains), mass suggestion (10 or more brains)</text>
    </action>
    <spells>plane shift, detect magic, silent image, invisibility, hypnotic pattern, major image, telekinesis, arcane eye, mislead, greater invisibility, mass suggestion</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 29,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Equinal Guardinal</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral good</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>93 (11d10+33)</hp>
    <speed>50 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Str +9, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +9, Perception +5, Religion +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Celestial, Common</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>radiant</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Headfirst Charge</name>
      <text>If the equinal moves at least 30 feet in a straight line toward a creature and ends within 5 feet of it, that creature must succeed on a DC 17 Strength saving throw or take 14 (4d6) bludgeoning damage and have the prone condition.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The equinal makes two Fist attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Fist</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 13 (2d6 + 6) bludgeoning damage plus 3 (1d6) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Fist|9|2d6+6+1d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rock</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, range 60/180 ft., one target. Hit: 22 (3d10 + 6) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 17 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Rock|9|3d10+6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shout (Recharge 6)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>The equinal lets out a booming shout. Each creature within 30 feet of the equinal must succeed on a DC 14 Constitution saving throw or have the stunned condition until the end of the equinal's next turn.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 33,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Eyestalk of Gzemnid</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>247 (15d20+90)</hp>
    <speed>50 ft., burrow 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>28</str>
    <dex>7</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>4</cha>
    <save>Wis +4, Con +11</save>
    <skill/>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages/>
    <cr>15</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft., tremorsense 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+5</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Tunneler</name>
      <text>The eyestalk can burrow through solid rock at half its burrow speed and leaves a 10-foot-diameter tunnel in its wake.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The eyestalk uses Eradication Gaze, if available, and makes one Bite attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 22 (3d8 + 9) piercing damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 19 Dexterity saving throw or be swallowed by the eyestalk. A swallowed creature is blinded and restrained, it has total cover against attacks and other effects outside the eyestalk, and it takes 21 (6d6) acid damage at the start of each of the eyestalk's turns.

	If the eyestalk takes 30 damage or more on a single turn from a creature inside it, the eyestalk must succeed on a DC 21 Constitution saving throw at the end of that turn or regurgitate all swallowed creatures, which fall prone in a space within 10 feet of the eyestalk. If the eyestalk dies, a swallowed creature is no longer restrained by it and can escape from the corpse by using 20 feet of movement, exiting prone.</text>
      <attack>Bite|14|3d8+9</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Eradication Gaze (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The eyestalk creates an area of magical devastation in a 150-foot cone. Any creature in that area must succeed on a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw or take 55 (10d10) necrotic damage. If this damage reduces a creature to 0 hit points, its body becomes a pile of fine violet dust.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel p. 88</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Farastu Demodand</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fiend</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>195 (26d8+78)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft., climb 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>8</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Wis +5, Dex +5</save>
    <skill>Survival +5, Stealth +5, Perception +9</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Demodand, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>11</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire</resist>
    <immune>acid, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>paralyzed, poisoned, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Boundless Movement</name>
      <text>The farastu ignores difficult terrain, and magical effects can't reduce its speed. It can spend 5 feet of movement to automatically remove the grappled condition from itself.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The farastu has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>The farastu can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without an ability check.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The farastu makes two Claw attacks and one Bite attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 16 (2d10 + 5) slashing damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 15, with disadvantage). The farastu has two claws, each of which can grapple one creature.</text>
      <attack>Claw|9|2d10+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit (with advantage against a creature the farastu is grappling), reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 12 (2d6 + 5) piercing damage plus 24 (7d6) acid damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|9|2d6+5+7d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The farastu casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Charisma as the spellcasting ability:

	• At will: invisibility (self only)
	• 1/Day each: dispel magic, fog cloud</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Summon Demodand (1/Day)</name>
      <recharge>1/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The farastu has a 40 percent chance of summoning 1 farastu demodand. A summoned demodand appears in an unoccupied space within 60 feet of the farastu, acts as an ally of the farastu, and can't summon other demodands. It remains for 1 minute, until it or the farastu dies, or until the farastu dismisses it as an action.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>invisibility, dispel magic, fog cloud</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 26,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Fated Shaker</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (16 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>76 (17d8)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Wis +6, Int +5</save>
    <skill>Insight +6, Investigation +5, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Common plus two more languages</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The shaker makes two Golden Rod or Radiant Bolt attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Golden Rod</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 6 (1d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage plus 9 (2d8) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Golden Rod|6|1d6+3+2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Radiant Bolt</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +6 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 14 (2d10 + 3) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Radiant Bolt|6|2d10+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The shaker casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 14):

	• At will: mage armor, mage hand
	• 1/Day each: enlarge/reduce, fly, suggestion</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Commanding Words (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The shaker speaks magical words to order a creature it can see within 30 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or be affected by one of the following effects (choose one or roll a d4):

1-2: Grovel. The target takes 14 (4d6) psychic damage, drops whatever it is holding, and has the prone condition.

3-4: Cower. The target takes 10 (3d6) psychic damage and has the frightened condition until the end of its next turn.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>mage armor, mage hand, enlarge/reduce, fly, suggestion</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 56,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Ferrumach Rilmani</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>136 (16d8+64)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Str +8, Con +8</save>
    <skill>Athletics +8, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>telepathy 120 ft., any two languages</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>psychic</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Bladed Edges</name>
      <text>A creature takes 10 (3d6) slashing damage if it starts its turn grappling or being grappled by the ferrumach.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Skewering Charge</name>
      <text>If the ferrumach moves at least 20 feet in a straight line toward a Large or smaller creature and ends within 5 feet of it, that creature must succeed on a DC 16 Strength saving throw or have the grappled condition (escape DC 18) and take 10 (3d6) piercing damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The ferrumach makes three Sharpened Limb or Bolt attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Sharpened Limb</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 9 (1d10 + 4) slashing damage plus 11 (2d10) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Sharpened Limb|8|1d10+4+2d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bolt</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage plus 11 (2d10) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Bolt|8|1d6+4+2d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The ferrumach casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 14):

	• At will: detect magic
	• 1/Day each: dispel magic, ice storm</text>
    </action>
    <spells>detect magic, dispel magic, ice storm</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 44,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Fraternity of Order Law Bender</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>137 (25d8+25)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>19</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Wis +7, Con +5</save>
    <skill>Insight +7, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Common plus three more languages</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The law bender makes three Arcane Burst attacks and uses Power of Authority or Spellcasting.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Arcane Burst</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Spell Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 90 ft., one target. Hit: 17 (2d12 + 4) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Arcane Burst|8|2d12+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Power of Authority</name>
      <text>The law bender targets a creature it can see within 60 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 16 Intelligence saving throw or take 10 (3d6) psychic damage and have the incapacitated condition for 1 minute. At the end of each of the target's turns, it can repeat the saving throw, ending the incapacitated condition on itself on a success. A target that succeeds on the saving throw becomes immune to this law bender's Power of Authority for 24 hours.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The law bender casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability:

	• At will: dispel magic, fly, mage armor, mage hand, prestidigitation</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spatial Loophole (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The law bender teleports, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying, up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space it can see.</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Probability Loophole (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>When the law bender or a creature it can see makes an attack roll, a saving throw, or an ability check, the law bender can cause the roll to be made with advantage or disadvantage.</text>
    </reaction>
    <spells>dispel magic, fly, mage armor, mage hand, prestidigitation</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 57,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Githzerai Futurist</name>
    <sortname>Githzerai, Futurist</sortname>
    <ancestry>Githzerai</ancestry>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>aberration (gith)</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (psychic defense)</ac>
    <hp>149 (23d8+46)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save>Str +6, Wis +7, Dex +7, Int +7</save>
    <skill>Insight +7, Arcana +7, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Common, Gith</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>truesight 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Psychic Defense</name>
      <text>While the githzerai is wearing no armor and wielding no shield, its AC includes its Wisdom modifier.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The githzerai makes three Unarmed Strike or Psychic Bolt attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Unarmed Strike</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 12 (2d8 + 3) bludgeoning damage plus 11 (2d10) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Unarmed Strike|7|2d8+3+2d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Psychic Bolt</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +7 to hit, range 60 ft., one creature. Hit: 21 (4d8 + 3) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Bolt|7|4d8+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>The githzerai casts one of the following spells, requiring no spell components and using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 15):

	• At will: dispel magic, levitate (self only), mage hand (the hand is invisible), see invisibility
	• 1/Day each: plane shift (self only), scrying (as an action), slow, telekinesis</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Future Insight (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>When the githzerai or a creature it can see makes an attack roll, a saving throw, or an ability check, the githzerai can cause the roll to be made with advantage or disadvantage.</text>
    </reaction>
    <spells>dispel magic, levitate, mage hand, see invisibility, plane shift, scrying, slow, telekinesis</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 30,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Githzerai Traveler</name>
    <sortname>Githzerai, Traveler</sortname>
    <ancestry>Githzerai</ancestry>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>aberration (gith)</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (psychic defense)</ac>
    <hp>44 (8d8+8)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Str +3, Wis +5, Dex +4, Int +4</save>
    <skill>Survival +5, Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common, Gith</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Psychic Defense</name>
      <text>While the githzerai is wearing no armor and wielding no shield, its AC includes its Wisdom modifier.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The githzerai makes three Unarmed Strike attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Unarmed Strike</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 6 (1d8 + 2) bludgeoning damage plus 4 (1d8) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Unarmed Strike|4|1d8+2+1d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>The githzerai casts one of the following spells, requiring no spell components and using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 13):

	• At will: mage hand (the hand is invisible)
	• 1/Day each: jump, plane shift (self only), see invisibility</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Matter Manipulation (Recharge 4-6) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>D4</recharge>
      <text>The githzerai manipulates the energy of the plane of existence it's on to produce one of the following effects (choose one or roll a d6):

1-2: Astral Step. The githzerai can teleport, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying, up to 40 feet to an unoccupied space it can see. In addition, its walking speed increases to 40 feet until the start of its next turn.

3-4: Growth. Flowers and vines grow around the githzerai until the start of its next turn, then vanish; the ground within 15 feet of the githzerai is difficult terrain for other creatures while the flowers and vines are present.

5-6: Retaliating Light. Multicolored lights surround the githzerai until the start of its next turn. For the effect's duration, whenever a creature within 5 feet of the githzerai hits it with a melee attack roll, that creature takes 3 (1d6) force damage, as magic lashes out in retribution.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>mage hand, jump, plane shift, see invisibility</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 31,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Githzerai Uniter</name>
    <sortname>Githzerai, Uniter</sortname>
    <ancestry>Githzerai</ancestry>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>aberration (gith)</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (psychic defense)</ac>
    <hp>123 (19d8+38)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Str +4, Wis +6, Dex +6, Int +5</save>
    <skill>Insight +6, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Common, Gith</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Psychic Defense</name>
      <text>While the githzerai is wearing no armor and wielding no shield, its AC includes its Wisdom modifier.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The githzerai makes three Unarmed Strike or Psychic Bolt attacks. It can replace any of these attacks with one use of its Pacifying Touch.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Unarmed Strike</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d8 + 3) bludgeoning damage plus 10 (3d6) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Unarmed Strike|6|1d8+3+3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Psychic Bolt</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +6 to hit, range 60 ft., one creature. Hit: 17 (5d6) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Bolt|6|5d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Pacifying Touch</name>
      <text>The githzerai touches one creature it can see within 5 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 14 Intelligence saving throw, or the githzerai chooses an action for that target: Attack, Cast a Spell, or Dash. The affected target can't take that action for 1 minute. At the end of each of the target's turns, it can repeat the saving throw, ending the effect on itself on a successful save. A target that succeeds on the saving throw becomes immune to this githzerai's Pacifying Touch for 24 hours.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>The githzerai casts one of the following spells, requiring no spell components and using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 14):

	• At will: mage hand (the hand is invisible), see invisibility
	• 1/Day each: plane shift (self only), telekinesis</text>
    </action>
    <spells>mage hand, see invisibility, plane shift, telekinesis</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 31,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Hands of Havoc Fire Starter</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (breastplate)</ac>
    <hp>65 (10d8+20)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Str +5, Con +4</save>
    <skill/>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common plus one more language</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>fire</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The fire starter makes two Havoc Hammer or Havoc Flask attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Havoc Hammer</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d8 + 3) bludgeoning damage plus 9 (2d8) fire damage. If the target is a creature, magical flames cling to it, causing it to take 3 (1d6) fire damage at the start of each of its turns. Immediately after taking this damage on its turn, the target can make a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw, ending the effect on itself on a successful save.</text>
      <attack>Havoc Hammer|5|1d8+3+2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Havoc Flask</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 30/90 ft., one target. Hit: 13 (2d12) fire damage. If the target is a creature, magical flames cling to it, causing it to take 3 (1d6) fire damage at the start of each of its turns. Immediately after taking this damage on its turn, the target can make a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw, ending the effect on itself on a successful save.

	After the fire starter throws the flask, roll a d6; on a 3 or lower, the fire starter has no more flasks to throw.</text>
      <attack>Havoc Flask|4|2d12</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 58,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Harmonium Captain</name>
    <sortname>Harmonium, Captain</sortname>
    <ancestry>Harmonium</ancestry>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>20 (plate armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>110 (17d8+34)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Str +7, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Common plus one more language</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Aura of Command</name>
      <text>Allies within 30 feet of the captain are immune to the charmed and frightened conditions. This aura is suppressed while the captain has the incapacitated condition.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The captain makes three Harmonium Blade attacks. The captain can also use Dictate if available.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Harmonium Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 9 (1d10 + 4) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) lightning damage.</text>
      <attack>Harmonium Blade|7|1d10+4+3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Dictate (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The captain verbally commands up to three creatures it can see within 60 feet of itself. This magical command must be to undertake an action or to refrain from taking actions (for example, "Throw down your weapons").

	A target must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or have the charmed condition for 1 minute, during which time it follows the captain's command. The effect ends early if the target takes damage or if it successfully completes the command. A target automatically succeeds on its saving throw if the command is directly harmful to itself, such as commanding it to walk into fire.

	A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a successful save.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 58,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Harmonium Peacekeeper</name>
    <sortname>Harmonium, Peacekeeper</sortname>
    <ancestry>Harmonium</ancestry>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>45 (7d8+14)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common plus one more language</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The peacekeeper has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the peacekeeper's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally doesn't have the incapacitated condition.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Electrified Mancatcher</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 8 (1d10 + 3) piercing damage plus 4 (1d8) lightning damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 13). Until the grappled condition ends, the target has the restrained condition and can't teleport, the peacekeeper can't make Electrified Mancatcher attacks, and the target takes 8 (1d10 + 3) lightning damage at the start of each of its turns.</text>
      <attack>Electrified Mancatcher|5|1d10+3+1d8</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 59,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Heralds of Dust Remnant</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>45 (7d8+14)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Stealth +6, Arcana +5, Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common plus three more languages</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>necrotic</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The remnant makes two Necrotic Surge attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Necrotic Surge</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Spell Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 14 (2d10 + 3) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Necrotic Surge|5|2d10+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The remnant casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 13):

	• At will: mage armor, mage hand, prestidigitation
	• 1/Day each: bane, dimension door, web</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Phase (2/Day) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>2/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The remnant becomes partially incorporeal for as long as it maintains concentration on the effect (as if concentration on a spell). While partially incorporeal, the remnant has resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>mage armor, mage hand, prestidigitation, bane, dimension door, web</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 59,
		AATM,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Hexton Modron</name>
    <sortname>Modron, Hexton</sortname>
    <ancestry>Modron</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful neutral</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>209 (22d12+66)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft., fly 40 ft.(hover)</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>19</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Wis +8, Int +9</save>
    <skill>Perception +13</skill>
    <passive>23</passive>
    <languages>all, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>13</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>lightning, psychic</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+5</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Axiomatic Mind</name>
      <text>The hexton can't be compelled to act in a manner contrary to its nature or its instructions.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Combat Ready</name>
      <text>The hexton has advantage on initiative rolls.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Disintegration</name>
      <text>If the hexton dies, its body disintegrates into dust, leaving behind anything it was carrying.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (4/Day)</name>
      <recharge>4/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the hexton fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Reactive</name>
      <text>The hexton can take up to three reactions per round but only one per turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The hexton makes one Pincer attack and two Tentacle attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Pincer</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 13 (2d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage plus 10 (3d6) force damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 17 Constitution saving throw or have the incapacitated condition until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Pincer|9|2d8+4+3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tentacle</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 15 (2d10 + 4) piercing damage, and if the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 14). Until this grapple ends, the hexton can't use this tentacle against other targets. The hexton has six tentacles, each of which can grapple one target.</text>
      <attack>Tentacle|9|2d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The hexton casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 17):

	• At will: detect magic, dispel magic, mending (as an action)
	• 1/Day each: plane shift (self only), protection from evil and good</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Counter Magic</name>
      <text>The hexton attempts to interrupt a creature it can see that is casting a spell. If the spell is 3rd level or lower, it fails and has no effect. If the spell is 4th level or higher, the hexton makes an Intelligence check (DC 10 + the spell's level). On a success, the spell fails and has no effect.</text>
    </reaction>
    <reaction>
      <name>Lightning Rebuke</name>
      <text>When a creature within 120 feet of the hexton damages it, the hexton magically retaliates with an arc of lightning. The creature must make a DC 17 Dexterity saving throw, taking 11 (2d10) lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
    </reaction>
    <spells>detect magic, dispel magic, mending, plane shift, protection from evil and good</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 37,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Hound Archon</name>
    <sortname>Hound, Archon</sortname>
    <ancestry>Hound</ancestry>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful good</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>65 (10d8+20)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Wis +4, Int +2</save>
    <skill>Insight +4, Stealth +3, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>all</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>lightning</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, paralyzed</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Aura of Menace</name>
      <text>As long as the archon doesn't have the incapacitated condition, each creature of the archon's choice that starts its turn within 20 feet of the archon must make a DC 12 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature has the frightened condition until the start of its next turn. On a successful save, the creature is immune to all archons' Aura of Menace for 24 hours.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The archon makes two Bite attacks. It can replace one of the attacks with a Shining Blade attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 14 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Bite|6|1d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shining Blade (True Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 11 (2d6 + 4) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Shining Blade|6|2d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The archon casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Charisma as the spellcasting ability:

	• At will: detect evil and good
	• 1/Day each: aid, continual flame</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Teleport</name>
      <text>The archon teleports, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying, to an unoccupied space it can see within 120 feet of itself.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Change Shape (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The archon magically transforms into any Medium or Large dog or wolf while retaining its game statistics (other than its size and losing its Shining Blade attack). The archon reverts to its true form if reduced to 0 hit points or if it uses a bonus action to do so.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>detect evil and good, aid, continual flame</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 16,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Kelubar Demodand</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fiend</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>187 (22d8+88)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>22</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Wis +7, Dex +6</save>
    <skill>Insight +7</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Demodand, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>13</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire</resist>
    <immune>acid, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>paralyzed, poisoned, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+5</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Acidic Secretions</name>
      <text>A creature that touches the kelubar or hits it with a melee attack while within 5 feet of it takes 5 (2d4) acid damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Boundless Movement</name>
      <text>The kelubar ignores difficult terrain, and magical effects can't reduce its speed. It can spend 5 feet of movement to automatically remove the grappled condition from itself.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The kelubar has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The kelubar makes two Bite attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 11 (1d10 + 6) piercing damage plus 18 (4d8) acid damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|11|1d10+6+4d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The kelubar casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Charisma as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 17):

	• At will: invisibility (self only)
	• 1/Day each: dispel magic, scrying (as an action)</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spit Acid</name>
      <text>The kelubar spits acid in a line 60 feet long and 5 feet wide. Each creature in that area must make a DC 17 Dexterity saving throw, taking 27 (6d8) acid damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Summon Demodand (1/Day)</name>
      <recharge>1/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The kelubar has a 40 percent chance of summoning its choice of 1d2 farastu demodands or 1 kelubar demodand. A summoned demodand appears in an unoccupied space within 60 feet of the kelubar, acts as an ally of the kelubar, and can't summon other demodands. It remains for 1 minute, until it or the kelubar dies, or until the kelubar dismisses it as an action.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Nauseating Fog (Recharge 6) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>The kelubar magically creates a cloud of greenish fog that fills a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on a point within 120 feet of itself. The cloud remains for 1 minute or until the kelubar uses this bonus action again. The cloud is heavily obscured and difficult terrain. Any creature that starts its turn in the cloud or enters the cloud for the first time on a turn must succeed on a DC 17 Constitution saving throw or have the poisoned condition until the end of its next turn.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>invisibility, dispel magic, scrying</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 27,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Kolyarut</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct (inevitable)</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful neutral</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>297 (35d8+140)</hp>
    <speed>50 ft., fly 35 ft.(hover)</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>25</int>
    <wis>22</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Wis +12, Cha +10, Int +13</save>
    <skill>Insight +12, History +13, Perception +12</skill>
    <passive>22</passive>
    <languages>all</languages>
    <cr>20</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>thunder; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The kolyarut is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (4/Day)</name>
      <recharge>4/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the kolyarut fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The kolyarut has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The kolyarut makes four Unerring Blade attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Unerring Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: automatic hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 24 force damage plus one of the following effects (choose one or roll a d6):

1-2: Disarm. The target drops one item it is holding of the kolyarut's choice

3-4: Imbalance. The target can't take reactions until the start of the kolyarut's next turn.

5-6: Push. If the target is Large or smaller, the target is pushed up to 15 feet away from the kolyarut.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Edict of Blades (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The kolyarut moves up to its speed without provoking opportunity attacks and can make one Unerring Blade attack against each creature it moves past. Whenever it hits a creature with an Unerring Blade attack during this movement, each spell of 5th level or lower on the creature ends, and the creature has the incapacitated condition until the end of the kolyarut's next turn.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Plane Shift (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The kolyarut casts plane shift, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability. The kolyarut can cast the spell normally, or it can cast the spell on an unwilling creature it can see within 60 feet of itself. If it uses the latter option, the targeted creature must succeed on a DC 18 Charisma saving throw or be sent to a teleportation circle in the Hall of Concordance in Sigil.</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Parry</name>
      <text>The kolyarut adds 6 to its AC against one attack roll that would hit it. To do so, the kolyarut must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
    </reaction>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 34,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Lantern Archon</name>
    <sortname>Archon, Lantern</sortname>
    <ancestry>Archon</ancestry>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful good</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>22 (5d6+5)</hp>
    <speed>0 ft., fly 60 ft.(hover)</speed>
    <str>1</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>all</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>lightning, radiant</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, grappled, paralyzed, prone, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Aura of Menace</name>
      <text>As long as the archon doesn't have the incapacitated condition, each creature of the archon's choice that starts its turn within 20 feet of the archon must make a DC 11 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature has the frightened condition until the start of its next turn. On a successful save, the creature is immune to all archons' Aura of Menace for 24 hours.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Illumination</name>
      <text>The archon sheds bright light in a 30-foot radius and dim light for an additional 30 feet.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Incorporeal Movement</name>
      <text>The archon can move through creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. If it ends its turn inside an object, it takes 5 (1d10) force damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The archon makes two Radiant Strike attacks. It can replace one attack with a use of Teleport.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Radiant Strike</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 60 ft., one target. Hit: 6 (1d6 + 3) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Radiant Strike|5|1d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The archon casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Charisma as the spellcasting ability:

	• At will: detect evil and good
	• 1/Day: aid</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Teleport</name>
      <text>The archon teleports, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying, to an unoccupied space it can see within 120 feet of itself.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shift Radiance (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The archon reduces its Illumination to shed only dim light in a 5-foot radius, or it returns the light to full intensity.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>detect evil and good, aid</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 17,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Maelephant</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>fiend</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (half plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>161 (17d10+68)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Str +8, Con +8</save>
    <skill>Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Infernal</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>acid, fire, lightning</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The maelephant has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The maelephant makes one Barbed Trunk attack and two Glaive attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Barbed Trunk</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 13 (2d8 + 4) piercing damage plus 13 (2d12) poison damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 14). Until this grapple ends, the target has the restrained condition. While it is grappling a creature, the maelephant can't use its barbed trunk to attack other creatures.</text>
      <attack>Barbed Trunk|8|2d8+4+2d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Glaive</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 15 (2d10 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Glaive|8|2d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Mind Poison (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The maelephant expels poisonous gas from its trunk in a 60-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 16 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 39 (6d12) poison damage and has the poisoned condition. While poisoned in this way, the creature loses all weapon and skill proficiencies, it can't cast spells, it can't understand language, and it has disadvantage on Intelligence saving throws. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. On a successful save, the target takes half as much damage only and is immune to this maelephant's Mind Poison for 24 hours.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 35,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Mercykiller Bloodhound</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>104 (16d8+48)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Survival +8, Perception +8</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages>Common plus one more language</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Portal Sense</name>
      <text>The bloodhound can sense the presence of portals within 30 feet of itself, including inactive portals, and instinctively knows the destination of each portal.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The bloodhound makes three Clawed Gauntlet attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Clawed Gauntlet</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d8 + 3) slashing damage plus 10 (3d6) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Clawed Gauntlet|6|1d8+3+3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Marked for Pursuit (3/Day) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The bloodhound attempts to place a magical mark on a creature it can see within 30 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 13 Charisma saving throw or become cursed for 24 hours. A creature missing any of its hit points has disadvantage on this saving throw. While cursed in this way, the bloodhound can sense the direction and distance to the target as long as the two are on the same plane of existence. If the target isn't on the same plane, the bloodhound knows what plane the target is on.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 60,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Mind's Eye Matter Smith</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>78 (12d8+24)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Cha +5, Int +4</save>
    <skill>Investigation +4, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Common plus two more languages</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The matter smith makes two Manifested Force attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Manifested Force</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Spell Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 10 (2d6 + 3) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Manifested Force|5|2d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The matter smith casts one of the following spells, using Charisma as the spellcasting ability:

	• At will: mage armor, mage hand, prestidigitation
	• 1/Day each: create food and water, fabricate (as an action)</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Planar Smithing (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The matter smith magically manipulates the energy of the plane of existence it's on to produce one of the following effects (choose one or roll a d4):

1-2: Chains:
      The matter smith creates spectral bindings around a creature it can see within 30 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw or have the restrained condition until the end of its next turn.

3-4: Magic Shield:
The matter smith conjures a floating, spectral shield that grants the matter smith a +5 bonus to its AC until the shield disappears at the start of the matter smith's next turn. The first time a creature misses a melee attack roll against the matter smith while the shield is conjured, that creature takes 7 (2d6) force damage.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>mage armor, mage hand, prestidigitation, create food and water, fabricate</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 60,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Morte</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>chaotic good</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>22 (4d4+12)</hp>
    <speed>0 ft., fly 30 ft.(hover)</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Stealth +5, Arcana +3</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|5|1d4+3</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel p. 10,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Musteval Guardinal</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral good</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>38 (11d6)</hp>
    <speed>35 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Dex +5, Cha +4</save>
    <skill>Stealth +7, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Celestial, Common</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>radiant</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The musteval makes two Bone Blade attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bone Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage plus 3 (1d6) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Bone Blade|5|1d6+3+1d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The musteval casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Charisma as the spellcasting ability:

	• At will: dancing lights
	• 1/Day each: disguise self, invisibility</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Skirmish Movement</name>
      <text>When a creature ends its turn within 5 feet of the musteval, the musteval can move up to half its speed. This movement doesn't provoke opportunity attacks.</text>
    </reaction>
    <spells>dancing lights, disguise self, invisibility</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 33,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Nonaton Modron</name>
    <sortname>Modron, Nonaton</sortname>
    <ancestry>Modron</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful neutral</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>161 (19d10+57)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., fly 30 ft.(hover)</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save>Wis +7, Int +7</save>
    <skill>Investigation +7, Perception +11</skill>
    <passive>21</passive>
    <languages>Modron, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Axiomatic Mind</name>
      <text>The nonaton can't be compelled to act in a manner contrary to its nature or its instructions.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Combat Ready</name>
      <text>The nonaton has advantage on initiative rolls.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Disintegration</name>
      <text>If the nonaton dies, its body disintegrates into dust, leaving behind anything it was carrying.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The nonaton makes three Arm attacks and uses Pillar of Truth or Spellcasting.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Arm</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 13 (2d8 + 4) piercing damage, and if the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 14). Until this grapple ends, the nonaton can't use this arm against other targets. The nonaton has nine arms, each of which can grapple one target.</text>
      <attack>Arm|8|2d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Pillar of Truth</name>
      <text>The nonaton chooses a point on the ground that it can see within 60 feet of itself. A 60-foot-tall, 20-foot-radius cylinder of magical force rises from that point. Each creature in that area must make a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 21 (6d6) force damage, and the creature reverts to its original form (if it's in a different form) and can't assume a different form until the end of its next turn. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The nonaton casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 15):

	• At will: detect magic, dispel magic, mending (as an action)
	• 1/Day each: plane shift (self only), protection from evil and good</text>
    </action>
    <spells>detect magic, dispel magic, mending, plane shift, protection from evil and good</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 38,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Octon Modron</name>
    <sortname>Modron, Octon</sortname>
    <ancestry>Modron</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful neutral</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>187 (22d10+66)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., fly 30 ft.(hover), swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Wis +7, Int +7</save>
    <skill>Perception +11</skill>
    <passive>21</passive>
    <languages>Modron, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>11</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>psychic</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Axiomatic Mind</name>
      <text>The octon can't be compelled to act in a manner contrary to its nature or its instructions.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Combat Ready</name>
      <text>The octon has advantage on initiative checks.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Disintegration</name>
      <text>If the octon dies, its body disintegrates into dust, leaving behind anything it was carrying.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The octon makes three Tentacle attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tentacle</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 14 (3d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage plus 9 (2d8) lightning damage.</text>
      <attack>Tentacle|8|3d6+4+2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The octon casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 15):

	• At will: detect magic, dispel magic, mending (as an action)
	• 1/Day each: plane shift (self only), protection from evil and good</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Whirlwind of Tentacles (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The octon rapidly extends and spins its ring of tentacles. Each creature within 20 feet of the octon must succeed on a DC 16 Strength saving throw or be pulled up to 10 feet in a straight line toward the octon. Then, the octon makes two Tentacle attacks against each creature within 10 feet of itself.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>detect magic, dispel magic, mending, plane shift, protection from evil and good</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 40,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Planar Incarnate</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>20 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>333 (18d20+144)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>26</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>20</wis>
    <cha>20</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Perception +12</skill>
    <passive>22</passive>
    <languages>all</languages>
    <cr>22</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>necrotic, poison, radiant; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, restrained, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+7</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the incarnate fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The incarnate has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Planar Form</name>
      <text>An incarnate on the Upper Planes is a Celestial. An incarnate on the Lower Planes is a Fiend.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The incarnate deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The incarnate makes two Slam or Energy Bolt attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: 27 (3d12 + 8) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|15|3d12+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Energy Bolt</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +12 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 32 (5d12) necrotic damage if the incarnate is a Fiend or radiant damage if the incarnate is a Celestial.</text>
      <attack>Energy Bolt|12|5d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Planar Exhalation (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The incarnate exhales concentrated energy native to its plane in a 60-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 23 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 52 (8d12) necrotic damage if the incarnate is a Fiend or radiant damage if the incarnate is a Celestial, and the creature has the blinded condition until the end of the incarnate's next turn. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.

Blinded:
	• A blinded creature can't see and automatically fails any ability check that requires sight.
	• Attack rolls against the creature have advantage, and the creature's attack rolls have disadvantage.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 41</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Razorvine Blight</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>plant</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands Common but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, deafened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (can't see beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>If the blight is motionless at the start of combat, it has advantage on its initiative roll. If a creature hasn't observed the blight move or act, that creature must succeed on a DC 18 Intelligence (Investigation) check to discern that the blight is animate.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>The blight can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The blight makes two Claw attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit (with advantage if the target is missing any of its hit points), reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 5 (1d6 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|4|1d6+2</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Life-Draining Vines (Recharge 6)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>Snaking vines erupt from the blight. Each creature within 10 feet of it must make a DC 12 Dexterity saving throw, taking 9 (2d8) slashing damage on failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. If at least one of the creatures that failed this save isn't a Construct or an Undead, the blight regains 9 hit points.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 42,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Septon Modron</name>
    <sortname>Modron, Septon</sortname>
    <ancestry>Modron</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful neutral</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>204 (24d10+72)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., fly 30 ft.(hover), swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>18</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Wis +7, Int +8</save>
    <skill>Perception +11</skill>
    <passive>21</passive>
    <languages>all, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>lightning, psychic</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Axiomatic Mind</name>
      <text>The septon can't be compelled to act in a manner contrary to its nature or its instructions.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Combat Ready</name>
      <text>The septon has advantage on initiative checks.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Disintegration</name>
      <text>If the septon dies, its body disintegrates into dust, leaving behind anything it was carrying.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The septon makes four Tentacle attacks and uses Lightning Network or Spellcasting.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tentacle</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 15 (2d10 + 4) piercing damage, and if the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 14). Until this grapple ends, the septon can't use this tentacle against other targets. The septon has seven tentacles, each of which can grapple one target.</text>
      <attack>Tentacle|8|2d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Lightning Network</name>
      <text>The septon conjures a field of electricity that fills a 30-foot cube originating from itself before dissipating. Each creature in that area must make a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 33 (6d10) lightning damage and has the stunned condition for 1 minute. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only. A stunned creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The septon casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 16):

	• At will: detect magic, dispel magic, mending (as an action)
	• 1/Day each: plane shift (self only), protection from evil and good, sending</text>
    </action>
    <spells>detect magic, dispel magic, mending, plane shift, protection from evil and good, sending</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 40,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Shator Demodand</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>fiend</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>195 (23d10+69)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>21</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>20</cha>
    <save>Wis +8, Dex +7</save>
    <skill>Stealth +7, Perception +13</skill>
    <passive>23</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Demodand, Infernal, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>16</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire</resist>
    <immune>acid, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+5</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Boundless Movement</name>
      <text>The shator ignores difficult terrain, and magical effects can't reduce its speed. It can spend 5 feet of movement to automatically remove the grappled condition from itself.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Jailer (1/Day)</name>
      <recharge>1/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The shator can cast the imprisonment spell, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (chaining effect only; spell save DC 18).</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Liquefaction Ritual</name>
      <text>The shator can perform a 1-minute ritual that turns all willing farastus and kelubars of its choice within 60 feet of itself into a living liquid form. Each liquefied demodand becomes enough liquid to fill a flask. A demodand's liquefaction lasts until a shator uses an action to end it or a creature opens a container holding the liquid. While liquefied in this way, a demodand has the paralyzed condition despite any immunity to that condition, it has immunity to all damage, and any curse affecting it is suspended.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The shator has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Numbing Secretions</name>
      <text>A creature that touches the shator or hits it with a melee attack while within 5 feet of it must succeed on a DC 17 Dexterity saving throw or have disadvantage on attack rolls and its speed halved until the end of its next turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The shator makes one Bite attack and two Enervating Trident attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 17 (3d6 + 7) piercing damage plus 26 (4d12) acid damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 16 Constitution saving throw or have the paralyzed condition until the start of the shator's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Bite|12|3d6+7+4d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Enervating Trident</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 18 (2d10 + 7) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Enervating Trident|12|2d10+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Inhibitory Spray (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The shator exhales a spray of slime in a line 100 feet long and 5 feet wide. Each creature in that area must make a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 40 (9d8) acid damage and has the paralyzed condition for 1 minute. The creature repeats the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The shator casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 18, +10 to hit with spell attacks):

	• At will: invisibility (self only), suggestion
	• 1/Day each: dispel magic, plane shift (to Carceri only), scrying (as an action)</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Summon Demodand (1/Day)</name>
      <recharge>1/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The shator has a 50 percent chance of summoning its choice of 1d4 farastu demodands, 1d2 kelubar demodands, or 1 shator demodand. A summoned demodand appears in an unoccupied space within 60 feet of the shator, acts as an ally of the shator, and can't summon other demodands. It remains for 1 minute, until it or the shator dies, or until the shator dismisses it as an action.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>invisibility, suggestion, dispel magic, plane shift, scrying</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 28,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Shemeshka</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fiend (yugoloth)</type>
    <alignment>neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>162 (25d8+50)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., fly 30 ft.(hover)</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>21</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Wis +8, Dex +7, Cha +9, Int +10</save>
    <skill>Insight +8, Deception +9, Perception +8</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages>all, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>14</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire, lightning; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>acid, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+5</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Shemeshka carries a magic crown called the Razorvine Tiara. In the hands of anyone other than Shemeshka, the Razorvine Tiara functions as a tentacle rod that deals slashing damage instead of bludgeoning damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (4/Day)</name>
      <recharge>4/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If Shemeshka fails a saving throw, she can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Shemeshka has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Shemeshka uses Arcane Flux or Spellcasting. She then makes one Claw attack or one attack with her Razorvine Tiara.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Arcane Flux</name>
      <text>Shemeshka causes a surge of arcane energy to burst around one creature she can see within 120 feet of herself. The target must make a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, the target takes 45 (7d12) force damage and has the incapacitated condition until the end of its next turn. On a successful save, the target takes half as much damage only.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 10 (2d4 + 5) slashing damage plus 14 (4d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|10|2d4+5+4d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Razorvine Tiara</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: 10 (3d6) slashing damage plus 9 (2d8) necrotic damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw, or its speed is halved and it has disadvantage on attack rolls and saving throws until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Razorvine Tiara|10|3d6+2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Shemeshka casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 18):

	• At will: alter self, darkness, invisibility (self only), mage hand, prestidigitation
	• 2/Day each: detect thoughts, dimension door, suggestion
	• 1/Day each: banishment, contact other plane (as an action), mind blank</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Teleport (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>Shemeshka teleports, along with any equipment she is wearing or carrying, up to 60 feet to an unoccupied space she can see.</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Fell Counterspell (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>Shemeshka utters a magical word to interrupt a creature she can see that is casting a spell. If the spell is 5th level or lower, it fails and has no effect. If the spell is 6th level or higher, Shemeshka makes an Intelligence check (DC 10 + the spell's level). On a success, the spell fails and has no effect. Whatever the spell's level, the caster gains the poisoned condition until the end of its next turn.</text>
    </reaction>
    <spells>alter self, darkness, invisibility, mage hand, prestidigitation, detect thoughts, dimension door, suggestion, banishment, contact other plane, mind blank</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 46,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Society of Sensation Muse</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>14 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>44 (8d8+8)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Dex +5, Cha +5</save>
    <skill>Insight +4, Performance +7, Stealth +5, Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common plus two more languages</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The muse casts one of the following spells, using Charisma as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 13):

	• At will: dancing lights
	• 1/Day each: comprehend languages, hypnotic pattern</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The muse makes two Beguiling Resonance attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Beguiling Resonance</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Spell Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 90 ft., one target. Hit: 9 (2d8) psychic damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 13 Charisma saving throw or have disadvantage on the next attack roll it makes until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Beguiling Resonance|5|2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Enchanting Presence (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>Each creature within 30 feet of the muse must make a DC 13 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature has the charmed condition for 1 minute. On a successful save, the creature becomes immune to any muse's Enchanting Presence for 24 hours.

	Whenever the muse deals damage to the charmed creature, the charmed creature can repeat the saving throw, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>dancing lights, comprehend languages, hypnotic pattern</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 61,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Sunfly</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic good</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>2 (1d4)</hp>
    <speed>10 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>4</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>4</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands Celestial but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Sting</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 2 (1d4) piercing damage. Additionally, if the sunfly is on an Outer Plane, it injects the target with a toxin, the effect of which is determined by the sunfly's location:

Upper Plane. The target sheds bright light in a 5-foot radius until the end of its next turn.

Neutral Plane. If the target is concentration on a spell or similar effect, it makes the Constitution saving throw with disadvantage to maintain its concentration.

Lower Plane. The target's speed is reduced by 5 feet until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Sting|5|1d4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Illumination (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The sunfly sheds bright light in a 5-foot radius and dim light for an additional 5 feet, or it uses a bonus action to extinguish the light.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 47,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Swarm of Sunflies</name>
    <sortname>Sunflies, Swarm</sortname>
    <ancestry>Sunflies</ancestry>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic good</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>22 (5d8)</hp>
    <speed>10 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>6</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>4</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands Celestial but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Swarm</name>
      <text>The swarm can occupy another creature's space and vice versa, and the swarm can move through any opening large enough for a Tiny dragonfly. The swarm can't regain hit points or gain temporary hit points.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Stings</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 0 ft., one creature in the swarm's space. Hit: 10 (3d4 + 3) piercing damage, or 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage if the swarm has half of its hit points or fewer. Additionally, if the swarm is on an Outer Plane, it injects the target with a toxin, the effect of which is determined by the swarm's location:

Upper Plane. The target sheds bright light in a 5-foot radius until the end of its next turn. During that time, the invisible condition has no effect on it.

Neutral Plane. If the target is concentration on a spell or similar effect, it loses its concentration.

Lower Plane. The target's speed is reduced by 10 feet until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Stings|5|3d4+3</attack>
      <attack>Stings (Half HP)|5|1d4+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Dazzling Lights (Recharge 6)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>The swarm shines its lights in a dazzling display. Each creature within 15 feet of the swarm must succeed on a DC 10 Constitution saving throw or have the stunned condition for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Illumination (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The swarm sheds bright light in a 15-foot radius and dim light for an additional 15 feet, or it uses a bonus action to extinguish the light.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 47</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Time Dragon Wyrmling</name>
    <sortname>Time Dragon, Wyrmling</sortname>
    <ancestry>Time Dragon</ancestry>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>dragon</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>75 (10d8+30)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., climb 30 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Wis +4, Con +6, Dex +3, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Stealth +6, Arcana +6, History +9, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Draconic plus any two languages</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>blindsight 10 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The dragon makes three Rend attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rend</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d6 + 4) slashing damage plus 3 (1d6) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Rend|7|1d6+4+1d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Time Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The dragon exhales a wave of shimmering light in a 15-foot cone. Nonmagical objects and vegetation in that area that aren't being worn or carried crumble to dust. Each creature in that area must make a DC 14 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 27 (6d8) force damage and is magically weakened as it is desynchronized from the time stream. While the creature is in this state, attack rolls against it have advantage. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only. A weakened creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 51,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Transcendent Order Conduit</name>
    <sortname>Transcendent Order, Conduit</sortname>
    <ancestry>Transcendent</ancestry>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (Unarmored Defense)</ac>
    <hp>97 (15d8+30)</hp>
    <speed>50 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>19</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Wis +7, Cha +4</save>
    <skill>Performance +4, Acrobatics +7, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Common plus one more language</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Instinctive Reflexes</name>
      <text>The conduit has advantage on initiative rolls, and it can't have disadvantage on attack rolls.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Unarmored Defense</name>
      <text>While the conduit is wearing no armor and wielding no shield, its AC includes its Wisdom modifier.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Reactive</name>
      <text>The conduit can take up to three reactions per round but only one per turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The conduit makes three Unarmed Strike attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Unarmed Strike</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 11 (2d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, the conduit can choose one of the following additional effects (up to once per turn each):

Incapacitate. The target must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or have the incapacitated condition until the end of the conduit's next turn.

Push. The target is pushed up to 10 feet horizontally away from the conduit.</text>
      <attack>Unarmed Strike|7|2d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Deflect Attack</name>
      <text>In response to being hit by an attack roll, the conduit partially deflects the blow. The damage the conduit takes from the attack is reduced by 1d10.</text>
    </reaction>
    <reaction>
      <name>Don't Be There</name>
      <text>When the conduit must make a saving throw, it can move up to half its speed without provoking opportunity attacks. If its new position moves it out of range or otherwise makes it impossible to be targeted by the effect, the conduit avoids the effect entirely.</text>
    </reaction>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 62,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Transcendent Order Instinct</name>
    <sortname>Transcendent Order, Instinct</sortname>
    <ancestry>Transcendent Order</ancestry>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (Unarmored Defense)</ac>
    <hp>49 (9d8+9)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Wis +5, Cha +3</save>
    <skill>Performance +3, Acrobatics +5, Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common plus one more language</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Unarmored Defense</name>
      <text>While the instinct is wearing no armor and wielding no shield, its AC includes its Wisdom modifier.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Reactive</name>
      <text>The instinct can take up to three reactions per round but only one per turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The instinct makes three Unarmed Strike attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Unarmed Strike</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d8 + 3) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Unarmed Strike|5|1d8+3</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Deflect Blow</name>
      <text>In response to being hit by a melee attack roll, the instinct partially deflects the blow. The damage the instinct takes from the attack is reduced by 1d6.</text>
    </reaction>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 62,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Vargouille Reflection</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>fiend</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>22 (5d4+10)</hp>
    <speed>5 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>6</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>2</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands Abyssal, Infernal, and any languages it knew before becoming a vargouille, but it can't speak</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire, lightning, psychic</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The vargouille has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|4|1d6+2+3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Abyssal Curse</name>
      <text>The vargouille targets one Humanoid within 5 feet of itself that has the incapacitated condition. The target must succeed on a DC 12 Charisma saving throw or become cursed. The cursed target's Charisma decreases by 1 after each hour, as its head takes on fiendish aspects, and its Charisma can't increase. The curse doesn't advance while the target is in sunlight or the area of a daylight spell. When the cursed target's Charisma becomes 2, the target dies, and its head tears from its body and becomes a new vargouille reflection. Casting remove curse, greater restoration, or a similar spell on the target before the transformation is complete ends the curse and restores the target's Charisma.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Horrific Reflection (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The vargouille's head mimics that of a Humanoid the vargouille can see within 120 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 12 Wisdom saving throw or take 10 (3d6) psychic damage and have the frightened condition for 1 hour or until the vargouille loses concentration (as if concentration on a spell). If the target's saving throw is successful or if the effect ends on it, the target is immune to the Horrific Reflection of all vargouille reflections for 1 hour.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 52,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Warden Archon</name>
    <sortname>Archon, Warden</sortname>
    <ancestry>Archon</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful good</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>136 (16d10+48)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Wis +7, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +5, Athletics +8, Perception +10</skill>
    <passive>20</passive>
    <languages>all</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>lightning</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft., truesight 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Aura of Menace</name>
      <text>As long as the archon doesn't have the incapacitated condition, each creature of the archon's choice that starts its turn within 20 feet of the archon must make a DC 15 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature has the frightened condition until the start of its next turn. On a successful save, the creature is immune to all archons' Aura of Menace for 24 hours.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Eternal Vigil</name>
      <text>The archon can't be surprised. Moreover, it knows when any creature uses a portal it is assigned to guard.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The archon makes two Claw attacks and one Tracker's Bite attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 12 (2d6 + 5) slashing damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, the target has the grappled condition (escape DC 18). The archon can have only one creature grappled in this way at a time.</text>
      <attack>Claw|8|2d6+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tracker's Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 15 (3d6 + 5) piercing damage. If the target is a creature, for the next 24 hours, the archon knows the distance and direction to the target while they are both on the same plane of existence.</text>
      <attack>Tracker's Bite|8|3d6+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The archon casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Charisma as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 15):

	• At will: detect evil and good
	• 1/Day each: aid, continual flame, protection from evil and good, scrying (as an action)</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Teleport</name>
      <text>The archon teleports, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying, to an unoccupied space it can see within 120 feet of itself.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>detect evil and good, aid, continual flame, protection from evil and good, scrying</spells>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 18,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands,
		Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Turn of Fortune's Wheel</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Young Time Dragon</name>
    <sortname>Time Dragon, Young</sortname>
    <ancestry>Time Dragon</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>dragon</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>210 (20d10+100)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft., climb 40 ft., fly 80 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Wis +6, Con +9, Dex +5, Cha +7</save>
    <skill>Stealth +9, Arcana +9, History +13, Perception +10</skill>
    <passive>20</passive>
    <languages>Draconic plus any four languages</languages>
    <cr>11</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The dragon makes three Rend attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rend</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 12 (2d6 + 5) slashing damage plus 7 (2d6) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Rend|9|2d6+5+2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Time Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The dragon exhales a wave of shimmering light in a 30-foot cone. Nonmagical objects and vegetation in that area that aren't being worn or carried crumble to dust. Each creature in that area must make a DC 17 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 31 (7d8) force damage and is magically weakened as it is desynchronized from the time stream. While the creature is in this state, attack rolls against it have advantage. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only. A weakened creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself after it succeeds on two of these saves.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Morte's Planar Parade p. 51</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
</compendium>
