<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <item>
    <name>Mimir</name>
    <detail>rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <weight>5</weight>
    <text>This skull-shaped device is filled with knowledge. The device weighs 5 pounds and is covered with subtle etchings of planar sigils.
	As a bonus action, you can toss the device into the air, whereupon it floats at a distance of 1d3 feet from you and you can access its properties. While the mimir is floating, a creature other than you can use an action to grasp or net the device, either by making a successful unarmed strike against AC 22 or a successful DC 22 Dexterity (Acrobatics) check. You can use a bonus action to seize and stow the device.
	The device has AC 22, 25 hit points, immunity to poison and psychic damage, and resistance to all other damage. It is considered to be an object that is being worn while it is floating near you.

Esoteric Knowledge: While the device is floating, you can use an action to cast legend lore from the device. The device speaks the revealed lore aloud. Once this property has been used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.

Planar Knowledge: The device knows basic, useful information about the planes of existence. While the device is floating, it verbally answers questions you or anyone you designate poses to it about that topic. It knows the information about the planes in the Dungeon Master's Guide, as well as basic information about the gate-towns of the Outlands (presented in chapter 3 of Sigil and the Outlands).

Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands p. 13</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Portal Compass</name>
    <detail>uncommon</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This portable arcane instrument points in the direction of the last portal it passed through while it and the portal are on the same plane of existence. If that portal no longer exists, the needle becomes static until the compass passes through a new portal.

Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands p. 13</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Sensory Stone</name>
    <detail>uncommon</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This small, smooth stone contains the essence of a single experience.
	As an action, you or a willing creature you designate can touch the stone and experience the sensation as if it happened to the designated creature. The illusory experience is fleeting and harmless, however real it might feel in the moment.

Record Sensation: You can use your reaction to record a short sensation lasting no longer than 6 seconds experienced by a creature of your choice within 30 feet of yourself, infusing the essence of that experience into the stone. This replaces any sensation already stored within the stone.

Siphon Sensation: As a bonus action, you can draw on the stone's magic to end the charmed or frightened condition on yourself, destroying the stone in the process.

Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands p. 13</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Trinket (Gate Warden)</name>
    <type>G</type>
    <text>When you make your character, you can roll once on the Gate Warden Trinkets table, instead of on the Trinkets table in the Player's Handbook, for your starting trinket.

Gate Warden Trinkets:
d6 | Trinket
1 | A tiny vial pendant filled with a drop of honey that glows faintly.
2 | A small lead ingot that has a strange thumbprint pressed into it and whispers when held tightly.
3 | Two lodestone spheres that chime when they attract each other.
4 | A smoldering pebble of coal that, while always hot, doesn't burn skin, fur, scales, or clothing.
5 | A feather that sheds dim light in a 5-foot radius.
6 | A ring made from a chain link that, once donned, won't come off without pulling painfully hard.

Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands p. 7</text>
    <roll description="Trinket">1d6</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Trinket (Planar Philosopher)</name>
    <type>G</type>
    <text>When you make your character, you can roll once on the Planar Philosopher Trinkets table, instead of on the Trinkets table in the Player's Handbook, for your starting trinket.

Planar Philosopher Trinkets:
d6 | Trinket
1 | Locket with a picture of my mentor and an inscription I can't read.
2 | Bleached cranium rat skull with colored glass beads in its eye sockets.
3 | Torn parchment with half a rebus painted on it.
4 | Bracelet of twisted razorvine stems.
5 | Fragment of a bronze blade covered in verdigris.
6 | Broken holy symbol of a forgotten god.

Source:	Planescape: Adventures in the Multiverse - Sigil and the Outlands p. 8</text>
    <roll description="Trinket">1d6</roll>
  </item>
</compendium>
