<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <background>
    <name>Knight Of Solamnia</name>
    <proficiency>Athletics, Survival</proficiency>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>You have trained to be a valorous warrior known as a Knight of Solamnia. Strict rules guide your every action, and you work to uphold them as you strive to defend the weak and oppose evil. Your honor is as important to you as your life.

	• Skill Proficiencies: Athletics, Survival
	• Tool Proficiencies: One type of musical instrument
	• Languages: Two of your choice
	• Equipment: An insignia of rank, a deck of cards, a set of common clothes, and a pouch containing 10 gp

Source:	Dragonlance: Shadow of the Dragon Queen p. 30</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Squire Of Solamnia</name>
      <text>You gain the Squire of Solamnia feat.

In addition, the Knights of Solamnia provide you free, modest lodging and food at any of their fortresses or encampments.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Building a Knight of Solamnia Character</name>
      <text>Any class that has martial prowess can be a good fit in the Knights of Solamnia. Fighters and paladins make up the bulk of the knighthood's forces. Clerics (often with the War domain) can also be found among the knights' ranks.
	For a more unusual take on a Knight of Solamnia character, consider playing a bard of the College of Valor (or the College of Swords from Xanathar's Guide to Everything) or a barbarian devoted to the ideals of the nature god Habbakuk (perhaps adopting the Path of the Zealot from Xanathar's Guide to Everything).</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Knight of Solamnia Trinkets</name>
      <text>When you make your character, roll once on the Knight of Solamnia Trinkets table instead of on the Trinkets table in the Player's Handbook for your starting trinket.

Knight of Solamnia Trinkets:
d6 | Trinket
1 | A flat silver disk you record your heroics upon
2 | A piece of a fallen knight's armor
3 | A pendant featuring a crown, a rose, or a sword
4 | The pommel of your mentor's sword
5 | A meaningful favor from someone you defended—perhaps a handkerchief or glove
6 | A locket with a sketch of a silver dragon inside</text>
      <roll description="Trinket">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
  <background>
    <name>Mage Of High Sorcery</name>
    <proficiency>Arcana, History</proficiency>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Your talent for magic came to the attention of the Mages of High Sorcery, an organization of spellcasters that study magic and prevent its misuse. You've trained among the Mages, but whether or not you'll face the dangerous tests required to become a true member of the group remains to be determined. Your passion for studying magic has likely already predisposed you toward one of the organization's three orders: the benevolent Order of the White Robes, the balance-pursuing Order of the Red Robes, or the ruthless Order of the Black Robes.
	In the world of Krynn, many refer to the Mages of High Sorcery as the Wizards of High Sorcery. The organization accepts more than wizards, though, with sorcerers, warlocks, and other spellcasters included among their ranks.

	• Skill Proficiencies: Arcana, History
	• Languages: Two of your choice
	• Equipment: A bottle of colored ink, an ink pen, a set of common clothes, and a pouch containing 10 gp

Source:	Dragonlance: Shadow of the Dragon Queen p. 31</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Initiate Of High Sorcery</name>
      <text>You gain the Initiate of High Sorcery feat.

In addition, the Mages of High Sorcery provide you with free, modest lodging and food indefinitely at any occupied Tower of High Sorcery and for one night at the home of an organization member.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Building a Mage of High Sorcery Character</name>
      <text>Mages of High Sorcery are typically sorcerers, warlocks, or wizards and might have any subclass. Spellcasters who gain their magic through devotion are less likely to be welcomed among the traditionalist mages. Nevertheless, the Mages of High Sorcery are shrewd, and they rarely let unique opportunities or individuals pass them by. Even members of martial classes who train in magic might find a rare place among the group's three orders.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Mage of High Sorcery Trinkets</name>
      <text>When you make your character, roll once on the Mage of High Sorcery Trinkets table instead of on the Trinkets table in the Player's Handbook for your starting trinket.

Mage of High Sorcery Trinkets
d6 | Trinket
1 | An unopened letter from your first teacher
2 | A broken wand made of black, red, or white wood
3 | A scroll bearing an incomprehensible formula
4 | A purposeless device covered in colored stones that can fold into various enigmatic shapes
5 | A pouch or spell book emblazoned with the triple moon symbol of the Mages of High Sorcery
6 | A lens through which you can see Krynn's invisible black moon, Nuitari</text>
      <roll description="Trinket">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
</compendium>
