<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <item>
    <name>Hoopak of Throne's Command</name>
    <detail>very rare</detail>
    <type>M</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <weight>2</weight>
    <property>M,A,S,F,2H</property>
    <dmg1>1d6</dmg1>
    <dmgType>P</dmgType>
    <range>40/160</range>
    <text>A hoopak is a sturdy stick with a sling at one end and a pointed tip at the other.

This weapon is bedecked in ornate gold filigree and deep-blue and maroon jewels. You gain a +1 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with this weapon. Additionally, you gain proficiency in the Intimidation and Persuasion skills if you don't already have it.

Spellcasting: The weapon has 5 charges. You can use a bonus action and expend 1 or more of its charges to cast one of the following spells (save DC 16): Command (1 charge), Zone of Truth (2 charges), Compulsion (4 charges), Banishment (4 charges), or Dominate Person (5 charges).
	The weapon regains 1d4 expended charges daily at dawn.

Special: When you make a melee attack with this weapon, you ignore its ammunition property. You can use the hoopak as a martial ranged weapon. If you do, it uses the ammunition property, uses sling bullets, and deals 1d4 bludgeoning damage on a hit.

Ammunition: You can use a weapon that has the ammunition property to make a ranged attack only if you have ammunition to fire from the weapon. Each time you attack with the weapon, you expend one piece of ammunition. The ammunition of a firearm is destroyed upon use. Drawing the ammunition from a quiver, case, or other container is part of the attack. Loading a one-handed weapon requires a free hand. At the end of the battle, you can recover half your expended ammunition by taking a minute to search the battlefield.

If you use a weapon that has the ammunition property to make a melee attack, you treat the weapon as an improvised weapon. A sling must be loaded to deal any damage when used in this way.

Finesse: When making an attack with a finesse weapon, you use your choice of your Strength or Dexterity modifier for the attack and damage rolls. You must use the same modifier for both rolls.

Two-Handed: This weapon requires two hands to use. This property is relevant only when you attack with the weapon, not when you simply hold it.

Proficiency: martial, hoopak
Source:	The Book of Many Things p. 39,
		Dragonlance: Shadow of the Dragon Queen p. 188</text>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon attacks +1</modifier>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon damage +1</modifier>
    <roll>1d4</roll>
    <roll description="Recharge">1d4</roll>
  </item>
</compendium>
