<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <race>
    <name>Kender</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>During the mythical origins of Krynn, Reorx, god of craft, indulged in an age of unfettered creation. Many peoples sprang from his divine forge, but not all among them remained as the god created them. Altered by unbridled magic, a group of gnomes were transformed and gifted almost supernatural curiosity and fearlessness. These were the first kender.
	Originating on the world of Krynn, kender are diminutive Humanoids that look like humans with pointed ears and diverse appearances. Kender have a supernatural curiosity that drives them to adventure. Due to this inquisitiveness, many kender find themselves falling through portals to other planes and worlds.
	Kender sometimes amass impressive collections of curiosities. Some might collect mundane knickknacks or relics from magical sites, while others might become professional thieves.

Source:	Dragonlance: Shadow of the Dragon Queen p. 27</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different score by 1, or increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>The typical life span of a player character in the D&amp;D multiverse is about a century, assuming the character doesn't meet a violent end on an adventure. Members of some races, such as dwarves and elves, can live for centuries—a fact noted in the description of the race.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creature Type</name>
      <text>You are a Humanoid.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Fearless</name>
      <text>You have advantage on saving throws you make to avoid or end the frightened condition on yourself. When you fail a saving throw to avoid or end the frightened condition on yourself, you can choose to succeed instead. Once you succeed on a saving throw in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Kender Curiosity</name>
      <text>Thanks to the mystical origin of your people, you gain proficiency with one of the following skills of your choice: Insight, Investigation, Sleight of Hand, Stealth, or Survival.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Taunt</name>
      <text>You have an extraordinary ability to fluster creatures. As a bonus action, you can unleash a string of provoking words at a creature within 60 feet of yourself that can hear and understand you. The target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw, or it has disadvantage on attack rolls against targets other than you until the start of your next turn. The DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma modifier (choose when you select this race).
	You can use this bonus action a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>Your character can speak, read, and write Common and one other language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for the character. The Player's Handbook offers a list of widespread languages to choose from. The DM is free to add or remove languages from that list for a particular campaign.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
</compendium>
