<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <race>
    <name>Smutsia (HB)</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <speed>25</speed>
    <ability>Con +2, Int +1</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Intelligent and curious beings, Smutsia are eager to explore and figure out all sorts of things. Smutsia are mammals and can at most birth one child a year. When a Smutsia is approaching maturity, it is sent ut to explore more of the world and find new places to live. All Smutsia are monogamous and have one partner for life, which they may have many children with over their lifetime.
	Having lived mostly in burrows and explored during the night, most Smutsia are somewhat afraid of direct sunlight as they don't know what it might do to them.
	Your evolution from pangolins has lead to you having similar traits

Source:	Daniel (Homebrew)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Baby smutsia learn to walk within days after their birth, reaching maturity at around 7 years old. It is rare for a smutsia to live longer than 25 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Adult Smutsia stand 4 feet tall and 5 feet long, averaging 70 pounds. Your size is small.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d4
Height = 3 feet + 8 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 55 + (2d6 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Sizse Modifier">2d4</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Accustomed to life underground, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Hefty Claws</name>
      <text>Your claws have evolved to dig for various insects through differing terrain. You have a base burrowing speed of 15 feet. In addition, your claws serve as your natural weapons, which you can use to make unarmed strikes. If you hit, you deal 1d4 + your Strength modifier slashing damage.</text>
      <roll description="Slashing Damage">1d4+%1</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Natural Armor</name>
      <text>The tough keratin scales covering your entire body grant you a great defensive advantage. Your base armor class is 14 + your Dexterity modifier and is not lowered by having worse armor. Unarmored defenses granted by classes also start with this bonus.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Tuck and Ball</name>
      <text>As a reaction when attacked before knowing if it hit, you can tuck into a ball. Granting a +5 to Armor Class, advantage on Strength and Constitution saving throws, and disadvantage on Dexterity saving throws. In addition, your speed becomes 0 and cannot be raised. These effects end as you emerge on the start of your next turn. You can use this feature a number of times equivalent to your proficiency bonus, gaining back all expended uses after a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>You have disadvantage on attack rolls and on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight when you, the target of your attack, or whatever you are trying to perceive is in direct sunlight.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Undercommon.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Changeling (HB)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Changelings are a humanoid race of shapechangers who conceal their true identities behind false faces. Their gifts of mimicry allow them to appear as members of any humanoid culture, playing the part of a dwarf one day and a dragonborn the next. Although changelings can adopt any guise, most rely on a few established personas, each with a developed history and a network of friends and acquaintances.

Source:	Unfired Arcana (Homebrew)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different score by 1, or increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creature Type</name>
      <text>You are a Fey</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>You are Medium or Small. You choose the size when you select this race.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Divergent Persona</name>
      <text>You can gain proficiency with one skill of your choice and one tool or weapon of your choice. Define a unique identity associated with each of those proficiencies; establish the name, race, gender, age, and other details. While you are in the form of this persona, the related proficiency bonus is doubled for any ability check you make that uses that proficiency.
	Whenever you finish a long rest, you can replace one or both of these proficiencies with a different proficiency of the same kind. For each proficiency you replace in this way, you must also replace the associated persona with a different one associated with the new proficiency.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>As an action, you can reshape your body into a Medium or Small creature, or you can revert to your true form. A creature you take the form of can be one you have seen, or one from your imagination. Your form has no bearing on your game statistics. No matter what form you take, no more than two of your appendages can function as hands.
	While you have a humanlike shape, you can wear clothing and armor made for a Humanoid of your size. When you transform, any equipment you are wearing or carrying that can't be worn or carried by the new form falls to the ground in your space.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Unsettling Visage</name>
      <text>When a creature you can see makes an attack roll against you, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on the roll. You must use this feature before knowing whether the attack hits or misses. Using this trait reveals your shapeshifting nature to any creature within 30 feet that can see you. You can use this trait a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and two other languages that you and your DM agree is appropriate for your character.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Mimic (HB)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>The bane of dungeon delvers across the multiverse, few adventurers would suspect that the things in their nightmares might be sitting across the campfire. Only a handful of mimics ever learn to take a humanoid form, and those that do often live a very lonely existence. However, hope is never completely absent. Adventuring makes for strange company, and the bonds that form between companions are far stronger than any adhesive mucus.

Source:	Unfired Arcana (Homebrew)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different score by 1, or increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creature Type</name>
      <text>You are a Monstrosity</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>You are Medium or Small. You choose the size when you select this race.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Adhesive</name>
      <text>When you come into physical contact with a creature, you can attempt to grapple them as a reaction. You also have advantage on ability checks you make to initiate, maintain, or escape a grapple.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Your fanged maw is a natural melee weapon, which you can use to make unarmed strikes. On a hit, it deals additional damage equal to your proficiency bonus, and the attack's damage type changes to acid or piercing (your choice).</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You can see in dim light within 60 feet of yourself as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You discern colors in that darkness only as shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While you are motionless and in the form of an object, you can remain hidden even from creatures that can see you.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>As an action, you can reshape your body into a creature or object of the same size as yourself, or you can revert to your shapeless true form. A creature or object you take the form of can be one you have seen, or one from your imagination. Your form has no bearing on your game statistics. No matter what form you take, no more than two of your appendages can function as hands.
	While you have a humanlike shape, you can wear clothing and armor made for a Humanoid of your size. When you transform, any equipment you are wearing or carrying that can't be worn or carried by the new form falls to the ground in your space.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and one other language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for your character.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
</compendium>
