<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <race>
    <name>Autognome (UA)</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Autognomes are mechanical beings built by rock gnomes in their image, usually with a particular purpose in mind. For example, a gnome might build an autognome to be a steadfast colleague or a loyal companion. Sometimes, because of a malfunction or a unique circumstance, an autognome becomes separated from its creator and strikes out on its own.
	An autognome bears a resemblance to its creator, and most autognomes are programmed to speak and understand Gnomish. The internal components used in an autognome's manufacture can vary wildly; one autognome might have an actual beating heart in its chest cavity, while another might be powered by stardust or intricate clockwork gears.
	Roll on the Autognome History table or choose an entry to determine what event set your auto gnome on the path to adventure. If nothing on the table appeals to you, work with your DM to create an origin story for your autognome.

Autognome History:
d8 | Story
1 | Your creator gave you autonomy and urged you to follow your dreams.
2 | Your creator died, leaving you to fend for yourself.
3 | A temporary malfunction caused you to harm your creator, and you fled rather than face reprisal.
4 | A glitch caused you to forget your original programming. You don't remember who made you or where you came from.
5 | You were stolen from your creator and long to return to them.
6 | You didn't like how you were being treated by your creator, so you ran away from home.
7 | Your creator built you to complete a special mission.
8 | You felt trapped in the role for which you were built and abandoned your creator, determined to find a greater purpose.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 80: Travelers of the Multiverse p. 2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different one by 1, or you increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Like gnomes, autognomes can live for centuries, up to 500 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Autognomes are inclined toward Neutral Good.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Gnomes are between 3 and 4 feet tall and average about 40 pounds. Your size is Small.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d4
Height = 2 feet + 11 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 35 + your size modifier</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creature Type</name>
      <text>You are a construct</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Armored Casing</name>
      <text>You are encased in thin metal or some other durable material. While you aren't wearing armor, your base Armor Class is 13 + your Dexterity modifier.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Built for Success</name>
      <text>You can add a d4 to one attack roll, ability check, or saving throw you make, and you can do so after seeing the d20 but before the effects of the roll are resolved. You can use this trait a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Mechanical Nature</name>
      <text>You have resistance to poison damage and immunity to disease, and you have advantage on saving throws against being paralyzed or poisoned. You don't need to eat, drink, or breathe.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Sentry's Rest</name>
      <text>When you take a long rest, you spend at least 6 hours in an inactive, motionless state, instead of sleeping. In this state, you appear inert, but you aren't unconscious.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Specialized Design</name>
      <text>You gain two tool proficiencies of your choice.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>True Life</name>
      <text>If the Mending spell is cast on you, you can expend a Hit Die, roll it, and regain a number of hit points equal to the roll plus your Constitution modifier (minimum of 1 hit point). In addition, your creator designed you to benefit from common spells that preserve life but that normally don't affect Constructs: Cure Wounds, Healing Word, and Spare the Dying.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and one other language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for the character.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Elf, Astral (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <proficiency>Perception</proficiency>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Long ago, groups of elves ventured from the Feywild to the Astral Plane to be closer to their gods. Life in the Silver Void has imbued their souls with a spark of divine light. That light manifests as a starry gleam in an astral elf's eyes.
	Because nothing ages in the Astral Plane, astral elves from that plane are thousands of years old, and their longevity gives them an unusual perspective on time. Some are prone to melancholy, while others display an absence of feeling. Many look for creative ways to occupy themselves. Whether they choose to live in quiet contemplation or strike out to explore the reaches of the multiverse, they tend to see things through the lens of time as having little or no meaning to them.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Travelers of The Multiverse p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different score by 1, or increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Astral elves who don't dwell on the Astral Plane can live to be over 750 years old.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Elves love freedom, variety, and self-expression, so they lean strongly toward the gentler aspects of chaos. They value and protect others' freedom as well as their own, and they are more often good than not.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creature Type</name>
      <text>You are a Humanoid.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d10
Height = 4 feet + 6 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 90 + (1d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d10</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">1d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Elves range from under 5 to over 6 feet tall and have slender builds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d10
Height = 4 feet + 6 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 90 + (1d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d10</roll>
      <roll description="Height Modifier">1d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Astral Fire</name>
      <text>You know one of the following cantrips of your choice: dancing lights, light, or sacred flame. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for it. (Choose when you select this race).</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light and in darkness as if it were dim light. You discern colors in that darkness only as shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>You have advantage on saving throws you make to avoid or end the charmed condition on yourself.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Keen Senses</name>
      <text>You have proficiency in the Perception skill.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Radiant Soul</name>
      <text>When you succeed on a death save, you can regain a number of hit points equal to your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma modifier (choose when you select this race). You can't use this trait again until you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Trance</name>
      <text>Elves don't need to sleep. Instead, they meditate deeply, remaining semiconscious, for 4 hours a day. (The Common word for such meditation is "trance.") While meditating, you can dream after a fashion; such dreams are actually mental exercises that have become reflexive through years of practice. After resting in this way, you gain the same benefit that a human does from 8 hours of sleep.
	If you meditate during a long rest, you finish the rest after only 4 hours. You otherwise obey all the rules for a long rest; only the duration is changed.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Trance Proficiencies</name>
      <text>Whenever you finish a long rest using your Trance trait, you gain two proficiencies, each one with a weapon or a tool of your choice (selected from the "Equipment" chapter of the Player's Handbook). You mystically acquire these proficiencies by drawing them from shared elven memory, and you retain them until you finish your next long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Elvish. Elvish is fluid, with subtle intonations and intricate grammar. Elven literature is rich and varied, and their songs and poems are famous among other races. Many bards learn their language so they can add Elvish ballads to their repertoires.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Giff (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Giff are tall, broad-shouldered folk with hippo-like features. Some have smooth skin, while others have short bristles on their faces and the tops of their heads. As beings of impressive size and unforgettable appearance, giff are noticed wherever they go.
	Storytelling is a rich tradition among giff, and it's not uncommon to see a giff recounting their past exploits to an enraptured crowd. Having a friendly giff nearby when a tavern brawl erupts can also be useful, for a giff can usually more than hold their own when pleasant revelry devolves into fisticuffs.
	The giff are split into two camps concerning how their name is pronounced. Half of them say it with a hard g, half with a soft g. Disagreements over the correct pronunciation often blossom into hard feelings, loud arguments, and headbutting contests, but rarely escalate beyond that.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Travelers of The Multiverse p. 2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different score by 1, or increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>The typical life span of a player character in the D&amp;D multiverse is about a century, assuming the character doesn't meet a violent end on an adventure. Members of some races, such as dwarves and elves, can live for centuries—a fact noted in the description of the race.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Player characters, regardless of race, typically fall into the same ranges of height and weight that humans have in our world. If you'd like to determine your character's height or weight randomly, consult the Random Height and Weight table in the Player's Handbook, and choose the row in the table that best represents the build you imagine for your character.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creature Type</name>
      <text>You are a Humanoid.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Speed</name>
      <text>Your walking speed is 30 feet, and you have a swimming speed equal to your walking speed.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Damage Dealer</name>
      <text>Like a hippopotamus in a crystalware shop, you are naturally adept at damaging things. When you roll a 1 on a damage die for a melee attack, you can reroll the die and use the new roll. You can do so no more than once per turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Hippo Build</name>
      <text>You have advantage on Strength-based ability checks and Strength saving throws. In addition, you count as one size larger when determining your carrying capacity and the weight you can push, drag, or lift.</text>
      <special>powerful build</special>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>Your character can speak, read, and write Common and one other language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for the character. The Player's Handbook offers a list of widespread languages to choose from. The DM is free to add or remove languages from that list for a particular campaign.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Hadozee (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Hadozees are people with simian features that long ago adapted to live among the tall trees of their home world. They are natural climbers, with feet as dexterous as their hands, even to the extent of having opposable thumbs. Membranes of skin hang loosely from their arms and legs. When stretched taut, these membranes enable a hadozee to glide.
	The first hadozees were hunted by large natural predators. To survive in this hostile environment, they developed an instinctual sense of community. Today, that same instinct compels many hadozees to cultivate friendships, knowing there is safety in numbers.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 80: Travelers of the Multiverse p. 3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different one by 1, or you increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>The typical life span of a player character in the D&amp;D multiverse is about a century, assuming the character doesn't meet a violent end on an adventure. Members of some races, such as dwarves and elves, can live for centuries—a fact noted in the description of the race.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>You are Medium or Small. You choose the size when you select this race.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creature Type</name>
      <text>You are Humanoid.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Speed</name>
      <text>You have a climbing speed equal to your walking speed.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Dexterous Feet</name>
      <text>You can take the Use an Object action as a bonus action.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Glide</name>
      <text>If you are not incapacitated or wearing heavy armor, you can extend your skin membranes and glide. When you do so, you can perform the following aerial maneuvers:

	• When you fall, you can move up to 5 feet horizontally for every 1 foot you descend.

	• When you would take damage from a fall, you can use your reaction to reduce the fall's damage to 0.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and one other language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for the character.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Plasmoid (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <resist>acid, poison</resist>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Plasmoids are amorphous beings with no typical shape. In the presence of other folk, they often adopt a similar form, but there's little chance of mistaking a plasmoid for anything else. They consume food by osmosis, the way an amoeba does, and excrete waste through tiny pores. They breathe by absorbing oxygen through another set of pores,and their limbs are strong and flexible enough to grasp and manipulate weapons and tools. Although most plasmoids are translucent gray, they can alter their color and translucence by absorbing dyes through their pores.
	Plasmoids don't have internal organs of the usual sort. Their bodies are composed of cells, fibers, plasma-like ooze, and clusters of nerves called ganglia. These nerves enable a plasmoid to detect light, heat, texture, sound, pain, and vibrations. Plasmoids can stiffen the outer layers of their bodies to maintain a human like shape, so they can wear clothing and accessories. They speak by forcing air out of tubular cavities that constrict to produce sound.
	When plasmoids sleep, they lose their rigidity and spread out and are sometimes mistaken for a rock or some other feature of the environment.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 80: Travelers of the Multiverse p. 3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different one by 1, or you increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>You are Medium or Small. You choose the size when you select this race.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creature type</name>
      <text>You are an Ooze.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Amorphous</name>
      <text>You can squeeze through a space as narrow as 1 inch wide, provided you are wearing and carrying nothing. You also have advantage on ability checks you make to initiate or escape a grapple.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light and in darkness as if it were dim light. You discern colors in that darkness only as shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>You can hold your breath for 1 hour.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Natural Resilience</name>
      <text>You have resistance to acid and poison damage, and you have advantage on saving throws against being poisoned.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Shape Self</name>
      <text>If you are not incapacitated, you can reshape your body to give yourself a head, one or two arms, one or two legs, and makeshift hands and feet, or you can revert to a limbless blob (no action required).
	As a bonus action, you can extrude a pseudopod that is up to 6 inches wide and 10 feet long or reabsorb it into your body. You can use this pseudopod to manipulate an object, open an unlocked door or container, stow or retrieve an item from an open container, or pour out the contents of a container. The pseudopod can't attack, activate magic items, or carry more than 10 pounds.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and one other language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for the character.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Thri-kreen (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Thri-kreen have insectile features and two pairs of arms. Their bodies are encased in protective chitin. They can alter the coloration of this carapace to blend in with their natural surroundings.

Although thri-kreen don't sleep, they do require periods of inactivity to revitalize themselves. During these periods, they are fully conscious and aware of what's happening around them.

Thri-kreen speak by clacking their mandibles and waving their antennae, indicating to other thri-kreen what they are thinking and feeling. Other creatures find this method of communication difficult to interpret and impossible to duplicate. To interact with other folk, thri-kreen rely on a form of telepathy.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 80: Travelers of the Multiverse p. 3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different one by 1, or you increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>You are Medium or Small. You choose the size when you select this race.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creature type</name>
      <text>You are a Monstrosity.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Chameleon Carapace</name>
      <text>While you aren't wearing armor, your carapace gives you a base Armor Class of 13 + your Dexterity modifier.

As an action, you can change the color of your carapace to match the color and texture of your surroundings, giving you advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide in those surroundings.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light and in darkness as if it were dim light. You discern colors in that darkness only as shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Secondary Arms</name>
      <text>You have two slightly smaller secondary arms below your primary pair of arms. The secondary arms function like your primary arms, with the following exceptions:

You can use a secondary arm to wield a weapon that has the light property, but you can't use a secondary arm to wield other kinds of weapons.

You can't wield a shield with a secondary arm</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Sleepless Revitalization</name>
      <text>You do not require sleep and can choose to remain conscious during a long rest, though you must still refrain from strenuous activity to gain the benefit of the rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Thri-kreen Telepathy</name>
      <text>You have the magical ability to communicate mentally with any number of willing creatures you can see within 120 feet of you. A contacted creature doesn't need to share a language with you, but it must be able to understand at least one language. Your telepathic link to a creature is broken if you and the creature move more than 120 feet apart, if either of you is incapacitated, or if either of you mentally breaks the contact (no action required).</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and one other language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for the character.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
</compendium>
