<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <race>
    <name>Kender (UA)</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Native to the world of Krynn, Kender are diminutive Humanoids that look like humans with pointed ears and diverse appearances. Kender have a supernatural curiosity that drives them on to adventures big and small. This curiosity is said to be connected to the whimsical magic of the Feywild, that some believe kender have a high affinity for. Due to their curiosity, many kender have found themselves falling through gates and portals to other planes and worlds.
	Unknown to most mortals, a magical phenomenon surrounds a kender. Spurred by their curiosity and love for trinkets, curios, and keepsakes, a kender's pouches or pockets will be magically filled with these objects. No one knows where these objects come from, not even the kender. This has led many kender to be mislabeled as thieves when they fish these items out of their pockets.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different score by 1, or increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>The typical life span of a player character in the D&amp;D multiverse is about a century, assuming the character doesn't meet a violent end on an adventure. Members of some races, such as dwarves and elves, can live for centuries—a fact noted in the description of the race.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creature Type</name>
      <text>You are a Humanoid.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Brave</name>
      <text>You have advantage on saving throws you make to avoid or end the frightened condition on yourself.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Kender Ace</name>
      <text>Starting at 3rd level, you possess a magical ability to pull an item out of a bag or another container; as a bonus action, you can reach into a container you're carrying and roll on the Kender Aces table to determine what item you pull out. The object glimmers softly and disappears after 1 hour. You can use this bonus action a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Kender Aces:
d6 | Item
1 | 5d6 gold pieces
2 | 1 simple weapon of your choice that has the light property
3 | 1 item of your choice from the Adventuring Gear table in the Player's Handbook. The item must cost no more than 1 gp and weigh no more than 1 lb.
4 | 1 random item from the Trinkets table in the Player's Handbook.
5 | Your choice of a crowbar or a grappling hook
6 | 1 item of your choice from the Tools table in the Player's Handbook. The item must cost no more than 10 gp.</text>
      <roll description="Item">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Gold Pieces">5d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Taunt</name>
      <text>You have a supernatural ability to home in on a creature's emotional raw nerves and craft a taunt that flusters that creature. As a bonus action, you can unleash a barrage of insults at a creature within 60 feet of you that can hear and understand you. The target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw (DC equal to 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Charisma modifier), or it has disadvantage on attack rolls until the start of your next turn.
	You can use this bonus action a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>Your character can speak, read, and write Common and one other language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for the character. The Player's Handbook offers a list of widespread languages to choose from. The DM is free to add or remove languages from that list for a particular campaign.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
</compendium>
