<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5">
  <race>
    <name>Brutan (HB)</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Str +2, Con +2</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>The imposing brutan are a proud group of saurians that originate from nomadic tribes found in the lush deserts of the far reaches of the world. Seen as monsters by most due to their stature and weaponized biology, the brutan face many difficulties acclimating to new cultures. Oftentimes, mercenary groups will raid brutan caravans for supplies and captives, taking advantage of their low numbers. Despite this, the brutan remain an honorable people and usually reciprocate kindness when it is given. Although their honorable ways have also coerced some tribes to enact vengeance against those who have wronged their people.

Source:	rattatooey (Homebrew)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creature Type</name>
      <text>You are a humanoid. You determine your appearance and whether you resemble any of your kin.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>You are Large.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>You have a powerful fanged maw that you can use to make unarmed strikes. When you hit with it, the strike deals 1d6 + your Strength modifier piercing damage, instead of the bludgeoning damage normal for an unarmed strike.
	Immediately after hitting, you can try to grapple the target as a bonus action. Until this grapple ends, you can't bite another target.</text>
      <roll description="Unarmed Strike, Piercing Damage">1d6+%1</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Focus</name>
      <text>You have advantage on saving throws to avoid or end the frightened condition on yourself.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Natural Armor</name>
      <text>Your body is covered in thick scales and bony plates. While you aren't wearing armor, your base Armor Class is 13 + your Constitution modifier.</text>
      <special>Unarmored Defense: Constitution</special>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Primal Vigor</name>
      <text>When under pressure, your predatory instincts grant you guidance in combat. When you hit a target with a melee attack, you can cause the target to take extra damage equal to your proficiency bonus. While you are missing half or more of your hit points, you also gain temporary hit points equal to your proficiency bonus.
	You can use this trait a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, but you can use it no more than once per turn. You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and one other language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for your character.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
</compendium>
