<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Sorcerer</name>
    <!-- Sorcerous Origin: Mage of Prismari (UA) -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sorcerous Origin: Mage of Prismari (UA)</name>
        <text>Mages of Prismari use surges of elemental energy to express who they are and how they see the world. To them, magic and motion are one and the same; both are exhibitions of raw creativity through which masterpieces are made. In their pursuit of the arts, some Prismari mages focus on perfecting the fine details of their technique, while others prefer to unleash their wild creative visions in dazzling spectacles of elemental power.

Upon selecting the Mage of Prismari subclass, you gain two features: Creative Skills and Kinetic Artistry.
	In this subclass's features, any reference to your class refers to the class from which you gained the subclass. If you're a druid, the College of Prismari counts as your circle; if you're a sorcerer, the magic of the college is the origin of your sorcery; and if you're a wizard, the college represents your arcane tradition.
	When you subsequently reach a level in your class that gives you a subclass feature, you gain one feature of your choice from the options presented here. Each feature has a class level prerequisite, as noted beneath its name. You must meet that prerequisite to gain the feature.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 4</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Creative Skills (Mage of Prismari (UA))</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you gain proficiency in two of the following skills of your choice: Acrobatics, Athletics, Nature, or Performance.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 4</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Kinetic Artistry (Mage of Prismari (UA))</name>
        <text>Also at 1st level, you can Dash as a bonus action. When you take this bonus action, choose one of the following additional effects:

Boreal Sweep. Icy water swirls around you. Until the end of your turn, you can move across the surface of water as if it were harmless solid ground. Additionally, when you leave a space within 5 feet of a creature, you can force that creature to make a Strength saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the creature is knocked prone. A creature can be affected by the water only once each turn.

Scorching Whirl. Flames wreath your steps. Once before the end of your turn, you can force each creature within 5 feet of you to make a Dexterity saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failure, a creature takes fire damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcasting modifier.

Thunderlight Jaunt. You take on a nimble lightning form. Until the end of your turn, you can move through the space of other creatures, and you do not provoke opportunity attacks. If you end your turn inside a creature's space, you are pushed into the nearest unoccupied space.

You can use a bonus action in this way a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 4</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Favored Medium (Mage of Prismari (UA))</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you have honed your forms of elemental expression to best suit your ideas. Choose one of the following damage types: cold, fire, or lightning. You gain resistance to that damage type.
	Additionally, when you cast a spell using a spell slot that deals the chosen damage type, you emit a spectacular aura of artistry, which extends 5 feet from you in every direction (but not through total cover) and lasts until the end of your next turn. While the aura is active, each creature of your choice has resistance to your chosen damage type while within the aura, as you shape your favored elemental medium around them.
	You can change your choice of damage type whenever you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 5</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Focused Expression (Mage of Prismari (UA))</name>
        <text>At 14th level, honing your talents, you skillfully infuse your motions with even more potent expressions of elemental might. Once per turn when you deal damage to at least one target, you gain an additional effect determined by the damage type chosen for your Favored Medium feature:

Cold. One of the targets of your choice takes an additional 1d6 cold damage and must make a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the target's speed is reduced by 10 feet until the end of its next turn, as ice mires it. A target can be affected by the ice only once per round.

Fire. One of the targets of your choice takes an additional 1d6 fire damage. Fortifying flames then dance around one creature of your choice within 30 feet of you. The chosen creature gains 1d6 temporary hit points.

Lightning. One of the targets of your choice takes an additional 1d6 lightning damage and must make a Dexterity saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the target is unable to take reactions until the end of its next turn, as residual lightning shocks its form.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 5</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Impeccable Physicality (Mage of Prismari (UA))</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, your relentless dedication and training have instilled an outstanding sense of precision and grace in your art. You gain proficiency in Dexterity saving throws if you do not already have it. Additionally, when you make a Dexterity saving throw, you can treat a d20 roll of a 9 or lower as a 10.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 5</text>
        <proficiency>Dexterity</proficiency>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Impeccable Physicality (Mage of Prismari (UA))</name>
        <text>At 18th level, your relentless dedication and training have instilled an outstanding sense of precision and grace in your art. You gain proficiency in Dexterity saving throws if you do not already have it. Additionally, when you make a Dexterity saving throw, you can treat a d20 roll of a 9 or lower as a 10.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 5</text>
        <proficiency>Dexterity</proficiency>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Sorcerous Origin: Mage of Quandrix (UA) -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sorcerous Origin: Mage of Quandrix (UA)</name>
        <text>For those who become Mages of Quandrix, math and magic go hand-in-hand. Such individuals learn to break down natural phenomena into their core numerical components and, through manipulating those, alter reality on a whim. Their talents range from tangible physics, like multiplying plant growth and redistributing elements of probability and acceleration, to bizarrely theoretical exercises that warp the fundamentals of space and self.

Upon selecting the Mage of Quandrix subclass, you gain two features: Quandrix Spells and Functions of Probability.
	In this subclass's features, any reference to your class refers to the class from which you gained the subclass. If you're a sorcerer, the magic of Quandrix is part of your sorcerous origin, and if you're a wizard, the college represents your arcane tradition.
	When you subsequently reach a level in your class that gives you a subclass feature, you gain one feature of your choice from the options presented here. Each feature has a class level prerequisite, as noted beneath its name. You must meet that prerequisite to gain the feature.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 5</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Quandrix Spells (Mage of Quandrix (UA))</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you learn the cantrip guidance and the 1st-level spell guiding bolt. You learn additional spells when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown on the Quandrix Spells table.
	Each of these spells counts as a class spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of spells you know. If you are a wizard, you can add these spells to your spellbook upon learning them, without expending any gold, and prepare them as normal.

Mage of Quandrix Expanded Spells:
Spell Level | Spells
Cantrip | Guidance
1st | Guiding Bolt
3rd | enlarge/reduce, spike growth
5th | aura of vitality, haste
7th | control water, freedom of movement
9th | circle of power, passwall

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 6</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Functions of Probability (Mage of Quandrix (UA))</name>
        <text>Also at 1st level, by iterating on the mathematical patterns of reality, you can nudge chance to tilt around a creature. When you cast a spell using a spell slot that targets at least one creature, you can choose that creature or another creature within 30 feet of it (including yourself) and add one of the following effects:

Diminishing Function. The chosen creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC, or the creature must roll a d6 and subtract the number rolled from the next attack roll it makes before the start of your next turn.

Supplemental Function. Once before the start of your next turn, the chosen creature can roll a d6 and add the number rolled to an attack roll or a saving throw of its choice. The creature can roll the d6 after rolling the d20 but must decide before any effects of the roll occur.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 6</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Velocity Shift (Mage of Quandrix (UA))</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you learn to manipulate kinetic formulas and alter the velocity of another creature. When a creature you can see starts its turn or moves to a space within 30 feet of you, you can use your reaction to force the creature to make a Charisma saving throw against your spell save DC, which it can choose to fail. On a failure, the creature is teleported to an unoccupied space of your choice that you can see within 30 feet of you.
	You can use your reaction in this way a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 6</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Null Equation (Mage of Quandrix (UA))</name>
        <text>At 14th level, through careful calculations, you beset your enemies with abstract equations that reduce their might. Once per turn, immediately after dealing damage to a creature, you can force the creature to make a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failure, the creature has disadvantage on Strength and Dexterity saving throws, and its weapon attacks deal only half damage. These effects last until the start of your next turn.
	You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 6</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Quantum Tunneling (Mage of Quandrix (UA))</name>
        <text>At 14th level, your mathematical expertise extends to altering the foundational equations of your very being. You gain resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage.
	Additionally, you can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain, but you take 1d10 force damage for every 5 feet you move while inside another creature or object. If you end your turn inside a creature or an object, you are shunted into the nearest unoccupied space you last occupied.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 6</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Quantum Tunneling (Mage of Quandrix (UA))</name>
        <text>At 18th level, your mathematical expertise extends to altering the foundational equations of your very being. You gain resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage.
	Additionally, you can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain, but you take 1d10 force damage for every 5 feet you move while inside another creature or object. If you end your turn inside a creature or an object, you are shunted into the nearest unoccupied space you last occupied.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 6</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
