<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Warlock</name>
    <!-- Otherworldly Patron: Mage of Lorehold (UA) -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Patron: Mage of Lorehold (UA)</name>
        <text>Mages of Lorehold are particularly concerned with the forces that underlie and drive history. Drawing inspiration from the scholars and adventurers of old, they manifest the arcane power of the past through ethereal dioramas and fantastical battle prowess. Lorehold mages are often found with a long-dead spirit summoned at their side—for who better to learn ancient history from than one who has experienced it first-hand?

Upon selecting the Mage of Lorehold subclass, you gain two features: Lorehold Spells and Ancient Companion.
	In this subclass's features, any reference to your class refers to the class from which you gained the subclass. If you're a bard, the College of Lorehold counts as your college; if you're a warlock, the magic of the college serves as your patron; and if you're a wizard, the college represents your arcane tradition.
	When you subsequently reach a level in your class that gives you a subclass feature, you gain one feature of your choice from the options presented here. Each feature has a class level prerequisite, as noted beneath its name. You must meet that prerequisite to gain the feature.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 2</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Lorehold Spells (Mage of Lorehold (UA))</name>
        <text>Beginning at 1st level, you learn the cantrip sacred flame and the 1st-level spell comprehend languages. You learn additional spells when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown on the Lorehold Spells table.
	Each of these spells counts as a class spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of spells you know. If you are a wizard, you can add these spells to your spellbook upon learning them, without expending any gold, and prepare them as normal.

Mage of Lorehold Expanded Spells:
Spell Level | Spells
Cantrip | Sacred Flame
1st | Comprehend Languages
3rd | knock, locate object
5th | speak with dead, spirit guardians
7th | arcane eye, stone shape
9th | destructive wave, legend lore

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 2</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ancient Companion (Mage of Lorehold (UA))</name>
        <text>Also at 1st level, you learn to call on the spirits of the ancient dead and house them temporarily in the remnants of old statues, so they may remain longer on this plane to bolster your studies and aid you in battle.
	Whenever you finish a short or long rest, you can call forth and bond with one such spirit, who comes to inhabit a Medium, freestanding statue within 10 feet of you to serve as your ancient companion. See this creature's game statistics in the Ancient Companion stat block, which uses your proficiency bonus (PB) in several places. When you bond with your ancient companion, choose the type of spirit you bond with: Healer, Sage, or Warrior. Your choice of spirit determines certain traits in its stat block. The statue determines the spirit's appearance.
	The ancient companion is friendly to you and your companions and obeys your commands. In combat, the companion shares your initiative count, but it takes its turn immediately after yours. It can move and use its reaction on its own, but the only action it takes on its turn is the Dodge action, unless you take a bonus action on your turn to command it to take another action. That action can be one in its stat block or some other action. If you are incapacitated, the companion can take any action of its choice, not just Dodge.
	As an action, you can touch the ancient companion and expend a spell slot of 1st-level or higher. The ancient companion regains a number of hit points equal to 10 times the level of spell slot expended.
	The companion perishes when it drops to 0 hit points, when you bond with a new ancient companion at the end of a short or long rest, or when you die. When the companion perishes, the spirit within returns to its plane of origin, and the statue becomes an inert object.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 2</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Lessons of the Past (Mage of Lorehold (UA))</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, through your studies, you learn how to better listen and take to heart the teachings of history. When you bond with your ancient companion, you gain the following additional benefits depending on the type of spirit you chose:

Healer. Your hit point maximum increases by an amount equal to your level in this class, and you gain the same number of hit points. When you regain hit points from a spell, you regain an additional 1d8 hit points.

Sage. You have advantage on ability checks using the Arcana, History, Nature, and Religion skills. Additionally, once per turn, when you deal damage to a creature with a spell of 1st-level or higher, you can deal an additional 1d8 force damage to that creature.

Warrior. If you use your action to cast a cantrip, you can make one weapon attack as part of that action. If that weapon attack hits, the target takes an additional 1d8 radiant damage.

When you bond with a new ancient companion of a different type, you immediately lose the benefits of your previous companion and gain the benefits from the new companion's type.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 3</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>War Echoes (Mage of Lorehold (UA))</name>
        <text>At 10th level, by pulling from the magic of the past, you can cause your opponent's old wounds to resonate anew. Once per turn, when a creature you can see hits a target with an attack roll, you can use your reaction to force the target to make a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failure, the target becomes vulnerable to one of the damage types dealt by the attack. This vulnerability lasts until the end of the target's next turn and affects the damage dealt by the triggering attack.
	You can use your reaction in this way a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 3</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>History's Whims (Mage of Lorehold (UA))</name>
        <text>Startign at 14th level, through steeping yourself in the chaotic whims of history, you learn how to briefly channel the wild nature of time itself. As a bonus action, you can enter a state of chronal chaos. When you enter this state, and at the start of each of your subsequent turns while in this state, you gain one of the following benefits of your choice:

Luck. You receive brief flashes of the future, steeling yourself against oncoming assaults. Whenever you make a saving throw against an effect that deals damage, you can roll a d6 and add the number rolled to the total.

Resistance. You rewind time, knitting together injuries as they occur. You have resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage.

Swiftness. Time stutters, slowing others but hurtling you forward. Your movement speed increases by 15 feet, and you do not provoke opportunity attacks.

The benefit lasts until the start of your next turn. You cannot choose the same benefit two rounds in a row.
	The state lasts for 1 minute and ends early if you're incapacitated. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot of 4th level or higher to use it again.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 4</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Otherworldly Patron: Mage of Silverquill (UA) -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Patron: Mage of Silverquill (UA)</name>
        <text>Mages of Silverquill hone the power of words. They channel the magic of light and shadow through words, whether spoken aloud, written, or signed through gestures. The words of a mage of Silverquill bring salvation to their allies and despair to their enemies.

Upon selecting the Mage of Silverquill subclass, you gain two features: Eloquent Apprentice and Silvery Barbs.
	In this subclass's features, any reference to your class refers to the class from which you gained the subclass. If you're a bard, the College of Silverquill counts as your college, if you're a warlock, the college counts as your patron, and if you're a wizard, the college counts as your tradition.
	When you subsequently reach a level in your class that gives you a subclass feature, you gain one feature of your choice from the options presented here. Each feature has a class level prerequisite, as noted beneath its name. You must meet that prerequisite to gain the feature.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 6</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Eloquent Apprentice (Mage of Silverquill (UA))</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you learn one cantrip of your choice, either sacred flame or vicious mockery. It doesn't count against the number of cantrips you know, and it is added to your class spell list if it isn't there already.
	Additionally, you gain proficiency in your choice of two of the following skills: Deception, Intimidation, Performance, Persuasion, or Insight.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 7</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Silvery Barbs (Mage of Silverquill (UA))</name>
        <text>Also at 1st level, you can invoke words laced with magic to demoralize your foes and turn their misfortune into a boon to bolster your allies. Immediately after a creature you can see within 60 feet of you succeeds on an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, you can use your reaction to demoralize the creature. Unless the creature is immune to being charmed, it rerolls the d20 and must use the lower roll. If the attack roll, ability check, or saving throw then fails, you can choose a different creature you can see within 60 feet of you (you can choose yourself). That creature is empowered, and can reroll one attack roll, ability check, or saving throw it makes within 1 minute and use the higher result. A creature can be empowered by only one use of this feature at a time.
	Once a creature fails an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw because of a reroll forced by this feature, you can't use the feature again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot to use it again.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 7</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Inky Shroud (Mage of Silverquill (UA))</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you learn the darkness spell, and it is added to your class spell list if it isn't there already. If you are a wizard, you add it to your spellbook, if it's not there already.
	You can cast the spell without expending a spell slot, and you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. When you cast the spell in this way, you can see normally through the darkness created, and when a creature you can see starts its turn in the darkness, you can deal 2d10 psychic damage to that creature.
	You can also cast the spell normally, without the additional effects, by using spell slots you have of 2nd level or higher.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 7</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Infusion of Eloquence (Mage of Silverquill (UA))</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, when you cast a spell that deals damage, you can invoke additional words of power to change the spell's damage type to your choice of psychic or radiant. Any creature damaged by the spell takes extra damage equal to your proficiency bonus and has its emotions swayed with despair or adoration, based on the damage type dealt:

Psychic. The creature is frightened of you until the start of your next turn.

Radiant. The creature is charmed by you until the start of your next turn.

You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 7</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Word of Power (Mage of Silverquill (UA))</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, you can invoke a word of power that is the pinnacle of your magical study. You gain the following options:

Deadly Despair. When the target of your Silvery Barbs fails an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw because of the reroll, you can invoke a word of despair to give the target vulnerability to one damage type of your choice until the start of your next turn.

Selfless Invocation. When a creature you can see within 60 feet of you takes damage, you can invoke a word of power using your reaction to grant the creature resistance to that damage, and you take an amount of psychic damage equal to the damage that creature takes.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 7</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Otherworldly Patron: Mage of Witherbloom (UA) -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Patron: Mage of Witherbloom (UA)</name>
        <text>Mages of Witherbloom draw their magic from the energy that endlessly flows from life to death, and back again. They see the duality of thriving life and inevitable death in all things, tapping and manipulating the transition of energy between these states. Some Witherbloom adherents focus on vital energies to nurture life and empower others, while others embrace the drain of vitality into decay to sap and strike down their foes.

Upon selecting the Mage of Witherbloom subclass, you gain two features: Witherbloom Spells and Essence Tap.
	In this subclass's features, any reference to your class refers to the class from which you gained the subclass. If you're a druid, the College of Witherbloom counts as your circle, and if you're a warlock, the college counts as your patron.
	When you subsequently reach a level in your class that gives you a subclass feature, you gain one feature of your choice from the options presented here. Each feature has a class level prerequisite, as noted beneath its name. You must meet that prerequisite to gain the feature.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 8</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Witherbloom Spells (Mage of Witherbloom (UA))</name>
        <text>You learn the cantrip spare the dying and the 1st-level spells cure wounds and inflict wounds. You learn additional spells when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown on the Witherbloom Spells table.
	Each of these spells count as a class spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of spells you know. If you are a druid, you always have the spells prepared, and they don't count against the number of spells you can prepare each day.

Mage of Witherbloom Expended Spells:
Spell Level | Spells
Canrip | Spare the Dying
1st | cure wounds, inflict wounds
3rd | lesser restoration, ray of enfeeblement
5th | revivify, vampiric touch
7th | blight, greater restoration
9th | antilife shell, mass cure wounds

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 8</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Essence Tap (Mage of Witherbloom (UA))</name>
        <text>Also at 1st level, as a bonus action, you can draw on a reservoir of life essence to empower yourself for 1 minute, or until you use this feature again. For the duration, you gain one of the following benefits of your choice:

Overgrowth. When you choose this benefit, and as a bonus action on subsequent turns while the benefit lasts, you can expend and roll one Hit Die. You regain a number of hit points equal to the number rolled plus your spellcasting ability modifier.

Withering Strike. When you deal damage, you can change the damage type to necrotic, and you ignore resistance to necrotic damage.

You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 8</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Witherbloom Brew (Mage of Witherbloom (UA))</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain proficiency with herbalism kits if you don't already have it.
	When you finish a long rest, you can use an herbalism kit and a pot or cauldron to create magical brews. You create a number of brews equal to your proficiency bonus. Each brew requires its own flask. A brew retains its magical potency for 24 hours or until it is used. For each brew, choose one of the following effects:

Fortifying. When you create this brew, choose a damage type from the following list: cold, fire, necrotic, poison, or radiant. A creature can drink this brew or administer it to another creature as an action. The recipient gains resistance to the chosen damage type for 1 hour.

Quickening. A creature can drink this brew or administer it to another creature as an action. The recipient regains 2d6 hit points, and one disease or condition from the following list affecting the recipient ends (brew user's choice): charmed, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned, stunned.

Toxifying. As an action, a creature can apply this brew to a simple or martial weapon. The next time the weapon or a piece of ammunition fired by it hits a creature within 1 hour, the target takes 2d6 poison damage and must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC or be poisoned for 1 minute.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 8</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Witherbloom Adept (Mage of Witherbloom (UA))</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, your connection to the flow of life force deepens. Once per turn when you deal necrotic damage or restore hit points using a spell, one target of the spell takes additional damage or regains additional hit points equal to your proficiency bonus.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 9</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Withering Vortex (Mage of Witherbloom (UA))</name>
        <text>At 14th level, when you cast a spell using a spell slot that deals necrotic damage to any number of creatures that aren't Undead or Constructs, choose one of the creatures that took damage. You drain an amount of life energy equal to half the damage dealt to the chosen creature. One creature other than yourself that you can see within 30 feet of you regains a number of hit points equal to the life energy drained.
	You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 9</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
