<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Druid</name>
    <!-- Druid Circle: Mage of Prismari -->
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Druid Circle: Mage of Prismari (UA)</name>
        <text>Mages of Prismari use surges of elemental energy to express who they are and how they see the world. To them, magic and motion are one and the same; both are exhibitions of raw creativity through which masterpieces are made. In their pursuit of the arts, some Prismari mages focus on perfecting the fine details of their technique, while others prefer to unleash their wild creative visions in dazzling spectacles of elemental power.

Upon selecting the Mage of Prismari subclass, you gain two features: Creative Skills and Kinetic Artistry.
	In this subclass's features, any reference to your class refers to the class from which you gained the subclass. If you're a druid, the College of Prismari counts as your circle; if you're a sorcerer, the magic of the college is the origin of your sorcery; and if you're a wizard, the college represents your arcane tradition.
	When you subsequently reach a level in your class that gives you a subclass feature, you gain one feature of your choice from the options presented here. Each feature has a class level prerequisite, as noted beneath its name. You must meet that prerequisite to gain the feature.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 4</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Creative Skills (Mage of Prismari (UA))</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you gain proficiency in two of the following skills of your choice: Acrobatics, Athletics, Nature, or Performance.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 4</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Kinetic Artistry (Mage of Prismari (UA))</name>
        <text>Also at 2nd level, you can Dash as a bonus action. When you take this bonus action, choose one of the following additional effects:

Boreal Sweep. Icy water swirls around you. Until the end of your turn, you can move across the surface of water as if it were harmless solid ground. Additionally, when you leave a space within 5 feet of a creature, you can force that creature to make a Strength saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the creature is knocked prone. A creature can be affected by the water only once each turn.

Scorching Whirl. Flames wreath your steps. Once before the end of your turn, you can force each creature within 5 feet of you to make a Dexterity saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failure, a creature takes fire damage equal to 1d4 + your spellcasting modifier.

Thunderlight Jaunt. You take on a nimble lightning form. Until the end of your turn, you can move through the space of other creatures, and you do not provoke opportunity attacks. If you end your turn inside a creature's space, you are pushed into the nearest unoccupied space.
	You can use a bonus action in this way a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 4</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Favored Medium (Mage of Prismari (UA))</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you have honed your forms of elemental expression to best suit your ideas. Choose one of the following damage types: cold, fire, or lightning. You gain resistance to that damage type.
	Additionally, when you cast a spell using a spell slot that deals the chosen damage type, you emit a spectacular aura of artistry, which extends 5 feet from you in every direction (but not through total cover) and lasts until the end of your next turn. While the aura is active, each creature of your choice has resistance to your chosen damage type while within the aura, as you shape your favored elemental medium around them.
	You can change your choice of damage type whenever you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 5</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Focused Expression (Mage of Prismari (UA))</name>
        <text>At 10th level, honing your talents, you skillfully infuse your motions with even more potent expressions of elemental might. Once per turn when you deal damage to at least one target, you gain an additional effect determined by the damage type chosen for your Favored Medium feature:

Cold. One of the targets of your choice takes an additional 1d6 cold damage and must make a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the target's speed is reduced by 10 feet until the end of its next turn, as ice mires it. A target can be affected by the ice only once per round.

Fire. One of the targets of your choice takes an additional 1d6 fire damage. Fortifying flames then dance around one creature of your choice within 30 feet of you. The chosen creature gains 1d6 temporary hit points.

Lightning. One of the targets of your choice takes an additional 1d6 lightning damage and must make a Dexterity saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the target is unable to take reactions until the end of its next turn, as residual lightning shocks its form.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 5</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Impeccable Physicality (Mage of Prismari (UA))</name>
        <text>Beginning at 14th level, your relentless dedication and training have instilled an outstanding sense of precision and grace in your art. You gain proficiency in Dexterity saving throws if you do not already have it. Additionally, when you make a Dexterity saving throw, you can treat a d20 roll of a 9 or lower as a 10.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 5</text>
        <proficiency>Dexterity</proficiency>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Druid Circle: Mage of Witherbloom -->
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Druid Circle: Mage of Witherbloom (UA)</name>
        <text>Mages of Witherbloom draw their magic from the energy that endlessly flows from life to death, and back again. They see the duality of thriving life and inevitable death in all things, tapping and manipulating the transition of energy between these states. Some Witherbloom adherents focus on vital energies to nurture life and empower others, while others embrace the drain of vitality into decay to sap and strike down their foes.

Upon selecting the Mage of Witherbloom subclass, you gain two features: Witherbloom Spells and Essence Tap.
	In this subclass's features, any reference to your class refers to the class from which you gained the subclass. If you're a druid, the College of Witherbloom counts as your circle, and if you're a warlock, the college counts as your patron.
	When you subsequently reach a level in your class that gives you a subclass feature, you gain one feature of your choice from the options presented here. Each feature has a class level prerequisite, as noted beneath its name. You must meet that prerequisite to gain the feature.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 8</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Witherbloom Spells (Mage of Witherbloom (UA))</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you learn the cantrip spare the dying and the 1st-level spells cure wounds and inflict wounds. You learn additional spells when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown on the Witherbloom Spells table.
	Each of these spells count as a class spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of spells you know. If you are a druid, you always have the spells prepared, and they don't count against the number of spells you can prepare each day.

Mage of Witherbloom Expended Spells:
Spell Level | Spells
Canrip | Spare the Dying
1st | cure wounds, inflict wounds
3rd | lesser restoration, ray of enfeeblement
5th | revivify, vampiric touch
7th | blight, greater restoration
9th | antilife shell, mass cure wounds

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 8</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Essence Tap (Mage of Witherbloom (UA))</name>
        <text>Also at 2nd level, as a bonus action, you can draw on a reservoir of life essence to empower yourself for 1 minute, or until you use this feature again. For the duration, you gain one of the following benefits of your choice:

Overgrowth. When you choose this benefit, and as a bonus action on subsequent turns while the benefit lasts, you can expend and roll one Hit Die. You regain a number of hit points equal to the number rolled plus your spellcasting ability modifier.

Withering Strike. When you deal damage, you can change the damage type to necrotic, and you ignore resistance to necrotic damage.

You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 8</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Witherbloom Brew (Mage of Witherbloom (UA))</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain proficiency with herbalism kits if you don't already have it.
	When you finish a long rest, you can use an herbalism kit and a pot or cauldron to create magical brews. You create a number of brews equal to your proficiency bonus. Each brew requires its own flask. A brew retains its magical potency for 24 hours or until it is used. For each brew, choose one of the following effects:

Fortifying. When you create this brew, choose a damage type from the following list: cold, fire, necrotic, poison, or radiant. A creature can drink this brew or administer it to another creature as an action. The recipient gains resistance to the chosen damage type for 1 hour.

Quickening. A creature can drink this brew or administer it to another creature as an action. The recipient regains 2d6 hit points, and one disease or condition from the following list affecting the recipient ends (brew user's choice): charmed, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned, stunned.

Toxifying. As an action, a creature can apply this brew to a simple or martial weapon. The next time the weapon or a piece of ammunition fired by it hits a creature within 1 hour, the target takes 2d6 poison damage and must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC or be poisoned for 1 minute.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 8</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Witherbloom Adept (Mage of Witherbloom (UA))</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, your connection to the flow of life force deepens. Once per turn when you deal necrotic damage or restore hit points using a spell, one target of the spell takes additional damage or regains additional hit points equal to your proficiency bonus.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 9</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Withering Vortex (Mage of Witherbloom (UA))</name>
        <text>At 14th level, when you cast a spell using a spell slot that deals necrotic damage to any number of creatures that aren't Undead or Constructs, choose one of the creatures that took damage. You drain an amount of life energy equal to half the damage dealt to the chosen creature. One creature other than yourself that you can see within 30 feet of you regains a number of hit points equal to the life energy drained.
	You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 79: Mages of Strixhaven p. 9</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
