<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <feat>
    <name>Cartomancer (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level; Sorcerer, Warlock, or Wizard Class</prerequisite>
    <text>You have learned to channel your magic through a deck of playing cards, granting you these benefits:

Card Focus. You can use a deck of cards as your spellcasting focus. When you use the deck as a focus to cast a spell that deals damage, roll a d4. You gain a bonus to one damage roll of the spell equal to the number rolled. This bonus applies to one creature of your choice that you can see damaged by the spell; you can use this benefit a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses of it when you finish a long rest.

Card Tricks. You learn the prestidigitation cantrip and can use it to create illusions that duplicate the effects of stage magic. When you use prestidigitation in this way, you can conceal the verbal and somatic components of the spell as mundane conversation and card-handling.

Hidden Ace. When you finish a long rest, you can choose one spell you know and imbue it into a card; the chosen spell must have a casting time of 1 action, and its level must be less than or equal to your proficiency bonus. While the card is imbued with the spell, you can use your bonus action to flourish the card and cast the spell within. The card then immediately loses its magic.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Wonders Of The Multiverse p. 6</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Guile Of The Cloud Giant (UA) (Dexterity)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Strike of the Giants (Cloud Giant) Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>You've manifested the airy speech and magic emblematic of cloud giants, granting you the following benefits:

Ability Score Increase. Increase your Dexterity, Constitution, or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20.

Cloudy Escape. When a creature you can see hits you with an attack roll, you can use your reaction to give yourself resistance to that attack's damage. You then teleport to an unoccupied space that you can see within 30 feet of yourself. You can use this reaction a number of times equal to half your proficiency bonus (rounded up), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Wonders Of The Multiverse p. 7</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">dexterity +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Rune Carver Adept (UA) (Intelligence)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Rune Carver Apprentice Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>Your ability to draw out power from runes has grown.
	Increase the ability score of the spellcasting ability chosen when you gained the Rune Carver Apprentice feat by 1, to a maximum of 20.
	Whenever you cast a spell from the Rune Spells table, or a spell of a school of magic associated with the spell you marked on an object from your Rune Carver Apprentice feat, you can invoke runic power, granting you one of these benefits of your choice:

Battle Runes. Choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of yourself. Until the end of that creature's next turn, it has advantage on the next attack roll it makes.

Healing Runes. Choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of yourself. That creature gains temporary hit points equal to your level.

Runic Winds. Choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of yourself. Until the end of that creature's turn, its movement doesn't provoke opportunity attacks, and its walking speed increases by 10 feet.

You can invoke runic power a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, but no more than once per spell you cast. You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Wonders Of The Multiverse p. 8</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">intelligence +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Rune Carver Adept (UA) (Wisdom)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Rune Carver Apprentice Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>Your ability to draw out power from runes has grown.
	Increase the ability score of the spellcasting ability chosen when you gained the Rune Carver Apprentice feat by 1, to a maximum of 20.
	Whenever you cast a spell from the Rune Spells table, or a spell of a school of magic associated with the spell you marked on an object from your Rune Carver Apprentice feat, you can invoke runic power, granting you one of these benefits of your choice:

Battle Runes. Choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of yourself. Until the end of that creature's next turn, it has advantage on the next attack roll it makes.

Healing Runes. Choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of yourself. That creature gains temporary hit points equal to your level.

Runic Winds. Choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of yourself. Until the end of that creature's turn, its movement doesn't provoke opportunity attacks, and its walking speed increases by 10 feet.

You can invoke runic power a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, but no more than once per spell you cast. You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Wonders Of The Multiverse p. 8</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">wisdom +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Rune Carver Adept (UA) (Charisma)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Rune Carver Apprentice Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>Your ability to draw out power from runes has grown.
	Increase the ability score of the spellcasting ability chosen when you gained the Rune Carver Apprentice feat by 1, to a maximum of 20.
	Whenever you cast a spell from the Rune Spells table, or a spell of a school of magic associated with the spell you marked on an object from your Rune Carver Apprentice feat, you can invoke runic power, granting you one of these benefits of your choice:

Battle Runes. Choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of yourself. Until the end of that creature's next turn, it has advantage on the next attack roll it makes.

Healing Runes. Choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of yourself. That creature gains temporary hit points equal to your level.

Runic Winds. Choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of yourself. Until the end of that creature's turn, its movement doesn't provoke opportunity attacks, and its walking speed increases by 10 feet.

You can invoke runic power a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, but no more than once per spell you cast. You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Wonders Of The Multiverse p. 8</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">charisma +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Scion Of Elemental Air (UA)</name>
    <text>You've been exposed to the primordial magic of the Elemental Plane of Air, granting you the following benefits:

Elemental Magic. You learn the minor illusion cantrip, using Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma as the spellcasting ability (choose when you select this feat).

Wind's Glide. You can use a bonus action to gain a flying speed equal to your walking speed until the end of your turn. If you are airborne at the end of your turn after using this movement and aren't held aloft by other means, you fall. You can use this bonus action a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Wonders Of The Multiverse p. 8</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Scion Of Elemental Earth (UA)</name>
    <text>You've been exposed to the primordial magic of the Elemental Plane of Earth, granting you the following benefits:

Elemental Magic. You learn the druidcraft cantrip, using Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma as the spellcasting ability (choose when you select this feat).

Earthen Shield. You can use a bonus action to conjure a bulwark of earth that provides half cover to you or a creature of your choice within 30 feet of yourself. The bulwark remains until the start of your next turn. You can create this bulwark a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Wonders Of The Multiverse p. 8</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Scion Of Elemental Fire (UA)</name>
    <text>You've been exposed to the primordial magic of the Elemental Plane of Fire, granting you the following benefits:

Elemental Magic. You learn the dancing lights cantrip, using Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma as the spellcasting ability (choose when you select this feat).

Fervent Blaze. You learn the produce flame cantrip, using the same spellcasting ability chosen for this feat's Elemental Magic benefit. You can cast produce flame as normal, and you can also cast it as a bonus action a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, regaining all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Wonders Of The Multiverse p. 9</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Scion Of Elemental Water (UA)</name>
    <text>You've been exposed to the primordial magic of the Elemental Plane of Water, granting you the following benefits:

Elemental Magic. You learn the thaumaturgy cantrip, using Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma as the spellcasting ability (choose when you select this feat).

Wave Surge. You can use a bonus action to create a forceful surge of water directed at a creature within 15 feet of you that you can see. The target must make a Strength saving throw; the DC for this save is equal to 8 + your proficiency bonus + the spellcasting ability modifier chosen for this feat, and a creature can choose to fail this saving throw. On a failure, the target is pushed up to 10 feet away from you or pulled up to 10 feet toward you (your choice). The water vanishes immediately after the creature succeeds or fails. You can create this effect a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Wonders Of The Multiverse p. 9</text>
  </feat>
</compendium>
