<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <race>
    <name>Glitchling (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Created by forces of planar law, glitchlings are winged, human-like creatures made from a merger of magic and machine. These explorers seek to learn all they can about the multiverse and its creatures. Some glitchlings then carry what they learn back to lawful planes, like Mechanus, to inform the orderly working of the multiverse. Others become enamored with travel and the peoples they encounter, and they seek to make a life of their own among the planes.
	Glitchlings begin their existences with rudimentary personalities. As they absorb information and experiences, their personalities grow, but many retain quirks associated with their lawful origins. You can roll or choose a quirk from the Orderly Quirk table or create your own.

Orderly Quirk:
d6 | Quirk
1 | I collect things, whether a specific kind of object or things made of a particular material.
2 | We think of ourselves as being a part of the collective, lawful forces of the multiverse and don't refer to ourselves as a singular being.
3 | I seek out new experiences so I can better understand the freedom of my existence.
4 | I preface things I say with a short description, such as: "observation," "interjection," or "query."
5 | I plan elaborate responses to every contingency, ready to execute at an instant's notice.
6 | I investigate people's intentions behind their actions, trying to solve the equation that guides them.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Wonders Of The Multiverse p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different one by 1, or increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>The typical life span of a player character in the D&amp;D multiverse is about a century, assuming the character doesn't meet a violent end on an adventure.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creature Type</name>
      <text>You are a Construct.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Armored Plating</name>
      <text>Your metal skin is reinforced with armor plates. While you aren't wearing armor, your base Armor Class is 14 + your Dexterity modifier.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Balance Chaos</name>
      <text>When you make an attack roll or a saving throw and roll a 9 or lower on the d20, you can balance chaos and treat the roll as a 10. You can balance chaos in this way a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Living Construct</name>
      <text>You were created to benefit from several spells that preserve life but that normally don't affect Constructs: cure wounds, healing word, mass cure wounds, mass healing word, and spare the dying.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Ordered Mind</name>
      <text>You have advantage on Wisdom (Insight) checks and on saving throws made to avoid or end the charmed condition on yourself.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Vestigial Wings</name>
      <text>You have vestigial wings that allow limited flight. When you move, you can engage your wings to gain a flying speed equal to your walking speed until the end of the current turn. If you are still aloft at the end of the turn with nothing else supporting you, you fall. You can use this trait a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>Your character can speak, read, and write Common and one other language that you and your DM agree is appropriate for the character.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
</compendium>
