<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Warlock</name>
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the D20 (HB)</name>
        <text>Select a number from 1 to 20. This is your Pact Number. Whenever an ally (or yourself) makes an attack roll, ability check, or saving throw, and the unmodified roll matches the Pact number, you can use your reaction to give yourself and that ally temporary hit points equal to your warlock level + your Charisma modifier. Should rerolls occur (for example the halflings lucky trait) then both of the dice count. You may choose a different Pact Number each time you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	The Dungeon Master p. 3 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Otherworldly Patron: The Dungeon Master (HB) -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Patron: The Dungeon Master (HB)</name>
        <text>You have seen beyond the veil of existentialism, into the chaos of chance and the madness of the metaverse, where the fabric of your world and others are weaved of spoken word, and the actions of each being are predetermined. This experience has awakened in you a minor control of the strings behind the world you know, but your abilities may wax and wane upon the whims of the Dungeon Master. Your patron is the one who creates and upholds the rules of reality. The Dungeon Master revels in stories. In return for your power, the Dungeon Master may direct you to take part in the important events of your time, or simply watch your story unfold. Beware. Though your insight into the world may be extensive, those who cannot see beyond the veil may ignore your words, or worse.

Source:	The Dungeon Master p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Expanded Spell List (The Dungeon Master (HB))</name>
        <text>The Dungeon Master lets you choose from an expanded list of spells when you learn a warlock spell. The following new spells are added to the warlock spell list for you.

The Dungeon Master Expanded Spells:
Spell Level | Spells
1st | Command, Identify
2nd | Augury, Detect Thoughts
3rd | Clairvoyance, Speak with Dead
4th | Fabricate, Locate Creature
5th | Creation, Passwall

Source:	The Dungeon Master p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Table Talk (The Dungeon Master (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, you can reach across the metaverse to speak to others under the watch of your patron. Your words have the ability to reach other players at any distance. You can talk with your other players and their characters even if you're not on the same plane of existence.
	Additionally, you gain proficiency in the Insight skill.

Source:	The Dungeon Master p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Metagaming (The Dungeon Master (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can read the strengths and weaknesses of other beings as if they were written on a page. As a bonus action, you can learn one thing of your choice about a creature from the following list:

	• Armor Class
	• Current Hit Points
	• One Ability Score or Saving Throw
	• One Damage Immunity or Resistance
	• One of the actions the creature can take
	• A special ability the creature possesses (like the Trolls regeneration)

You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	The Dungeon Master p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>With Advantage? (The Dungeon Master (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, your patron grants you the ability to rewrite an event in the immediate timeline. When a D20 is rolled, you can roll another D20 and choose which one gets used. You can choose to use this ability after the die is rolled, but before the outcome of the roll is determined. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: The DM p. 2</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>With Advantage?</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
        <subclass>The Dungeon Master (HB)</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Plot Armor (The Dungeon Master (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level you have peeked behind the layers of reality, and learned just what your enemy is capable of and what they are going to do. As a bonus action, select one creature that you can see. For the next minute, you have advantage on all rolls that directly involve the target (including attack rolls and ability checks), as well as on saving throws and opposed checks based on the target's actions. In addition, the target has disadvantage on all attack rolls, ability checks, and saving throws that involve you in any capacity.
	As a bonus action while this ability is active, you can transfer the benefits to an ally you can see. You lose the benefits yourself, but each round counts twice against its duration. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short rest.

Source:	The Dungeon Master p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Plot Armor</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
        <subclass>The Dungeon Master (HB)</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
  <spell>
    <name>Command</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Dungeon Master (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Identify</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Dungeon Master (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Augury</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Dungeon Master (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Detect Thoughts</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Dungeon Master (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Clairvoyance</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Dungeon Master (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Speak with Dead</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Dungeon Master (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Fabricate</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Dungeon Master (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Locate Creature</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Dungeon Master (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Creation</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Dungeon Master (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Passwall</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Dungeon Master (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
</compendium>
