<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Warlock</name>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Patron: The Kraken (Livestream)</name>
        <text>You have made a pact with a kraken that lurks somewhere in the oceans of the world. Krakens are eldritch, ancient and terrifying creatures; incomprehensible alien knowledge lurks within their minds. Forged by the gods themselves as weapons of war, krakens are known to control the rain and storms in the region around them. Many farmers or sailors are drawn to worship krakens in the hope of fair weather or safe seas, but you commune with it more deeply.

Source:	Livestream</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Expanded Spell List (The Kraken (Livestream))</name>
        <text>The Kraken lets you choose from an expanded list of spells when you learn a warlock spell. The following spells are added to the warlock spell list for you.

Kraken Patron Expanded Spells:
Spell Level | Spells
1st | thunderwave, create or destroy water
2nd | augury, gust of wind
3rd | call lightning, water breathing
4th | evard's black tentacles, control water
5th | control winds, maelstrom

Source:	Livestream</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Grasp of the Kraken (The Kraken (Livestream))</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, you gain the ability to call forth spectral tentacles that grab at your foes.

As an action, pick a point you can see within 60 feet of you. A horde of grasping tendrils appears at that point. Creatures of your choice within 10 feet of that point must make a Strength saving throw against your warlock spell save DC. Creatures that fail their saving throws are grappled for 1 minute or until you use this ability again. The spectral tentacle's Strength (Athletics) bonus is 2 + your proficiency bonus and its reach is 10 feet.

Source:	Livestream</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Inky Escape (The Kraken (Livestream))</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to call upon your patron to escape from your foes.

As a reaction when you take damage, you can cast darkness centered on a point within 5 feet of you. The spell lasts until the end of your next turn, and it has no effect on your vision.

Once you use this ability, you cannot use it until you complete a short or long rest.

Source:	Livestream</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Scion of the Depths (The Kraken (Livestream))</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, your patron accepts you into its inner court of servitors. You gain the ability to breathe water and a swim speed equal to your normal speed. If you already have a swim speed, you double it.

You gain immunity to lightning damage. When your immunity reduces damage from an effect to 0, you can use your reaction to cause creatures of your choice that you can see within 30 feet of you to take lightning damage equal to your Charisma modifier + your proficiency bonus.

Source:	Livestream</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Unleash the Kraken (The Kraken (Livestream))</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain the ability to call upon your patron for aid.

As an action, you open a portal at a point you can see within 30 ft. of you and choose one of the following effects.

Transport:
You and up to 5 willing creatures of your choice that you can see are grasped by tentacles that emerge from the portal. A second portal opens at a point of your choice within 100 miles that you have visited within the past 24 hours. A second portal opens, depositing you and your chosen allies there.

Fury:
The tentacles slam onto your foes. Pick up to 5 creatures that you can see within 30 feet of the portal. Those creatures must make Dexterity saving throws against your warlock spell save DC. Creatures that fail their saving throw take 10d6 bludgeoning damage and are restrained for 1 minute. Those that succeed take half the bludgeoning damage and are not restrained. On its turn, a restrained creature can use its action to attempt a DC 15 Strength (Athletics) or Dexterity (Acrobatics) check to end the restrained condition.

Once you use this ability, you cannot use it again until you complete a long rest.

Source:	Livestream</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>

  <spell>
    <name>Thunderwave</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Kraken (UA))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Create or Destroy Water</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Kraken (UA))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Augury</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Kraken (UA))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Gust of Wind</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Kraken (UA))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Call Lightning</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Kraken (UA))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Water Breathing</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Kraken (UA))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Evard's Black Tentacles</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Kraken (UA))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Control Water</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Kraken (UA))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Control Winds</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Kraken (UA))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maelstrom</name>
    <classes>Warlock (The Kraken (UA))</classes>
  </spell>
</compendium>
