<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <item>
    <name>Lycan Yklwa</name>
    <detail>rare</detail>
    <type>M</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <weight>3</weight>
    <property>T</property>
    <dmg1>1d8</dmg1>
    <dmgType>P</dmgType>
    <range>10/30</range>
    <text>A yklwa (pronounced YICK-ul-wah) is a simple melee weapon that is the traditional weapon of Chultan warriors. A yklwa consists of a 3-foot wooden shaft with a steel or stone blade up to 18 inches long. Although it has the thrown weapon property, the yklwa is not well balanced for throwing.

Made from the claws, teeth, and bones of lycanthropes, these weapons are particularly effective against other lycanthropes or vampires. You gain a +2 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with this weapon.
	Additionally, on a successful attack against a lycanthrope, the target is forced back into its human form unless it succeeds on a DC 10 Charisma saving throw. Also, damage done to vampires with lycan weapons cannot be regenerated until the creature finishes a short rest.

Thrown: If a weapon has the Thrown property, you can throw the weapon to make a ranged attack. If the weapon is a melee weapon, you use the same ability modifier for that attack roll and damage roll that you would use for a melee attack with the weapon. For example, if you throw a handaxe, you use your Strength, but if you throw a dagger, you can use either your Strength or your Dexterity, since the dagger has the Finesse property.

Range: A weapon that can be used to make a ranged attack has a range shown in parentheses after the ammunition or thrown property. The range lists two numbers. The first is the weapon's normal range in feet, and the second indicates the weapon's maximum range. When attacking a target beyond normal range, you have disadvantage on the attack roll. You can't attack a target beyond the weapon's long range.

Proficiency: simple, yklwa
Source:	Grim Hollow: Lairs of Etharis p. 111,
		Tomb of Annihilation p. 32</text>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon attacks +2</modifier>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon damage +2</modifier>
  </item>
</compendium>
