<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <spell>
    <name>Acid Splash (UA)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>60 feet</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>School: Evocation, Fighter (Eldritch Knight), Rogue (Arcane Trickster), Sorcerer, Wizard, Artificer, Sorcerer (Clockwork Soul), Bard, Wizard (School of Invention (UA)), Druid</classes>
    <text>You create an acidic bubble and hurl it at a point within range, where it explodes in a 5- foot-radius sphere. Each creature in that sphere must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take 1d6 Acid damage.

Cantrip Upgrade: This spell's damage increases by 1d6 when you reach levels 5 (2d6), 11 (3d6), and 17 (4d6).

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Bastions and Cantrips p. 22</text>
    <roll description="Acid Damage" level="0">1d6</roll>
    <roll description="Acid Damage" level="5">2d6</roll>
    <roll description="Acid Damage" level="11">3d6</roll>
    <roll description="Acid Damage" level="17">4d6</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Blade Ward (UA)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>A</school>
    <time>Reaction, which you take in response to a visible creature targeting you with a melee attack</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>School: Abjuration, Fighter (Eldritch Knight), Rogue (Arcane Trickster), Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</classes>
    <text>You trace a sigil of warding, imposing Disadvantage on the creature's attack roll against you.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Bastions and Cantrips p. 22</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Chill Touch (UA)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>N</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Touch</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>School: Necromancy, Touch Spells, Fighter (Eldritch Knight), Rogue (Arcane Trickster), Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</classes>
    <text>You channel the chill of the grave toward one creature you try to touch. Make a melee spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 1d10 Necrotic damage, and it can't regain Hit Points until the end of your next turn.

Cantrip Upgrade: This spell's damage increases by 1d10 when you reach levels 5 (2d10), 11 (3d10), and 17 (4d10).

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Bastions and Cantrips p. 22</text>
    <roll description="Necrotic Damage" level="0">1d10</roll>
    <roll description="Necrotic Damage" level="5">2d10</roll>
    <roll description="Necrotic Damage" level="11">3d10</roll>
    <roll description="Necrotic Damage" level="17">4d10</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Friends (UA)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EN</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>10 feet</range>
    <components>S, M (some makeup)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
    <classes>School: Enchantment, Fighter (Eldritch Knight), Rogue (Arcane Trickster), Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Wizard (Psionics (UA))</classes>
    <text>You magically emanate a sense of friendship toward one visible creature within range. The target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or have the Charmed condition for the duration. The target succeeds automatically if it isn't a Humanoid, if you're fighting it, or if you have cast this spell on it within the past 24 hours.
	The spell ends early if the target takes damage or if you make an attack roll, deal damage, or force anyone to make a saving throw.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Bastions and Cantrips p. 22</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Poison Spray (UA)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>N</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>30 feet</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>School: Conjuration, Fighter (Eldritch Knight), Rogue (Arcane Trickster), Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Artificer</classes>
    <text>You launch a mist of toxic energy at a creature within range. Make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 1d12 Poison damage.

Cantrip Upgrade: This spell's damage increases by 1d12 when you reach levels 5 (2d12), 11 (3d12), and 17 (4d12).

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Bastions and Cantrips p. 22</text>
    <roll description="Poison Damage" level="0">1d12</roll>
    <roll description="Poison Damage" level="5">2d12</roll>
    <roll description="Poison Damage" level="11">3d12</roll>
    <roll description="Poison Damage" level="17">4d12</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Produce Flame (UA)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>C</school>
    <time>1 Bonus Action</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>10 minutes</duration>
    <classes>School: Conjuration, Druid</classes>
    <text>A flickering flame appears in your hand and remains there for the duration. While there, the flame emits no heat and ignites nothing, and it sheds bright light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet. The spell ends if you dismiss it as a Bonus Action or if you cast it again.
	Until the spell ends, you can take a Magic action to hurl fire at a creature or an object within 60 feet of you. Make a ranged spell attack. On a hit, the target takes 1d8 fire damage.

Cantrip Upgrade: This spell's damage increases by 1d8 when you reach levels 5 (2d8), 11 (3d8), and 17 (4d8).

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Bastions and Cantrips p. 23</text>
    <roll description="Fire Damage" level="0">1d8</roll>
    <roll description="Fire Damage" level="5">2d8</roll>
    <roll description="Fire Damage" level="11">3d8</roll>
    <roll description="Fire Damage" level="17">4d8</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Shillelagh (UA)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>T</school>
    <time>1 Bonus Action</time>
    <range>Touch</range>
    <components>V, S, M (mistletoe, a shamrock leaf, and a Club or Quarterstaff)</components>
    <duration>1 minute</duration>
    <classes>School: Transmutation, Touch Spells, Touch Spells, Druid, Sorcerer (Giant Soul (UA))</classes>
    <text>A Club or Quarterstaff you are holding is imbued with nature's power. For the duration, you can use your spellcasting ability instead of Strength for the attack and damage rolls of melee attacks using that weapon, and the weapon's damage die becomes a d8. If the attack deals damage, it can be Force damage or the weapon's normal damage type (your choice).
	The spell ends early if you cast it again or if you let go of the weapon.

Cantrip Upgrade: The weapon's damage die changes when you reach levels 5 (d10), 11 (d12), and 17 (2d6).

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Bastions and Cantrips p. 23</text>
    <roll description="Weapon Damage Die" level="0">1d8</roll>
    <roll description="Weapon Damage Die" level="5">1d10</roll>
    <roll description="Weapon Damage Die" level="11">1d12</roll>
    <roll description="Weapon Damage Die" level="17">2d6</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Shocking Grasp (UA)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Touch</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>School: Evocation, Touch Spells, Touch Spells, Fighter (Eldritch Knight), Rogue (Arcane Trickster), Sorcerer, Wizard, Artificer, Sorcerer (Giant Soul (UA))</classes>
    <text>Lightning springs from your hand to deliver a shock to a creature you try to touch. Make a melee spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 1d8 Lightning damage, and it can't make Opportunity Attacks until the start of its next turn.

Cantrip Upgrade: This spell's damage increases by 1d8 when you reach levels 5 (2d8), 11 (3d8), and 17 (4d8).

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Bastions and Cantrips p. 23</text>
    <roll description="Lightning Damage" level="0">1d8</roll>
    <roll description="Lightning Damage" level="5">2d8</roll>
    <roll description="Lightning Damage" level="11">3d8</roll>
    <roll description="Lightning Damage" level="17">4d8</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Spare The Dying (UA)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>N</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>15 feet</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>School: Necromancy, Touch Spells, Cleric, Druid, Artificer, Druid (Mage of Witherbloom), Warlock (Mage of Witherbloom), Cleric (Grave Domain)</classes>
    <text>Choose a creature within range that has 0 Hit Points yet is alive. The creature becomes Stable.

Cantrip Upgrade: The spell's range doubles when you reach levels 5 (30 feet), 11 (60 feet), and 17 (120 feet).

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Bastions and Cantrips p. 23</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>True Strike (UA)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>D</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>S, M (a weapon with which you have proficiency)</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>School: Divination, Fighter (Eldritch Knight), Rogue (Arcane Trickster), Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</classes>
    <text>Guided by a flash of magical insight, you make one attack with the weapon used in the spell's casting. The attack uses your spellcasting ability for the attack and damage rolls instead of using Strength or Dexterity. If the attack deals damage, it can be Radiant damage or the weapon's normal damage type (your choice).

Cantrip Upgrade: Whether you choose to deal Radiant damage or the weapon's normal damage type, the attack deals extra Radiant damage when you reach levels 5 (1d6), 11 (2d6), and 17 (3d6).

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Bastions and Cantrips p. 23</text>
    <roll description="Radiant Damage" level="5">1d6</roll>
    <roll description="Radiant Damage" level="11">2d6</roll>
    <roll description="Radiant Damage" level="17">3d6</roll>
  </spell>
</compendium>
