<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <race>
    <name>Aarakocra (DMG)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>20</speed>
    <ability>Dex +2, Wis +2</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Sequestered in high mountains atop tall trees, the aarakocra evoke fear and wonder. Many of these birdfolk hail from the boundless vistas of the Elemental Plane of Air. They are immigrants, refugees, scouts, and explorers, their outposts functioning as footholds in a world both strange and alien.

Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Aarakocra reach maturity by age 3. Compared to humans, aarakocra don't usually live longer than 30 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Most aarakocra are good and rarely choose sides when it comes to law and chaos. Tribal leaders and warriors might be lawful, while explorers and adventurers might tend toward chaotic.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Aarakocra are about 5 feet tall. They have thin, lightweight bodies that weigh between 80 and 100 pounds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 4 feet + 3 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 70 + (1d4 × your size modifier)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Flight</name>
      <text>You have a flying speed of 50 feet. To use this speed, you can't be wearing medium or heavy armor.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Dive Attack</name>
      <text>If you are flying and dive at least 30 ft. straight toward a target and then hit it with a melee weapon attack, the attack deals an extra 1d6 damage to the target.</text>
      <roll description="Extra Damage">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Talons</name>
      <text>You are proficient with your unarmed strikes, which deal 1d4 slashing damage on a hit.</text>
      <roll description="Slashing Damage">1d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Auran.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Aasimar (DMG)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Cha +2, Wis +1</ability>
    <resist>necrotic, radiant</resist>
    <spellAbility>Charisma</spellAbility>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Whereas tieflings have fiendish blood in their veins, aasimar are the descendants of celestial beings. These folk generally appear as glorious humans with lustrous hair, flawless skin, and piercing eyes. Aasimar often attempt to pass as humans in order to right wrongs and defend goodness on the Material Plane without drawing undue attention to their celestial heritage. They strive to fit into society, although they usually rise to the top, becoming revered leaders and honorable heroes.

Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 286,
		Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 166</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Aasimar mature at the same rate as humans but live a few years longer.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Due to their celestial heritage, Aasimar are often good. However, some Aasimar fall into evil, rejecting their heritage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Aasimar are built like well-proportioned humans. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d10
Height = 4 feet + 8 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 110 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Thanks to your celestial heritage, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of grey.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Celestial Resistance</name>
      <text>You have resistance to necrotic and radiant damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Celestial Legacy</name>
      <text>You know the light cantrip. Once you reach 3rd level, you can cast the lesser restoration spell once with this trait, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest. Once you reach 5th level, you can cast the daylight spell once with this trait as a 3rd-level spell, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Celestial.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Bullywug (DMG NPC)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>20</speed>
    <ability>Int -2, Cha -2</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Bullywugs are considered full-grown at 3 years of age. The average lifespan of a bullywug is 50 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Bullywugs can be of any alignment, but tend to be chaotic and evil.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Your size is Medium, however bullywugs vary in size and weight. Most are about 4 to 5 feet tall and weight 80 to 120 pounds.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>You can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Speak with Frogs and Toads</name>
      <text>You can communicate simple concepts to frogs and toads when you speak in Bullywug.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Swamp Camouflage</name>
      <text>You have advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide in swampy terrain.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Standing Leap</name>
      <text>Your long jump is up to 20 feet and your high jump is up to 10 feet, with or without a running start.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Swim speed</name>
      <text>You have a base swimming speed of 40 feet.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Bullywug.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Elf, Eladrin (DMG)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Dex +2, Int +1</ability>
    <proficiency>Perception</proficiency>
    <weapons>Longsword, Shortsword, Longbow, Shortbow</weapons>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Elves are a magical people of otherworldly grace, living in places of ethereal beauty, in the midst of ancient forests or in silvery spires glittering with faerie light, where soft music drifts through the air and gentle fragrances waft on the breeze. Elves love nature and magic, art and artistry, music and poetry.

Creatures of magic with strong ties to nature, eladrin live in the twilight realm of the Feywild. Their cities sometimes cross over into the Material Plane, appearing briefly in mountain valleys or deep forest glades before fading back into the Feywild.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 23,
		Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 286</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Slender and Graceful</name>
      <text>With their unearthly grace and fine features, elves appear hauntingly beautiful to humans and members of many other races. They are slightly shorter than humans on average, ranging from well under 5 feet tall to just over 6 feet. They are more slender than humans, weighing only 100 to 145 pounds. Males and females are about the same height, and males are only marginally heavier than females.

Elves' coloration encompasses the normal human range and also includes skin in shades of copper, bronze, and almost bluish-white, hair of green or blue, and eyes like pools of liquid gold or silver. Elves have no facial and little body hair. They favor elegant clothing in bright colors, and they enjoy simple yet lovely jewelry.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>A Timeless Perspective</name>
      <text>Elves can live well over 700 years, giving them a broad perspective on events that might trouble the shorterlived races more deeply. They are more often amused than excited, and more likely to be curious than greedy. They tend to remain aloof and unfazed by petty happenstance. When pursuing a goal, however, whether adventuring on a mission or learning a new skill or art, elves can be focused and relentless. They are slow to make friends and enemies, and even slower to forget them. They reply to petty insults with disdain and to serious insults with vengeance.

Like the branches of a young tree, elves are flexible in the face of danger. They trust in diplomacy and compromise to resolve differences before they escalate to violence. They have been known to retreat from intrusions into their woodland homes, confident that they can simply wait the invaders out. But when the need arises, elves reveal a stern martial side, demonstrating skill with sword, bow, and strategy.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Hidden Woodland Realms</name>
      <text>Most elves dwell in small forest villages hidden among the trees. Elves hunt game, gather food, and grow vegetables, and their skill and magic allow them to support themselves without the need for clearing and plowing land. They are talented artisans, crafting finely worked clothes and art objects. Their contact with outsiders is usually limited, though a few elves make a good living by trading crafted items for metals (which they have no interest in mining).

Elves encountered outside their own lands are commonly traveling minstrels, artists, or sages. Human nobles compete for the services of elf instructors to teach swordplay or magic to their children.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Exploration and Adventure</name>
      <text>Elves take up adventuring out of wanderlust. Since they are so long-lived, they can enjoy centuries of exploration and discovery. They dislike the pace of human society, which is regimented from day to day but constantly changing over decades, so they find careers that let them travel freely and set their own pace. Elves also enjoy exercising their martial prowess or gaining greater magical power, and adventuring allows them to do so. Some might join with rebels fighting against oppression, and others might become champions of moral causes.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Elf Names</name>
      <text>Elves are considered children until they declare themselves adults, some time after the hundredth birthday, and before this period they are called by child names.

On declaring adulthood, an elf selects an adult name, although those who knew him or her as a youngster might continue to use the child name. Each elf's adult name is a unique creation, though it might reflect the names of respected individuals or other family members. Little distinction exists between male names and female names; the groupings here reflect only general tendencies. In addition, every elf bears a family name, typically a combination of other Elvish words. Some elves traveling among humans translate their family names into Common, but others retain the Elvish version.

Child Names: Ara, Bryn, Del, Eryn, Faen, Innil. Lael, Mella, Naill, Naeris, Phann, Rael, Rinn, Sai, Syllin, Thia, Vall

Male Adult Names: Adran, Aelar, Aramil, Arannis, Aust, Beiro, Berrian, Carric, Enialis, Erdan, Erevan, Galinndan, Hadarai, Heian, Himo, Immeral, Ivellios, Laucian, Mindartis, Paelias, Peren, Quarion, Riardon, Rolen, Soveliss, Thamior, Tharivol, Theren, Varis

Female Adult Names: Adrie, Althaea, Anastrianna, Andraste, Antinua, Bethrynna, Birel, Caelynn, Drusilia, Enna, Felosial, Ielenia, Jelenneth, Keyleth, Leshanna, Lia, Meriele, Mialee, Naivara, Quelenna, Quillathe, Sariel, Shanairra, Shava, Silaqui, Theirastra, Thia, Vadania, Valanthe, Xanaphia

Family Names (Common Translations): Amakiir (Gemflower), Amastacia (Starflower), Galanodel (Moonwhisper), Holimion (Diamonddew), Ilphelkiir (Gemblossom), Liadon (Silverfrond), Meliamne (Oakenheel), Nai'lo (Nightbreeze), Siannodel (Moonbrook), Xiloscient (Goldpetal)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Although elves reach physical maturity at about the same age as humans, the elven understanding of adulthood goes beyond physical growth to encompass worldly experience. An elf typically claims adulthood and an adult name around the age of 100 and can live to be 750 years old.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Elves love freedom, variety, and self-expression, so they lean strongly toward the gentler aspects of chaos. They value and protect others' freedom as well as their own, and they are more often good than not.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Elves range from under 5 to over 6 feet tall and have slender builds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d10
Height = 4 feet + 6 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 90 + (1d4 × your size modifier)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Accustomed to twilit forests and the night sky, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Keen Senses</name>
      <text>You have proficiency in the Perception skill</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put you to sleep</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Trance</name>
      <text>Elves don't need to sleep. Instead, they meditate deeply, remaining semiconscious, for 4 hours a day. (The Common word for such meditation is "trance.") While meditating, you can dream after a fashion; such dreams are actually mental exercises that have become reflexive through years of practice. After resting in this way, you gain the same benefit that a human does from 8 hours of sleep.
	If you meditate during a long rest, you finish the rest after only 4 hours. You otherwise obey all the rules for a long rest; only the duration is changed.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Elf Weapon Training</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with the longsword, shortsword, shortbow, and longbow</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Fey Step</name>
      <text>You can cast the misty step spell once using this trait. You regain the ability to do so when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Elvish. Elvish is fluid, with subtle intonations and intricate grammar. Elven literature is rich and varied, and their songs and poems are famous among other races. Many bards learn their language so they can add Elvish ballads to their repertoires</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Gnoll (DMG NPC)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Str +2, Int -2</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Your fanged maw is a natural weapon, which you can use to make unarmed strikes. If you hit with it, you deal piercing damage equal to 1d4 + your Strength modifier, instead of the bludgeoning damage normal for an unarmed strike.</text>
      <roll description="Piercing Damage">1d4+%1</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Rampage</name>
      <text>When you reduce a creature to 0 hit points with a melee attack on your turn, you can take a bonus action to move up to half your speed and make a bite attack.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Gnome, Deep (DMG)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>20</speed>
    <ability>Str +1, Dex +2</ability>
    <spellAbility>Intelligence</spellAbility>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>A constant hum of busy activity pervades the warrens and neighborhoods where gnomes form their close-knit communities. Louder sounds punctuate the hum: a crunch of grinding gears here, a minor explosion there, a yelp of surprise or triumph, and especially bursts of laughter. Gnomes take delight in life, enjoying every moment of invention, exploration, investigation, creation, and play.

Forest gnomes and rock gnomes are the gnomes most commonly encountered in the lands of the surface world. There is another subrace of gnomes rarely seen by any surface-dweller: deep gnomes, also known as svirfneblin. Guarded, and suspicious of outsiders, svirfneblin are cunning and taciturn, but can be just as kind-hearted, loyal, and compassionate as their surface cousins.

Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Vibrant Expression</name>
      <text>A gnome's energy and enthusiasm for living shines through every inch his or her tiny body. Gnomes average slightly over 3 feet tall and weigh 40 to 45 pounds. Their tan or brown faces are usually adorned with broad smiles (beneath their prodigious noses), and their bright eyes shine with excitement. Their fair hair has a tendency to stick out in every direction, as if expressing the gnome's insatiable interest in everything around.
	A gnome's personality is writ large in his or her appearance. A male gnome's beard, in contrast to his wild hair, is kept carefully trimmed but often styled into curious forks or neat points. A gnome's clothing, though usually made in modest earth tones, is elaborately decorated with embroidery, embossing, or gleaming jewels.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Delighted Dedication</name>
      <text>As far as gnomes are concerned, being alive is a wonderful thing, and they squeeze every ounce of enjoyment out of their three to five centuries of life. Humans might wonder about getting bored over the course of such a long life, and elves take plenty of time to savor the beauties of the world in their long years, but gnomes seem to worry that even with all that time, they can't get in enough of the things they want to do and see.
	Gnomes speak as if they can't get the thoughts out of their heads fast enough. Even as they offer ideas and opinions on a range of subjects, they manage to listen carefully to others, adding the appropriate exclamations of surprise and appreciation along the way.
	Though gnomes love jokes of all kinds, particularly puns and pranks, they're just as dedicated to the more serious tasks they undertake. Many gnomes are skilled engineers, alchemists, tinkerers, and inventors. They're willing to make mistakes and laugh at themselves in the process of perfecting what they do, taking bold (sometimes foolhardy) risks and dreaming large.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Bright Burrows</name>
      <text>Gnomes makes their homes in hilly, wooded lands. They live underground but get more fresh air than dwarves do, enjoying the natural, living world on the surface where ever they can. Their homes are well hidden by both clever construction and simple illusions. Welcome visitors are quickly ushered into the bright, warm burrows. Those who are not welcome are unlikely to find the burrows in the first place.
	Gnomes who settle in human lands are commonly gemcutters, engineers, sages, or tinkerers. Some human families retained gnome tutors, ensuring that their pupils enjoy a mix of serious learning and delighted enjoyment. A gnome might tutor several generations of a single human family over the course of his or her long life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Gnome Names</name>
      <text>Gnomes love names, and most have half a dozen or so. A gnome's mother, father, clan elder, aunts, and uncles each give the gnome a name, and various nicknames from just about everyone else might or might not stick over time. Gnome names are typically variants on the names of ancestors or distant relatives, though some are truly new inventions. When dealing with humans and others who are "Stuffy" about names, a gnome learns to use no more than three names; A personal name, a clan name, and a nickname, choosing the one in each category that's the most fun to say.

Male Names: Alston, Alvyn, Boddynock, Brocc, Ettrgell, Dimble, Eldon, Erky, Fonkin, Frug, Gerbo, Gimble, Glim, Jebeddo, Kellen, Namfoodle. Orryn, Roondar, Seebo, Warryn, Wrenn, Zook

Female Names: Bimpnottin, Breena, Caramip, Carlin, Donella, Duvamil, Ella, Ellyjobell, Ellywick, Lilli, Loopmottin, Lorilla, Mardnab, Nissa, Nyx, Oda, Orla, Roywyn, Shamil, Tana, Waywocket, Zanna

Clan Names: Beren, Daergel, Folkor, Garrick, Nackle, Murnig, Ningcl, Raulnor, Seheppen, Timbers, Turen

Nicknames: Aleslosh, Aslthearth, Badger, Cloak, Doublelock, Filchbatter, Fnipper, Ku, Nina, Oneshoe, Pock, Sparklegem, Scumbleduck</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Seeing The World</name>
      <text>Curious and impulsive, gnomes might take up adventuring as a way to see the world or for the love of exploring. As lovers of gems and other fine items, some gnomes take to adventuring as s quick, if dangerous, path to wealth. Regardless of what spurs them to adventure, gnomes who adopt this way of life eke as much enjoyment out of it as they do out of any other activity they undertake, sometimes to the great annoyance of their adventuring companions.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Deep gnomes are short-lived for gnomes. They mature at the same rate humans do and are considered full-grown adults by 25. They live 200 to 250 years, although hard toil and the dangers of the Underdark often claim them before their time.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Svirfneblin believe that survival depends on avoiding entanglements with other creatures and not making enemies, so they favor neutral alignments. They rarely wish others ill, and they are unlikely to take risks on behalf of others.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>A typical svirfneblin stands about 3 to 3½ feet tall and weighs 80 to 120 pounds. Your size is Small.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d4
Height = 2 feet + 11 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 35 + your size modifier</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Gnome Cunning</name>
      <text>You have advantage on Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws against magic.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Superior Darkvision</name>
      <text>Accustomed to life underground, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 120 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>You have an innate ability to cast the following spells, requiring no material components:

	• At will: nondetection (self only)
	• 1/Day each: blindness/deafness, blur, disguise self

Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for these spells.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Gnomish, Terran, and Undercommon.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Goblin (DMG NPC)</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Str -2, Dex +2</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Goblins occupy an uneasy place in a dangerous world, and they react by lashing out at any creatures they believe they can bully. Cunning in battle and cruel in victory, goblins are fawning and servile in defeat, just as in their own society lower castes must scrape before those of greater status and as goblin tribes bow before other goblinoids.

Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Goblins mature faster than humans, reaching adulthood around age 12. They age noticeably faster, and though few goblins live to old age, the most cautious rarely live longer than 50 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Most goblins are wildly chaotic, with no particular inclination toward good or evil but a strong tendency toward mischief.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Goblins are between 3 and 4 feet tall and weigh between 40 and 80 pounds. Your size is Small.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d4
Height = 3 feet + 5 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 35 + your size modifier</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Nimble Escape</name>
      <text>You can take the Disengage or Hide action as a bonus action on each of your turns.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Accustomed to life underground, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Goblin.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Grimlock (DMG NPC)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Str +2, Cha -2</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Blindsight</name>
      <text>You have no eyes, and cannot be blinded. You can perceive your surroundings within 30 ft., or 10 ft. while deafened. You are considered blind beyond this radius.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Keen Hearing and Smell</name>
      <text>You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or smell.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Stone Camouflage</name>
      <text>You have advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide in rocky terrain.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Undercommon.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Hobgoblin (DMG NPC)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>War is the lifeblood of hobgoblins. Its glories are the dreams that inspire them. Its horrors don't feature in their nightmares. Cowardice is more terrible to hobgoblins than dying, for they carry their living acts into the afterlife. A hero in death becomes a hero eternal.

Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Hobgoblins mature at the same rate as humans and have lifespans similar in length to theirs.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Hobgoblin society is built on fidelity to a rigid, unforgiving code of conduct. As such, they tend toward lawful evil.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Hobgoblins are between 5 and 6 feet tall and weigh between 150 and 200 pounds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d10
Height = 4 feet + 8 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 110 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Martial Advantage</name>
      <text>Once per turn, you can deal an extra 2d6 damage to a creature you hit with a weapon attack if that creature is within 5 ft. of an ally of yours that isn't incapacitated.</text>
      <roll description="Extra Damage">2d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Goblin.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Kenku (DMG NPC)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Dex +2</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Haunted by an ancient crime that robbed them of their wings, the flightless kenku wander the world as vagabonds and burglars who live at the edge of human society. Kenku suffer from a sinister reputation that is not wholly unearned, but they can prove to be valuable allies.

Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Kenku have shorter lifespans than humans. They reach maturity at about 12 years old and can live to 60.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Kenku are chaotic creatures, rarely making enduring commitments, and they care mostly for preserving their own hides. They are generally chaotic neutral in outlook.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Kenku are around 5 feet tall and weigh between 90 and 120 pounds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 4 feet + 4 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 50 + (1d6 × your size modifier)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Ambusher</name>
      <text>In the first round of a combat, you have advantage on attack rolls against any creature who is surprised.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Mimicry</name>
      <text>You can mimic any sounds you have heard, including voices. A creature that hears the sounds can tell they are imitations with a successful DC 14 Wisdom (Insight) check.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can read and write Common and Auran, but you can only speak using your Mimicry trait.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Kobold (DMG NPC)</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Dex +2, Str -4</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Kobolds are often dismissed as cowardly, foolish, and weak, but these little reptilian creatures actually have a strong social structure that stresses devotion to the tribe, are clever with their hands, and viciously work together in order to overcome their physical limitations.

Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Kobolds reach adulthood at age 6 and can live up to 120 years but rarely do so.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Kobolds are fundamentally selfish, making them evil, but their reliance on the strength of their group makes them trend toward law.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Kobolds are between 2 and 3 feet tall and weigh between 25 and 35 pounds. Your size is Small.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>You have advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of your allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Accustomed to life underground, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>You have disadvantage on attack rolls and on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight when you, the target of your attack, or whatever you are trying to perceive is in direct sunlight.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Draconic.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Kuo-Toa (DMG NPC)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Kuo-toa, also known as gogglers and men-fish, were a debased, piscine race of warm-blooded and amphibious creatures that dwelt in the Underdark. Sinister secrets lurked below the surface of their alien minds, for the kuo-toa were fanatics plagued by mental instability that saw things others couldn't and worshiped gods that didn't exist | at least until they believed hard enough.

Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>You can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Otherworldly Perception</name>
      <text>You can sense the presence of any creature within 30 feet of you that is invisible or on the Ethereal Plane. You can pinpoint such a creature that is moving.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Slippery</name>
      <text>You have advantage on ability checks and saving throws made to escape a grapple.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Superior Darkvision</name>
      <text>You have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 120 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, you have disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Undercommon.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Lizardfolk (DMG)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Str +2, Int -2</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Lizardfolk possess an alien and inscrutable mindset, their desires and thoughts driven by a different set of basic principles than those of warm-blooded creatures. Their dismal swamp homes might lie hundreds of miles from the nearest human settlement, but the gap between their way of thinking and that of the smooth-skins is far greater.

Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Lizardfolk Personality</name>
      <text>You can use the Lizardfolk Quirks table to determine a personality quirk for a lizardfolk character or to inspire a unique mannerism.

Lizardfolk Personality:
d8 | Quirk
1 | You hate waste and see no reason not to scavenge fallen enemies. Fingers are tasty and portable!
2 | You sleep best while mostly submerged in water.
3 | Money is meaningless to you.
4 | You think there are only two species of humanoid: lizardfolk and meat.
5 | You have learned to laugh. You use this talent in response to all emotional situations, to better fit in with your comrades.
6 | You still don't understand how metaphors work. That doesn't stop you from using them at every opportunity.
7 | You appreciate the soft humanoids who realize they need chain mail and swords to match the gifts you were born with.
8 | You enjoy eating your food while it's still wriggling.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Lizardfolk reach maturity around age 14 and rarely live longer than 60 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Lizardfolk are a little bulkier and taller than humans, and their colorful frills make them appear even larger. Your size is Medium.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Most lizardfolk are neutral. They see the world as a place of predators and prey, where life and death are natural processes. They wish only to survive, and prefer to leave other creatures to their own devices.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>You can hold your breath for up to 15 minutes at a time.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Natural Armor</name>
      <text>Your scales function as natural armor, granting you a +3 bonus to Armor Class.</text>
      <modifier category="bonus">ac +3</modifier>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Draconic.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Merfolk (DMG NPC)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>10</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Merfolk are an amphibious race, born and at home in the water but comfortable on dry land. Humanoid in form, they have skin of ivory, silver, russet, blue, or deep purple. Long fins extend from the backs of their forearms and calves, and their fingers and toes are webbed. The hairlike growths on their heads are either thick and bristly like the needles of a sea urchin, or long and wavy, resembling fine seaweed. In either case, these growths typically range in color from red to warm brown to black. Male merfolk have similar growths extending down from their cheekbones.

Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>You can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Aquan.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Orc (DMG)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Str +2, Int -2</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>To feel the thunder of orcish war drums outside the gate and to hear a chorus of voices growling, "Gruumsh!" is the nightmare of every civilized place in the world. For no matter how thick its walls, skilled its archers, or brave its knights, few settlements have ever withstood a full-scale onslaught of orcs.
	Every soldier who lives through a fight with orcs tells of confronting a hulking foe that can cleave through a warrior with a single blow, part of a force that can cut down enemies as though they were trembling stalks of wheat before the scythe. Only a skilled and determined hero can hope to survive single combat with an orc.
	Savage and fearless, orc tribes are ever in search of elves, dwarves, and humans to destroy. Motivated by their hatred of the civilized races of the world and their need to satisfy the demands of their deities, the orcs know that if they fight well and bring glory to their tribe, Gruumsh will call them home to the plane of Acheron. It is there in the afterlife where the chosen ones will join Gruumsh and his armies in their endless extraplanar battle for supremacy.

Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Orcs reach adulthood at age 12 and live up to 50 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Orcs are vicious raiders, who believe that the world should be theirs. They also respect strength above all else and believe the strong must bully the weak to ensure that weakness does not spread like a disease. They are usually chaotic evil.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Orcs are usually over 6 feet tall and weigh between 230 and 280 pounds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 5 feet + 4 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 175 + (2d6 × your size modifier)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Accustomed to life underground, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Aggressive</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, you can move up to your speed toward a hostile creature that you can see.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Orc.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Skeleton (DMG NPC)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Dex +2, Int -4, Cha -4</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Brittle Bones</name>
      <text>You are vulnerable to bludgeoning damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Undead Nature</name>
      <text>You are immune to poison damage and exhaustion, and you can't be poisoned. You don't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can't speak, but you can understand the languages you knew in life.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Troglodyte (DMG NPC)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Str +2, Con +2, Int -4, Cha -4</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Chameleon Skin</name>
      <text>You have advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Stench</name>
      <text>Any creature other than a Troglodyte that starts its turn within 5 ft. of you must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned until the start of the creature's next turn. On a successful saving throw, the creature is immune to the stench of all Troglodytes for 1 hour.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, you have disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Natural Armor</name>
      <text>Your thick hide grants you a +1 bonus to Armor Class.</text>
      <modifier category="bonus">ac +1</modifier>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Troglodyte.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Zombie (DMG NPC)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Str +1, Con +2, Int -6, Wis -4, Cha -4</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Source:	Dungeon Master's Guide (2014) p. 282</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Undead Fortitude</name>
      <text>If damage reduces you to 0 hit points, you must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5 + the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, you drop to 1 hit point instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Undead Nature</name>
      <text>You are immune to poison damage and exhaustion, and you can't be poisoned. You don't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can't speak, but you can understand the languages you knew in life.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
</compendium>
