<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <!-- Blade of the Medusa -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>%name% of the Medusa</name>
    <detail>very rare, cursed (requires attunement)</detail>
    <match>Double-Bladed Scimitar,Greatsword,Longsword,Rapier,Scimitar,Shortsword</match>
    <text>When you attack a creature with this magic weapon and roll a 20 on the attack roll, the creature must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw in addition to suffering the attack's normal effects. On a failed save, the creature is restrained and must make another Constitution saving throw at the end of each of its turns. If it successfully saves against this effect three times, the effect ends. If it fails its saves three times, it is turned to stone and subjected to the petrified condition for 1 hour.
	A creature is immune to this effect if it is immune to damage of the weapon's type, does not have a body made of flesh, or has legendary actions.

Curse: This weapon is cursed, and becoming attuned to it extends the curse to you. Until the curse is broken with a remove curse spell or similar magic, you are unwilling to part with the weapon. Whenever you attack a creature with this weapon and roll a 1 on the attack roll, you must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or be restrained and forced to make additional saves against being petrified, as above.</text>
    <source>Lost Laboratory of Kwalish p. 53</source>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Gambler's Blade -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Gambler's %name%</name>
    <detail>rare, cursed (requires attunement)</detail>
    <match>Double-Bladed Scimitar,Greatsword,Longsword,Rapier,Scimitar,Shortsword</match>
    <text>Choose a magical bonus of +1 to +3. This sword gains that bonus to its attack and damage rolls. For each point of bonus you choose for the sword, you take a corresponding penalty (−1 to −3) to your death saving throws. You can change this magical bonus each day at dawn.

Curse: This weapon is cursed, and becoming attuned to it extends the curse to you. Until the curse is broken with a remove curse spell or similar magic, you are unwilling to part with the weapon.</text>
    <source>Lost Laboratory of Kwalish p. 55</source>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Polymorph Blade -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Polymorph %name%</name>
    <detail>very rare, cursed (requires attunement)</detail>
    <match>Double-Bladed Scimitar,Greatsword,Longsword,Rapier,Scimitar,Shortsword</match>
    <text>When you attack a creature with this magic weapon and roll a 20 on the attack roll, the creature must make a DC 15 Wisdom saving throw in addition to suffering the attack's normal effects. On a failed save, the creature also suffers the effects of a polymorph spell. Roll a d20 and consult the following table to determine the form the target creature is transformed into.

Polymorph:
d20 | New Form
1 | Tyrannosaurus Rex
2 | Giant Ape
3 | Elephant
4 | Giant scorpion
5 | Rhinoceros
6 | Polar bear
7 | Giant toad
8 | Giant eagle
9 | Black bear
10 | Crocodile
11 | Wolf
12 | Riding Horse
13 | Ox
14 | Giant frog
15 | Poisonous snake
16 | Hawk
17 | Octopus
18 | Cat
19 | Rat
20 | Rabbit

A creature is immune to this effect if it is immune to damage of the weapon's type, is a shapechanger, or has legendary actions.

Curse: This weapon is cursed, and becoming attuned to it extends the curse to you. Until the curse is broken with a remove curse spell or similar magic, you are unwilling to part with the weapon. Whenever you attack a creature with this weapon and roll a 1 on the attack roll, you suffer the effect of a polymorph spell for 1 hour, rolling on the table to determine your new form.</text>
    <source>Lost Laboratory of Kwalish p. 56</source>
    <roll description="Polymorph">1d20</roll>
  </itemtemplate>
</compendium>
