<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Druid (One DnD)</name>
    <hd>8</hd>
    <proficiency>Intelligence, Wisdom, Arcana, Animal Handling, Insight, Medicine, Nature, Perception, Religion, Survival</proficiency>
    <spellAbility>Wisdom</spellAbility>
    <numSkills>2</numSkills>
    <armor>Light Armor, Shields</armor>
    <weapons>Simple Weapons</weapons>
    <tools>herbalism kit</tools>
    <subclass>Druid Subclass</subclass>

    <autolevel level="1"><slots>2, 2</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2"><slots>2, 3</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3"><slots>2, 4, 2</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4"><slots>3, 4, 3</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5"><slots>3, 4, 3, 2</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6"><slots>3, 4, 3, 3</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7"><slots>3, 4, 3, 3, 1</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8"><slots>3, 4, 3, 3, 2</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9"><slots>3, 4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10"><slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11"><slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12"><slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13"><slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14"><slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15"><slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16"><slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17"><slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18"><slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19"><slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1</slots></autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20"><slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 2, 2, 1, 1</slots></autolevel>

    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Starting Druid</name>
        <text>As a 1st-level Druid, you begin play with 8 + your Constitution modifier hit points.

You are proficient with the following items, in addition to any proficiencies provided by your race or background.

	• Armor: Light Armor, Shields
	• Weapons: Simple Weapons
	• Tools: herbalism kit
	• Skills: Choose two from Arcana, Animal Handling, Insight, Medicine, Nature, Perception, Religion, and Survival

As a level 1 character, you start with the following equipment, or you can forgo it and spend 50 GP on equipment of your choice:

	• Druidic Focus
	• Quarterstaff
	• Explorer's Pack
	• Herbalism Kit
	• Leather Armor
	• Shield
	• Sickle
	• 9 GP

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 8</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Multiclass Druid</name>
        <text>If your group uses the multiclassing rules in the Player's Handbook, here's what you need to know if you choose Druid as one of your classes.

Ability Score Minimum:
As a multiclass character, you must have a score of at least 13 in the Druid's primary ability, Wisdom, to take a level in this class or to take a level in another class if you're already a Druid.

Armor Training:
When you gain your first Druid level, you gain armor training with the following: Light Armor and Shields.

Spell Slots:
Add all your Druid levels to the appropriate levels from other classes to determine your available spell slots for casting spells, as detailed in the multiclassing rules.

You prepare spells for each of your classes individually, referring to the spell slots of an individual class to determine the number and levels of the spells you prepare for it.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 8</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature>
        <name>Druidic</name>
        <text>You know Druidic, the secret language of Druids. While learning this ancient tongue, you also unlocked the magic of speaking to animals; you always have the Speak with Animals spell prepared.

You can use Druidic to leave hidden messages. You and others who know Druidic automatically spot such a message. Others spot the message's presence with a successful DC 15 Intelligence (Investigation) check but can't decipher it without magic.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 8</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature>
        <name>Primal Order</name>
        <text>You have dedicated yourself to one of the following sacred roles of your choice:

Magician:
You know one extra cantrip from the Druid spell list (see your Spellcasting feature for information on preparing spells). In addition, your mystical connection to nature gives you a bonus to your Intelligence (Nature) checks. The bonus equals your Wisdom modifier (minimum of +1).

Warden:
Trained for battle, you gain Martial Weapon proficiency and armor training with Medium Armor.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 8</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
        <text>You have learned to cast spells through studying the mystical forces of nature. See the Player's Handbook for the rules on spellcasting. The information below details how you use those rules as a Druid.

Cantrips:
You know two cantrips of your choice from the Druid spell list. Rather than choosing, you may start with the Druidcraft and Produce Flame cantrips.

Whenever you gain a Druid level, you can replace one of your cantrips with another cantrip of your choice from the Druid spell list.

When you reach levels 4 and 10 in this class, you learn another cantrip of your choice from the Druid spell list, as shown in the Cantrips column of the Druid table.

Spell Slots:
The Druid table shows how many spell slots you have to cast your spells of level 1 and higher. To cast one of these spells, you must expend a slot of the spell's level or higher. You regain all expended spell slots when you finish a Long Rest.

Prepared Spells of Level 1+:
You prepare the list of spells of level 1 and higher that are available for you to cast with this feature. To start, choose four level 1 spells from the Druid spell list. Rather than choosing, you may start with the Animal Friendship, Cure Wounds, Faerie Fire, and Thunderwave spells.

The number of spells on your list also increases as you gain Druid levels, as shown in the Prepared Spells column of the Druid table. Whenever that number increases, choose additional spells from the Druid spell list until the number of spells on your list matches the number on the table. The chosen spells must be of a level for which you have spell slots. For example, if you're a level 3 Druid, your list of prepared spells can include six spells of levels 1 and 2 in any combination.

If another Druid feature gives spells that you always have prepared, those spells don't count against the number of spells on the list you prepare with this Spellcasting feature, but those spells otherwise follow the rules in this feature.

Changing Your Prepared Spells:
Whenever you finish a Long Rest, you can change your list of prepared spells, replacing one or more of the spells there with other Druid spells for which you have spell slots. Preparing a new list requires time spent in meditation: at least 1 minute per spell level for each spell you add to the list.

Spellcasting Ability:
Wisdom is your Spellcasting Ability for your Druid spells.

Spellcasting Focus:
You can use a Druidic Focus as a Spellcasting Focus for the spells you prepare for this class.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 9</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature>
        <name>Wild Companion</name>
        <text>You can summon a nature spirit that assumes an animal form to aid you. As a Magic action, you can expend a spell slot or a use of Wild Shape to cast the Find Familiar spell without material components.

When you cast the spell in this way, the familiar is a Fey, and it disappears when you finish a Long Rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 9</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature>
        <name>Wild Shape</name>
        <text>The power of nature infuses you, allowing you to assume the form of an animal. As a Bonus Action, you transform into a Beast form that you have learned for this feature (see "Known Forms" below). You stay in that form for a number of hours equal to half your Druid level or until you use Wild Shape again, have the Incapacitated condition, or die. You can also leave the form early as a Bonus Action.

Known Forms:
You know a number of forms for this feature equal to 2 plus half your Druid level (round up), chosen from among Beast stat blocks in the Player's Handbook that have a maximum Challenge Rating of 1/4 and that lack a Fly Speed. Rather than choosing, you may start with the Riding Horse, Spider, and Wolf. Whenever you finish a Long Rest, you can replace one of your known forms with another eligible form.

When you gain certain Druid levels, the maximum Challenge Rating for your forms increases, as shown in the Beast Shapes table. In addition, starting at level 8, you can adopt a form that has a Fly Speed.

When choosing a new form, you may look in the Monster Manual or elsewhere for eligible Beasts if the DM permits you to do so.

Druid Level | Max CR | Fly Speed
2 | 1/4 | No
4 | 1/2 | No
8 | 1 | Yes

Number of Uses:
You can use Wild Shape twice. You regain one expended use when you finish a Short Rest, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a Long Rest.

You gain additional uses when you reach certain Druid levels, as shown in the Wild Shape column of the Druid table.

Rules While Transformed:
While in a form, you retain your personality, memories, and ability to speak, and the following rules apply:

Game Statistics:
Your game statistics are replaced by the statistics of the Beast, but you retain your Hit Points; Hit Dice; Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma scores; class features; languages; and feats. You also retain your skill and saving throw proficiencies and use your Proficiency Bonus for them, in addition to gaining those of the creature. If the creature has the same proficiency as you and the bonus in its stat block is higher than yours, use the creature's bonus instead of yours. If the creature has any legendary or lair actions, you can't use them.

Temporary Hit Points:
When you assume a Wild Shape form, you gain a number of Temporary Hit Points equal to your Druid level.

No Spellcasting:
You can't cast spells, but transforming doesn't break your Concentration on a spell you've already cast or prevent you from taking actions that are part of a spell, such as the Call Lightning spell, that you've already cast.

Objects:
Your ability to handle objects is determined by the form's limbs rather than your own. In addition, you choose whether your equipment falls to the ground in your space, merges into your new form, or is worn by it. Worn equipment functions as normal, but the DM decides whether it is practical for the new form to wear a piece of equipment based on the creature's size and shape. Your equipment doesn't change size or shape to match the new form, and any equipment that the new form can't wear must either fall to the ground or merge with it. Equipment that merges with the form has no effect until you leave the form.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 9</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Wild Shape</name>
        <value>2</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter></autolevel>

    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature>
        <name>Druid Subclass</name>
        <text>You gain a Druid subclass of your choice: Circle of the Land, Circle of the Moon, Circle of the Sea, or Circle of the Stars. Only The Circle of the Moon subclass is detailed after this class's description.

A subclass is a specialization that grants you special abilities at certain Druid levels. For the rest of your career, you gain each of your subclass's features that are of your Druid level and lower.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 10</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat or another feat of your choice for which you qualify.

As shown on the Druid table, you gain this feature again at levels 8, 12, 16, and 19.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 10</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="5">
      <feature>
        <name>Wild Resurgence</name>
        <text>If you have no uses of Wild Shape left, you can give yourself one use by expending a spell slot (no action required). You can do so only once per turn.

In addition, you can expend one use of Wild Shape (no action required) to give yourself a level 1 spell slot, and you can't do so again until you finish a Long Rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 10</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Wild Resurgence</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter></autolevel>

    <autolevel level="6">
      <counter>
        <name>Wild Shape</name>
        <value>3</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter></autolevel>

    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature>
        <name>Elemental Fury</name>
        <text>The might of the elements flows through you. You gain one of the following options of your choice:

Potent Spellcasting:
You add your Wisdom modifier to the damage you deal with any Druid cantrip.

Primal Strike:
Once on each of your turns when you hit a creature with an attack roll using a weapon or a Beast form's attack in Wild Shape, you can cause the target to take an extra 1d8 Cold, Fire, Lightning, or Thunder damage (choose when you hit).

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 10</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat or another feat of your choice for which you qualify.

As shown on the Druid table, you gain this feature again at levels 8, 12, 16, and 19.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 10</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="9">
      <feature>
        <name>Commune with Nature</name>
        <text>You are an expression of nature itself and can commune with the natural world all around you; you always have the Commune with Nature spell prepared.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat or another feat of your choice for which you qualify.

As shown on the Druid table, you gain this feature again at levels 8, 12, 16, and 19.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 10</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature>
        <name>Improved Elemental Fury</name>
        <text>The option you chose for Elemental Fury grows more powerful:

Potent Spellcasting:
When you cast a Druid cantrip with a range of 10 feet or greater, the spell's range increases by 300 feet.

Primal Strike:
The extra damage of your Primal Strike increases to 2d8.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat or another feat of your choice for which you qualify.

As shown on the Druid table, you gain this feature again at levels 8, 12, 16, and 19.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 10</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="16">
      <counter>
        <name>Wild Shape</name>
        <value>4</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter></autolevel>

    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature>
        <name>Beast Spells</name>
        <text>While using Wild Shape, you can cast spells in Beast form, except for any spell that has a Material component with a cost specified or that consumes its Material component.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="19" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat or another feat of your choice for which you qualify.

As shown on the Druid table, you gain this feature again at levels 8, 12, 16, and 19.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 10</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="20">
      <feature>
        <name>Archdruid</name>
        <text>The vitality of nature constantly blooms within you, granting you the following benefits:

Evergreen Wild Shape:
Whenever you roll Initiative and have no uses of Wild Shape left, you regain one expended use of it.

Nature Magician:
You can convert uses of Wild Shape into a spell slot (no action required). Choose a number of your unexpended uses of Wild Shape and convert them into a single spell slot, with each use contributing 2 spell levels. You must then finish a Long Rest before you can do so again. For example, if you convert two uses of Wild Shape, you produce a level 4 spell slot.

Longevity:
The primal magic that you wield causes you to age more slowly. For every 10 years that pass, your body ages only 1 year.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Druid Subclass: Circle Of The Moon (One DnD)</name>
        <text>Druids of the Circle of the Moon draw on the magic of the moon to transform themselves and to guard the wilds. Their order gathers under the full moon to share news and perform rituals. They wander the deepest parts of the wilderness, where they might go for weeks before crossing paths with another person, let alone another Druid.

Changeable as the moon, a Druid of this circle might prowl as a great cat one night, soar over the treetops as an eagle the next day, and crash through the undergrowth as a bear to drive off a trespassing monster. The wild is in the Druid's blood.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Circle Of The Moon (One DnD): Circle Spells</name>
        <text>Your connection to this circle ensures that you always have certain spells ready. When you reach a Druid level specified in the Circle of the Moon Spells table, you thereafter always have the listed spells prepared.

In addition, you can cast the spells from this feature while you are in Wild Shape form.

Circle Of The Moon (One DnD) Spells:
Level | Spells
3 | Cure Wounds, Moonbeam, Starry Wisp*
5 | Vampiric Touch
7 | Fount of Moonlight*
9 | Dawn

*The spell is introduced in this document.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Circle Of The Moon (One DnD): Circle Forms</name>
        <text>You have learned ancient techniques that allow you to channel lunar magic when you assume a Wild Shape form, granting you the following benefits:

Challenge Rating:
The maximum Challenge Rating for the form equals your Druid level divided by 3 (round down).

Armor Class:
Your AC equals 13 plus your Wisdom modifier until you leave the form.

Temporary Hit Points:
You gain a number of Temporary Hit Points equal to three times your Druid level.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 12</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Circle Of The Moon (One DnD): Improved Circle Forms</name>
        <text>While in a Wild Shape form, you gain the following benefits:

Lunar Radiance:
Each of your attacks in a Wild Shape form can deal its normal damage type or Radiant damage. You make this choice each time you hit with those attacks.

Increased Toughness:
You can add your Wisdom modifier to your Constitution saving throws.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 12</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Circle Of The Moon (One DnD): Moonlight Step</name>
        <text>You magically transport yourself, reappearing amid a burst of moonlight. As a Bonus Action, you teleport up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space you can see, and you have Advantage on the next attack roll you make before the end of this turn.

You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a Long Rest. You can also regain uses by expending a spell slot of level 2 or higher for each use you want to restore (no action required).

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 12</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Circle Of The Moon (One DnD): Lunar Form</name>
        <text>The power of the moon suffuses you, granting you the following benefits:

Improved Lunar Radiance:
Each of your attacks in a Wild Shape form deals an extra 1d10 Radiant damage on a hit.

Shared Moonlight:
Whenever you use Moonlight Step, you can also teleport one willing creature. That creature must be within 10 feet of you, and you teleport it to an unoccupied space you can see within 10 feet of your destination space.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 12</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>

  <spell>
    <name>Cure Wounds</name>
    <classes>Druid (Moon (One DnD))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Moonbeam</name>
    <classes>Druid (Moon (One DnD))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Starry Wisp (UA)</name>
    <classes>Druid (Moon (One DnD))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Vampiric Touch</name>
    <classes>Druid (Moon (One DnD))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Fount of Moonlight (UA)</name>
    <classes>Druid (Moon (One DnD))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Dawn</name>
    <classes>Druid (Moon (One DnD))</classes>
  </spell>
</compendium>
