<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Monk (One DnD)</name>
    <hd>8</hd>
    <proficiency>Strength, Dexterity, Acrobatics, Athletics, History, Insight, Religion, Stealth</proficiency>
    <spellAbility/>
    <numSkills>2</numSkills>
    <armor>none</armor>
    <weapons>Simple Weapons, Martial Weapons that have the Light property</weapons>
    <tools>Artisan's Tools or Musical Instrument</tools>
    <subclass>Monk Subclass</subclass>

    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Starting Monk</name>
        <text>As a 1st-level Monk, you begin play with 8 + your Constitution modifier hit points.

You are proficient with the following items, in addition to any proficiencies provided by your race or background.

	• Armor: none
	• Weapons: Simple Weapons, Martial Weapons that have the Light property
	• Tools: Choose one type of Artisan's Tools or Musical Instrument
	• Skills: Choose two from Acrobatics, Athletics, History, Insight, Religion, and Stealth

As a level 1 character, you start with the following equipment, or you can forgo it and spend 65 GP on equipment of your choice:

	• Artisan's Tools
	• Dagger (5)
	• Explorer's Pack
	• Musical Instrument
	• Spear
	• 9 GP

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 14</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Multiclass Monk</name>
        <text>If your group uses the multiclassing rules in the Player's Handbook, here's what you need to know if you choose Monk as one of your classes.

Ability Score Minimum:
As a multiclass character, you must have a score of at least 13 in the Monk's primary abilities, Dexterity and Wisdom, to take a level in this class or to take a level in another class if you're already a Monk.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 14</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature>
        <name>Martial Arts</name>
        <text>Your practice of martial arts gives you mastery of combat styles that use your Unarmed Strike and Monk Weapons, which are Simple Melee Weapons and Martial Weapons with the Light property.

You gain the following benefits while you are unarmed or wielding only Monk Weapons and you aren't wearing armor or wielding a Shield:

Bonus Unarmed Strike:
You can make one Unarmed Strike as a Bonus Action.

Dexterous Attacks:
You can use Dexterity instead of Strength for the attack and damage rolls of your Unarmed Strikes and Monk Weapons. In addition, when you choose the Grapple or Shove option, you can use your Dexterity modifier instead of Strength to determine the saving throw DC.

Martial Arts Die:
You can roll a d6 in place of the normal damage of your Unarmed Strike or Monk Weapons. This die changes as you gain Monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table. (d8 at level 5, d10 at level 11, d12 at level 17)

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 14</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature>
        <name>Unarmored Defense</name>
        <text>While you aren't wearing any armor or wielding a Shield, your base Armor Class equals 10 plus your Dexterity and Wisdom modifiers.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 15</text>
        <special>Unarmored Defense: Wisdom</special>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature>
        <name>Monk's Discipline</name>
        <text>Your self-discipline and martial training allow you to harness a well of extraordinary energy within yourself. Your access to this energy is represented by a number of Discipline Points. Your Monk level determines the number of points you have, as shown in the Discipline Points column of the Monk table.

You can spend these points to fuel certain Monk features. You start knowing three such features: Flurry of Blows, Patient Defense, and Step of the Wind, each of which is detailed below.

When you spend a Discipline Point, it is unavailable until you finish a Short Rest or Long Rest, at the end of which you regain all your expended points.

Some features that use Discipline Points require your target to make a saving throw. The saving throw DC equals 8 plus your Proficiency Bonus plus your Wisdom modifier.

Flurry of Blows:
You can spend 1 Discipline Point to make two Unarmed Strikes as a Bonus Action.

Patient Defense:
You can take the Disengage action as a Bonus Action. Alternatively, you can spend 1 Discipline Point to take both the Disengage and the Dodge actions as a Bonus Action.

Step of the Wind:
You can take the Dash action as a Bonus Action. Alternatively, you can spend 1 Discipline Point to take both the Disengage and Dash actions as a Bonus Action, and your jump distance is doubled for the turn.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 15</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>2</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature>
        <name>Uncanny Metabolism</name>
        <text>When you roll Initiative, you can regain all expended Discipline Points. When you do so, roll your Martial Arts die, and regain a number of Hit Points equal to your Monk level plus the number rolled.

Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a Long Rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 15</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Uncanny Metabolism</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature>
        <name>Unarmored Movement</name>
        <text>Your speed increases by 10 feet while you aren't wearing armor or wielding a Shield. This bonus increases when you reach certain Monk levels, as shown on the Monk table.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 15</text>
        <modifier category="bonus">speed +10</modifier>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature>
        <name>Deflect Attacks</name>
        <text>You can use your Reaction to deflect melee and ranged attacks against you that deal Bludgeoning, Piercing, or Slashing damage. When you do so, the total damage you take from the attack is reduced by 1d10 plus your Dexterity modifier plus your Monk level.

If you reduce the damage to 0, you can spend 1 Discipline Point to redirect some of the attack's force. If you do so, choose a creature within 5 feet of you if the attack was a melee attack or 60 feet of yourself that isn't behind Total Cover if the attack was a ranged attack. That creature must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take damage equal to two rolls of your Martial Arts die plus your Dexterity modifier. The damage is the same type dealt by the attack.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 15</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>3</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature>
        <name>Monk Subclass</name>
        <text>You gain a Monk subclass of your choice: Warrior of Mercy, Warrior of Shadow, Warrior of the Four Elements, or Warrior of the Hand. Only The Warrior of the Hand subclass is detailed after this class's description.

A subclass is a specialization that grants you special abilities at certain Monk levels. For the rest of your career, you gain each of your subclass's features that are of your Monk level and lower.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 15</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat or another feat of your choice for which you qualify.

As shown on the Monk table, you gain this feature again at levels 8, 12, 16, and 19.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 15</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>4</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="4">
      <feature>
        <name>Slow Fall</name>
        <text>You can use your Reaction when you fall to reduce any damage you take from the fall by an amount equal to five times your Monk level.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 16</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="5">
      <feature>
        <name>Extra Attack</name>
        <text>You can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 16</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>5</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="5">
      <feature>
        <name>Stunning Strike</name>
        <text>Once per turn when you hit a creature with a Monk Weapon or an Unarmed Strike, you can spend 1 Discipline Point to attempt a stunning strike. The target must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the target has the Stunned condition until the start of your next turn. On a successful save, the target takes Force damage equal to a roll of your Martial Arts die plus your Wisdom modifier.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 16</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature>
        <name>Empowered Strikes</name>
        <text>Whenever you deal damage with your Unarmed Strike, it can deal your choice of Force damage or its normal damage type.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 16</text>
        <modifier category="bonus">speed +5</modifier>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>6</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature>
        <name>Evasion</name>
        <text>When you are subjected to an effect that allows you to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, you instead take no damage if you succeed on the saving throw, and only half damage if you fail.

You don't benefit from this feature if you have the Incapacitated condition.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 16</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>7</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat or another feat of your choice for which you qualify.

As shown on the Monk table, you gain this feature again at levels 8, 12, 16, and 19.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 15</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>8</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="9">
      <feature>
        <name>Acrobatic Movement</name>
        <text>While you aren't wearing armor or wielding a Shield, you gain the ability to move along vertical surfaces and across liquids on your turn without falling during the movement.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 16</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>9</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature>
        <name>Heightened Discipline</name>
        <text>Your training has pushed your body and mind to new levels. Your Flurry of Blows, Patient Defense, and Step of the Wind gain the following benefits:

Flurry of Blows:
You can spend 1 Discipline Point to use Flurry of Blows and make three Unarmed Strikes with it instead of two.

Patient Defense:
When you spend a Discipline Point to use Patient Defense, you gain a number of Temporary Hit Points equal to two rolls of your Martial Arts die.

Step of the Wind:
When you spend a Discipline Point to use Step of the Wind, you can choose a willing creature within 5 feet of you that is Large or smaller. You move the creature with you until the end of your turn. The creature's movement doesn't provoke Opportunity Attacks.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 16</text>
        <modifier category="bonus">speed +5</modifier>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>10</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature>
        <name>Self-Restoration</name>
        <text>Through sheer force of will, you can remove one of the following conditions from yourself at the end of each of your turns: Charmed, Frightened, or Poisoned.

In addition, forgoing food and drink doesn't give you levels of Exhaustion.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 16</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="11">
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>11</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat or another feat of your choice for which you qualify.

As shown on the Monk table, you gain this feature again at levels 8, 12, 16, and 19.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 15</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>12</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="13">
      <feature>
        <name>Deflect Energy</name>
        <text>You can now use your Deflect Attacks feature against attacks that deal any damage type, not just Bludgeoning, Piercing, or Slashing.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 16</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>13</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature>
        <name>Disciplined Survivor</name>
        <text>Your physical and mental discipline grant you proficiency in all saving throws.

Additionally, whenever you make a saving throw and fail, you can spend 1 Discipline Point to reroll it and take the second result.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 16</text>
        <proficiency>constitution, intelligence, wisdom, charisma</proficiency>
        <modifier category="bonus">speed +5</modifier>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>14</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature>
        <name>Perfect Discipline</name>
        <text>When you roll Initiative and have 3 Discipline Points or fewer, you regain expended Discipline Points until you have 4.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 16</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>15</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat or another feat of your choice for which you qualify.

As shown on the Monk table, you gain this feature again at levels 8, 12, 16, and 19.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 15</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>16</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="17">
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>17</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature>
        <name>Superior Defense</name>
        <text>At the start of your turn, you can spend 3 Discipline Points to perfectly bolster yourself against harm for 1 minute or until you have the Incapacitated condition. During that time, you have resistance to all damage except Force damage.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 16</text>
        <modifier category="bonus">speed +5</modifier>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>18</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="19" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat or another feat of your choice for which you qualify.

As shown on the Monk table, you gain this feature again at levels 8, 12, 16, and 19.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 15</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>19</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="20">
      <feature>
        <name>Body And Mind</name>
        <text>You have honed your body and mind to new heights. Your Dexterity and Wisdom scores increase by 4. Your maximum for those scores is now 26.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 16</text>
        <modifier category="ability score">dexterity +4</modifier>
        <modifier category="ability score">wisdom +4</modifier>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Discipline Points</name>
        <value>20</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Monk Subclass: Warrior Of The Hand (One DnD)</name>
        <text>Warriors of the Hand are masters of unarmed combat. They learn techniques to push and trip their opponents and manipulate their own energy to protect themselves from harm.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 17</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Warrior Of The Hand (One DnD): Open Hand Technique</name>
        <text>Whenever you hit a creature with an attack granted by your Flurry of Blows, you can impose one of the following effects on that target:

Addle:
The target can't make Opportunity Attacks until the start of its next turn.

Push:
The target must succeed on a Strength saving throw, or you push it up to 15 feet away from yourself.

Topple:
The target must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw, or it has the Prone condition.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 17</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Warrior Of The Hand (One DnD): Wholeness Of Body</name>
        <text>You gain the ability to heal yourself. As a Bonus Action, you can roll your Martial Arts die. You regain a number of Hit Points equal to the number rolled plus your Wisdom modifier (minimum of 1 Hit Point regained).

You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a Long Rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 17</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Warrior Of The Hand (One DnD): Fleet Step</name>
        <text>You can easily stride out of harm's way. When you take a Bonus Action other than Step of the Wind, you can also use Step of the Wind as part of that Bonus Action.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 17</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Warrior Of The Hand (One DnD): Quivering Palm</name>
        <text>You gain the ability to set up lethal vibrations in someone's body. When you hit a creature with an Unarmed Strike, you can spend 4 Discipline Points to start these imperceptible vibrations, which last for a number of days equal to your Monk level. The vibrations are harmless unless you use your action to end them. Alternatively, when you take the Attack action on your turn, you can replace one of the attacks with this action. To use this action, you and the target must be on the same plane of existence. When you use this action, the target must make a Constitution saving throw, taking 10d12 Force damage on a failed save or half as much damage on a successful one.

You can have only one creature under the effect of this feature at a time. You can end the vibrations harmlessly without using an action.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Player's Handbook Playtest 8 p. 17</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
