<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <race>
    <name>Gith, Githyanki (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Int +1, Str +2</ability>
    <armor>Light Armor, Medium Armor</armor>
    <spellAbility>Intelligence</spellAbility>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>The warlike githyanki and the contemplative githzerai are a sundered people | two cultures that utterly despise one another. The brutal githyanki are trained from birth as warriors, while the githzerai hone their minds to a razor's edge in their fortresses within Limbo. But before there were githyanki or githzerai, these creatures were a single race enslaved by the illithids.
	Although they attempted to overthrow their masters many times, their rebellions were repeatedly crushed until a great leader named Gith arose. After much bloodshed, Gith and her followers threw off the yoke of their illithid masters, but another leader named Zerthimon emerged in the aftermath of battle. Zerthimon challenged Gith's motives, claiming that her strict martial leadership and desire for vengeance amounted to little more than another form of slavery for her people. A rift erupted between followers of each leader, and they eventually became the two races whose enmity endures to this day: the Githyanki in the way of Gith, and the Githzerai in the way of Zerthimon.
	Whether these tall, gaunt creatures were peaceful or savage, cultured or primitive before the illithids enslaved and changed them, none can say. Not even the original name of their race remains from that distant time.

The githyanki plunder countless worlds from the decks of their astral vessels and the backs of red dragons. Feathers, beads, gems, and precious metals decorate their armor and weapons | the legendary silver swords with which they cut through their foes. Since winning their freedom from the illithids, the githyanki have become ruthless conquerors under the rulership of their dread lich-queen, Vlaakith.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Eladrin And Gith p. 2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Githyanki Character Concepts</name>
      <text>d4 | Githyanki Personality Trait
1 | When I'm bored I make my own excitement, and I'm always bored.
2 | I treat others as if they were animals that simply don't know any better.
3 | Violence is a spice that makes life worth living.
4 | Old age is a concept that I find fascinating. Maybe someday I too will be aged.

d4 | Githyanki Ideal
1 | Fidelity. Warriors are only as good as the vows they keep.
2 | Power. The weak rule the strong.
3 | Duty. It is by Vlaakith's will alone that I act.
4 | Freedom. No strong soul should be enslaved. Better to die first than live as another's puppet.

d4 | Githyanki Bond
1 | There is no greater duty than to serve the Revered Queen.
2 | Humanity thrives only because we conquered the illithids. Therefore, what is theirs is ours.
3 | Without battle, life has no purpose.
4 | Life is but a spark in the dark. We all go dark, but those who dare can burn bright.

d4 | Githyanki Flaw
1 | Hunger and thirst are unbearable pains to me.
2 | I can't see a non-githyanki as a real threat.
3 | I follow orders, regardless of their implications.
4 | I start projects but never finish them.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Gith reach adulthood in their late teens and live for about a century.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Githyanki tend toward lawful evil. They are self-centered, violent, and arrogant, yet they remain the faithful servants of their lich-queen, Vlaakith. Renegade Githyanki tend toward chaos as they have forsaken her will.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Gith are taller and leaner than humans, with most a slender 6 feet in height.

Average height
5'1"-7'
Average weight
92-196 lb

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d12
Height = 5 feet + 0 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 100 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Decadent Mastery</name>
      <text>You learn one language of your choice, and you are proficient with one skill or tool of your choice. In the timeless city of Tu'narath, Githyanki have bountiful time to master odd bits of knowledge.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Martial Prodigy</name>
      <text>You are proficient with light and medium armor. Your people are ever ready for war.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Githyanki Psionics</name>
      <text>You know the mage hand cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast jump once with this trait, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest. When you reach 5th level, you can cast the misty step spell once with this trait, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.
	Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for these spells. You can cast all of them without components.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Gith.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Gith, Githzerai (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Int +1, Wis +2</ability>
    <spellAbility>Wisdom</spellAbility>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>The warlike githyanki and the contemplative githzerai are a sundered people | two cultures that utterly despise one another. The brutal githyanki are trained from birth as warriors, while the githzerai hone their minds to a razor's edge in their fortresses within Limbo. But before there were githyanki or githzerai, these creatures were a single race enslaved by the illithids.
	Although they attempted to overthrow their masters many times, their rebellions were repeatedly crushed until a great leader named Gith arose. After much bloodshed, Gith and her followers threw off the yoke of their illithid masters, but another leader named Zerthimon emerged in the aftermath of battle. Zerthimon challenged Gith's motives, claiming that her strict martial leadership and desire for vengeance amounted to little more than another form of slavery for her people. A rift erupted between followers of each leader, and they eventually became the two races whose enmity endures to this day: the Githyanki in the way of Gith, and the Githzerai in the way of Zerthimon.
	Whether these tall, gaunt creatures were peaceful or savage, cultured or primitive before the illithids enslaved and changed them, none can say. Not even the original name of their race remains from that distant time.
	Focused philosophers and austere ascetics, the githzerai pursue lives of rigid order. Lean and muscular, they wear unadorned clothing free of ornamentation, keeping their own counsel and trusting few creatures outside of their own kind. Having turned their backs on their warlike githyanki kin, the githzerai maintain a strict monastic lifestyle, dwelling on islands of order in the vast sea of chaos that is the plane of Limbo.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Eladrin And Gith p. 3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Githzerai Character Concepts</name>
      <text>d4 | Githzerai Personality Trait
1 | All energy must be expended to a useful end. Frivolity is the first step to defeat.
2 | Patience in all things. The first step in any venture is the most treacherous.
3 | Emotions are a trap, meant to weaken the intellect and disturb the nerves. Pay them no heed.
4 | Begin only those tasks you will finish. Strike only that which you will kill.

d4 | Githzerai Ideal
1 | Faith. Zerthimon shall return, and I will be worthy to walk beside him.
2 | Courage. The mind can master anything if it is unfettered by fear.
3 | Duty. My people survive only because those like me place their needs above our own.
4 | Freedom. No strong soul should be enslaved. Better to die first than live as another's puppet.

d4 | Githzerai Bond
1 | Zerthimon provides an example of conduct that I strive to duplicate.
2 | Menyar-Ag hand-picked me for my duties, and I will never betray the trust he showed in me.
3 | Vlaakith and her toadies will be defeated, if not by me then by those who follow in my footsteps.
4 | I will not rest until the last elder brain is destroyed.

d4 | Githzerai Flaw
1 | I see githyanki machinations behind every threat.
2 | I believe in the supremacy of the gith and that githzerai and githyanki will align to rule the multiverse.
3 | I respond to even minor threats with overwhelming displays of force.
4 | The next time I laugh will be the first. The sound of merriment takes me to the edge of violence.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Gith reach adulthood in their late teens and live for about a century.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Githzerai tend toward lawful neutral. Their rigorous training in psychic abilities requires an implacable mental discipline.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Gith are taller and leaner than humans, with most a slender 6 feet in height.

Average height
5'1"-7'
Average weight
92-196 lb

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d12
Height = 4 feet + 11 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 90 + (1d4 × your size modifier)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Monastic Training</name>
      <text>You gain a +1 bonus to AC while you aren't wearing medium or heavy armor and aren't using a shield. All Githzerai receive basic training from monks, and the monks among them are unmatched in their defensive abilities.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Githzerai Psionics</name>
      <text>You know the mage hand cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast shield once with this trait, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest. When you reach 5th level, you can cast the detect thoughts spell once with this trait, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.
	Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for these spells. You can cast all of them without components.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Gith.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Elf, Eladrin (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Dex +2, Cha +1</ability>
    <proficiency>Perception</proficiency>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Eladrin are elves native to the Feywild, a realm of unpredictability and boundless magic. At your DM's option, you can select eladrin as the subrace for an elf character, instead of one of the elf subraces in the Player's Handbook.
	As creatures of the Feywild, eladrin can be wildly unpredictable. They tend toward an alignment of chaotic neutral, mixing a love of freedom with benign self-interest. Eladrin that embrace good or evil take their beliefs to an extreme, serving as great champions of justice or terrifying villains.

The chaotic eladrin are creatures of powerful emotions, infused with a power that can align with the magic of the seasons.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Eladrin And Gith p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>The Four Seasons</name>
      <text>Each eladrin has four distinct personality states—one for each season—that they shift between when they experience powerful emotion.

Autumn is the season of peace and goodwill, when summer's harvest is shared with all. Eladrin adopt this personality when overcome with contentment.

Winter is the season of dolor, when the vibrant energy of the world slumbers. It is a time of sadness and regret, entered when eladrin are overcome with sorrow.

Spring is the season of cheerfulness and unfettered celebration, marked by merriment as winter's sorrow passes. Eladrin enter this state when overcome with joy.

Summer is the season of boldness and aggression, a time of unfettered energy. Eladrin enter this state when overcome with fury.

You may create personality traits and flaws for each of your seasons, reflecting an eladrin's tempestuous personality. You can roll on the following tables or read them for inspiration. To add some chaos to your character, you may roll on these tables each time you change seasons.

Autumn:
d4 | Autumn Personality Trait
1 | If someone is in need, you never withhold aid.
2 | You share what you have, with little regard to your own needs.
3 | There are no simple meals, only lavish feasts.
4 | You stock up on fine food and drink. You hate going without such comforts.

d4 | Autumn Flaw
1 | You trust others without thought.
2 | You give to the point that you leave yourself without necessary supplies.
3 | Everyone is your friend, or a potential friend.
4 | You spend excessively on creature comforts.

Winter:
d4 | Winter Personality Trait
1 | The worst case is the most likely case.
2 | You preserve what you have. Better to hunger today and have food for tomorrow.
3 | The world is full of dangers. You never let your guard drop.
4 | A penny spent is a penny lost forever.

d4 | Winter Flaw
1 | Everything dies eventually. Why bother building anything that is meant to last?
2 | Nothing matters to you, and you allow others to guide your actions.
3 | Your needs come first. In winter, all must watch out for themselves.
4 | You speak only to point out the flaws in others'
plans.

Spring:
d4 | Spring Personality Trait
1 | Every day is the greatest day of your life.
2 | You do everything with enthusiasm, even the most mundane chores.
3 | You love music and song. You supply a tune yourself if no one else can.
4 | You can't stay still.

d4 | Spring Flaw
1 | You overdrink.
2 | Toil is for drudges. Yours should be a life of leisure.
3 | A pretty face infatuates you in an instant, but your fancy passes with equal speed.
4 | Anything worth doing is worth overdoing.

Summer
d4 | Summer Personality Trait
1 | You believe that direct confrontation is the best way to solve problems.
2 | Overwhelming force can solve almost anything. The tougher the problem, the more force you apply.
3 | You stand tall and strong so that others can lean on you.
4 | You maintain an intimidating front. Better to prevent fights with a show of force than be led to harm others.

d4 | Summer Flaw
1 | You are stubborn. Let others change.
2 | The best option is one that is swift, unexpected, and overwhelming.
3 | Punch first. Talk later.
4 | Your fury can carry you through anything.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increase</name>
      <text>Your Intelligence or Charisma score increases by 1 (your choice).</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Although elves reach physical maturity at about the same age as humans, the elven understanding of adulthood goes beyond physical growth to encompass worldly experience. An elf typically claims adulthood and an adult name around the age of 100 and can live to be 750 years old.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Elves love freedom, variety, and self-expression, so they lean strongly toward the gentler aspects of chaos. They value and protect others' freedom as well as their own, and they are more often good than not.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Elves range from under 5 to over 6 feet tall and have slender builds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d10
Height = 4 feet + 6 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 90 + (1d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d10</roll>
      <roll description="Height Modifier">1d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Accustomed to twilit forests and the night sky, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Keen Senses</name>
      <text>You have proficiency in the Perception skill.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put you to sleep.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Trance</name>
      <text>Elves don't need to sleep. Instead, they meditate deeply, remaining semiconscious, for 4 hours a day. (The Common word for such meditation is "trance.") While meditating, you can dream after a fashion; such dreams are actually mental exercises that have become reflexive through years of practice. After resting in this way, you gain the same benefit that a human does from 8 hours of sleep.

If you meditate during a long rest, you finish the rest after only 4 hours. You otherwise obey all the rules for a long rest; only the duration is changed.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Fey Step</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, you can magically teleport up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space you can see. Once you use this trait, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Shifting Seasons</name>
      <text>At the end of each short or long rest, you can align yourself with the magic of one season, regardless of the season that is dominating your personality. Doing so allows you to cast a certain cantrip, as shown in the Shifting Seasons Cantrips table. When you align yourself with a season's magic, you lose the cantrip associated with the previous season and gain the cantrip associated with the new season.
	Your spellcasting ability for these cantrips is Intelligence or Charisma, whichever is higher.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Elvish. Elvish is fluid, with subtle intonations and intricate grammar. Elven literature is rich and varied, and their songs and poems are famous among other races. Many bards learn their language so they can add Elvish ballads to their repertoires.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
</compendium>
