<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <!-- Blood Curses spell table-->
  <spell>
    <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of the Anxious</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Curses</classes>
    <text>As a bonus action, you harry the body or mind of a creature within 30 feet of you, making them susceptible to forceful influence. Until the end of your next turn, Charisma (Intimidation) checks made against the cursed creature have advantage.

Amplify: The next Wisdom saving throw the cursed creature makes before this curse ends has disadvantage.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of Binding</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Curses</classes>
    <text>As a bonus action, you attempt to bind a Large or smaller creature you can see within 30 feet of you, which must make a Strength saving throw. On a failure, the cursed creature's speed is reduced to 0 and it can't use reactions until the end of your next turn.

Amplify: This curse lasts for 1 minute and can affect any creature regardless of size. The cursed creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the curse on itself on a success.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of Bloated Agony</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Curses</classes>
    <text>As a bonus action, you curse a creature that you can see within 30 feet of you, causing its body to swell until the end of your next turn. For the duration, the creature has disadvantage on Strength checks and Dexterity checks, and takes 1d8 necrotic damage if it makes more than one attack during its turn.

Amplify: This curse lasts for 1 minute. The cursed creature can make a Constitution saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the curse on itself on a success.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of Corrosion</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Curses</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 15th level, Order of the Mutant

As a bonus action, you cause a creature within 30 feet of you to become poisoned. The cursed creature can make a Constitution saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the curse on itself on a success.

Amplify: The cursed creature takes 4d6 necrotic damage when you inflict this curse, and it takes this damage again each time it fails a Constitution saving throw to end the curse.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of the Exorcist</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Curses</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 15th level, Order of the Ghostslayer

As a bonus action, you choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of you that is charmed or frightened, or which is under a possession effect. The target creature is no longer charmed, frightened, or possessed.

Amplify: A creature that charmed, frightened, or possessed the target of your curse takes 3d6 psychic damage and must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or be stunned until the end of your next turn.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of Exposure</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Curses</classes>
    <text>When a creature you can see within 30 feet of you takes damage from an attack or spell, you can use your reaction to temporarily weaken its resilience. Until the end of the target's next turn, it loses resistance to all the damage types dealt by the triggering attack or spell (including for that triggering effect).

Amplify: The target instead loses invulnerability to the damage types of the triggering attack or spell, but has resistance to those damage types until the end of its next turn.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of the Eyeless</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Curses</classes>
    <text>When a creature you can see within 30 feet of you makes an attack, you can use your reaction to roll one hemocraft die and subtract the number rolled from the creature's attack roll. You can choose to use this feature after the creature's roll, but before the DM determines whether the attack hits or misses. The creature is immune to this curse if it is immune to the blinded condition.

Amplify: You apply this curse to all the creature's attack rolls until the end of the creature's turn. You roll separately for each affected attack.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of the Fallen Puppet</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Curses</classes>
    <text>When a creature you can see within 30 feet of you drops to 0 hit points, you can use your reaction to instill that creature with a final act of aggression. The creature immediately makes one weapon attack against a target of your choice within its range.

Amplify: You can first cause the cursed creature to move up to half its speed, and you grant a bonus to its attack roll equal to your Hemocraft modifier (minimum of +1).

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of the Howl</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Curses</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 18th level, Order of the Lycan

As an action, you unleash a bloodcurdling howl. Each creature within 30 feet of you that can hear you must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or become frightened of you until the end of your next turn. If a creature fails its saving throw by 5 or more, it is stunned while frightened in this way. A creature that succeeds on its saving throw is immune to this blood curse for the next 24 hours.
	You can choose any number of creatures you can see to be unaffected by the howl.

Amplify: The range of this curse increases to 60 feet.

Frightened:
	• A frightened creature has disadvantage on ability checks and attack rolls while the source of its fear is within line of sight.
	• The creature can't willingly move closer to the source of its fear.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of the Marked</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Curses</classes>
    <text>As a bonus action, you mark a creature that you can see within 30 feet of you. Until the end of your turn, whenever you hit the cursed creature with a weapon for which you have an active crimson rite, you roll an additional hemocraft die when determining the extra damage from the rite.

Amplify: The next attack roll you make against the target before the end of your turn has advantage.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of the Muddled Mind</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Curses</classes>
    <text>As a bonus action, you curse a creature that you can see within 30 feet of you that is concentrating on a spell or using a feature that requires concentration. That creature has disadvantage on the next Constitution saving throw it makes to maintain concentration before the end of your next turn.

Amplify: The cursed creature has disadvantage on all Constitution saving throws made to maintain concentration until the end of your next turn.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of the Soul Eater</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Curses</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 18th level, Order of the Profane Soul

When a creature that isn't a construct or undead is reduced to 0 hit points within 30 feet of you, you can use your reaction to offer their life energy to your patron in exchange for power. Until the end of your next turn, you make attacks with advantage and you have resistance to all damage.

Amplify: Additionally, you regain an expended warlock spell slot. Once you've amplified this blood curse, you must finish a long rest before you can amplify it again.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <!-- Mutagens spell table-->
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Aether</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 11th level Blood Hunter

You have a flying speed of 20 feet for 1 hour. However, you have disadvantage on Strength checks and Dexterity checks during this time.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Alluring</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>Your skin and voice become malleable, allowing you to enhance your appearance and presence. You have advantage on Charisma checks. However, you have disadvantage on initiative rolls.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Celerity</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>Your Dexterity score increases by 3, as does your maximum for that score. However, you have disadvantage on Wisdom saving throws. Your Dexterity score and your maximum increase by 4 if you consume this mutagen at 11th level, and by 5 at 18th level.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Conversant</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>You have advantage on Intelligence checks. However, you have disadvantage on Wisdom checks.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Cruelty</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 11th level Blood Hunter

When you use the Attack action, you can make one additional weapon attack as a bonus action. However, you have disadvantage on Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Deftness</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>You have advantage on Dexterity checks. However, you have disadvantage on Wisdom checks.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Embers</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>You have resistance to fire damage and vulnerability to cold damage.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Gelid</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>You have resistance to cold damage and vulnerability to fire damage.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Impermeable</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>You have resistance to piercing damage and vulnerability to slashing damage.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Mobility</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>You have immunity to the grappled and restrained conditions. However, you have disadvantage on Strength checks. At 11th level, you are also immune to the paralyzed condition.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Nighteye</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>You have darkvision out to a range of 60 feet. If you already have darkvision, its range increases by 60 feet. However, you have disadvantage on attack rolls and on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight when you, the target of your attack, or whatever you are trying to perceive is in direct sunlight.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Percipient</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>You have advantage on Wisdom checks. However, you have disadvantage on Charisma checks.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Potency</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>Your Strength score increases by 3, as does your maximum for that score. However, you have disadvantage on Dexterity saving throws. Your Strength score and your maximum increase by 4 if you consume this mutagen at 11th level, and by 5 at 18th level.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Precision</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 11th level Blood Hunter

Your weapon attacks score a critical hit on a roll of 19 or 20. However, you have disadvantage on Strength saving throws.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Rapidity</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>Your speed increases by 10 feet. However, you have disadvantage on Intelligence checks. At 15th level, your speed increases by an additional 5 feet.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Reconstruction</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 7th level Blood Hunter

For 1 hour, at the start of each of your turns when you have at least 1 hit point but fewer hit points than half your hit point maximum, you regain hit points equal to your proficiency bonus. However, your speed is reduced by 10 feet during this time.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Sagacity</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>Your Intelligence score increases by 3, as does your maximum for that score. However, you have disadvantage on Charisma saving throws. Your Intelligence score and your maximum increase by 4 if you consume this mutagen at 11th level, and by 5 at 18th level.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Shielded</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>You have resistance to slashing damage, and you have vulnerability to bludgeoning damage.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Unbreakable</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>You have resistance to bludgeoning damage, and you have vulnerability to piercing damage.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mutagen: Vermillion</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Blood Hunter (Order of the Mutant): Mutagens</classes>
    <text>You gain an additional use of your Blood Maledict feature. However, you have disadvantage on death saving throws.

Source:	Blood Hunter (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
</compendium>
