<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <monster>
    <name>Dream Eater</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>77 (14d8+14)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 50 ft. (hover)</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>20</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>21</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Deep Speech, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>Bludgeoning, Piercing or Slashing damage from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>Psychic</immune>
    <conditionImmune>Blinded, Charmed, Frightened, Grappled, Paralyzed, Petrified, Restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 120 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ghastly Visions</name>
      <text>Each creature that starts its turn within 30 feet of the dream eater must make a DC 16 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature is frightened of the dream eater until the start of the creature's next turn. If a creature's saving throw is successful, the creature is immune to this dream eater's Ghastly Visions trait for the next 24 hours.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Incorporeal Movement</name>
      <text>The dream eater can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. It takes 5 (1d10) force damage if it ends its turn inside an object.</text>
      <attack>Incorporeal Movement||1d10</attack>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The dream eater has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The dream eater makes two Ensnaring Shriek attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ensnaring Shriek</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Spell Attack: +8 to hit, reach 15 ft. or range 60 ft., one target. Hit: 12 (2d6 + 5) psychic damage, and if the target is a Medium or smaller creature, the target must succeed on a DC 16 Charisma saving throw or be pulled up to 15 feet toward the dream eater.</text>
      <attack>Ensnaring Shriek|+8|2d6+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Engulfing Nightmare (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The dream eater targets one creature within 5 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 16 Wisdom saving throw or be engulfed by the dream eater, as the dream eater envelops the creature in a miasma of its worst fears.

When the dream eater engulfs a target, the dream eater enters its space, and the target immediately takes 10 (3d6) psychic damage. An engulfed target is restrained and blinded, and it takes an additional 10 (3d6) psychic damage at the start of each of the dream eater's turns. When the dream eater moves, the engulfed target moves with it.

The dream eater can have only one target engulfed at a time. An engulfed target escapes at the start of its turn by making a DC 16 Wisdom saving throw. On a successful save, the target escapes; the target is no longer engulfed, and it enters a space of its choice within 5 feet of the dream eater. A creature within 15 feet of the dream eater also can use its action to attempt to free an engulfed target. Doing so requires the creature to use its action to make a DC 16 Charisma (Persuasion) check to convince the engulfed target the nightmare isn't real, with the target escaping on a success. The creature making the check takes 10 (3d6) psychic damage, regardless of the check's success or failure, as its mind brushes against the nightmare.</text>
      <attack>Engulfing Nightmare||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Originating from the dream-warped elven realm of Silvanesti, dream eaters are violent manifestations of nightmares and subconscious terrors. The true appearance of a dream eater is obscured, as the dream eater twists its hazy form into surreal illusions of its foes' greatest fears. However, all dream eaters share one thing: a gaping, always-smiling mouth, which it reveals before engulfing its prey in a phantasmagorical nightmare.
	The key to defeating a dream eater lies not in brute force but in the ability to pierce its illusions and wrest others from its terrors. As such, bards and other persuasive adventurers find themselves uniquely poised to confront a hungering dream eater.

Source:	Monstrous Compendium Vol. 2 - Dragonlance Creatures p. 3</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Ember</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>dragon (adult chromatic)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>20 (special equipment)</ac>
    <hp>270 (20d12+140)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., climb 40 ft., fly 80 ft.</speed>
    <str>28</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>25</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>22</cha>
    <save>Dex +7, Con +14, Wis +9, Cha +13</save>
    <skill>Perception +16, Religion +10, Stealth +14</skill>
    <passive>26</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>22</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>Fire</immune>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+7</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Calescent Aura</name>
      <text>At the start of Ember's turn, Ember can force any number of creatures of his choice within 10 feet of himself to make a DC 22 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 7 (2d6) fire damage and is frightened of Ember until the start of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Calescent Aura||2d6</attack>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (5/Day)</name>
      <recharge>5/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If Ember fails a saving throw, he can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>In battle, Ember dons magical plate armor custom-forged for his use. While wearing the armor, Ember adds his Charisma modifier to his weapon damage rolls (included in the attack descriptions), and his AC can't be lower than 20.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Ember makes one Bite attack and two Claw attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +16 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 26 (2d10 + 15) piercing damage plus 13 (2d6 + 6) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+16|2d10+15</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||2d6+6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +16 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 22 (2d6 + 15) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+16|2d6+15</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Firestorm Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>Ember exhales roiling flames and ash in a 90-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 22 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 56 (16d6) fire damage and is pushed up to 30 feet away from Ember and knocked prone. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage with no other effects. If a creature is reduced to 0 hit points by this effect, the creature immediately dies, and its body is reduced to ash.</text>
      <attack>Firestorm Breath||16d6</attack>
    </action>
    <legendary>
      <name>Legendary Actions (3/Turn)</name>
      <recharge>3/TURN</recharge>
      <text>Ember can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Ember regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Pursuit</name>
      <text>Ember moves up to 40 feet in a straight line toward one creature he can see. This movement ignores opportunity attacks.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Searing Bite (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Ember makes one Bite attack. If the attack hits, it deals an additional 7 (2d6) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Searing Bite||2d6</attack>
    </legendary>
    <description>"Emperor Ariakas,

Glory to the Dragon Queen's name! Our designs on Abanasinia unfold according to your plans. This is no thanks to the so-called "adviser" I've been saddled with, the dragon Ember. The beast is terrifying, both in might and cunning, but it undermines my every design and terrorizes my forces. It's too canny to be caught, but I'm certain some portion of the troops we've lost to Qualinesti ambushes in fact smolder in the wyrm's gut. It thinks I don't hear, but it whispers curses in reply to my every command. Were it not one of our queen's favored children, I would have replaced my bed linens with its hide.

I will complete our queen's work with the troops at my disposal, but when I return to Neraka, I would have this viper reassigned. I recommend to Icewall.

By Her Will, Verminaard
Highlord of the Red Dragon Army"

Also known as Pyros, Ember is an imperious and ruthless red dragon who serves the Dragon Queen Takhisis. In his service to the Dragon Queen, Ember has taken on many roles at her behest—including that of a black-robed human member of the Mages of High Sorcery—but he is best known as the adviser of Dragon Highlord Verminaard, leader of the Red Dragon Army.
	Empowered by Takhisis herself, Ember's innate fire can sear those nearby, and his breath weapon is a molten storm of ash and flame. In combat, Ember wears a set of magic plate armor that bolsters his already-impressive might, allowing him to annihilate entire cohorts with terrifying ease.

Source:	Monstrous Compendium Vol. 2 - Dragonlance Creatures p. 5</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Forest Master</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>celestial (unicorn)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Good</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>105 (14d10+28)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>19</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Int +4, Wis +7</save>
    <skill>Insight +7, Nature +4, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Celestial, Elvish, Sylvan, telepathy 60 ft.</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>Poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>Charmed, Paralyzed, Poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The Forest Master casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 15):

	• At will: druidcraft, fog cloud, guidance
	• 2/Day each: goodberry, greater restoration, pass without trace, speak with plants</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (2/Day)</name>
      <recharge>2/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the Forest Master fails a saving throw, he can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The Forest Master has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Master of Beasts</name>
      <text>The Forest Master can comprehend and communicate with any Beast, even if the Beast knows no languages.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The Forest Master makes either two Hooves attacks, two Moon Bolt attacks, or one of each.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Hooves</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 11 (2d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Hooves|+7|2d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Moon Bolt</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +7 to hit, range 60 ft., one target. Hit: 11 (2d6+4) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Moon Bolt|+7|2d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Erupting Briars (Recharge 4-6) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>D4</recharge>
      <text>The Forest Master touches his horn to the earth and causes a 5-foot-tall wall of briars to erupt in a 90-foot line that is 10 feet wide. When the wall appears, each creature in its area is pushed into the nearest unoccupied space adjacent to the wall and must make a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw, taking 27 (6d8) piercing damage on a failed save or half as much damage on a successful one.

The wall of briars lasts until the start of the Forest Master's next turn. The wall blocks line of sight and counts as difficult terrain for all creatures except the Forest Master. The first time a creature enters the wall's area on a turn, that creature must succeed on a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw or take 13 (3d8) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Erupting Briars||6d8</attack>
      <attack>First Time||3d8</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Misty Escape</name>
      <text>If the Forest Master takes damage from a melee attack, he, along with any equipment he is wearing or carrying, teleports to an unoccupied space within 30 feet that he can see.</text>
    </reaction>
    <spells>druidcraft, fog cloud, guidance, goodberry, greater restoration, pass without trace, speak with plants</spells>
    <description>Said to be older than the trees themselves, the Forest Master is a wise and powerful unicorn who rules over the creatures of Darken Wood in Krynn. The ancient being's body is wreathed in protective briars, and moonlight dances around the unicorn's horn. Those who threaten the Forest Master's lands find themselves beguiled by magical mist and nigh-impregnable thorny thickets, but those who gain the Forest Master's favor are blessed with healing and protected as they traverse the woods.

Source:	Monstrous Compendium Vol. 2 - Dragonlance Creatures p. 6</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Foresworn</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>82 (11d8+33)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Str +8, Wis +7</save>
    <skill/>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>the languages it knew in life</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>Necrotic, Bludgeoning, Piercing or Slashing damage from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>Poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>Exhaustion, Frightened, Grappled, Paralyzed, Petrified, Poisoned, Prone, Restrained, Unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The foresworn casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 15):

	• 2/Day each: command, detect evil and good 
	• 1/Day: wall of force</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Duty-Bound</name>
      <text>The foresworn is bound to enacting a singular duty it pledged itself to in life. While this duty is incomplete, whenever the foresworn is destroyed, it re-forms at its previous location after 3 (1d6) days, with all its hit points restored.</text>
      <attack>Duty-Bound||1d6</attack>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Incorporeal Movement</name>
      <text>The foresworn can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. It takes 5 (1d10) force damage if it ends its turn inside an object.</text>
      <attack>Incorporeal Movement||1d10</attack>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The foresworn doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The foresworn makes three Spectral Polearm attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spectral Polearm</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 12 (2d6 + 5) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Spectral Polearm|+8|2d6+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Phantasmic Battalion (Recharge 5-6) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The foresworn summons a battalion of ghostly soldiers to its aid. The ghostly soldiers fill a 10-foot-cube centered on the foresworn, move with the foresworn when the foresworn moves, and last until the start of the foresworn's next turn. While the ghostly soldiers are present, the area they occupy is considered difficult terrain for all creatures except the foresworn, and the foresworn's reach for melee weapon attacks increases by 10 feet.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>command, detect evil and good, wall of force</spells>
    <description>Foresworn are the spirits of fallen Solamnic knights who attend to their duty long after death. Armed with spectral armor and weaponry, a foresworn maintains the martial prowess it had in life and can call on magic and its fallen brethren for aid.
	Like revenants, foresworn fixate on a singular purpose, and they refuse to abandon their undead state until the duty they had in life is fulfilled. For example, a foresworn might be pledged to protect a family's bloodline from harm or guard a dangerous artifact against thieves. If a foresworn is destroyed before it can complete its duty, it returns within a few days, its strength and purpose renewed.

Source:	Monstrous Compendium Vol. 2 - Dragonlance Creatures p. 7</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Irda Seeker</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>Any Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Dex +4, Cha +5</save>
    <skill>Insight +6, Perception +6, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft., truesight 5 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The seeker uses Augment Physicality, if available, and makes two Crystal Blade attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Crystal Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 5 (1d6 + 2) force damage, plus 7 (2d6) force damage if the seeker is Large.</text>
      <attack>Crystal Blade|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage||2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Augment Physicality (1/Day)</name>
      <recharge>1/DAY</recharge>
      <text>For 1 minute, the seeker magically heightens its physical ability and increases in size, along with anything it is wearing or carrying. While augmented, the seeker is Large, and makes Strength and Dexterity saving throws with advantage. If the seeker lacks the room to become Large, it attains the maximum size possible in the space available.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Change Shape (1/Day)</name>
      <recharge>1/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The seeker magically transforms to look and feel like a Medium Humanoid it has seen. Any equipment the seeker is wearing or carrying isn't transformed, and the seeker's statistics don't change. The seeker reverts to its true form if the seeker is reduced to 0 hit points or if the seeker uses an action to end the transformation.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Veil Walk (Recharge 4-6) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>D4</recharge>
      <text>The seeker, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying, turns invisible and teleports to an unoccupied space it can see within 30 feet of itself. The seeker remains invisible until the start of its next turn or until immediately after the seeker makes an attack roll, whichever comes first.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Irda seekers are skilled spies who use their magic to disguise themselves and gather intelligence for their allies. In combat, irda seekers can momentarily cloak themselves as they dart around the battlefield.

Irda:
The Dragon Queen created the irda long ago. While most irda embraced their wicked creator's teachings, some of them adopted the philosophies of other deities. Those irda who don't serve the Dragon Queen live in hidden communities across Krynn, avoiding the eyes of their creator and her minions.
	Distantly related to oni, ogres, and other giant folk, irda have shimmering skin that ranges through shades of indigo and sea green. Their innate magic provides them with limited shape-shifting abilities and the power to create illusions.

Source:	Monstrous Compendium Vol. 2 - Dragonlance Creatures p. 8</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Irda Veil Keeper</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>giant (sorcerer)</type>
    <alignment>Any Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>49 (9d8+9)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>19</cha>
    <save>Int +4, Wis +5, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +4, Insight +7, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>Charmed, Frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft., truesight 5 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The veil keeper casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Charisma as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 14):

	• At will: dancing lights, minor illusion
	• 2/Day each: invisibility, major image, phantasmal force
	• 1/Day: hallucinatory terrain (as an action)</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The veil keeper uses Augment Physicality, if available, and makes two Mirage Flare attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Mirage Flare</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Spell Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 60 ft., one target. Hit: 11 (2d6 + 4) radiant damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or be charmed by the veil keeper until the start of the veil keeper's next turn. While charmed in this way, a creature is incapacitated as it is beset by hypnotic, illusory visions.</text>
      <attack>Mirage Flare|+6|2d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Augment Physicality (1/Day)</name>
      <recharge>1/DAY</recharge>
      <text>For 1 minute, the veil keeper magically obscures it location, heightens its physical ability, and increases in size, along with anything it is wearing or carrying. While the veil keeper is augmented, attack rolls against it have disadvantage, it is Large, and it makes Strength and Dexterity saving throws with advantage. If the veil keeper lacks the room to become Large, it attains the maximum size possible in the space available. These augmentations end if the veil keeper is incapacitated.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Change Shape (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The veil keeper magically transforms to look and feel like a Medium Humanoid it has seen. Any equipment the veil keeper is wearing or carrying isn't transformed, and the veil keeper's statistics don't change. The veil keeper reverts to its true form if the veil keeper is reduced to 0 hit points or if the veil keeper uses an action to end the transformation.</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Obscuring Mist</name>
      <text>If a creature that the veil keeper can see within 30 feet of itself is targeted by an attack, the veil keeper surrounds the creature with illusory mist, granting the creature half cover until the start of the veil keeper's next turn.</text>
    </reaction>
    <spells>dancing lights, minor illusion, invisibility, major image, phantasmal force, hallucinatory terrain</spells>
    <description>Masters of their innate illusory powers, irda veil keepers protect their companions by weaving magical mirages that disorient foes. Rumors say that the most skilled irda veil keepers can keep entire enclaves hidden, guarding a community's inhabitants from the outside world for centuries.

Irda:
The Dragon Queen created the irda long ago. While most irda embraced their wicked creator's teachings, some of them adopted the philosophies of other deities. Those irda who don't serve the Dragon Queen live in hidden communities across Krynn, avoiding the eyes of their creator and her minions.
	Distantly related to oni, ogres, and other giant folk, irda have shimmering skin that ranges through shades of indigo and sea green. Their innate magic provides them with limited shape-shifting abilities and the power to create illusions.

Source:	Monstrous Compendium Vol. 2 - Dragonlance Creatures p. 9</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Nevermind Gnome Inventor</name>
    <npc>YES</npc>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>Any Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>14 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>36 (8d6+8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>18</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Dex +5, Int +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, Investigation +6, Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Gnomish</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Always Thinking Ahead</name>
      <text>The inventor has advantage on initiative rolls.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The inventor makes two Flying Fangtrap attacks. It can replace one of these attacks with Thunderscream Gadget if it's available.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Flying Fangtrap</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 60 ft., one target. Hit: 8 (1d10 + 3) piercing damage, and the creature must succeed on a DC 14 Dexterity saving throw or have its speed reduced to 0 until the start of the inventor's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Flying Fangtrap|+5|1d10+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Thunderscream Gadget (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The inventor produces a gadget that emits a screeching wave of sound in a 30-foot cone originating from the inventor. Each creature in that area must make a DC 14 Constitution saving throw, taking 10 (3d6) thunder damage on a failed save or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Thunderscream Gadget||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Flash Powder</name>
      <text>If the inventor is damaged by a creature it can see within 15 feet of itself, the inventor retaliates by flinging brilliantly explosive powder at the creature. The creature must succeed on a DC 14 Dexterity saving throw or be blinded until the end of its next turn.</text>
    </reaction>
    <description>"Who among us hasn't marveled at a majestic bird soaring high above and thought, "I can do better"?

First, thanks to the work of esteemed elavationist, Rirordinees Thrump, we created lifts to climb the heights of Mount Nevermind. Then, with the gnomeflinger, we brushed the heavens as gracefully as skipping stones. Now, let me present the next stage in automated ascendancy:
the cloud clinger!

Where is it, you ask? You're seated in it! And in just three... two... one..."
— Last words of inventor Meeka Mallowswain prior to her disappearance

Brimming with innovative ideas and reckless enthusiasm, the inventors of Mount Nevermind love any chance to showcase their creations. These talented inventors use their cleverness and technological know-how to outwit foes.

Nevermind Gnomes:
Mount Nevermind is a hollow, dormant volcano on the island of Sancrist in Krynn. Within the mountain, a vibrant community of rock gnome tinkerers and other inventors relentlessly study various scientific pursuits to create mechanical marvels.

Source:	Monstrous Compendium Vol. 2 - Dragonlance Creatures p. 10</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Nevermind Gnome Mastermind</name>
    <npc>YES</npc>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>Any Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>82 (15d6+30)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Dex +7, Con +5, Int +8</save>
    <skill>Arcana +8, Investigation +8, Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Gnomish</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Always Thinking Ahead</name>
      <text>The mastermind has advantage on initiative rolls.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>The mastermind can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check. This trait doesn't function if the mastermind is grappling creatures in both of its clockwork claws.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The mastermind makes two Clockwork Claw attacks. The mastermind can replace one of these attacks with Generate Gadget if it's available.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Clockwork Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage, and if the target is a Medium or smaller creature, the target is grappled (escape DC 15). Until this grapple ends, the target takes 10 (3d6) piercing damage at the start of each of the mastermind's turns. The mastermind has two claws, each of which can grapple only one target.</text>
      <attack>Clockwork Claw|+7|2d6+4</attack>
      <attack>Grapple||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Generate Gadget (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The mastermind quickly assembles a clockwork gadget, producing one of the following effects (the mastermind's choice):</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Chattergrab</name>
      <text>Parts of this gadget look like gnashing metal teeth. This gadget hurtles toward a creature the mastermind can see within 60 feet of itself. The creature must succeed on a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw or take 31 (7d8) piercing damage and be incapacitated until the start of the mastermind's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Chattergrab||7d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Phasmoball</name>
      <text>The mastermind launches this gadget to a point the mastermind can see within 30 feet of itself, where the gadget unleashes a cloud of mind-warping gases in a 10-foot-radius sphere. Each creature within the sphere must succeed on a DC 16 Wisdom saving throw or take 11 (2d10) psychic damage and be frightened of the mastermind until the start of the mastermind's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Phasmoball||2d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Thunderscream</name>
      <text>This gadget emits a screeching wave of sound in a 30-foot cone originating from the mastermind. Each creature in that area must make a DC 16 Constitution saving throw, taking 21 (6d6) thunder damage on a failed save or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Thunderscream||6d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>The gnome masterminds of Mount Nevermind temper their creativity with years of experience. While they still create wild inventions on a whim, these masterminds also wield at least one more stable clockwork invention—typically something that affords the mastermind more movement, extends their reach with extra appendages, or both.

Nevermind Gnomes:
Mount Nevermind is a hollow, dormant volcano on the island of Sancrist in Krynn. Within the mountain, a vibrant community of rock gnome tinkerers and other inventors relentlessly study various scientific pursuits to create mechanical marvels.

Source:	Monstrous Compendium Vol. 2 - Dragonlance Creatures p. 11</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Thanoi Hunter</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Any Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>14 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Str +6, Con +4</save>
    <skill>Athletics +6, Perception +5, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Aquan, Common</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>Cold</immune>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>The hunter can hold its breath for up to 10 minutes.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The hunter has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the hunter's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The hunter makes one Bone Harpoon attack and one Tusk attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bone Harpoon</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 10 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. Hit: 8 (1d8 + 4) piercing damage. Hit or Miss: The harpoon returns to the hunter's hand.</text>
      <attack>Bone Harpoon|+6|1d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tusk</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 6 (1d4 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Tusk|+6|1d4+4</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Thanoi are walrus-like beings who dwell in the frozen wastelands of Krynn. They sport thick, ivory tusks, which they use both to defend themselves and to poke breathing holes in sea ice as they swim.
	Often at odds with the monstrous creatures that live in the frozen wastes, thanoi are adept hunters. In addition to their tusks, they use harpoons on long ropes that they can quickly reel back. Groups of thanoi hunters work together to take down monsters far larger than themselves, including remorhazes and white dragons.

Source:	Monstrous Compendium Vol. 2 - Dragonlance Creatures p. 12</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Traag Draconian</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>68 (8d10+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>21</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save>Str +8, Con +6</save>
    <skill/>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>Charmed, Frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Blood Frenzy</name>
      <text>The draconian has advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Controlled Fall</name>
      <text>If the draconian falls and isn't incapacitated, it subtracts up to 50 feet from the fall when calculating the fall's damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Death Throes</name>
      <text>If the draconian is reduced to 0 hit points, its body erupts into sludge that fills a 10-foot-radius sphere. Each creature within that area must succeed on a DC 14 Dexterity saving throw or be covered in the sludge for 1 minute. While covered in the sludge, a creature's speed is halved. A creature can use its action to scrape the sludge off itself or another creature within 5 feet of itself.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The draconian makes two Claw attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 14 (2d8 + 5) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+8|2d8+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Flaming Carnage (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The draconian indulges its rage, wreathing itself in fire and moving up to its speed. The draconian can enter creatures' spaces during this move. During this movement, when the draconian enters a creature's space, the creature must make a DC 14 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, the creature takes 22 (4d10) fire damage and is knocked prone. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage and is pushed to the nearest space out of the draconian's path. A creature can be affected by this draconian's Flaming Carnage only once during a turn.</text>
      <attack>Flaming Carnage||4d10</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Violent Retaliation</name>
      <text>If a creature within 10 feet of the draconian hits it with an attack, the draconian can make one Claw attack against that creature. If the Claw attack hits, it deals an additional 4 (1d8) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Violent Retaliation||1d8</attack>
    </reaction>
    <description>In their experimentation with corrupting dragon eggs, the Dragon Armies created traag draconians, the precursor to what would become baaz draconian foot soldiers. Unlike their draconian brethren, traag draconians are little more than bloodthirsty engines of carnage. Few commanders have successfully used a traag draconian's reckless violence to their advantage in battle; for most, a traag draconian is as much of a danger to its allies as it is to its enemies. Even magic cannot tame a traag draconian's thirst for violence.
	A traag draconian's vestigial wings lack the strength to support its hulking body in true flight, and they only minimally help to slow a falling traag's descent. Its metallic scales are coated in a sickly patina. In battle, the draconian can charge its body with vicious fire, burning all in its wake. When a traag draconian dies, its body explodes in a thick, disgusting sludge.

Source:	Monstrous Compendium Vol. 2 - Dragonlance Creatures p. 13</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Verminaard</name>
    <npc>YES</npc>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (cleric, human)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>20 (+2 plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>143 (22d8+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>22</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Wis +10, Cha +9</save>
    <skill>Perception +16, Religion +9</skill>
    <passive>26</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>17</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>Fire</immune>
    <conditionImmune>Charmed, Frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Verminaard casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 18):

	• At will: light, thaumaturgy 
	• 2/Day each: bane, fear, freedom of movement, greater restoration, hold monster, revivify</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Draconic Command</name>
      <text>Whenever a Dragon or a creature with the Draconic Devotion trait within 30 feet of Verminaard makes an attack roll, the creature can roll a d4 and add the number rolled to the attack roll.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If Verminaard fails a saving throw, he can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Verminaard wears +2 plate armor and wields the mace Nightbringer, which grants him darkvision as well as immunity to fire damage and to the charmed and frightened conditions (included above).</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Verminaard makes two Nightbringer attacks and uses Malediction.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Nightbringer</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 12 (1d6 + 9) bludgeoning damage plus 10 (4d4) radiant damage. If the target is a creature, the target must succeed on a DC 20 Constitution saving throw or be blinded until the start of Verminaard's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Nightbringer|+15|1d6+9</attack>
      <attack>Radiant Damage||4d4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Malediction</name>
      <text>Verminaard utters an unholy word, causing profane fire to descend on one creature Verminaard can see within 60 feet of himself. The creature must make a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw, taking 11 (2d10) necrotic damage plus 11 (2d10) radiant damage on a failed save or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Malediction||2d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Dragon Queen's Favor (5/Day) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>5/DAY</recharge>
      <text>Verminaard or one creature he can see within 60 feet of himself magically regains 17 (2d12 + 4) hit points.</text>
      <attack>Dragon Queen's Favor||2d12+4</attack>
    </action>
    <legendary>
      <name>Legendary Actions (3/Turn)</name>
      <recharge>3/TURN</recharge>
      <text>Verminaard can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Verminaard regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Tactical Movement</name>
      <text>Verminaard moves up to his speed or commands a mount he is riding to move up to its speed. This movement doesn't provoke opportunity attacks.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Fervent Strike (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Verminaard makes one Nightbringer attack. If this attack hits, it deals an additional 7 (2d6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Fervent Strike||2d6</attack>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Cast a Spell (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>Verminaard uses Spellcasting.</text>
    </legendary>
    <spells>light, thaumaturgy, bane, fear, freedom of movement, greater restoration, hold monster, revivify</spells>
    <description>"Ariakas,

As the Dragon Queen wills me to obey, here is my assessment of your servant, Verminaard of Nidus: Unchanged. The man remains a blustering dastard awash in blessings earned by his blood rather than his brains. He glories in Takhisis's favor and wields her power in manners both frivolous and brutal. In their bunks, his troops whisper of his zealotry and claim that those missing from their ranks have been sacrificed on his secret altar. I don't dismiss this possibility.

While his work progresses, it is the effort of an instrument as blunt as the mace he wields.

Verminaard thinks himself invincible, and I pray to her majesty that I'm present when she divests him of that delusion.

I hope you find these reports illuminating.

Ember"

Dragon Highlord Verminaard leads the Red Dragon Army—the largest and most powerful of the Dragon Queen's forces—with fanatic zeal and ruthless might. Though prophesied to banish evil forces from the lands of Krynn, Verminaard was tempted by Takhisis and her promises of glory. Corrupted by the Dragon Queen, Verminaard rose to become one of her champions, claiming command of the fiercest among the Dragon Armies.
	Verminaard's extreme devotion to Takhisis allows him to channel her unholy power on the battlefield, bolstering those under his command while raining cursed fire on his foes. His towering silhouette is often wreathed in the fire of Ember, his red dragon companion and adviser.

Draconic Devotion:
Verminaard's stat block references the Draconic Devotion monster trait. Though this trait does not appear in any of the creatures in this compendium, you will find several monsters with the Draconic Devotion trait terrorizing the lands of Krynn in the book Dragonlance:
Shadow of the Dragon Queen.

Source:	Monstrous Compendium Vol. 2 - Dragonlance Creatures p. 15</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <item>
    <name>Nightbringer</name>
    <detail>mace, legendary (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>M</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <weight>4</weight>
    <dmg1>1d6</dmg1>
    <dmgType>B</dmgType>
    <text>This heavy mace has a dark oaken handle and a head of blackened steel trimmed with gold. In combat, the mace's head is wreathed in inky black energy.
	You gain a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with this weapon. When you hit with an attack roll using it, the target takes an additional 4d4 radiant damage. If you have an evil alignment, you also gain the following benefits when attuned to Nightbringer:

Blessing of the Dragon Queen: You are immune to the charmed and frightened conditions, and you gain immunity to one of the following damage types (choose when you attune to the weapon): acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison.

Eyes of Midnight: You have darkvision with a range of 60 feet. If you already have darkvision, its range increases by 60 feet.

Midnight Shroud: The weapon has 6 charges. When you hit a creature with an attack using this weapon, you can expend one charge to force the creature to make a DC 20 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the creature is blinded until the start of your next turn. The weapon regains 1d6 expended charges daily at dawn.

Proficiency: simple, mace
Source:	Monstrous Compendium Vol. 2 - Dragonlance Creatures p. 14</text>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon attacks +3</modifier>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon damage +3</modifier>
    <roll description="Radiant Damage">4d4</roll>
    <roll description="Recharge">1d6</roll>
  </item>
</compendium>
