<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <race>
    <name>Changeling (UA Races of Eberron)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Cha +2</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>"Long ago there was a woman named Jes, and she had one hundred children. Her rivals conspired against her and swore to kill her children. Jes begged the Sovereigns for help, but their only answer was the wind and rain. In the depths of her despair, a lonely traveler took her hand. "I will protect your children if they follow my path. Let them wander the world. They may be shunned and feared, but they will never be destroyed." Jes agreed, and the traveler gave her his cloak. When she draped it over her children their old faces melted away, and they could be whoever they wanted to be. And so it remains. Though the Children are shunned by all, the gift of the Traveler protects them still."
— Chance, changeling priest

A changeling can shift its face and form with a thought. Many changelings use this gift as a form of artistic and emotional expression, but it is an invaluable tool for grifters, spies, and others who wish to deceive. This leads many people to treat known changelings with fear and suspicion.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Races Of Eberron p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Hidden People</name>
      <text>Hidden People Changelings are spread across Khorvaire. Wherever humans can be found, there are changelings; the question is whether their presence is known.
	Changelings are born to one of three paths. A few are born and raised in stable communities, where changelings are true to their nature and deal openly with the people around them. Some are orphans, raised by other races, who find their way in the world without ever knowing another like themselves. Still others are part of the nomadic changeling clans spread across the Five Nations who keep their true nature hidden from the single-skins. Some of these clans maintain safe havens in major cities and communities, but most prefer to wander, following the unpredictable path of the Traveler.
	In creating a changeling adventurer, consider the character's relationships with the people around them. Does the character conceal their true changeling nature, or do they embrace it? Do they have connections to a changeling community or clan, or are they alone and in search of companions?</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Masks and Personas</name>
      <text>In their natural form, changelings are slender and pale with colorless eyes and silver-white hair. A changeling can alter its physical appearance with a thought. While this can be used to deceive others, it is a natural form of expression for the changeling. A changeling shifts shapes the way others might change clothes. A casual shape—one created on the spur of the moment, with no depth or history—is called a mask. A changeling mask can be used to express a mood or to serve a specific purpose and then never used again. However, many changelings develop identities that have more depth. They build an identity over time, crafting a persona, with history and beliefs. This focused identity helps a changeling pinpoint a particular skill or emotion. A changeling adventurer might have personas for many situations, including negotiation, investigation, and combat. Personas can be shared by multiple changelings; there might be three healers in a community, but whoever is on duty will adopt the persona of Tek, the kindly old medic. Personas can even be passed down through a family, allowing a younger changeling to take advantage of contacts established by previous users of the persona.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Changeling Names</name>
      <text>A changeling might use a different name for each mask and persona, adopting new names as easily as they develop new faces. The true name of a changeling tends to be monosyllabic; however, there are often accents to a changeling's name that are expressed through shapeshifting, something single-skins will likely miss. For instance, two changelings might have the name Jin, but one is Jin-with-vivid-blue-eyes and one is Jin-with-golden-cheeks.
	Changelings have a fluid relationship with gender, seeing it as one characteristic to change among many others.

Changeling Names: Bin, Cas, Dox, Fie, Hars, Jin, Lam, Mas, Nix, Ot, Paik, Ruz, Sim, Toox, Vil, Yug</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Your Charisma score increases by 2, and either your Dexterity or your Intelligence increases by 1 (your choice).</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Changelings mature slightly faster than humans but share a similar lifespan—typically a century or less. While a Changeling can shapeshift to conceal their age, the effects of aging still catch up to them.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Changelings hate to be bound in any way, and those who follow the path of the Traveler believe that chaos and change are important aspects of life. Most tend toward pragmatic neutrality as opposed to being concerned with lofty ideals. Few Changelings embrace evil.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>In their natural forms, Changelings average between 5 and 6 feet in height, with a slender build. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d4
Height = 5 feet + 1 inch + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 115 + (2d4 x your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d4</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Change Appearance</name>
      <text>As an action, you can transform your appearance or revert to your natural form. You can't duplicate the appearance of a creature you've never seen, and you revert to your natural form if you die.
	You decide what you look like, including your height, weight, facial features, the sound of your voice, coloration, hair length, sex, and any other distinguishing characteristics. You can make yourself appear as a member of another race, though none of your game statistics change. You also can't appear as a creature of a different size than you, and your basic shape stays the same; if you're bipedal, you can't use this trait to become quadrupedal, for instance. Your clothing and other equipment don't change in appearance, size, or shape to match your new form, requiring you to keep a few extra outfits on hand to make the most compelling disguise possible.
	Even to the most astute observers, your ruse is usually indiscernible. If you rouse suspicion, or if a wary creature suspects something is amiss, you have advantage on any Charisma (Deception) check you make to avoid detection.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Changeling Instincts</name>
      <text>You gain proficiency with two of the following skills of your choice: Deception, Insight, Intimidation, or Persuasion</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Unsettling Visage</name>
      <text>When a creature you can see makes an attack roll against you, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on the roll. You must use this feature before knowing whether the attack hits or misses.
	Using this trait reveals your shapeshifting nature to any creature within 30 feet that can see you. Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Divergent Persona</name>
      <text>You gain proficiency with one tool of your choice. Define a persona associated with that proficiency: establish the name, race, gender, age, and other details. While you are in the form of this persona, the related proficiency bonus is doubled for any ability check you make that uses that proficiency.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and two other languages of your choice.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Kalashtar (UA Races of Eberron)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Cha +1, Wis +1</ability>
    <resist>psychic</resist>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>"I am kalashtar, born of two worlds. Over a thousand years ago, my ancestor bound her bloodline to the spirit Kashtai, and I am a child of that union. Kashtai moves within me. Her memories come to me in dreams, and at times her voice whispers in the silence of my mind. As long as at least one of my sisters is alive, Kashtai will survive—and as long as she lives, she will fight ilLashtavar."
—Lakashtai, servant of the light

The kalashtar are a compound race created from the union of humanity with renegade spirits from the plane of dreams—spirits called the quori. Kalashtar are often seen as wise, spiritual people with great compassion for others. But there is an unmistakable alien quality to the kalashtar, and they are haunted by the conflicts of their otherworldly spirits.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Races Of Eberron p. 3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Bound to Spirits</name>
      <text>Every kalashtar has a connection to a spirit of light, shared by other members of their bloodline. Physically, kalashtar appear human, but the spiritual connection affects them in a variety of ways. Kalashtar have symmetrical, slightly angular features. Their movements and body language are different from those of humans; most beings find it graceful, but to some it feels unnerving. The eyes of a kalashtar often glow when it is focused on a task or feeling strong emotions.
	The kalashtar can't directly communicate with their quori spirits. A kalashtar might experience the relationship as a sense of instinct and inspiration, drawing on the memories of the spirit when they dream. This connection grants the kalashtar minor psionic abilities, as well as protection from psychic attacks. All of these dream-spirits are virtuous, but some are warriors, while others are more contemplative or kind; a kalashtar player and DM can work together to determine the nature of the linked spirit. Typically, a kalashtar knows the name and nature of their spirit, but some—for instance, an orphan kalashtar raised among outsiders—might know nothing of their spirit or the source of their psychic gifts.
	The bond to the spirit can cause some kalashtar to display unusual quirks of behavior. A kalashtar player can roll or select a trait from the following table.

Kalashtar Quirks:
d10 | Quirk
1 | You try to understand the motives and feelings of your enemies.
2 | You prefer using telepathy over speaking aloud.
3 | You feel a strong drive to protect the innocent.
4 | You apply dream logic to mundane situations.
5 | You discuss things out loud with your quori spirit.
6 | You suppress your emotions and rely on logic.
7 | You are strongly influenced by the emotions of those around you.
8 | You prefer to find nonviolent solutions to problems whenever possible.
9 | You are driven by a warrior spirit and will fight for any noble cause.
10 | You are obsessed with Dreaming Dark conspiracies.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Hunted by Nightmares</name>
      <text>The virtuous spirits tied to the kalashtar fled from the dream realm of Dal Quor to escape the evil spirits that dominate the realm. The rebel quori believe that through meditation and devotion, they can eventually change the fundamental nature of Dal Quor, shifting the balance from darkness to light. Thus, most kalashtar communities focus on acts of devotion to the faith known as the Path of Light. But the dark powers of Dal Quor have their own plans on Eberron. Through the force known as the Dreaming Dark, these monsters are manipulating the people of Khorvaire and eliminating kalashtar whenever possible.
	Many kalashtar defend themselves from the Dreaming Dark by living in close-knit communities, focusing on devotion to the Path of Light. But some among the kalashtar feel obliged to seek out the agents of the Dreaming Dark and oppose their plans, or simply to protect the innocent however they can. There are some kalashtar who have grown up isolated from their kind, who know nothing about Dal Quor or the Dreaming Dark. Such orphans may use their abilities for personal gain or otherwise act against the virtuous instincts of their quori spirits; this can often cause internal conflicts and violent mood swings.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Kalashtar Names</name>
      <text>A kalashtar name is formed by the blend of a personal prefix tied to the name of the quori spirit within the kalashtar. Each spirit has a gender identity, but this may or may not match the gender identity of the kalashtar host. Thus, a female kalashtar might have what others would consider a masculine name, because she's tied to a spirit with a masculine identity. Kalashtar orphans are unlikely to know the names of their spirits and instead take names from the cultures they're raised in.

Male Quori Names: Hareth, Khad, Kosh, Melk, Tash, Ulad, Vash

Female Quori Names: Ashana, Ashtai, Ishara, Nari, Tana, Tari, Vakri

Kalashtar Names: Coratash, Dalavash, Dolishara, Halakosh, Khoratari, Koratana, Lanhareth, Molavakri, Nevitash, Sorashana, Torashtai, Valakhad, Vishara</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Kalashtar develop physically at the same rate as humans do and have similar lifespans.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>The noble spirit tied to a Kalashtar drives it toward lawful and good behavior. Most Kalashtar combine self-discipline with compassion for all sentient beings, but some Kalashtar resist the virtuous influence of their spirit.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d6
Height = 5 feet + 4 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 110 + (1d6 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d6</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Dual Mind</name>
      <text>When you make a Wisdom saving throw, you can use your reaction to gain advantage on the roll. You can use this trait immediately before or after you roll, but before any of the roll's effects occur.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Mental Discipline</name>
      <text>You have resistance to psychic damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Mind Link</name>
      <text>You can speak telepathically to any creature you can see within 60 feet of you. You don't need to share a language with the creature for it to understand your telepathic messages, but the creature must be able to understand at least one language or be telepathic itself.
	As a bonus action when you're speaking telepathically to a creature, you can give that creature the ability to speak telepathically to you until the start of your next turn. To use this ability, the creature must be within 60 feet of you and able to see you.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Severed from Dreams</name>
      <text>Kalashtar sleep, but they don't connect to the plane of dreams as other creatures do. Instead, their minds draw from the memories of their otherworldly spirit while they sleep. As such, you are immune to spells and other magical effects that require you to dream, like the dream spell, but not to spells and effects that put you to sleep, like the sleep spell.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Psychic Glamour</name>
      <text>Choose one of the following skills: Insight, Intimidation, Performance, or Persuasion. You have advantage on all ability checks you make with that skill.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common, Quori, and one other language of your choice.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <!-- <race>
    <name>Shifter, Beasthide (UA Races of Eberron)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Dex +1, Con +2</ability>
    <proficiency>Athletics, Perception</proficiency>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>"Geth's ancient heritage rose up from deep within him, spreading out from the core of his being. Some shifters manifested terrible claws, massive fangs, astounding speed, or heightened senses. Geth's gift from his lycanthrope ancestors was sheer toughness. Strength seeped into his bones and flooded his flesh. His skin hardened, and his hair became coarse like an animal's tough hide. A sense of invincibility spread through him. For the moment, at least, he felt unstoppable!"
—Don Bassingthwaite, The Binding Stone

Shifters are sometimes called the weretouched, as many believe that they are the descendants of humans and lycanthropes. They are humanoids with a bestial aspect. While they can't fully change shape, they can temporarily enhance their animalistic features—a state they call shifting. Whatever their origins, shifters have evolved into a unique race. A shifter walks on the knife's edge between the wilds and the world around them. Do they embrace their primal instincts or the path of civilization?

Stoic and solid, a beasthide shifter draws strength and stamina from the beast within. Beasthide shifters are typically tied to the bear or the boar, but any creature known for its toughness could apply.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Races Of Eberron p. 6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>The Beast Within</name>
      <text>Early in childhood, a shifter forms a bond with a beast within: a totemic force that shapes their body and mind. Some shifters believe that these spirits are independent entities, and they might speak of Bear or Wolf as ancestors or guides. Most just see the beast within as a formidable expression of their inner nature, something that emerges over time as the shifter's personality takes shape. The beast within is a pool of powerful instincts, and its influence is revealed by the shifter's personality: a feline shifter might be cool and distant, driven by predatory instincts, while a shifter with a lupine spirit is drawn to find and protect a pack. When a shifter fully embraces this beast within, they physically transform for a short time.
	This beast within is reflected by the shifter's subrace. The following subraces are especially common:

Beasthide often signifies the bear or boar: stoic, stubborn and thick-skinned.

Longtooth shifters typically have lupine traits and are attracted to pack life.

Swiftstride shifters are often predatory and feline, but a swiftstride could also be a cunning rat who darts through the shadows.

Wildhunt shifters are born from any creature that tracks its prey.

While the beast within certainly has a physical impact on a shifter, it also has a spiritual and psychological effect. Two beasthide shifters share the same special ability, but if one has the aspect of the boar and the other is more like a bear, they'll be quite different in personality. With any shifter, identifying the beast within is a crucial part of understanding the character.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Similar and Diverse</name>
      <text>Shifters are similar to humans in height and build but are more naturally lithe and flexible. Their facial features have a bestial cast, with large eyes, flat noses, and pointed ears; most shifters also have prominent canine teeth. They grow fur-like hair on nearly every part of their bodies.
	The traits of the beast within affect a shifter's appearance as well. A swiftstride shifter might have catlike eyes and delicate build, while a beasthide shifter is likely a massive brute built like a bear. While a shifter's appearance might remind an onlooker of an animal, they remain clearly identifiable as shifters even when at their most feral.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>The Journey Yet to Come</name>
      <text>Shifters have a strong presence in the Eldeen Reaches, and they often live among humans and can be found in rural areas across Khorvaire. While they form powerful bonds with friends and kin, shifters place great value on selfreliance and freedom. It's a shifter proverb to "always be prepared for the journey yet to come," and most shifters strive to be ready for change or opportunity.
	Shifters have a natural inclination toward classes with a primal connection. A shifter barbarian draws their rage from the beast within. A shifter ranger indulges their urge to wander and hunt. A shifter rogue harnesses their own predatory instincts. But shifters can pursue any path or faith.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Shifter Names</name>
      <text>Shifters have no language of their own and often live in blended communities. As such, shifter names typically overlap with the names of other cultures in their region. Many shifters prefer to keep their personal names for their friends and use "wandering names" with strangers. These are usually tied to an obvious physical or personality trait.

Shifter Names: Badger, Bear, Cat, Fang, Grace, Grim, Moon, Rain, Red, Scar, Stripe, Swift, Whiskers, Wolf</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Shifters are quick to mature both physically and emotionally, reaching young adulthood at age 10. They rarely live to be more than 70 years old.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Shifters tend toward neutrality, being more focused on survival than concepts of good and evil. A love of personal freedom can drive Shifters toward chaotic alignments.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Shifters range from 5 to almost 7 feet tall, depending on their subrace. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 4 feet + 6 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 90 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Keen Senses</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with the Perception skill.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Shifting</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, you can assume a more bestial appearance. This transformation lasts for 1 minute, until you die, or until you revert to your normal appearance as a bonus action. When you shift, you gain temporary hit points equal to your level + your Constitution modifier (minimum of 1 temporary hit point). You also gain additional benefits that depend on your Shifter subrace, described below.
	Once you shift, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Tough</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with the Athletics skill.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Shifting Feature</name>
      <text>Whenever you shift, you gain 1d6 additional temporary hit points, and while shifted, you have a +1 bonus to your AC.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common.</text>
    </trait>
  </race> -->
  <!-- <race>
    <name>Shifter, Longtooth (UA Races of Eberron)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Dex +1, Str +2</ability>
    <proficiency>Intimidation, Perception</proficiency>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>"Geth's ancient heritage rose up from deep within him, spreading out from the core of his being. Some shifters manifested terrible claws, massive fangs, astounding speed, or heightened senses. Geth's gift from his lycanthrope ancestors was sheer toughness. Strength seeped into his bones and flooded his flesh. His skin hardened, and his hair became coarse like an animal's tough hide. A sense of invincibility spread through him. For the moment, at least, he felt unstoppable!"
—Don Bassingthwaite, The Binding Stone

Shifters are sometimes called the weretouched, as many believe that they are the descendants of humans and lycanthropes. They are humanoids with a bestial aspect. While they can't fully change shape, they can temporarily enhance their animalistic features—a state they call shifting. Whatever their origins, shifters have evolved into a unique race. A shifter walks on the knife's edge between the wilds and the world around them. Do they embrace their primal instincts or the path of civilization?

Longtooth shifters are fierce and aggressive, but they form deep bonds with their friends. Many longtooth shifters have canine traits that become more pronounced as they shift, but they might instead draw on tigers, hyenas, or other predators.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Races Of Eberron p. 6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>The Beast Within</name>
      <text>Early in childhood, a shifter forms a bond with a beast within: a totemic force that shapes their body and mind. Some shifters believe that these spirits are independent entities, and they might speak of Bear or Wolf as ancestors or guides. Most just see the beast within as a formidable expression of their inner nature, something that emerges over time as the shifter's personality takes shape. The beast within is a pool of powerful instincts, and its influence is revealed by the shifter's personality: a feline shifter might be cool and distant, driven by predatory instincts, while a shifter with a lupine spirit is drawn to find and protect a pack. When a shifter fully embraces this beast within, they physically transform for a short time.
	This beast within is reflected by the shifter's subrace. The following subraces are especially common:

Beasthide often signifies the bear or boar: stoic, stubborn and thick-skinned.

Longtooth shifters typically have lupine traits and are attracted to pack life.

Swiftstride shifters are often predatory and feline, but a swiftstride could also be a cunning rat who darts through the shadows.

Wildhunt shifters are born from any creature that tracks its prey.

While the beast within certainly has a physical impact on a shifter, it also has a spiritual and psychological effect. Two beasthide shifters share the same special ability, but if one has the aspect of the boar and the other is more like a bear, they'll be quite different in personality. With any shifter, identifying the beast within is a crucial part of understanding the character.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Similar and Diverse</name>
      <text>Shifters are similar to humans in height and build but are more naturally lithe and flexible. Their facial features have a bestial cast, with large eyes, flat noses, and pointed ears; most shifters also have prominent canine teeth. They grow fur-like hair on nearly every part of their bodies.
	The traits of the beast within affect a shifter's appearance as well. A swiftstride shifter might have catlike eyes and delicate build, while a beasthide shifter is likely a massive brute built like a bear. While a shifter's appearance might remind an onlooker of an animal, they remain clearly identifiable as shifters even when at their most feral.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>The Journey Yet to Come</name>
      <text>Shifters have a strong presence in the Eldeen Reaches, and they often live among humans and can be found in rural areas across Khorvaire. While they form powerful bonds with friends and kin, shifters place great value on selfreliance and freedom. It's a shifter proverb to "always be prepared for the journey yet to come," and most shifters strive to be ready for change or opportunity.
	Shifters have a natural inclination toward classes with a primal connection. A shifter barbarian draws their rage from the beast within. A shifter ranger indulges their urge to wander and hunt. A shifter rogue harnesses their own predatory instincts. But shifters can pursue any path or faith.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Shifter Names</name>
      <text>Shifters have no language of their own and often live in blended communities. As such, shifter names typically overlap with the names of other cultures in their region. Many shifters prefer to keep their personal names for their friends and use "wandering names" with strangers. These are usually tied to an obvious physical or personality trait.

Shifter Names: Badger, Bear, Cat, Fang, Grace, Grim, Moon, Rain, Red, Scar, Stripe, Swift, Whiskers, Wolf</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Shifters are quick to mature both physically and emotionally, reaching young adulthood at age 10. They rarely live to be more than 70 years old.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Shifters tend toward neutrality, being more focused on survival than concepts of good and evil. A love of personal freedom can drive Shifters toward chaotic alignments.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Shifters range from 5 to almost 7 feet tall, depending on their subrace. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 4 feet + 6 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 90 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Keen Senses</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with the Perception skill.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Shifting</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, you can assume a more bestial appearance. This transformation lasts for 1 minute, until you die, or until you revert to your normal appearance as a bonus action. When you shift, you gain temporary hit points equal to your level + your Constitution modifier (minimum of 1 temporary hit point). You also gain additional benefits that depend on your Shifter subrace, described below.
	Once you shift, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Fierce</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with the Intimidation skill.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Shifting Feature</name>
      <text>While shifted, you can use your elongated fangs to make an unarmed strike as a bonus action. If you hit with your fangs, you can deal piercing damage equal to 1d6 + your Strength modifier, instead of the bludgeoning damage normal for an unarmed strike.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common.</text>
    </trait>
  </race> -->
  <!-- <race>
    <name>Shifter, Swiftstride (UA Races of Eberron)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>35</speed>
    <ability>Dex +1, Dex +2, Cha +1</ability>
    <proficiency>Acrobatics, Perception</proficiency>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>"Geth's ancient heritage rose up from deep within him, spreading out from the core of his being. Some shifters manifested terrible claws, massive fangs, astounding speed, or heightened senses. Geth's gift from his lycanthrope ancestors was sheer toughness. Strength seeped into his bones and flooded his flesh. His skin hardened, and his hair became coarse like an animal's tough hide. A sense of invincibility spread through him. For the moment, at least, he felt unstoppable!"
—Don Bassingthwaite, The Binding Stone

Shifters are sometimes called the weretouched, as many believe that they are the descendants of humans and lycanthropes. They are humanoids with a bestial aspect. While they can't fully change shape, they can temporarily enhance their animalistic features—a state they call shifting. Whatever their origins, shifters have evolved into a unique race. A shifter walks on the knife's edge between the wilds and the world around them. Do they embrace their primal instincts or the path of civilization?

Swiftstride shifters are graceful and quick. Typically feline in nature, swiftstride shifters are often aloof and difficult to pin down physically or socially.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Races Of Eberron p. 6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>The Beast Within</name>
      <text>Early in childhood, a shifter forms a bond with a beast within: a totemic force that shapes their body and mind. Some shifters believe that these spirits are independent entities, and they might speak of Bear or Wolf as ancestors or guides. Most just see the beast within as a formidable expression of their inner nature, something that emerges over time as the shifter's personality takes shape. The beast within is a pool of powerful instincts, and its influence is revealed by the shifter's personality: a feline shifter might be cool and distant, driven by predatory instincts, while a shifter with a lupine spirit is drawn to find and protect a pack. When a shifter fully embraces this beast within, they physically transform for a short time.
	This beast within is reflected by the shifter's subrace. The following subraces are especially common:

Beasthide often signifies the bear or boar: stoic, stubborn and thick-skinned.

Longtooth shifters typically have lupine traits and are attracted to pack life.

Swiftstride shifters are often predatory and feline, but a swiftstride could also be a cunning rat who darts through the shadows.

Wildhunt shifters are born from any creature that tracks its prey.

While the beast within certainly has a physical impact on a shifter, it also has a spiritual and psychological effect. Two beasthide shifters share the same special ability, but if one has the aspect of the boar and the other is more like a bear, they'll be quite different in personality. With any shifter, identifying the beast within is a crucial part of understanding the character.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Similar and Diverse</name>
      <text>Shifters are similar to humans in height and build but are more naturally lithe and flexible. Their facial features have a bestial cast, with large eyes, flat noses, and pointed ears; most shifters also have prominent canine teeth. They grow fur-like hair on nearly every part of their bodies.
	The traits of the beast within affect a shifter's appearance as well. A swiftstride shifter might have catlike eyes and delicate build, while a beasthide shifter is likely a massive brute built like a bear. While a shifter's appearance might remind an onlooker of an animal, they remain clearly identifiable as shifters even when at their most feral.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>The Journey Yet to Come</name>
      <text>Shifters have a strong presence in the Eldeen Reaches, and they often live among humans and can be found in rural areas across Khorvaire. While they form powerful bonds with friends and kin, shifters place great value on selfreliance and freedom. It's a shifter proverb to "always be prepared for the journey yet to come," and most shifters strive to be ready for change or opportunity.
	Shifters have a natural inclination toward classes with a primal connection. A shifter barbarian draws their rage from the beast within. A shifter ranger indulges their urge to wander and hunt. A shifter rogue harnesses their own predatory instincts. But shifters can pursue any path or faith.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Shifter Names</name>
      <text>Shifters have no language of their own and often live in blended communities. As such, shifter names typically overlap with the names of other cultures in their region. Many shifters prefer to keep their personal names for their friends and use "wandering names" with strangers. These are usually tied to an obvious physical or personality trait.

Shifter Names: Badger, Bear, Cat, Fang, Grace, Grim, Moon, Rain, Red, Scar, Stripe, Swift, Whiskers, Wolf</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Shifters are quick to mature both physically and emotionally, reaching young adulthood at age 10. They rarely live to be more than 70 years old.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Shifters tend toward neutrality, being more focused on survival than concepts of good and evil. A love of personal freedom can drive Shifters toward chaotic alignments.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Shifters range from 5 to almost 7 feet tall, depending on their subrace. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 4 feet + 6 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 90 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Keen Senses</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with the Perception skill.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Shifting</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, you can assume a more bestial appearance. This transformation lasts for 1 minute, until you die, or until you revert to your normal appearance as a bonus action. When you shift, you gain temporary hit points equal to your level + your Constitution modifier (minimum of 1 temporary hit point). You also gain additional benefits that depend on your Shifter subrace, described below.
	Once you shift, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Graceful</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with the Acrobatics skill.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Swift Stride</name>
      <text>Your walking speed increases by 5 feet.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Shifting Feature</name>
      <text>While shifted, your walking speed increases by 5 feet. Additionally, you can move up to 10 feet as a reaction when an enemy ends its turn within 5 feet of you. This movement doesn't provoke opportunity attacks.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common.</text>
    </trait>
  </race> -->
  <!-- <race>
    <name>Shifter, Wildhunt (UA Races of Eberron)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Dex +1, Wis +2</ability>
    <proficiency>Perception, Survival</proficiency>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>"Geth's ancient heritage rose up from deep within him, spreading out from the core of his being. Some shifters manifested terrible claws, massive fangs, astounding speed, or heightened senses. Geth's gift from his lycanthrope ancestors was sheer toughness. Strength seeped into his bones and flooded his flesh. His skin hardened, and his hair became coarse like an animal's tough hide. A sense of invincibility spread through him. For the moment, at least, he felt unstoppable!"
—Don Bassingthwaite, The Binding Stone

Shifters are sometimes called the weretouched, as many believe that they are the descendants of humans and lycanthropes. They are humanoids with a bestial aspect. While they can't fully change shape, they can temporarily enhance their animalistic features—a state they call shifting. Whatever their origins, shifters have evolved into a unique race. A shifter walks on the knife's edge between the wilds and the world around them. Do they embrace their primal instincts or the path of civilization?

Wildhunt shifters are sharp and insightful. Some are constantly alert, wary for possible threats. Others focus on their intuition, searching within. Wildhunt shifters are excellent hunters, and they also tend to become the spiritual leaders of shifter communities.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Races Of Eberron p. 6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>The Beast Within</name>
      <text>Early in childhood, a shifter forms a bond with a beast within: a totemic force that shapes their body and mind. Some shifters believe that these spirits are independent entities, and they might speak of Bear or Wolf as ancestors or guides. Most just see the beast within as a formidable expression of their inner nature, something that emerges over time as the shifter's personality takes shape. The beast within is a pool of powerful instincts, and its influence is revealed by the shifter's personality: a feline shifter might be cool and distant, driven by predatory instincts, while a shifter with a lupine spirit is drawn to find and protect a pack. When a shifter fully embraces this beast within, they physically transform for a short time.
	This beast within is reflected by the shifter's subrace. The following subraces are especially common:

Beasthide often signifies the bear or boar: stoic, stubborn and thick-skinned.

Longtooth shifters typically have lupine traits and are attracted to pack life.

Swiftstride shifters are often predatory and feline, but a swiftstride could also be a cunning rat who darts through the shadows.

Wildhunt shifters are born from any creature that tracks its prey.

While the beast within certainly has a physical impact on a shifter, it also has a spiritual and psychological effect. Two beasthide shifters share the same special ability, but if one has the aspect of the boar and the other is more like a bear, they'll be quite different in personality. With any shifter, identifying the beast within is a crucial part of understanding the character.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Similar and Diverse</name>
      <text>Shifters are similar to humans in height and build but are more naturally lithe and flexible. Their facial features have a bestial cast, with large eyes, flat noses, and pointed ears; most shifters also have prominent canine teeth. They grow fur-like hair on nearly every part of their bodies.
	The traits of the beast within affect a shifter's appearance as well. A swiftstride shifter might have catlike eyes and delicate build, while a beasthide shifter is likely a massive brute built like a bear. While a shifter's appearance might remind an onlooker of an animal, they remain clearly identifiable as shifters even when at their most feral.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>The Journey Yet to Come</name>
      <text>Shifters have a strong presence in the Eldeen Reaches, and they often live among humans and can be found in rural areas across Khorvaire. While they form powerful bonds with friends and kin, shifters place great value on selfreliance and freedom. It's a shifter proverb to "always be prepared for the journey yet to come," and most shifters strive to be ready for change or opportunity.
	Shifters have a natural inclination toward classes with a primal connection. A shifter barbarian draws their rage from the beast within. A shifter ranger indulges their urge to wander and hunt. A shifter rogue harnesses their own predatory instincts. But shifters can pursue any path or faith.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Shifter Names</name>
      <text>Shifters have no language of their own and often live in blended communities. As such, shifter names typically overlap with the names of other cultures in their region. Many shifters prefer to keep their personal names for their friends and use "wandering names" with strangers. These are usually tied to an obvious physical or personality trait.

Shifter Names: Badger, Bear, Cat, Fang, Grace, Grim, Moon, Rain, Red, Scar, Stripe, Swift, Whiskers, Wolf</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Shifters are quick to mature both physically and emotionally, reaching young adulthood at age 10. They rarely live to be more than 70 years old.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Shifters tend toward neutrality, being more focused on survival than concepts of good and evil. A love of personal freedom can drive Shifters toward chaotic alignments.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Shifters range from 5 to almost 7 feet tall, depending on their subrace. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 4 feet + 6 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 90 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Keen Senses</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with the Perception skill.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Shifting</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, you can assume a more bestial appearance. This transformation lasts for 1 minute, until you die, or until you revert to your normal appearance as a bonus action. When you shift, you gain temporary hit points equal to your level + your Constitution modifier (minimum of 1 temporary hit point). You also gain additional benefits that depend on your Shifter subrace, described below.
	Once you shift, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Natural Tracker</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with the Survival skill.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Mark the Scent</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, you can mark one creature you can see within 10 feet of you. Until the end of your next long rest, your proficiency bonus is doubled for any ability check you make to find the marked creature, and you always know the location of that creature if it is within 60 feet of you. You can't use this trait again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Shifting Feature</name>
      <text>While shifted, you have advantage on Wisdom checks.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common.</text>
    </trait>
  </race> -->
  <race>
    <name>Warforged, Envoy (UA Races of Eberron)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Con +1</ability>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>"Pierce was built by design, while you were built by accident," Lakashtai said. "The soul is what matters, not the shape of the vessel."
	"What makes you think he has a soul?" Gerrion said.
	"What makes you think you do?"
—Keith Baker, The Shattered Land

The warforged were built to fight in the Last War. The first warforged were mindless automatons, but House Cannith devoted vast resources to improving these steel soldiers. An unexpected breakthrough produced fully sentient soldiers, blending organic and inorganic materials. Warforged may be made from wood and metal, but they can feel pain and emotion. Built as weapons, they must now find a purpose beyond the war. A warforged can be a steadfast ally, a cold-hearted killing machine, or a visionary in search of purpose and meaning.

As an envoy, you were designed with a certain specialized function in mind. You might be an assassin, a healer, or an entertainer, to name a few possibilities. Envoys are the rarest of the warforged subraces, and yours could be a unique design.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Races Of Eberron p. 69</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Living Steel and Stone</name>
      <text>Warforged are formed from a blend of organic and inorganic materials. Root-like cords infused with alchemical fluids serve as their muscles, wrapped around a framework of steel, darkwood, or stone. Armored plates form a protective outer shell and reinforce joints. All warforged share a common facial design, with a hinged jaw and crystal eyes embedded beneath a reinforced brow ridge. A sigil is engraved into the center of the forehead; this is unique to each warforged. Beyond these common elements of warforged design, the precise materials and build of a warforged vary based on the purpose for which it was designed. A juggernaut warrior is a massive brute sheathed in heavy steel plates, while a skirmisher can be crafted from wood and light mithral to grant it lithe and elegant movement.
	While they are formed from stone and steel, warforged are humanoids. Resting, healing magic, and the Medicine skill all provide the same benefits to warforged that they do to other humanoids. A warforged can focus its mind on its body as it rests, adjusting its shape and form to assume one of a few defensive postures. A warforged who expects heavy combat might focus on durability, while during a time of peace they might be content to adopt a lighter, less aggressive form.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Warforged Personality</name>
      <text>The warforged were built to serve and to fight. For most of their existence, warforged had a clearly defined function and were encouraged to focus purely on that role. The Treaty of Throne hold gave them freedom, but many warforged struggle both to find a place in the post-war world and to relate to the creatures that created them.
	The typical warforged shows little emotion. Many warforged embrace a concrete purpose—protecting allies, completing a contract, or other pursuits—and devote themselves to this task as they once did to war. However, there are warforged who delight in exploring their feelings and their freedom. Most warforged have no interest in religion, but some embrace faith and mysticism, seeking higher purpose and deeper meaning.
	The typical warforged has a muscular, sexless body shape. Some warforged ignore the concept of gender entirely, while others adopt a gender identity in emulation of the creatures around them.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Quirks</name>
      <text>Whether due to some flaw in their creation or ignorance of how other creatures operate, warforged often acquire an odd personality trait or two. A warforged player can choose to roll or select a trait from the Warforged Quirks table.

Warforged Quirks:
d10 | Quirk
1 | You analyze (out loud) the potential threat posed by every creature you meet.
2 | You don't understand emotions and often misread emotional cues.
3 | You are fiercely protective of anyone you consider a friend.
4 | You often say the things you are thinking aloud without realizing it.
5 | You try to apply wartime tactics and discipline to every situation.
6 | You don't know how to filter your feelings and are prone to dramatic emotional outbursts.
7 | You don't understand clothing beyond its utility and assume that what a creature wears denotes its job and status.
8 | You are obsessed with your appearance, and constantly polish and buff your armor.
9 | You are deeply concerned with following proper procedures and protocols.
10 | War is the only thing that makes sense to you, and you're always looking for a fight.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Warforged Names</name>
      <text>Warforged were assigned numerical designations for use in military service. Many of them adopted nicknames, often given to them by their comrades. As free individuals, some have chosen new names as a way to express their path in life. A few take on human names, often the name of a fallen friend or mentor.

Warforged Names: Anchor, Banner, Bastion, Blade, Blue, Bow, Church, Crunch, Crystal, Dagger, Dent, Five, Glaive, Hammer, Iron, Lucky, Mace, Pants, Pierce, Red, Rusty, Scout, Seven, Shield, Slash, Smith, Spike, Stone, Temple, Vault, Wall, Wood</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Two ability scores of your choice increases by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>A typical Warforged is between two and thirty years old. The maximum lifespan of the Warforged remains a mystery; so far, Warforged have shown no signs of deterioration due to age.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Most Warforged take comfort in order and discipline, tending toward law and neutrality, but some have absorbed the morality—or lack thereof—of the beings they served with.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Your size is Medium. Most Warforged stand between 5 and 6½ feet tall. Build is affected by your subrace.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d6
Height = 5 feet + 10 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 270 + (1d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d6</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">1d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Warforged Resilience</name>
      <text>You were created to have remarkable fortitude, represented by the following benefits:

	• You have advantage on saving throws against being poisoned, and you have resistance to poison damage.

	• You are immune to disease.

	• You don't need to eat, drink, or breathe.

	• You don't need to sleep and don't suffer the effects of exhaustion due to lack of rest, and magic can't put you to sleep.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Sentry's Rest</name>
      <text>When you take a long rest, you must spend at least six hours of it in an inactive, motionless state, rather than sleeping. In this state, you appear inert, but it doesn't render you unconscious, and you can see and hear as normal.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Integrated Protection</name>
      <text>Your body has built-in protective layers, which determine your Armor Class. You gain no benefit from wearing armor, but if you are using a shield, you apply its bonus as normal.
	You can alter your body to enter different defensive modes; each time you finish a long rest, choose one mode to adopt from the Integrated Protection table, provided you meet the mode's prerequisite.

Integrated Protection:
Mode | Prerequisite | Armor Class
Darkwood core (unarmored) | None | 11 + your Dexterity modifier (add proficiency bonus if proficient with light armor)
Composite plating (armor) | Medium armor proficiency | 13 + your Dexterity modifier (maximum of 2) + your proficiency bonus
Heavy plating (armor) | Heavy armor proficiency | 16 + your proficiency bonus; disadvantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Specialized Design</name>
      <text>You gain one skill proficiency of your choice, one tool proficiency of your choice, and fluency in one language of your choice.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Integrated Tool</name>
      <text>Choose one tool you're proficient with. This tool is integrated into your body, and you double your proficiency bonus for any ability checks you make with it. You must have your hands free to use this integrated tool.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Envoys: Specialized Design</name>
      <text>As the name implies, most Warforged were built to fight in the Last War. The vast majority of Warforged are juggernauts or skirmishers—soldiers and scouts who fought under the banner of one of the Five Nations. Warforged envoys, however, were designed to perform other functions. As an envoy, you have a skill, a tool proficiency, and a tool that's part of your body. When you make an envoy character, consider the following questions: What is your purpose? How does your skill and your tool reflect that purpose? What form does your integrated tool take? If you have embedded thieves' tools, for instance, are your fingers actually lockpicks, or can you produce keys from various parts of your body? The following characters are examples of Warforged with integrated tools.

Lute is a bard with the entertainer background; his namesake instrument folds out of his left arm.

Compass Rose is a wizard with the outlander background. A keen explorer, she uses her built-in cartographer's tools to record the paths she travels.

Masque is an infiltrator. A rogue with the charlatan background and an integrated disguise Kit, she was built to blend in and assassinate. Cannith built six Warforged of her design, and Masque has vowed to hunt down and destroy the other five.

In developing your integrated tool, remember that you must have your hands free to use it. Masque, the infiltrator mentioned above, doesn't shapeshift like a changeling; she has to manually adjust her appearance.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Warforged, Juggernaut (UA Races of Eberron)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Con +1, Str +2</ability>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>"Pierce was built by design, while you were built by accident," Lakashtai said. "The soul is what matters, not the shape of the vessel."
	"What makes you think he has a soul?" Gerrion said.
	"What makes you think you do?"
—Keith Baker, The Shattered Land

The warforged were built to fight in the Last War. The first warforged were mindless automatons, but House Cannith devoted vast resources to improving these steel soldiers. An unexpected breakthrough produced fully sentient soldiers, blending organic and inorganic materials. Warforged may be made from wood and metal, but they can feel pain and emotion. Built as weapons, they must now find a purpose beyond the war. A warforged can be a steadfast ally, a cold-hearted killing machine, or a visionary in search of purpose and meaning.

You're an imposing war machine built for close combat and raw might. You tower over your comrades: juggernaut warforged stand between 6 and 7 feet in height and can weigh up to 450 pounds.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Races Of Eberron p. 69</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Living Steel and Stone</name>
      <text>Warforged are formed from a blend of organic and inorganic materials. Root-like cords infused with alchemical fluids serve as their muscles, wrapped around a framework of steel, darkwood, or stone. Armored plates form a protective outer shell and reinforce joints. All warforged share a common facial design, with a hinged jaw and crystal eyes embedded beneath a reinforced brow ridge. A sigil is engraved into the center of the forehead; this is unique to each warforged. Beyond these common elements of warforged design, the precise materials and build of a warforged vary based on the purpose for which it was designed. A juggernaut warrior is a massive brute sheathed in heavy steel plates, while a skirmisher can be crafted from wood and light mithral to grant it lithe and elegant movement.
	While they are formed from stone and steel, warforged are humanoids. Resting, healing magic, and the Medicine skill all provide the same benefits to warforged that they do to other humanoids. A warforged can focus its mind on its body as it rests, adjusting its shape and form to assume one of a few defensive postures. A warforged who expects heavy combat might focus on durability, while during a time of peace they might be content to adopt a lighter, less aggressive form.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Warforged Personality</name>
      <text>The warforged were built to serve and to fight. For most of their existence, warforged had a clearly defined function and were encouraged to focus purely on that role. The Treaty of Throne hold gave them freedom, but many warforged struggle both to find a place in the post-war world and to relate to the creatures that created them.
	The typical warforged shows little emotion. Many warforged embrace a concrete purpose—protecting allies, completing a contract, or other pursuits—and devote themselves to this task as they once did to war. However, there are warforged who delight in exploring their feelings and their freedom. Most warforged have no interest in religion, but some embrace faith and mysticism, seeking higher purpose and deeper meaning.
	The typical warforged has a muscular, sexless body shape. Some warforged ignore the concept of gender entirely, while others adopt a gender identity in emulation of the creatures around them.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Quirks</name>
      <text>Whether due to some flaw in their creation or ignorance of how other creatures operate, warforged often acquire an odd personality trait or two. A warforged player can choose to roll or select a trait from the Warforged Quirks table.

Warforged Quirks:
d10 | Quirk
1 | You analyze (out loud) the potential threat posed by every creature you meet.
2 | You don't understand emotions and often misread emotional cues.
3 | You are fiercely protective of anyone you consider a friend.
4 | You often say the things you are thinking aloud without realizing it.
5 | You try to apply wartime tactics and discipline to every situation.
6 | You don't know how to filter your feelings and are prone to dramatic emotional outbursts.
7 | You don't understand clothing beyond its utility and assume that what a creature wears denotes its job and status.
8 | You are obsessed with your appearance, and constantly polish and buff your armor.
9 | You are deeply concerned with following proper procedures and protocols.
10 | War is the only thing that makes sense to you, and you're always looking for a fight.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Warforged Names</name>
      <text>Warforged were assigned numerical designations for use in military service. Many of them adopted nicknames, often given to them by their comrades. As free individuals, some have chosen new names as a way to express their path in life. A few take on human names, often the name of a fallen friend or mentor.

Warforged Names: Anchor, Banner, Bastion, Blade, Blue, Bow, Church, Crunch, Crystal, Dagger, Dent, Five, Glaive, Hammer, Iron, Lucky, Mace, Pants, Pierce, Red, Rusty, Scout, Seven, Shield, Slash, Smith, Spike, Stone, Temple, Vault, Wall, Wood</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Two ability scores of your choice increases by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>A typical Warforged is between two and thirty years old. The maximum lifespan of the Warforged remains a mystery; so far, Warforged have shown no signs of deterioration due to age.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Most Warforged take comfort in order and discipline, tending toward law and neutrality, but some have absorbed the morality—or lack thereof—of the beings they served with.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Your size is Medium. Most Warforged stand between 5 and 6½ feet tall. Build is affected by your subrace.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d6
Height = 5 feet + 10 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 270 + (1d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d6</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">1d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Warforged Resilience</name>
      <text>You were created to have remarkable fortitude, represented by the following benefits:

	• You have advantage on saving throws against being poisoned, and you have resistance to poison damage.

	• You are immune to disease.

	• You don't need to eat, drink, or breathe.

	• You don't need to sleep and don't suffer the effects of exhaustion due to lack of rest, and magic can't put you to sleep.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Sentry's Rest</name>
      <text>When you take a long rest, you must spend at least six hours of it in an inactive, motionless state, rather than sleeping. In this state, you appear inert, but it doesn't render you unconscious, and you can see and hear as normal.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Integrated Protection</name>
      <text>Your body has built-in protective layers, which determine your Armor Class. You gain no benefit from wearing armor, but if you are using a shield, you apply its bonus as normal.
	You can alter your body to enter different defensive modes; each time you finish a long rest, choose one mode to adopt from the Integrated Protection table, provided you meet the mode's prerequisite.

Integrated Protection:
Mode | Prerequisite | Armor Class
Darkwood core (unarmored) | None | 11 + your Dexterity modifier (add proficiency bonus if proficient with light armor)
Composite plating (armor) | Medium armor proficiency | 13 + your Dexterity modifier (maximum of 2) + your proficiency bonus
Heavy plating (armor) | Heavy armor proficiency | 16 + your proficiency bonus; disadvantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Iron Fists</name>
      <text>When you hit with an unarmed strike, you can deal 1d4 + your Strength modifier bludgeoning damage, instead of the normal damage for an unarmed strike.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Powerful Build</name>
      <text>You count as one size larger when determining your carrying capacity and the weight you can push, drag, or lift.</text>
      <special>powerful build</special>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Warforged, Skirmisher (UA Races of Eberron)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>35</speed>
    <ability>Con +1, Dex +2</ability>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>"Pierce was built by design, while you were built by accident," Lakashtai said. "The soul is what matters, not the shape of the vessel."
	"What makes you think he has a soul?" Gerrion said.
	"What makes you think you do?"
—Keith Baker, The Shattered Land

The warforged were built to fight in the Last War. The first warforged were mindless automatons, but House Cannith devoted vast resources to improving these steel soldiers. An unexpected breakthrough produced fully sentient soldiers, blending organic and inorganic materials. Warforged may be made from wood and metal, but they can feel pain and emotion. Built as weapons, they must now find a purpose beyond the war. A warforged can be a steadfast ally, a cold-hearted killing machine, or a visionary in search of purpose and meaning.

You were built to scout the edges of battle and outmaneuver your enemies. You are lean and designed for speed.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Races Of Eberron p. 69</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Living Steel and Stone</name>
      <text>Warforged are formed from a blend of organic and inorganic materials. Root-like cords infused with alchemical fluids serve as their muscles, wrapped around a framework of steel, darkwood, or stone. Armored plates form a protective outer shell and reinforce joints. All warforged share a common facial design, with a hinged jaw and crystal eyes embedded beneath a reinforced brow ridge. A sigil is engraved into the center of the forehead; this is unique to each warforged. Beyond these common elements of warforged design, the precise materials and build of a warforged vary based on the purpose for which it was designed. A juggernaut warrior is a massive brute sheathed in heavy steel plates, while a skirmisher can be crafted from wood and light mithral to grant it lithe and elegant movement.
	While they are formed from stone and steel, warforged are humanoids. Resting, healing magic, and the Medicine skill all provide the same benefits to warforged that they do to other humanoids. A warforged can focus its mind on its body as it rests, adjusting its shape and form to assume one of a few defensive postures. A warforged who expects heavy combat might focus on durability, while during a time of peace they might be content to adopt a lighter, less aggressive form.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Warforged Personality</name>
      <text>The warforged were built to serve and to fight. For most of their existence, warforged had a clearly defined function and were encouraged to focus purely on that role. The Treaty of Throne hold gave them freedom, but many warforged struggle both to find a place in the post-war world and to relate to the creatures that created them.
	The typical warforged shows little emotion. Many warforged embrace a concrete purpose—protecting allies, completing a contract, or other pursuits—and devote themselves to this task as they once did to war. However, there are warforged who delight in exploring their feelings and their freedom. Most warforged have no interest in religion, but some embrace faith and mysticism, seeking higher purpose and deeper meaning.
	The typical warforged has a muscular, sexless body shape. Some warforged ignore the concept of gender entirely, while others adopt a gender identity in emulation of the creatures around them.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Quirks</name>
      <text>Whether due to some flaw in their creation or ignorance of how other creatures operate, warforged often acquire an odd personality trait or two. A warforged player can choose to roll or select a trait from the Warforged Quirks table.

Warforged Quirks:
d10 | Quirk
1 | You analyze (out loud) the potential threat posed by every creature you meet.
2 | You don't understand emotions and often misread emotional cues.
3 | You are fiercely protective of anyone you consider a friend.
4 | You often say the things you are thinking aloud without realizing it.
5 | You try to apply wartime tactics and discipline to every situation.
6 | You don't know how to filter your feelings and are prone to dramatic emotional outbursts.
7 | You don't understand clothing beyond its utility and assume that what a creature wears denotes its job and status.
8 | You are obsessed with your appearance, and constantly polish and buff your armor.
9 | You are deeply concerned with following proper procedures and protocols.
10 | War is the only thing that makes sense to you, and you're always looking for a fight.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Warforged Names</name>
      <text>Warforged were assigned numerical designations for use in military service. Many of them adopted nicknames, often given to them by their comrades. As free individuals, some have chosen new names as a way to express their path in life. A few take on human names, often the name of a fallen friend or mentor.

Warforged Names: Anchor, Banner, Bastion, Blade, Blue, Bow, Church, Crunch, Crystal, Dagger, Dent, Five, Glaive, Hammer, Iron, Lucky, Mace, Pants, Pierce, Red, Rusty, Scout, Seven, Shield, Slash, Smith, Spike, Stone, Temple, Vault, Wall, Wood</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Two ability scores of your choice increases by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>A typical Warforged is between two and thirty years old. The maximum lifespan of the Warforged remains a mystery; so far, Warforged have shown no signs of deterioration due to age.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Most Warforged take comfort in order and discipline, tending toward law and neutrality, but some have absorbed the morality—or lack thereof—of the beings they served with.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Your size is Medium. Most Warforged stand between 5 and 6½ feet tall. Build is affected by your subrace.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d6
Height = 5 feet + 10 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 270 + (1d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d6</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">1d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Warforged Resilience</name>
      <text>You were created to have remarkable fortitude, represented by the following benefits:

	• You have advantage on saving throws against being poisoned, and you have resistance to poison damage.

	• You are immune to disease.

	• You don't need to eat, drink, or breathe.

	• You don't need to sleep and don't suffer the effects of exhaustion due to lack of rest, and magic can't put you to sleep.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Sentry's Rest</name>
      <text>When you take a long rest, you must spend at least six hours of it in an inactive, motionless state, rather than sleeping. In this state, you appear inert, but it doesn't render you unconscious, and you can see and hear as normal.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Integrated Protection</name>
      <text>Your body has built-in protective layers, which determine your Armor Class. You gain no benefit from wearing armor, but if you are using a shield, you apply its bonus as normal.
	You can alter your body to enter different defensive modes; each time you finish a long rest, choose one mode to adopt from the Integrated Protection table, provided you meet the mode's prerequisite.

Integrated Protection:
Mode | Prerequisite | Armor Class
Darkwood core (unarmored) | None | 11 + your Dexterity modifier (add proficiency bonus if proficient with light armor)
Composite plating (armor) | Medium armor proficiency | 13 + your Dexterity modifier (maximum of 2) + your proficiency bonus
Heavy plating (armor) | Heavy armor proficiency | 16 + your proficiency bonus; disadvantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Swift</name>
      <text>Your walking speed increases by 5 feet.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Light Step</name>
      <text>When you are traveling alone for an extended period of time (one hour or more), you can move stealthily at a normal pace. (See chapter 8 of the Player's Handbook for information about travel pace.)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
</compendium>
