<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <monster>
    <name>Gaea Trout (Stormchaser)</name>
    <sortname>Trout, Gaea</sortname>
    <ancestry>Trout</ancestry>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (halfling)</type>
    <alignment>chaotic good</alignment>
    <ac>14 (mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>42 (12d6)</hp>
    <speed>25 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save>Int +5, Wis +3</save>
    <skill>Arcana +5, Sleight Of Hand +3</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>Common, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Gaea is a 3rd-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). She has the following wizard spells prepared:

	• Cantrips (at will): mage hand, message, shocking grasp
	• 1st level (4 slots): comprehend languages, mage armor, shield, silent image
	• 2nd level (2 slots): blur, enlarge/reduce</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Brave</name>
      <text>Gaea has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Lucky</name>
      <text>When Gaea rolls a 1 on the d20 for an attack roll, ability check, or saving throw, she can reroll the die and must use the new roll.</text>
    </trait>
    <reaction>
      <name>Portent</name>
      <text>Gaea has two portent dice which are d20s and are rolled at the end of a long rest. She can replace any attack roll, skill check, or saving throw made by herself or a creature she can see with one of these dice.</text>
    </reaction>
    <spells>mage hand, message, shocking grasp, comprehend languages, mage armor, shield, silent image, blur, enlarge/reduce</spells>
    <description>Source:	Stormchasers (u/Selachian) (Homebrew)</description>
    <environment>Any</environment>
  </monster>
  <!-- Stormchasers, Gaea Trout -->
  <monster>
    <name>Toosday Embers (Stormchaser)</name>
    <sortname>Embers, Toosday</sortname>
    <ancestry>Embers</ancestry>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (gnome)</type>
    <alignment>chaotic neutral</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>54 (12d6+12)</hp>
    <speed>25 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Str +1, Dex +5</save>
    <skill>Perception +4, Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Gnome</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Toosday is a 3rd-level spellcaster. Wisdom is his spelcasting ability. He has the following ranger spells prepared:

	• 1st level (3 slots): animal friendship, cure wounds, hunter's mark, protection from evil and good</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Planar Warrior</name>
      <text>Toosday's attacks ignore damage resistances and also deal an extra 1d6 force damage (included in the description).</text>
      <attack>Force Damage||1d6</attack>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Natural Explorer</name>
      <text>Toosday's explorational training have given him the following benefits:

	• Toosday ignores difficult terrtain.
	• Toosday has advantage on initiative rolls.
	• On the first round of combat, Toosday has advantage on attacks made against creatures that have not taken a yet acted.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Gnome Cunning</name>
      <text>Toosday has advantage on all Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws against magic.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Toosday makes two shortsword attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target, Hit: 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage plus 3 (1d6) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|5|1d6+3</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage||1d6</attack>
    </action>
    <spells>animal friendship, cure wounds, hunter's mark, protection from evil and good</spells>
    <description>Source:	Stormchasers (u/Selachian) (Homebrew)</description>
    <environment>Any</environment>
  </monster>
  <!-- Stormchasers, Toosday Embers -->
  <monster>
    <name>Dire Panther</name>
    <sortname>Panther, Dire</sortname>
    <ancestry>Panther</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>chaotic neutral</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>37 (5d10+10)</hp>
    <speed>50 ft., climb 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Perception +4, Stealth +6</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>-</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Pounce</name>
      <text>If the panther moves at least 20 feet straight toward a creature and then hits it with a claw attack on the same turn, that target must succeed on a DC Strength saving throw or be knocked prone. If the target is prone, the panther can make one bite attack against it as a bonus action.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5ft., one target. Hit: 10 (2d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|5|2d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5ft., one target. Hit: 8 (2d4 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|5|2d4+3</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Source:	Stormchasers (u/Selachian) (Homebrew)</description>
    <environment>Any</environment>
  </monster>
  <!-- Dire Panther -->
  <monster>
    <name>Awilo Nefasi, the Greater Storm Elemental</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>lawful neutral</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>114 (12d12+36)</hp>
    <speed>45 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>20</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Auran</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical weapons</resist>
    <immune>lightning, poison, thunder</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Air Form</name>
      <text>The elemental can enter a hostile creature's space and stop there. It can move through a space as narrow as 1 inch wide without squeezing.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Body of the Storm</name>
      <text>A strong wind blows around the elemental in a 10 foot radius, confering the following effects:

	• Unprotected flames in that area are extinguished.
	• The area is difficult terrtain for all other creatures.
	• Ranged weapon attack rolls have disadvantage if they pass in or out of the range.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Heart of the Storm</name>
      <text>A creature attempting to leave the storm's space must succeed on a DC 17 Strength saving throw.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Rage of the Storm</name>
      <text>A creature that starts its turn in the elemental's space takes 4 (1d8) lightning damage and 4 (1d8) thunder damage.</text>
      <attack>Rage of the Storm||1d8</attack>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Seige Monster</name>
      <text>The elemental does double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5ft., one target. Hit 14 (2d8 + 5) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|8|2d8+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ball Lightning (Recharge 6)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>The elemental summons 2 (1d4) Motes of Lightning in unoccupied spaces within 60 feet.</text>
      <attack>Ball Lightning||1d4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Disperse</name>
      <text>The elemental becomes invisible until it uses an action to return to normal. While invisible in this way, the elemental's traits Body of the Storm, Heart of the Storm, and Rage of the Storm are inactive.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Whirlwind (Recharge 4-6)</name>
      <recharge>D4</recharge>
      <text>Each creature in the elemental's space must make a DC 16 Strength saving throw. On a failure, a target takes 15 (3d8 + 2) bludgeoning damage and is flung up 40 feet away from the elemental and knocked prone. If a Thrown target strikes an object, such as a wall or floor, the target takes 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage for every 10 feet it was Thrown. If the target is Thrown at another creature, that creature must succeed on a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw or take the same damage and be knocked prone. If the saving throw is successful, the target takes half the bludgeoning damage and isn't flung away or knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Whirlwind||3d8+2</attack>
      <attack>Thrown||1d6</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Storm Surge</name>
      <text>When a creature comes within 5 feet of the elemental, it can cause that creature to attempt a DC 17 Strength saving throw. On a failure, that creature is pulled 5 feet into the elemental's space.</text>
    </reaction>
    <description>Rage Unbound, Power Unprecedented. Whether he began his life as a normal air elemental or was created with this much power is unknown. Awilo Nefasi displays higher intelligence than other air elementals, but, that intelligence comes with a price: cold, unbridled fury. Awilo Nefasi is known for flying into destructive rages

Absent Ambition. Although he is powerful enough to command his own retinue of air elementals and act as a Major Lord on the Elemental Plane of Air, Awilo Nefasi is content to serve his life as a brute. He has worked in the employ of much of the nobility at one point or another. It's become something of an unspoken rule that one can only enlist the services of the storm for a quarter-century or so before selling him off to another.

Eye of the storm It is common knowledge on the Elemental Plane of Air that at the center of even the most endlessly raging of storms there is a place of silence, peace and serenity. If the same can be said of Awilo Nefasi, anyone who's ever tried to find it has paid a hefty price.

Father of Sparks. Awilo Nefasi's ability to generate other elementals is something of an oddity. He takes note of this trait only in that it aids him in combat, providing him with allies. These creations do not live long lives, even if they survive the combat. After merely a few hours they fizzle into balls of plasma, leaving the slight scent of ozone on the air.

Source:	Stormchasers (u/Selachian) (Homebrew)</description>
    <environment>Any</environment>
  </monster>
  <!-- Awilo Nefasi the Greater Storm Elemental -->
  <monster>
    <name>Mote of Lightning</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>31 (7d6+7)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., fly 30 ft. (hover)</speed>
    <str>6</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Auran</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical weapons</resist>
    <immune>lightning, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Air Form</name>
      <text>The elemental can enter a hostile creature's space and stop there. It can move through a space as narrow as 1 inch wide without squeezing.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Electrostatic Cloud</name>
      <text>At the start of each of the mote's turns, each creature within 5 feet of it takes 4 (1d8) lightning damage. A Large or smaller creature damaged this way must succeed on a DC 11 Constitution save or become stunned until the end of the creature's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Electrostatic Cloud||1d8</attack>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Shock</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: 6 (1d8 + 2) lightning damage, and if the target is a Large or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 11 Constitution save or become stunned until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Shock|4|1d8+2</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Experts believe the mote is a juvenile air elemental, though this has never been proven. What is known is that these volatile creatures are malicious in intent and when a large amount of them gather, they can generate enough power to change the weather.

Cloud of Electricity. Resembling little more than wisps of cloud and vapour, the body of the mote is barely visible, and even when viewed clearly seems to be little more than smoke. The air around the mote crackles with energy, and occasionally short arcs of lighting will shoot from it.

Source:	Stormchasers (u/Selachian) (Homebrew)</description>
    <environment>Any</environment>
  </monster>
  <!-- Mote of Lightning -->
</compendium>
