<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Wizard</name>
    <!-- Arcane Tradition: Runecrafter (UA) -->
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Arcane Tradition: Runecrafter (UA)</name>
        <text>Runecrafter wizards enhance their spellcasting through the ancient power of runes. Though the tradition originated with the giant rune casters of old, runecraft magic has expanded to encompass countless languages and practitioners across different worlds.
	For many runecrafters, the runes they wield are as every bit unique and personal as their spellbook. Some strive to honor the practice's origins among the giants, engraving their runes on decorative stones that adorn their spellcasting implements, while others messily scribble their runes on scraps of paper.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Giant Options p. 3</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Runes Of Understanding (Runecrafter (UA))</name>
        <text>Beginning at 2nd level, your study of runecraft has unlocked the ability to decode runes and languages, regardless of their origin; you always have comprehend languages prepared, you can cast it without expending a spell slot, and the spell doesn't count against the number of spells you have prepared.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Giant Options p. 3</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Runic Empowerment (Runecrafter (UA))</name>
        <text>Also at 2nd level, when you choose this subclass, you learn how to amplify your magic through the application of various runes. Your knowledge of these runes is stored in your spellbook, though you determine the runes' cosmetic appearance. For example, your runes could be engraved into the cover of your spellbook, glowing whenever you cast a spell, or you could work the shape and meaning of the runes directly into a spell's somatic and verbal components.
	When you cast a spell using a spell slot, you can invoke one of the following runes:

Life Rune. When you invoke this rune, choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of you (you can choose yourself). The chosen creature gains temporary hit points equal to 5 times the level of the spell slot expended.

War Rune. When you invoke this rune, choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of you. Until the end of your next turn, attack rolls that target the chosen creature gain a bonus equal to half the level of the spell slot expended (rounded up, minimum of +1).

Wind Rune. When you invoke this rune, your speed increases by a number of feet equal to 5 times the level of the spell slot expended, and your movement doesn't provoke opportunity attacks. These benefits last until the start of your next turn.

You can invoke no more than one rune per spell. You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Giant Options p. 3</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sigils Of Warding (Runecrafter (UA))</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you can call on a rune of protection to guard yourself against threats. When you fail a Strength, Dexterity, or Constitution saving throw, you can use your reaction to expend one use of your Runic Empowerment and succeed on the saving throw instead.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Giant Options p. 3</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Rune Maven (Runecrafter (UA))</name>
        <text>At 10th level, your understanding of runecraft has grown immensely. Whenever you use your Arcane Recovery feature, you also regain a number of your expended uses of Runic Empowerment. The number of uses you regain can be no more than half your Intelligence modifier, rounded up (minimum of 1).

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Giant Options p. 3</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Engraved Enmity (Runecrafter (UA))</name>
        <text>You have mastered the art of wielding your runes directly against your foes. As a bonus action, you can target one creature you can see within 60 feet of yourself. The creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC or be magically marked by an enmity rune.
	The enmity rune appears as a faintly glowing mote of energy that hovers over the marked creature, which suffers the following effects:

Runecraft's Bane. The creature has disadvantage on saving throws made against spells you cast.

Unveiled Enemy. The radiance of the glowing rune makes the creature visible if it's invisible, and the creature can't become invisible while the rune persists.

Woeful Curse. When you mark the creature, and as a bonus action on subsequent turns for the duration, you can invoke the enmity rune to curse the creature until the start of your next turn. The next time one of your allies hits the cursed creature with an attack roll, the target also takes 1d8 force damage, and the curse ends.

The enmity rune lasts for 1 minute or until you lose your concentration (as if you were concentrating on a spell). Once you have marked a creature in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot of 3rd level or higher to use this feature again.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Giant Options p. 3</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
