<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <monster>
    <name>Gourdon Applegrove</name>
    <sortname>Applegrove, Gourdon</sortname>
    <npc>YES</npc>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>neutral good</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>189 (18d10+90)</hp>
    <speed>20 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Int +10, Wis +7</save>
    <skill>Arcana +15, History +15, Investigation +10</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>All</languages>
    <cr>14</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>damage from spells</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>charmed</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Parasitic Pal</name>
      <text>Gourdon and Jack are bound together as one entity, they can not move away from each other and any spell or damage targeting one of them effects the other as well. Though each have their own turn in the initiative order.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Gourdon has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Combat Preparation</name>
      <text>Gourdon casts stoneskin and mind blank on himself before combat.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Gourdon is an 18th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). Gourdon can cast detect magic and misty Step at will and has the following wizard spells prepared:

	• Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp
	• 1st level (4 slots): shield, identify, feather fall magic missile
	• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, hold person
	• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, lightning bolt
	• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, fire shield, stoneskin
	• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, scrying, wall of force
	• 6th level (1 slot): globe of invulnerability
	• 7th level (1 slot): teleport
	• 8th level (1 slot): mind blank
	• 9th level (1 slot): time stop</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Headbutt</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 12 (2d10 + 1) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Headbutt|6|2d10+1</attack>
    </action>
    <slots>0,4,3,3,3,3,1,1,1,1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, shield, identify, feather fall magic missile, detect thoughts, mirror image, hold person, counterspell, fly, lightning bolt, banishment, fire shield, stoneskin, cone of cold, scrying, wall of force, globe of invulnerability, teleport, mind blank, time stop</spells>
    <description>Gourdon Applegrove, once upon a time, would have been indistinguishable from your everyday, run-of-the-mill wizardfolk. Old, bearded, robed, he was an unassuming man, naive despite the fact that his experience had left him something of a master of the arcane arts. Everyone knew him, and they should; he had been around for ages, and was as much a part of the town as the trees that grew there.

The only skill Gourdon seemed incapable of mastering was the craft of not growing old and dying like most people his age seemed to be keen on. Sure, he had colleagues that dabbled in necromancy, but there must be less unsavoury ways to keep from kicking the bucket. All his research led him to one place, the untapped world of magic that belonged to The Fey.

So with a hop, skip, and plane shift, Gourdon found himself in the Feywilds. A gorgeous place as far as he was concerned; it was a shame he hadn't visited in his youth. Now, an old man hobbling around in the Feywilds is likely to draw attention, and attention was indeed drawn, from a mischievous fey who called himself Jack.

Jack struck up a bargain with Gourdon: Jack would greatly extend Gourdon's life in exchange for Gourdon bringing Jack out of the Feywilds to explore the Material Plane. This seemed a simple enough request, and the wizard agreed. To no one's shock, the fine print of the bargain had been concealed, much to Jack's delight and Gourdon's chagrin. Gourdon emerged from the deal as gnarled, warty old tortoise, and Jack had taken the form of a carved pumpkin as his shell.

While not in his preferred spirit animal, Gourdon has taken his predicament in stride, and continues life more as less as normal: reading, napping, researching magics, and having tea and scones. Jack remains on his back, growing bored and disgruntled at the mundanity of the wizard's life. His trickery is persistent and ire is easy to gain, however, some adventurers have been able to avoid conflict with an offering of candy or sweets.

Perhaps together they have it in them for one more adventure.

Source:	Shmeckerel - Gourdon Applegrove &amp; Jack (Homebrew)</description>
    <environment>Any</environment>
  </monster>
  <!-- Gourdon Applegrove-->
  <monster>
    <name>Jack</name>
    <npc>YES</npc>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>189 (18d10+90)</hp>
    <speed>0 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>20</cha>
    <skill>Deception +7, Intimidation +7</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Ignan, Infernal, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>damage from spells</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>charmed</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Parasitic Pal</name>
      <text>Gourdon and Jack are bound together as one entity, they can not move away from each other and any spell or damage targeting one of them effects the other as well. Though each have their own turn in the initiative order.
Jack shares AC &amp; HP with Gourdon.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Spellcasting. Jack is a 12th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 15, +7 to hit with spell attacks). Jack has the following spells prepared:

	• Cantrips (at will): dancing lights, fire bolt, mage hand, produce flame, thaumaturgy
	• 1st level (4 slots): burning hands, faerie fire, hellish rebuke, sleep
	• 2nd level (3 slots): flaming sphere, heat metal, scorching ray
	• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, dispel magic, fireball
	• 4th level (3 slots): polymorph, wall of fire
	• 5th level (2 slots): telekinesis
	• 6th level (1 slot): irresistible dance</text>
    </trait>
    <slots>0,4,3,3,3,2,1</slots>
    <spells>dancing lights, fire bolt, mage hand, produce flame, thaumaturgy, burning hands, faerie fire, hellish rebuke, sleep, flaming sphere, heat metal, scorching ray, counterspell, dispel magic, fireball, polymorph, wall of fire, telekinesis, irresistible dance</spells>
    <description>Gourdon Applegrove, once upon a time, would have been indistinguishable from your everyday, run-of-the-mill wizardfolk. Old, bearded, robed, he was an unassuming man, naive despite the fact that his experience had left him something of a master of the arcane arts. Everyone knew him, and they should; he had been around for ages, and was as much a part of the town as the trees that grew there.

The only skill Gourdon seemed incapable of mastering was the craft of not growing old and dying like most people his age seemed to be keen on. Sure, he had colleagues that dabbled in necromancy, but there must be less unsavoury ways to keep from kicking the bucket. All his research led him to one place, the untapped world of magic that belonged to The Fey.

So with a hop, skip, and plane shift, Gourdon found himself in the Feywilds. A gorgeous place as far as he was concerned; it was a shame he hadn't visited in his youth. Now, an old man hobbling around in the Feywilds is likely to draw attention, and attention was indeed drawn, from a mischievous fey who called himself Jack.

Jack struck up a bargain with Gourdon: Jack would greatly extend Gourdon's life in exchange for Gourdon bringing Jack out of the Feywilds to explore the Material Plane. This seemed a simple enough request, and the wizard agreed. To no one's shock, the fine print of the bargain had been concealed, much to Jack's delight and Gourdon's chagrin. Gourdon emerged from the deal as gnarled, warty old tortoise, and Jack had taken the form of a carved pumpkin as his shell.

While not in his preferred spirit animal, Gourdon has taken his predicament in stride, and continues life more as less as normal: reading, napping, researching magics, and having tea and scones. Jack remains on his back, growing bored and disgruntled at the mundanity of the wizard's life. His trickery is persistent and ire is easy to gain, however, some adventurers have been able to avoid conflict with an offering of candy or sweets.

Perhaps together they have it in them for one more adventure.

Source:	Shmeckerel - Gourdon Applegrove &amp; Jack (Homebrew)</description>
    <environment>Any</environment>
  </monster>
  <!-- Jack-->
  <monster>
    <name>Draxolotl</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>dragon (aquatic)</type>
    <alignment>neutral</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>297 (18d20+108)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., swim 70 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>20</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Str +14, Wis +8, Cha +8</save>
    <skill>Perception +14</skill>
    <passive>24</passive>
    <languages>Draconic, Aquan</languages>
    <cr>20</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The draxolotl can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>The draxolotl regains 15 hit points at the start of its turn if it has at least 1 hit point. The draxolotl is able to fully regenerate lost body parts over a period of months.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The draxolotl makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its claws. It can make one tail attack in place of its two claw attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: 26 (3d12 + 7) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|13|3d12+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 16 (2d8 + 7) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|13|2d8+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: 26 (3d12 + 7) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 20 Strength saving throw or be pushed up to 10 feet away from the draxolotl and knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Tail|13|3d12+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Water Jet (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The draxolotl exhales a jet of water in a 60-foot line that is 10 feet wide. Each creature in that line must make a DC 20 Dexterity saving throw, taking 52 (8d12) bludgeoning damage on a failed save and is pushed to the end of the 60 ft line. A creature that collides with a solid object during this movement takes an additional d6 bludgeoning damage for every 5 ft travelled. A creature that succeeds the saving throw takes half as much damage and is not pushed.</text>
      <attack>Water Jet||8d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Vacuum (Recharge 5-6).</name>
      <text>While under water, the draxolotl inhales a large volume of water. Any huge or smaller creature within a 60 ft cone must make a DC 20 Strength saving throw or be pulled 20 ft. The draxolotl can use its bite attack against any creature that is pulled within 15 ft of the draxolotl with this ability as a free action. If the attack hits, the target is swallowed. The swallowed target is blinded and restrained, it has total cover against attacks and other effects outside the draxolotl, and it takes 20 (3d12) acid damage at the start of each of the draxolotl's turns. The draxolotl can have only three target swallowed at a time.

A swallowed creature can attempt a DC 25 Strength saving throw to escape from the draxolotl. On a success the swallowed creature exits the draxolotl prone and within 5 ft of the draxolotl.

If the draxolotl dies, a swallowed creature is no longer restrained by it and can escape from the corpse using 5 feet of movement, exiting prone.

The use of this action automatically recharges the water jet action.</text>
      <attack>Vacuum||3d12</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Draxolotls tend to be fair tempered and curious in nature, though they can get upset and throw tantrums over seemingly innocuous incidents. Depending on the personality of the draxolotl, this tantrum could be anything from pouting and refusing to leave their underwater cave lair for years on end to full on aggression towards anything unfortunate enough to cross its path.

A draxolotl shares the desire to hoard treasure with many of its draconic kin. However, there is one key difference: a draxolotl sees great value in any object from the surface, but sees no advantage to having more than one of the same object. To have a coin would be wonderful, but a pile of coins just seems messy. Many ship captains will take advantage of this trait and carry a slew of mundane objects on their vessel on the chance they come across a draxolotl. They will barter for protection or passage through the draxolotl's territories. A clever individual may be able to convince a draxolotl that one object is somehow different from another object of the same type, for example by stressing the difference between a fork with 4 prongs and a fork with 3. After all, a fork with only 3 prongs is a trident - completely different.

One species not often found near a draxolotl's lair are whales. To a draxolotl, whale blubber is the most high quality delicacy imaginable. They will hunt down and consume any whales that come anywhere near their territories. A whale carcass is always an acceptable tribute to a draxolotl.

Source:	Shmeckerel (Homebrew)</description>
    <environment>Any</environment>
  </monster>
  <!-- Dragon, Draxolotl -->
  <monster>
    <name>Froggoth</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>7 (3d6-3)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>7</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>8</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>—</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>psychic</immune>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>truesight 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The froggoth can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Standing Leap</name>
      <text>The froggoth's long jump is up to 10 ft. and its high jump is up to 5 ft., with or without a running start.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Psychic Miasma</name>
      <text>All creatures within 10 feet of the froggoth that are not a froggoth must succeed a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature becomes charmed while within 10 feet of the froggoth. While charmed by this effect, the creature is incapacitated and has a speed of 0.

The spell ends for an affected creature if it takes any damage or if someone else uses an action to shake the creature out of its stupor.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Hallucinatory Aura</name>
      <text>Any creature within 60 feet of the froggoth that is not a froggoth must make a DC 14 Wisdom save. On a failed save the creature views the terrain as shifting and swirling. The area becomes difficult terrain and it is impossible to determine the location of environmental hazards. The froggoth is also invisible to the creature.

On a successful saving throw, the creature is immune to the froggoth's aura for 1 minute.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Psychic Shock</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +3 to hit, range 10 ft., one target. Hit: 2d4 psychic damage.The froggoth can only use this action against a target that is charmed by Psychic Miasma.</text>
      <attack>Shock|3|2d4</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Froggoths, while larger than a typical frog, share a similar level of intelligence and instinct. Assumed to be from the Far Realm, these amphibians have become folded around themselves, creating a circlet of eyes and legs that allow it to see all.

Luckily, froggoths are timid and non-malicious. They have a tendency to flee should they sense anything they consider to be predatory or threatening. These creatures have an innate psychic aura that disorients predators and adventurers alike, which only grows larger and more powerful the more froggoths are in the area. At distance this aura can cause hallucinations shifting the scenery or creating a brand new setting. The closer you get, the stronger the aura, so near a froggoth all but the most strong willed will likely end up incapacitated. While not any more aggressive than a typical frog, froggoths have still become a nuisance to travelers who wander a bit too close.

During mating season, a spawning frenzy can occur, drawing froggoths together in groups, causing a swarm effect. Large groups together are significantly more dangerous, as their aura of effect compounds, and worse, they become much more territorial. A plague of froggoths can quickly compromise the safety of nearby towns, and pose a threat to even highly experienced adventurers.

Source:	Shmeckerel - Froggoths (Homebrew)</description>
    <environment>Any</environment>
  </monster>
  <!-- Froggoth -->
  <monster>
    <name>Swarm of Froggoth</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>swarm of small aberrations</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>97 (15d10+15)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Perception +8</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages>—</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>psychic</immune>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>truesight 45 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The swarm of froggoth can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Standing Leap</name>
      <text>The swarm of froggoth's long jump is up to 10 ft. and its high jump is up to 5 ft., with or without a running start.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Psychic Miasma</name>
      <text>All creatures within 20 feet of the swarm of froggoth that are not a froggoth must succeed a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature becomes charmed. While charmed by this effect, the creature is incapacitated and has a speed of 0.

The spell ends for an affected creature if it takes any damage or if someone else uses an action to shake the creature out of its stupor.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Hallucinatory Aura</name>
      <text>Any creature within 120 feet of the swarm of froggoth that is not a froggoth must make a DC 17 Wisdom save. On a failed save the creature views the terrain as shifting and swirling. The area becomes difficult terrain and it is impossible to determine the location of environmental hazards. The swarm of froggoth is also invisible to the creature.

On a successful saving throw, the creature is immune to the swarm of froggoth's aura for 1 minute.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Swarm</name>
      <text>The swarm can occupy another creature's space and vice versa, and the swarm can move through any opening large enough for a froggoth. The swarm can't regain hit points or gain temporary hit points. The effective range of the aura is halved when the swarm's HP is reduced below half.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Psychic Shock</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +8 to hit, range 20 ft., one target. Hit: 27 (6d8) psychic damage. (3d8 psychic damage if the swarm is below half HP). The swarm of froggoth can only use this action against a target that is charmed by Psychic Miasma.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Shock|8|6d8</attack>
      <attack>Half Swarm|8|3d8</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Froggoths, while larger than a typical frog, share a similar level of intelligence and instinct. Assumed to be from the Far Realm, these amphibians have become folded around themselves, creating a circlet of eyes and legs that allow it to see all.

Luckily, froggoths are timid and non-malicious. They have a tendency to flee should they sense anything they consider to be predatory or threatening. These creatures have an innate psychic aura that disorients predators and adventurers alike, which only grows larger and more powerful the more froggoths are in the area. At distance this aura can cause hallucinations shifting the scenery or creating a brand new setting. The closer you get, the stronger the aura, so near a froggoth all but the most strong willed will likely end up incapacitated. While not any more aggressive than a typical frog, froggoths have still become a nuisance to travelers who wander a bit too close.

During mating season, a spawning frenzy can occur, drawing froggoths together in groups, causing a swarm effect. Large groups together are significantly more dangerous, as their aura of effect compounds, and worse, they become much more territorial. A plague of froggoths can quickly compromise the safety of nearby towns, and pose a threat to even highly experienced adventurers.

Source:	Shmeckerel - Froggoths (Homebrew)</description>
    <environment>Any</environment>
  </monster>
  <!-- Froggoth, Swarm -->
  <monster>
    <name>Plague of Froggoth</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>swarm of small aberrations</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14</ac>
    <hp>324 (24d20+72)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Perception +13</skill>
    <passive>23</passive>
    <languages>—</languages>
    <cr>14</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>psychic</immune>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>truesight 90 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The plague of froggoth can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Standing Leap</name>
      <text>The plague of froggoth's long jump is up to 10 ft. and its high jump is up to 5 ft., with or without a running start.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Psychic Miasma</name>
      <text>All creatures within 30 feet of the plague of froggoth that are not a froggoth must succeed a DC 21 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature becomes charmed. While charmed by this effect, the creature is incapacitated and has a speed of 0.

The spell ends for an affected creature if it takes any damage or if someone else uses an action to shake the creature out of its stupor.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Hallucinatory Aura</name>
      <text>Any creature within 500 feet of the plague of froggoth that is not a froggoth must make a DC 21 Wisdom save. On a failed save the creature views the terrain as shifting and swirling. The area becomes difficult terrain and it is impossible to determine the location of environmental hazards. The plague of froggoth is also invisible to the creature.

On a successful saving throw, the creature is immune to the plague of froggoth's aura for 1 minute.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Swarm</name>
      <text>The plague can occupy another creature's space and vice versa, and the plague can move through any opening large enough for a froggoth. The plague can't regain hit points or gain temporary hit points. The effective range of the aura is halved when the plague's HP is reduced below half.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Psychic Shock</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +16 to hit, range 80 ft., one target. Hit: 8d12 psychic damage (4d12 psychic damage if the plague is below half HP). The plague of froggoth can only use this action against a target that is charmed by Psychic Miasma.</text>
      <attack>Shock|16|8d12</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Froggoths, while larger than a typical frog, share a similar level of intelligence and instinct. Assumed to be from the Far Realm, these amphibians have become folded around themselves, creating a circlet of eyes and legs that allow it to see all.

Luckily, froggoths are timid and non-malicious. They have a tendency to flee should they sense anything they consider to be predatory or threatening. These creatures have an innate psychic aura that disorients predators and adventurers alike, which only grows larger and more powerful the more froggoths are in the area. At distance this aura can cause hallucinations shifting the scenery or creating a brand new setting. The closer you get, the stronger the aura, so near a froggoth all but the most strong willed will likely end up incapacitated. While not any more aggressive than a typical frog, froggoths have still become a nuisance to travelers who wander a bit too close.

During mating season, a spawning frenzy can occur, drawing froggoths together in groups, causing a swarm effect. Large groups together are significantly more dangerous, as their aura of effect compounds, and worse, they become much more territorial. A plague of froggoths can quickly compromise the safety of nearby towns, and pose a threat to even highly experienced adventurers.

Source:	Shmeckerel - Froggoths (Homebrew)</description>
    <environment>Any</environment>
  </monster>
  <!-- Froggoth, Plague -->
</compendium>
