<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <background>
    <name>Astral Drifter</name>
    <proficiency>Insight, Religion</proficiency>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>For longer than you can remember, you have traversed the Astral Sea. There, you experienced firsthand the wonders of the Silver Void: you stopped aging and no longer felt hunger or thirst. Driven by wanderlust, you drifted from one part of the Astral Sea to another, like a mote of dust on the wind. You have lost count of the decades that have passed since you arrived here.
	In your travels, you have camped on the petrified hulks of dead gods and narrowly escaped the psychic winds that sweep across the Astral Sea while also avoiding prolonged contact with the plane's most dangerous denizens.

	• Skill Proficiencies: Insight, Religion
	• Languages: Two of your choice (Celestial or Gith recommended)
	• Equipment: A set of traveler's clothes, a diary, an ink pen, a bottle of ink, and a pouch containing 10 gp

Source:	Spelljammer: Adventures in Space - Astral Adventurer's Guide p. 7</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Longevity</name>
      <text>You are 20d6 years older than you look, because you have spent that much time in the Astral Sea without aging.</text>
      <roll description="Years">20d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Divine Contact</name>
      <text>You gain the Magic Initiate feat from the Player's Handbook and must choose cleric for the feat.
	In the Astral Sea, you crossed paths with a wandering deity. The encounter was brief and nonviolent, yet it made a lasting impression on you. This deity saw fit to share one secret or obscure bit of cosmic lore with you. Work with your DM to determine the details of this knowledge and its impact on the campaign.
	Roll on the Divine Contact table to determine which deity you encountered, or work with your DM to identify a more suitable choice.

Divine Contact:
d10 | Wandering Deity
1 | Corellon, god of art and magic (chaotic good)
2 | Tymora, god of good fortune (chaotic good)
3 | Fharlanghn, god of horizons and travel (neutral good)
4 | Istus, god of fate and destiny (neutral)
5 | Nuada, god of war and warriors (neutral)
6 | Zivilyn, god of wisdom (neutral)
7 | Arawn, god of life and death (neutral evil)
8 | Hecate, god of magic and moons (chaotic evil)
9 | Celestian, god of stars and wanderers (neutral)
10 | Ptah, god of knowledge and secrets (lawful neutral)</text>
      <roll description="Wandering Deity">1d10</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
  <background>
    <name>Wildspacer</name>
    <proficiency>Athletics, Survival</proficiency>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>You were raised in the void of Wildspace—home to asteroid miners, moon farmers, and other hardy folk. Perhaps you grew up in a far-flung settlement such as the Rock of Bral, or you spent your early years on the crew of a spelljamming ship, performing helpful chores such as swabbing the deck, loading and offloading cargo, and scraping barnacles off the hull.
	Whatever your history, life in Wildspace has toughened you so well that you are as brave as a miniature giant space hamster when it comes to facing the terrors and other challenges of the airless night.

	• Skill Proficiencies: Athletics, Survival
	• Tool Proficiencies: Navigator's tools, vehicles (space)
	• Equipment: A belaying pin (club), a set of traveler's clothes, a grappling hook, 50 feet of hempen rope, and a pouch containing 10 gp

Source:	Spelljammer: Adventures in Space - Astral Adventurer's Guide p. 8</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Close Encounter</name>
      <text>You had a harrowing encounter with one of Wildspace's many terrors. You escaped with your life, but the encounter left you with a scar or two, or perhaps a recurring nightmare. Roll on the Close Encounter table to determine which creature nearly got the best of you. Creatures marked with an asterisk appear in Boo's Astral Menagerie; the others are described in the Monster Manual.

d10 | Creature
1 | Beholder
2 | Cosmic horror*
3 | Feyr*
4 | Lunar dragon*
5 | Mind flayer
6 | Neh-thalggu*
7 | Neogi*
8 | Space clown*
9 | Vampirate*
10 | Void scavver*</text>
      <roll description="Creature">1d10</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Wildspace Adaptation</name>
      <text>You gain the Tough feat from the Player's Handbook. In addition, you learned how to adapt to zero gravity. Being weightless doesn't give you disadvantage on any of your melee attack rolls (see "Weightlessness" in chapter 2).</text>
    </trait>
  </background>
</compendium>
