<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <item>
    <name>Basic Fishing Equipment</name>
    <type>G</type>
    <value>0.1</value>
    <text>Basic Fishing Equipment includes a pole, a line, a hook, and either a lure or some bait.
	Fishing is a popular pastime in Wildspace and the Astral Sea, though this activity isn't possible aboard a ship that is moving faster than its flying speed. At the end of each hour spent fishing, a character can make a DC 15 Wisdom (Survival) check. A failed check indicates no fish is caught during that hour. On a successful check, roll a d10 and consult the Fishing table to determine the catch.

Fishing:
d10 | Catch
1-2 | Tiny, inedible fish (a creature that consumes it is poisoned for 1 hour)
3-5 | Tiny, edible fish (feeds one person)
6-8 | Small, edible fish (feeds up to four people)
9 | Hostile space eel (see Boo's Astral Menagerie; feeds up to twelve people)
10 | Hostile gray scavver (see Boo's Astral Menagerie; feeds up to twenty people), some other creature of the DM's choosing, or an Tiny object of the DM's choosing

Source:	Spelljammer: Adventures in Space - Astral Adventurer's Guide p. 21</text>
    <roll description="Catch">1d10</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Keg of Alchemist's Fire</name>
    <type>G</type>
    <text>A keg of alchemist's fire lobbed at a creature or an object deals 21 (6d6) fire damage on a hit. Further, the target is set ablaze and takes the damage again every round (in the case of a creature, at the start of each of its turns) until the fire is put out. A creature within reach of the blaze can take an action to smother the flames using a blanket or carpet, reducing the fire damage by 2d6. Three such actions are needed to fully put out the fire.

Source:	Spelljammer: Adventures in Space - Light of Xaryxis p. 35</text>
    <roll description="Fire Damage">6d6</roll>
    <roll description="Damage Reduction">2d6</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Fish Suit</name>
    <detail>very rare</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This bulky suit, which fully encases your head and body, takes 1 minute to don or doff. While worn, it enables you to breathe in an airless environment and renders you immune to the harmful effects of any gas that surrounds you. The suit also grants you a swimming speed equal to your walking speed while underwater, or a flying speed equal to your walking speed in an environment with no gravity.

Source:	Spelljammer: Adventures in Space - Astral Adventurer's Guide p. 22</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Spelljamming Helm</name>
    <detail>rare (requires attunement by a spellcaster)</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>The function of this ornate chair is to propel and maneuver a ship on which it has been installed through space and air. It can also propel and maneuver a ship on water or underwater, provided the ship is built for such travel. The ship in question must weigh 1 ton or more.
	The sensation of being attuned to a spelljamming helm is akin to the pins-and-needles effect one experiences after one's arm or leg falls asleep, but not as painful.
	While attuned to a spelljamming helm and sitting in it, you gain the following abilities for as long as you maintain concentration (as if concentrating on a spell):

	• You can use the spelljamming helm to move the ship through space, air, or water up to the ship's speed. If the ship is in space and no other objects weighing 1 ton or more are within 1 mile of it, you can use the spelljamming helm to move the vessel fast enough to travel 100 million miles in 24 hours.

	• You can steer the vessel, albeit in a somewhat clumsy fashion, in much the way that a rudder or oars can be used to maneuver a seafaring ship.

	• At any time, you can see and hear what's happening on and around the vessel as though you were standing in a location of your choice aboard it.

Transfer Attunement: You can use an action to touch a willing spellcaster. That creature attunes to the spelljamming helm immediately, and your attunement to it ends.

Source:	Spelljammer: Adventures in Space - Astral Adventurer's Guide p. 23</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Talarith</name>
    <detail>legendary (requires attunement by a reigar who created it)</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>The reigar who creates this piece of jewelry chooses its form: bracelet, brooch, diadem, or necklace. While the reigar wears the talarith, any weapon wielded by the reigar deals an extra 1d6 force damage when it hits.
	As an action, a reigar can use its talarith to summon a golem that looks just like the reigar. The golem obeys the reigar's commands and uses the reigar's statistics, except it is a Construct that doesn't have a talarith of its own. The golem vanishes after 1 hour, or when it is reduced to 0 hit points. After summoning a golem, the reigar must finish a short or long rest before this property can be used again.

Source:	Spelljammer: Adventures in Space - Boo's Astral Menagerie p. 47</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Wildspace Orrery</name>
    <detail>uncommon</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>Inside a Wildspace system, this portable arcane device automatically tracks the positions and movements of all suns, planets, moons, and comets within that system, projecting a display of all these bodies in the space above its current location. In that display, a white, pulsating pinprick of light marks the orrery's location.

Source:	Spelljammer: Adventures in Space - Astral Adventurer's Guide p. 23</text>
  </item>
</compendium>
