<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <background>
    <name>Monster (HB)</name>
    <proficiency>Intimidation, Survival</proficiency>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>You are a dragon who was permanently polymorphed, a vampire who was raised from the dead, a cured lycanthrope, or some other monster who has had their form changed into a living humanoid. Years of your life were spent as a being that haunts the nightmares of many. What were you? What terrible deeds did you commit? What magic transformed you into your new form?
	When your physical form changed, so did your mind. You appreciate and perhaps even embrace the culture, laws, and customs of your new form, but not without growing pains. Learning to live as something else is a struggle, even if your mind is committed to the task. Memories, enemies, and lost friends from your old life haunt you. As a person who walks between two worlds, the restless life of adventure might be the only that feels comfortable for it allows you to unleash your past savagery while retaining your new heart.

	• Skill Proficiencies: Intimidation, Survival
	• Languages: Choose any two languages. (If applicable, at least one should be a language your monster form spoke.)
	• Equipment: A set of common clothes, 10 feet of chain that was once used to bind you, a sketch of what you looked like as a monster, and a belt pouch containing 5 gp

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Monster Type</name>
      <text>There are many kinds of monsters and the true polymorph spell makes it possible for you to have been any of them before your transformation. You might have been a mighty giant, savage gnoll, or mindless ooze. Choose the type of monster you were in your previous life, or roll on the table below.

Monster Types:
d12 | Monster Type
1 | Aberration
2 | Construct
3 | Dragon
4 | Elemental
5 | Fey
6 | Fiend
7 | Giant
8 | Humanoid
9 | Monstrosity
10 | Ooze
11 | Plant
12 | Undead</text>
      <roll description="Monster Type">1d12</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: A Little Off</name>
      <text>You have a reputation for being a little odd, almost as if you're uncomfortable in your own skin and around people. Whenever you act in a way that is strange or taboo, but not intentionally offensive, dangerous, or against the law, people tend to ignore you. This lets you get away with strange behavior like showing up at parties you weren't invited to, pushing through a crowd to shake a noble's hand, eating food off of someone else's plate, or taking a nap in a public place. Most people brush you off as weird, but harmless.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
      <text>As a person who was once something else, you are never truly at peace. You're not used to your new form or home and your old lair doesn't suit the new you. Former monsters are restless and many use their old bloodlust to defend those they would have once devoured from threats that are all too familiar. Even those who accept their new place know deep inside them is violence waiting for release.

d8 | Personality Trait
1 | I only use my hands and not utensils when I eat.
2 | I growl when I am threatened and purr when I am content.
3 | When someone asks me about my past, I change the subject.
4 | I prefer all my meat rare (or raw).
5 | Darkness and shadows are a comfort to me.
6 | I never back down from a fight.
7 | I embrace every comfort civilization has to offer with gusto.
8 | I prefer the company of animals to people.

d6 | Ideal
1 | Redemption. I must protect others from that which I used to be. (Good)
2 | Power. I am still a monster at heart and will claw my way to greatness. (Evil)
3 | Friendship. I strive to be the person my friends think I am. (Neutral)
4 | Freedom. The only way to discover where I belong is to be myself no matter the circumstance. (Chaotic)
5 | Order. I keep the monster inside by following a strict routine of normalcy. (Lawful)
6 | Aspiration. The world will know me for who I am now, not what I was. (Any)

d6 | Bond
1 | I still think about my old lair and go there in my mind whenever I need to calm down.
2 | There is one victim of my monstrosity that I cannot forget.
3 | When I was a monster, I had a special piece of treasure stolen from my hoard that I wish to recover.
4 | An adventurer I wronged as a monster hunts me.
5 | As a monster I had a mentor of the same species who does not know my current fate.
6 | As a monster I took trophies from my victims, which I still have.

d6 | Flaw
1 | Given the chance I escalate every argument to violence.
2 | Drinking brings out my inner monster.
3 | Forgiveness is weakness - all wrongs, even mistakes, must be punished.
4 | I beg others to perform social interactions on my behalf.
5 | I enjoy being contrary just to drive others mad.
6 | If I see something delicious, I must eat it.</text>
      <roll description="Personality Trait">1d8</roll>
      <roll description="Ideal">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Bond">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Flaw">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
  <background>
    <name>Feytouched (HB)</name>
    <proficiency/>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>You were kidnapped as a young child by the Fey and spirited away to the Feywild. Within the confines of this mysterious magical realm, those taken in such a manner usually do not survive long especially when Hags or other dark Fey creatures are involved. However, some do manage to avoid such a fate and are raised as slaves, servants, playthings, or companions, etc.
	You were more fortunate than most of your ilk surviving long enough to demonstrate a natural connection to the Feywild and reveal yourself to be Feytouched, i.e. a kindred spirit. Earning your freedom, you were then permitted to come and go from the Feywild as you please.

	• Skill Proficiencies: Choose Two Skills of Nature, Animal Handling, Insight, Medicine, Perception, Deception, Performance, Persuasion
	• Tool Proficiencies: Choose One Tool of Alchemist's Supplies, Carpenter's Tools, Cobbler's Tools, Cook's Utensils, Jeweler's Tools, Painter's Supplies, Tinker's Tools, Weaver's Tools, Woodcarver's Tools, Herbalism Kit, Flute, Lyre, Pan Flute, Lute, Viol
	• Languages: Sylvan
	• Equipment: A set of traveler's clothes, a musical instrument, a potion of healing, and a small pouch containing 10 gold pieces

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Kindred Spirit</name>
      <text>Even though you may not be of actual Fey blood or racial stock, all Fey you encounter will recognize you as Feytouched and treat you as one of their own. You know the customs and culture of Fey society and find acceptance in their communities.
	Feytouched that leave the Feywild will automatically succeed on any saving throws needed to retain their memories of their stay in the Feywild but such memories can be jumbled or a little hazy and contribute to their overall eccentric behaviors.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
      <text>Feytouched tend towards being rather free-spirited, carefree, mischievous, and cunning. Growing up in the Feywild as they have some may act a tad off and exhibit eccentric or erratic behaviors while others may be completely mad as a hatter.

d8 | Personality Trait
1 | I'm oblivious to etiquette and social expectations.
2 | I eat like a pig and have bad manners.
3 | I hide scraps of food and trinkets away in my pockets.
4 | I feel tremendous empathy for all who suffer.
5 | I live for the thrill of discovery.
6 | I tell anyone and everyone about the things that torment me.
7 | I refuse to sit still, I will never reveal why.
8 | I am always the outsider looking in.

d8 | Ideal
1 | Greater Good. My gifts are meant to be shared with all, not used for my own benefit.
2 | I try to help those in need, no matter what the personal cost.
3 | Inquisitive. Everything is new, but I have a thirst to learn.
4 | I'll stop the spirits that haunt me or die trying.
5 | The voices speak to me and usually they forget to tell me about the rules.
6 | I strive to find truth, no matter how crazy it seems.
7 | I seek to unlock the very secrets of reality.
8 | Beauty. We do our work to make the world a more beautiful place.

d8 | Bond
1 | I would sacrifice my life and my soul to protect the innocent.
2 | No one else should have to endure the hardships I've been through.
3 | There's evil in me, I can feel it. It must never be set free.
4 | It is difficult to get anyone to take me seriously.
5 | I always knew I was meant for something greater. This is it!
6 | I protect those who cannot protect themselves.
7 | I suffer awful visions of a coming disaster and will do anything to prevent it.
8 | Those who fight beside me are those worth dying for.

d8 | Flaw
1 | I talk to spirits that no one else can see.
2 | I say whatever comes to my mind.
3 | I have certain rituals that I must follow every day. I can never break them.
4 | I have an addiction, or several.
5 | I often forget what happened in the past, and am always mixing my history up.
6 | When nervous tends to repeat the same phrases over and over again.
7 | I have no concept of the value of money and place little importance on it.
8 | I reject conventional society norms and advocate simple, idealistic values others consider odd.</text>
      <roll description="Personality Trait">1d8</roll>
      <roll description="Ideal">1d8</roll>
      <roll description="Bond">1d8</roll>
      <roll description="Flaw">1d8</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
  <background>
    <name>Farmer (HB)</name>
    <proficiency>Animal Handling, Nature</proficiency>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>You were what most common folk are - a farmer. You worked on a lord's estate, their land, or you worked for a company and you produced resources from the land in return for food, shelter, clothing, protection, and other benefits. Farmers focus on raising living things and harvesting various useful goods - mostly food - from the land. Farmers make up the vast majority of the peasantry, alongside other raw resource producers, such as miners and fishermen. Farmers are a hearty, enduring folk, they work long hours under the sun often doing dirty and exhausting or even disgusting work.
	How did you become a farmer, and for how long were you one? What did you do on your farm? Were you the landlord of the farm, or were you just a farmhand? And what caused you to leave that life behind? Was your home destroyed by war? Were you cast out for some crime? Did you flee taxes you could not pay? Were you called to join the Lord's army? Was your home stolen by an unscrupulous rival? How did you learn your current profession?

	• Skill Proficiencies: Animal handling and Nature
	• Tool Proficiencies: Land Vehicles and Farm Implements
	• Languages: You only speak Common
	• Equipment: A farm implement (such as a pitchfork or shovel), a set of work clothes or common clothes, a wide brimmed hat, a sack containing 5 gp worth of trade goods, and a belt pouch containing 5 gp or 1d4 + 2 gp

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Farm</name>
      <text>Not every farm is alike; there are a vast range of goods produced by farmers of different sorts, and nearly all farms focus on just one product or a limited group of products.

d6 | Farm
1 | Rancher. You raised animals for slaughter most likely for food, but also for leather, furs, and other useful materials.
2 | Grazier. You harvested goods produced by animals such as milk, eggs, feathers, or wool.
3 | Stockman. You bred animals to sell for work or as pets such as guard dogs, racing horses, and griffons.
4 | Peasant. You harvested edible or useful plants such as wheat, corn crops, or apples at an orchard.
5 | Forester. You grew trees for ornament or construction such as trees grown for bow staves, boat masts, or buildings.
6 | Silk. You raised silk worms or another exotic animal, and harvested their silk.</text>
      <roll description="Farm">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Of The land</name>
      <text>You lack the formal education of the higher classes, but for how little you may know there is a great deal that you understand. You have a practical, working knowledge of astrology and meteorology, and can easily track the time and date as well as predict the weather within a few hours, or days if you're lucky. You understand the "secrets of life"; the needs of life (water, light, air, salt, etc.), the patterns of physical inheritance, and the connections between different plants and animals.
	At the DM's discretion, this can be represented by allowing a farmer to cast commune with nature once per long rest, except that the range is limited to environments common to you within 10 feet and you can only choose one of the first two choices.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Variant Feature: Of The People</name>
      <text>For better or for worse, you are just very normal. Among commoners and on the road, most people just don't notice you, and security checks at city gates or on the road are often brisk and half-hearted. People tend to trust that you're just another face in the crowd. However, whenever you are some place commoners should not be, or normally are not seen, you stand out like a sore thumb and draw a good deal of attention, one way or another. You are unlikely to be preceded by your reputation, if you even have one, and if you do, nobody expects you to be them.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Variant Farmer: Fieldhand</name>
      <text>From working away endlessly in the fields all day, you've become a pretty sturdy individual who can endure quite a lot. Those that face you know they're in for a long and grueling fight.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Variant Feature: Work Until You Drop</name>
      <text>Now when most think about a Farmer, they don't exactly think of some complete badass going out to slay dragons, rescue consistently imperiled nobility, and save the day. More often than not they're simply seen as peasant; background individuals that aren't much of a threat. However, they can be a lot tougher than expected.
	As a Farmer, you aren't made to deal massive amount of damage right away. However, what you excel at is delivering constant damage and wearing an opponent out over time. You're used to playing the waiting game, and fighting creatures is no different for you. Every encounter with you is an endurance match that others don't often succeed in, as you are made to withstand quite a good deal of damage and frequently hinder your enemies.
	Whether or not you're some Joe Schmo that got roped into traveling with a band of adventurers one way or another, or a commoner who got fed up with the troubles you and your fellow peasants face and decided to solve them yourself: you are a formidable foe and constant nuisance to enemies you face, while being a humble teammate to work alongside of.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
      <text>When creating a Farmer, it is important to remember that is it not a class typically seen as the brave heroes out to save the world. You are usually the typical peasant or commoner that stays to the background while more flamboyant members of society move about the world and make an impact in it.
	As such, some important questions to ask would be: Why is your Farmer adventuring? Did they accidentally get roped into traveling with other adventurers and it's too hard to get out of it now? Did you want a life outside of working in the field all day? Or were you fed up with the everyday troubles your fellow peasants faced and decided to go out on your own to solve them?
	You can further expand on this depending on the campaign's background: Are there many troubles that you commoners face? Is the ruling body of where you live corrupt? Did you start out as a commoner? Or did you escape some other life and decide to settle down, only to somehow be pulled into drama once more?

d8 | Personality Trait
1 | I'm always early to bed and early to rise.
2 | I keep my gear and supplies in careful check.
3 | I speak with a distinctive drawl or accent common to my class.
4 | I always save up as much as I can, spending and consuming only what I must.
5 | When work needs doing, I do the work.
6 | I keep constant track of the sun, moon, stars, seasons, and weather.
7 | I like to sleep in the sun when I can.
8 | I'm always chewing on a sprig of grass, a toothpick, tobacco, seeds, or preserved meat.

d6 | Ideal
1 | Fill the Need. There are a lot of hungry mouths in the world, with enough hands the world can feed them all. (Good)
2 | It's a Living. I do what I'm good at because what I'm good at is good for me. (Neutral)
3 | Brutal Practicality. Bury a fish or bury a man, just get the job done. (Evil)
4 | Hard Work. A labor of love is a purpose and meaning. (Lawful)
5 | A Simple Way of Life. If it ain't broke, don't fix it! (Neutral)
6 | Amusement. Playing a hand in the growth and development of things delights me. (Chaotic)

d6 | Bond
1 | I want to find that special someone and raise a home full of children.
2 | I'll never forget the family farm I grew up on.
3 | Some day, I'll be the lord of my own land.
4 | I want to grow or raise the biggest or best example of my profession to prove I am the best!
5 | My son was sent to war and never returned. I must find him!
6 | I am out to start a homestead of my own in an unexplored fringe territory.

d6 | Flaw
1 | I can be lazy and sleepy, sneaking off to take naps when work can wait.
2 | I am absurdly isolated, innocent, or pious.
3 | I believe in and obey my nation's nobility blindly.
4 | I abandoned my home to avoid taxation, conscription, or court and cannot return.
5 | I am not used to being wealthy and tend to overindulge.
6 | I show off to attractive people too much.</text>
      <roll description="Personality Trait">1d8</roll>
      <roll description="Ideal">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Bond">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Flaw">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
  <background>
    <name>Chef (HB)</name>
    <proficiency/>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>You are someone who knows the value of a properly seasoned stew and can tell the difference between spices by sight, taste, scent, and even their texture. From the soldiers marching in the fields, to the warm haven of an inn, to the bowls of the largest keeps, to the homes of the common folk you know that food and need of food is what brings together everyone of every nation, religion, race, and creed. Food is your passion, it is your mission, it is your religion.

	• Skill Proficiencies: Choose two of History, Medicine, Nature, Survival
	• Tool Proficiencies: You are proficient with Cook's Utensils
	• Equipment: Cook's Utensils, a cooking pot, a small knife, 2 full waterskins, 10 rations, and a book of your recipes

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Passion for Food</name>
      <text>You can find the choicest and best ingredients in just about any environment. For any roll relating to finding food or ingredients add 2d6 to your roll and for any food you make add 1d4 Hit Points to the creature who consumed the dish.
	In your pursuit of a veteran palate you have tasted foods both fair and foul, and thus have grown resistant to them. You have advantage on any Constitution saving throw involving consumption of materials or liquids including potions and poisons.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
      <text>Many things can influence a person's life long love affair with food. Maybe you were starving and lost and rescued by a traveling chef. Perhaps are inheriting your love from your grandparent who showed you tried and true recipes passed down the generations. You might even have been a beggar that dreamed of dining on the choice cuts of meat in decadent sauces that only the rich were privy to and decided to only dine on the best. Whatever the reason food is your passion!

d8 | Personality Trait
1 | Cooking is like a dance and the kitchen is my dance floor.
2 | My knowledge of flavor combinations can make even the most joyless eater smile.
3 | If I make a mistake or even slightly burn it I through it out. Thankfully I am great enough that I almost never have to.
4 | Once you step into the kitchen you step into my kingdom, and regardless if you are king or serf I will have obedience within it.
5 | Food is meant to make you smile. Food is my passion and my life, so I am always smiling.
6 | If you cause me to make a mistake in my cooking I am liable to try to put you in the pot next.
7 | Do not call me a cook. I am a chef, a gourmet! To say otherwise is to invoke my wrath.
8 | Recipes are meant to be passed down, so any chance I get to teach another to cook I do it with zeal.

d6 | Ideal
1 | Adventurous. The only way to know if something tastes good or bad is to taste it. (Chaotic)
2 | Fame. I will sabotage and undercut other chefs to boost my own status and spread my fame faster. (Evil)
3 | Empathy. I don't care who you are, if you are hungry I will feed you in a heartbeat. (Good)
4 | Showmanship. I will turn the whole cooking process into a show to create smiles before the meal and serve them good food to make them smile after the meal too. (Any)
5 | Respect. The reputation I have created has been no small feat in the making. I believe I am due a certain amount of respect for it. (Any)
6 | Perfection. If I see one small misstep in the cooking process at the hands of a lesser chef or cook I will berate for them. (Evil)

d6 | Bond
1 | I must pass on my recipes before I die.
2 | The person that taught me to cook is always foremost in my mind when preparing food or making new recipes.
3 | I am the last bastion of hope in a bland world. I will bring flavor.
4 | My tools were inherited so every nick, dent, and scratch is a fond memory for me.
5 | I wish to feed the masses. Starvation is an abomination and I will slay it with tasty treats.
6 | I will become the best. I have to.

d6 | Flaw
1 | I have a tendency to taste all my recipes multiple times, sometimes eating the whole thing before it's even done.
2 | I add bacon to EVERY recipe and believe it makes everything better.
3 | I do not trust food or drink not prepared by me, and must check it for poison or worse too much salt.
4 | Sometimes in an effort to make a perfect dish I throw out perfectly fine dishes and end up wasting food.
5 | I cannot hold my wine very well and often do things I regret after drinking it.
6 | I secretly look down on the filthy masses that greedily eat sub par food as if it were the finest of dishes.</text>
      <roll description="Personality Trait">1d8</roll>
      <roll description="Ideal">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Bond">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Flaw">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
  <background>
    <name>Gourmand (HB)</name>
    <ancestry>Chef (HB)</ancestry>
    <proficiency/>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>You are someone who knows the value of a properly seasoned stew and can tell the difference between spices by sight, taste, scent, and even their texture. From the soldiers marching in the fields, to the warm haven of an inn, to the bowls of the largest keeps, to the homes of the common folk you know that food and need of food is what brings together everyone of every nation, religion, race, and creed. Food is your passion, it is your mission, it is your religion.
	You have made it your mission to taste and create only the finest and most expensive foods possible. You refuse to eat the bland slop of the masses and often insist on making your own food at inns. As a result of your passion for gourmet food you have spent a considerable amount of time in the presence of the wealthy elite, nobles, and even royalty and could easily pass muster among them. Some may even have heard of your famous dishes and will insist that you make it for them.

	• Skill Proficiencies: Choose two of History, Medicine, Nature, Survival
	• Tool Proficiencies: You are proficient with Cook's Utensils
	• Equipment: Cook's Utensils, a cooking pot, a small knife, 2 full waterskins, 10 rations, and a book of your recipes

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Chef in Sheep's Clothing</name>
      <text>In situations involving the social, political, and economic elite you are able to gain entry by your reputation and bearing alone, and may even be hired to cook some of your famous dishes. Wealthy people will often go out of their way to try to convince you to cook for them, you have advantage on persuasion rolls against them.
	When dealing with other cooks you have an inspired an almost religious reverence for your techniques and cooking styles. Any persuasion or intimidation roll against cooks have advantage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
      <text>Many things can influence a person's life long love affair with food. Maybe you were starving and lost and rescued by a traveling chef. Perhaps are inheriting your love from your grandparent who showed you tried and true recipes passed down the generations. You might even have been a beggar that dreamed of dining on the choice cuts of meat in decadent sauces that only the rich were privy to and decided to only dine on the best. Whatever the reason food is your passion!

d8 | Personality Trait
1 | Cooking is like a dance and the kitchen is my dance floor.
2 | My knowledge of flavor combinations can make even the most joyless eater smile.
3 | If I make a mistake or even slightly burn it I through it out. Thankfully I am great enough that I almost never have to.
4 | Once you step into the kitchen you step into my kingdom, and regardless if you are king or serf I will have obedience within it.
5 | Food is meant to make you smile. Food is my passion and my life, so I am always smiling.
6 | If you cause me to make a mistake in my cooking I am liable to try to put you in the pot next.
7 | Do not call me a cook. I am a chef, a gourmet! To say otherwise is to invoke my wrath.
8 | Recipes are meant to be passed down, so any chance I get to teach another to cook I do it with zeal.

d6 | Ideal
1 | Adventurous. The only way to know if something tastes good or bad is to taste it. (Chaotic)
2 | Fame. I will sabotage and undercut other chefs to boost my own status and spread my fame faster. (Evil)
3 | Empathy. I don't care who you are, if you are hungry I will feed you in a heartbeat. (Good)
4 | Showmanship. I will turn the whole cooking process into a show to create smiles before the meal and serve them good food to make them smile after the meal too. (Any)
5 | Respect. The reputation I have created has been no small feat in the making. I believe I am due a certain amount of respect for it. (Any)
6 | Perfection. If I see one small misstep in the cooking process at the hands of a lesser chef or cook I will berate for them. (Evil)

d6 | Bond
1 | I must pass on my recipes before I die.
2 | The person that taught me to cook is always foremost in my mind when preparing food or making new recipes.
3 | I am the last bastion of hope in a bland world. I will bring flavor.
4 | My tools were inherited so every nick, dent, and scratch is a fond memory for me.
5 | I wish to feed the masses. Starvation is an abomination and I will slay it with tasty treats.
6 | I will become the best. I have to.

d6 | Flaw
1 | I have a tendency to taste all my recipes multiple times, sometimes eating the whole thing before it's even done.
2 | I add bacon to EVERY recipe and believe it makes everything better.
3 | I do not trust food or drink not prepared by me, and must check it for poison or worse too much salt.
4 | Sometimes in an effort to make a perfect dish I throw out perfectly fine dishes and end up wasting food.
5 | I cannot hold my wine very well and often do things I regret after drinking it.
6 | I secretly look down on the filthy masses that greedily eat sub par food as if it were the finest of dishes.</text>
      <roll description="Personality Trait">1d8</roll>
      <roll description="Ideal">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Bond">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Flaw">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
  <background>
    <name>Courtesan (HB)</name>
    <proficiency>Persuasion, Sleight of Hand</proficiency>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Nobles, politicians, criminals, the common man; hell, maybe even an orc or two. At some point in your life, you have been with all manner of society's finest and worst through your profession. Your profession, whether through freedom of choice, or a cruel twist of unfortunate events, is one that utilizes a very specific set of skills: the art of seduction. Though your circumstances may be unfortunate, you use them to your advantage. Whether it is using your body to persuade a client to change their mind on an issue, using your unique skill set to distract clients while you steal from right under their noses, or even playing the part of a cheap assassin.
	When making a character with this background ask yourself these question: What led your character to these circumstances? Was it a twisted and unfortunate fate? Or was it a vocation of choice? How much do you charge for your services? Are you self employed, or do you work under a pimp? Where do you work? Where is your place of work? These are the questions you must consider and consider wisely, for they will shape your character, in the beginning of their journey at least.

	• Skill Proficiencies: Persuasion, Sleight of Hand
	• Tool Proficiencies: Disguise kit
	• Languages: One standard language of your choice
	• Equipment: A set of fine clothes, a purse containing 5 gp, a disguise kit, and a small gilded mirror

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Seducer's Wiles</name>
      <text>Your experiences with every creature have taught you how to use your tempting looks and inviting attitude to bring anyone of either gender in your embrace. You can call upon a creature  that can see and hear you, and gain its attention without it suspecting something (other than what you offer).</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>History of Service</name>
      <text>d4 | History of Service
1 | I was under the wing of royalty, always loyal to their whims.
2 | I have broken so many hearts, either for gold or fun.
3 | I used to offer my services in a brothel.
4 | My services always opened even the best locked doors.</text>
      <roll description="History">1d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Variant Feature: Jaded</name>
      <text>During your work, you've come across some truly twisted stuff, both people's actions and the people themselves. Some of which you experienced much more closely than you'd probably have preferred. As such, precious little truly shocks you anymore. You tend to remain relatively calm and rational through events and scenes that leave others sick to their stomach.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
      <text>When creating a Courtesan, think about how they feel about their situation. Do they enjoy their work? Do they hate it? Is there a reason they're doing it? This can be useful in deciding how your Courtesan will act.

d8 | Personality Trait
1 | I am highly flamboyant; I like to exaggerate my movements and mannerisms.
2 | My speech is like a switch; I speak either very warmly or very coldly to anyone.
3 | I am unafraid to get up-close and "personal" with some people or situations.
4 | I keep silent about any shortcomings I may be experiencing. I can't stand being pitied.
5 | I am extremely flirtatious, even with friends.
6 | I prefer to leave things finished, rather then let bygones be bygones.
7 | I love being the center of attention, but I don't envy those who take that from me.
8 | I am quite hesitant to name my profession when asked about it.

d6 | Ideal
1 | Everyone uses others, why should I act any different? (Evil)
2 | I sympathize with those who work hard but gain little in their endeavors. (Good)
3 | I secretly love the work I do, despite what any naysayers may call me. (Any)
4 | When I'm doing you a service, I am yours. If I'm not, I want nothing to do with you. (Chaotic)
5 | My favorite clients are the ones who are kind and generous to others. (Lawful)
6 | My body and soul are my own, no matter what anyone else may say about me. (Neutral)

d6 | Bond
1 | I am highly skeptical when someone offers me something without asking for anything in return.
2 | I don't concern myself with the turmoil spawned from other's problems.
3 | There is someone I'm waiting for so we can live together.
4 | I know a secret about one of my clients that could cost me my life if revealed.
5 | My clients are all I have.
6 | I have a child, and I would do anything for them.

d6 | Flaw
1 | Despite my own ability to read people, I myself am very easily read by others.
2 | If someone has some kind of debt over me, I feel obligated to fulfill said debt no matter what.
3 | I sometimes expect or wish for others would take care of my problems.
4 | Depending on the pay, I will do anything for a client.
5 | I use any means I have at my disposal to complete a goal.
6 | I love presents or gifts, and cannot refuse one, even if I know doing so is a bad idea.</text>
      <roll description="Personality Trait">1d8</roll>
      <roll description="Ideal">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Bond">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Flaw">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
  <background>
    <name>Cultist (HB)</name>
    <ancestry>Acolyte</ancestry>
    <proficiency/>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>You are, or once were, a member of a cult — a religious splinter sect or a secret society of occult study. You might still be active within the cult, receiving orders from its secret masters. Or perhaps you've rejected its authority, and now the cult wants to bring you back into the fold... or silence you forever. In either case, you live at the crossroads of criminality and faith or arcane study.
	Work with your DM to determine the nature of the cult's devotion. It might be a god, celestial, demon, devil, dragon, fey, or genie. It might be a cabal dedicated to arcane study, with an archmage or lich at its head. A cult without strictly enforced rules is soon stamped out by the forces of orthodoxy, however; no matter what your cult's nature, their dictates present challenges in the daily lives of adherents.

	• Skill Proficiencies: Choose two of Arcana, Deception, Intimidation and Religion
	• Languages: Two of your choice
	• Equipment: A holy symbol or tattoo signifying membership in the cult, a book of heretical or blasphemous truths, 5 sticks of incense, vestments or robes of occult significance, sacrificial dagger, a set of common clothes, and a belt pouch containing 15 gp

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Cult Network</name>
      <text>You know the locations of your cult's safehouses, shrines, and sanctums in many settlements and wilderness areas. In such a network, you can find at least one loyal member of the cult, who can provide food and a safe place to rest for you and up to six people that you vouch for. Large cities always have a safehouse, while smaller settlements are 50% likely to have one. Remote wilderness areas have one safehouse in any 100-square-mile area. If you have left the cult, you can use the safehouse, drawing attention from the cult only 50% of the time.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
      <text>A rejection of socially-accepted belief or behavior, and adherence to strict and potentially isolating set of rules, defines the life of the cultist. Their expectation of persecution shapes their interactions, even with people who do not know about their cult connections. Their belief in their secret, superior understanding can be hard for them to conceal.

d8 | Personality Trait
1 | I try to hide as much of my face as possible, out of habit and fear of recognition.
2 | I believe that I possess esoteric wisdom on a wide variety of topics.
3 | Every event is part of the plan of the Secret Masters.
4 | I carry the holy symbols and texts of a dozen religions, just in case.
5 | My outward cynicism hides a core of hope.
6 | I have foreseen my own death, and have no fear of any other demise.
7 | The cult's rites and taboos take up much of my spare time and energy.
8 | When I meet new people, I look for the potential for new novices.

d6 | Ideal
1 | Freedom. I will get the cult's hooks out of my life, whatever it takes. (Good)
2 | Tradition. My family has an ancient history with the cult, and I will honor it until my dying day. (Lawful)
3 | Revelation. I must undermine the false dogmas that blind everyone around me. (Chaotic)
4 | Power. The cult is my path to something greater, and I will pay any cost. (Evil)
5 | Hierarchy. Some were made to serve, others to lead. (Neutral)
6 | Aspiration. The cult's demands are harsh, but I will rise through the ranks. (Any)

d6 | Bond
1 | A priceless talisman of the cult was stolen, and I will earn great favor by returning it.
2 | The cult's mysteriarch is like a mother to me; I value our relationship more than the cult itself.
3 | The gods I was raised to worship ignored my prayers as my loved ones lay dying, but the cult heard and answered.
4 | I must prevent the people I love from learning about my involvement with the cult.
5 | I want to put my past with the cult behind me and atone for the harm I've done.
6 | A powerful inquisitor knows my face, and my connection to the cult.

d6 | Flaw
1 | I am quick to anger when my beliefs are slighted.
2 | I weasel out of telling the plain truth when a question makes me uncomfortable.
3 | I believe that everyone around me is hiding multiple layers of secrets.
4 | Anyone who looks into my eyes can't doubt that I am stark raving mad..
5 | I have crossed over into death and returned, and it put a deep fear into me.
6 | I keep secrets even from those closest to me.</text>
      <roll description="Personality Trait">1d8</roll>
      <roll description="Ideal">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Bond">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Flaw">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
  <background>
    <name>Cultist (HB)</name>
    <ancestry>Acolyte</ancestry>
    <proficiency/>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>You are a member of a cult, either presently or formerly. You devoted long, strenuous days of your life towards whatever intangible, metaphysical force that guides your faith, but at last, that has changed. Perhaps your deity of choice reached out to you to give you a mission, perhaps you finally hung up the dark robes and ceremonial knife to start a new chapter in your life, whatever the case may be, you've decided to take what you've learned from your life as a worshiper of the ungodly, and embark on a new chapter of your life as an adventurer.
	Talk with your DM to figure out the specifics of your cult of origin, to see if there are any other areas of play that might be influenced by your experience with dark rituals and the arcane.

	• Skill Proficiencies: Choose two of Arcana, Religion, Nature, Medicine, Intimidation
	• Languages: Two of your choice
	• Equipment: A symbol relating to membership in your cult, a book detailing your dark rituals, 5 candlesticks, dark hooded vestments (or others that relate to your cult), a set of common clothes, and a pouch containing 15 gp

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew),
		Player's Handbook (2014) p. 127</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Shadow-Caller's Instinct</name>
      <text>As a cultist, you have a connection to places of worship, and the rituals used to summon extraplanar beings. You have advantage when making an Arcana or Religion check to uncover the origins or purpose of an object relating to Demons, Devils, or Aberrations. Talk to your DM if you wish to swap out one of these creature types for one that more closely resembles your cult's theme.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Variant Feature: Void-Touched Charisma</name>
      <text>As a cultist, you have an innate connection to other followers of your faith, and can command the respect of followers of cults with similar values. You and your adventuring companions can expect to receive free healing and care at a outpost, shrine, or other established presence of your faith.
	You also may have dedicated yourself to a cult at a particular place of worship where you have residence. While at or near your home, you can call upon fellow cultists for assistance, so long as it does not require them to engage in an overly-hazardous task, and you remain in good-standing with your cult.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
      <text>d6 | Personality Trait
1 | I see omens in every event and action. The gods try to speak to us we just need to listen.
2 | Nothing can shake my optimistic attitude.
3 | I quote (or misquote) sacred texts and proverbs in almost every situation.
4 | I am tolerant (or intolerant) of other faiths and respect (or condemn) the worship of other gods.
5 | I've enjoyed fine food, drink, and high society among my temple's elite. Rough living grates on me.
6 | I've spent so long in the temple that I have little practical experience dealing with people in the outside world.

d5 | Ideal
1 | Tradition. The ancient traditions of worship and sacrifice must be preserved and upheld. (Lawful)
2 | Change. We must help bring about the changes the gods are constantly working in the world. (Chaotic)
3 | Power. I hope to one day rise to the top of my faith's religious hierarchy. (Lawful)
4 | Faith. I trust that my deity will guide my actions. I have faith that if I work hard, things will go well. (Lawful)
5 | Aspiration. I seek to prove myself worthy of my god's favor by matching my actions against his or her teachings. (Any)

d6 | Bond
1 | I would die to recover an ancient relic of my faith that was lost long ago.
2 | I will someday get revenge on the corrupt temple hierarchy who branded me a heretic.
3 | I owe my life to the priest who took me in when my parents died.
4 | Everything I do is for the common people.
5 | I will do anything to protect the temple where I served.
6 | I seek to preserve a sacred text that my enemies consider heretical and seek to destroy.

d6 | Flaw
1 | I judge others harshly, and myself even more severely.
2 | I put too much trust in those who wield power within my temple's hierarchy.
3 | My piety sometimes leads me to blindly trust those that profess faith in my god.
4 | I am inflexible in my thinking.
5 | I am suspicious of strangers and expect the worst of them.
6 | Once I pick a goal, I become obsessed with it to the detriment of everything else in my life.</text>
      <roll description="Personality Trait">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Ideal">1d5</roll>
      <roll description="Bond">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Flaw">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
  <background>
    <name>Runaway Noble (HB)</name>
    <ancestry>Noble</ancestry>
    <proficiency/>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>You are familiar with wealth and status. You once carried a noble title, and your family still owns land, collects taxes, and wields significant political influence. Something in your past caused you to run from your family. Be it a banishment, voluntary exile to protect your family, or another reason, you no longer reap the rewards of your family's name. If your family still holds status and your relationship with them is still favorable, perhaps they send you gifts in hopes that you return safely. Alternatively, perhaps you were forced into exile and your family has stripped everything from you, including your name and rank.
	Work with your DM to come up with an appropriate title and determine how much authority that title carries or carried. A noble title doesn't stand on its own—it's connected to an entire family, and whatever title you hold, you will pass it down to your own children. Not only do you need to determine your noble title, but you should also work with the DM to describe your family and their influence on you. Also work out the details of your reason for running away, and the impact that may have on your family, your house, your country, or even the world itself.
	Is your exile one that is barely spoken of and whispered only in rumors? Was your running away the talk of the town for weeks, fueling the gossip in taverns and inns? Was your banishment handled by the sovereign or by the head of your house? When you ran away, what state did you leave your house in? Is your family on the verge of collapse? Or are they even better off without you around?
	What was your position in the family? Are you the heir to the head of the family? Have you already inherited the title? How do you feel about that responsibility? To what lengths will you go to restore your position? How does the head of your family feel about your absence?
	Does your family have a coat of arms? An insignia you might wear on a signet ring? Particular colors you wear all the time? An animal you regard as a symbol of your line or even a spiritual member of the family? If so, do you still wear them or shun your house and blame them for your predicament? How does your family feel about your use of their coat of arms, colors, or insignia? Are their punishments for using your family's name and status without the proper authority?
	These details help establish your family and your title as features of the world of the campaign.

	• Skill Proficiencies: History or Arcana, Persuasion or Intimidation, Athletics or Acrobatics
	• Tool Proficiencies: One type of gaming set, vehicles (land)
	• Languages: One of your choice
	• Equipment: An old set of fine clothes that are worn and barely fit, a signet ring, and a purse containing the only coin you could grab from your house before you ran (25 gp)

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew),
		Player's Handbook (2014) p. 135</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Reason for Running Away</name>
      <text>For whatever reason, you had to leave. You may have angered your family, fallen in with a bad crown, disobeyed your sovereign, or even simply loved the wrong person. In the end, you left.

Reason for Running Away:
d8 | Reason for Running Away
1 | My family was disgraced and lost everything. I am on a quest to redeem their name and help them rise to prominence once more.
2 | Life was miserable for me growing up. As soon as I was able to, I gathered what I could and left to seek a life of adventure.
3 | I had to leave to protect my house. An outside force threatened or blackmailed me to leave or else my house would suffer the consequences.
4 | I fell in with a bad crowd and absconded with a portion of my family's wealth. Returning home could mean imprisonment or death.
5 | I found out a dark secret. Now my conscience won't let me stay. I must decide whether to protect or expose my house.
6 | My family has harsh coming-of-age expectations. I was expected to face a near-impossible task and chose to run away instead. My shame haunts me and my family.
7 | I fell in love with a member of a rival family and was ostracized for it. I hope to one day restore peace between our families with a marriage of our houses.
8 | My sovereign ordered me to dismantle or destroy my house. I became a fugitive to protect them from myself and my vows.</text>
      <roll description="Reason for Running Away">1d8</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Knowledge of Status</name>
      <text>Despite your circumstances, you are of noble birth. While you have been shunned from noble society for now, you still have a detailed knowledge of its inner workings. You know all the best masquerades, balls, and dances, as well as how to act around other nobility. Some common folk may still look up to you, and might even go out of their way to help you. You know all of the local lords and ladies, and for better or worse, they know of you. If you so choose, you may secure an audience with a local noble. Though, be aware as this may have consequences and could end with you in chains.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
      <text>Nobles are born and raised to a very different lifestyle than most people ever experience, and their personalities reflect that upbringing. However, choosing or being forced to abandon that lifestyle can have a lasting effect, for good or ill. Your personality traits, ideals, bonds, and flaws should reflect the struggle you went through when leaving your family.

d8 | Personality Trait
1 | I often talk wistfully about my house and how I long to return some day.
2 | As soon as I left, I hardened myself to the realities of the world, becoming cold and bitter.
3 | I still carry myself with dignity and poise, reminding everyone around me that I am still of noble birth.
4 | I constantly write home to a few family members that still desire to keep in contact with me.
5 | I have come to expect a certain level of decorum around me and will chastise those who are impolite or rude.
6 | I do not hold myself any higher than others, regardless of where I come from. We are all equal.
7 | If you hurt me or mine, I will not stop hunting you until you are dead or worse.
8 | I have lost my friends and family, and this sadness follows me wherever I go.

d6 | Ideal
1 | Respect. Respect is still due to me because of my birthright, but all people regardless of station deserve to be treated with dignity. (Good)
2 | Responsibility. One day I will return home to face my family, whether I return victorious or in chains. (Lawful)
3 | Independence. I will do everything in my power to remain free of the bondage of my house. (Chaotic)
4 | Power. I will crush my family into dust and from their ashes I will raise a new, stronger house. (Evil)
5 | Family. Nothing is more important than helping my family in any way I can. (Any)
6 | Noble Reclamation. For the good of my family, the realm, or even the world, I must restore my family's good name. (Good)

d6 | Bond
1 | I will face any test to win back the approval of my family.
2 | My house's alliance with another noble family must be rebuilt at all costs.
3 | I love my family more than anything, and I have sacrificed my lifestyle to protect them.
4 | I had a romantic tryst with the heir of a family that my family despises. I love them still, and am constantly torn between them and my family.
5 | Despite my circumstances, my loyalty to my sovereign is unwavering, and I will serve with or without my house.
6 | With my fall from my house, I have become an icon of the common people.

d6 | Flaw
1 | I have lost everything and my broken pride makes me hesitant to accept help.
2 | I hide a truly scandalous secret that could ruin my family forever.
3 | I will leap to defend my family's name, with often violent results.
4 | I cannot control certain urges that have earned me my family's ire.
5 | I am oblivious to anything that does not involve me.
6 | I have brought shame to my family, and I continue to do so with nearly every word I say.</text>
      <roll description="Personality Trait">1d8</roll>
      <roll description="Ideal">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Bond">1d6</roll>
      <roll description="Flaw">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
</compendium>
