<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Warlock</name>
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Aegis (HB)</name>
        <text>You can use your action to create a pact shield in your empty hand or pact armor equipped on your person. You can choose the form that this aegis takes, up to medium armor. You are proficient with it while you wield it. If you create a shield, you can use somatic components while using it.
	Your pact aegis disappears if it is more than 5 feet away from you for 1 minute or more. It also disappears if you use this feature again, if you dismiss the aegis (no action required), or if you die.
	You can transform one magic shield OR one magic suit of armor into your pact aegis by performing a special ritual while you hold it. You perform the ritual over the course of 1 hour, which can be done during a short rest. You can then dismiss the aegis, shunting it into an extradimensional space, and it appears whenever you create your pact aegis thereafter. You can't affect an artifact or a sentient item in this way. The shield or armor ceases being your pact aegis if you die, if you perform the 1-hour ritual on a different item, or if you use a 1-hour ritual to break your bond to it. The aegis appears at your feet if it is in the extradimensional space when the bond breaks.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Beast (HB)</name>
        <text>You can use your action to shapeshift into one beast of CR 1 or lower. This beast, once chosen, is the same each time you use this feature. If the creature has a swimming speed, you do not gain that particular feature until 4th level, and if it has a flying speed, you do not gain that particular feature until 8th level. When you shapeshift, it lasts for one hour or until you drop to 0 HP in that form, at which point you revert back to yourself. Once you use this ability, you cannot use it again until you complete a short or long rest.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Charm (HB)</name>
        <text>You have 1 luck point. Whenever you make an attack roll, ability check, or saving throw, you may spend 1 luck point to roll an additional d20. You can use this ability after the original roll, but before the outcome is revealed. You choose which of the d20s is used for the attack roll, ability check, or saving throw.
	You can also spend one luck point when an attack roll is made against you. Roll a d20, and choose whether the attacker's roll uses their d20 roll or yours. If multiple creatures use a luck point on the same roll, they cancel out, resulting in no additional dice. You regain your luck point when you finish a long rest.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Claw (HB)</name>
        <text>One of your hands turns into a claw of pure magical energy. This claw can act as your arcane focus. It can be used for a magical unarmed strike, which uses your Charisma modifier for its attack and damage rolls. The claw deals 1d6 damage of your choice of slashing or piercing. This claw can also extend up to 10 feet. Through this feature, you can use your attack to cast any spell, invocation, or patron ability with a range of 5 feet or touch at any creature within 10 feet of you, and you can add the claw's damage to those effects.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Deck (HB)</name>
        <text>You gain a magic deck of cards from your patron. After a long rest, you may draw one card, gaining the benefit granted by the card until the beginning of your next long rest.

The Fool. You take half damage from falling, and do not suffer ill effects from heat or cold. You also gain the Rustic Hospitality feature from the Folk Hero background.

The Magician. You have advantage on your first Arcana check of the day. Choose one Wizard cantrip. You can cast it today as if it were a Warlock cantrip.

The High Priestess. You have advantage on your first Nature check of the day. Choose one Druid cantrip. You can cast it today as if it were a Warlock cantrip.

The Empress. You have advantage on your first Persuasion check of the day. You can cast suggestion by expending a warlock spell slot today.

The Emperor. You have advantage on your first Intimidation check of the day. You can cast command by expending a warlock spell slot today.

The Heirophant. You have advantage on your first Religion check of the day. You gain the ability to use the cleric's Turn Undead feature once today, with the following changes:

	◦ You can only target a single creature
	◦ The DC to turn it is determined using 8 + your Deception bonus

The Lovers. You can use an action to know what a creature most desires. Following the use of this action, you gain advantage on all Charisma checks targeting that creature for a number of rounds equal to your Charisma modifier.

The Chariot. You gain a +10 bonus to your movement speed for the day.

Strength. You have advantage on your first Athletics check of the day. You also count as one size larger for purposes of lifting and carrying.

The Hermit. You have advantage on your first Survival check of the day. You also gain one benefit of your choice granted by the Ranger's Natural Explorer feature.

Wheel of Fortune. Draw two cards from The Deck today. Gain both benefits.

Justice. Today, when fighting creatures you have witnessed breaking the law recently, your critical hit range increases to 19-20. "The law" in this case could be the law of the land you're currently in, the law of the land you are from, or your own personal "law" or code of conduct.

The Hanged Man. You gain no usable benefit from the Deck today but you gain one piece of meta knowledge, as chosen by the DM.

Death. You have advantage on death saving throws today.

Temperance. You don't need to eat, drink, or breathe today.

The Devil. You have advantage on your first Deception check of the day. You also have resistance to fire damage today.

The Tower. You gain the ability to take the Dodge action for free on your turn, but when you do, any attacks you make have disadvantage for that round.

The Star. Gain Darkvision for today. If you already have darkvision from another source, the range increases by 30 feet.

The Moon. You have one free use of Disguise Self today. Use it well!

The Sun. Today your initiative is whatever you want it to be, regardless of what your game statistics would say.

Judgment. You may permanently change your alignment by one step. All creatures that previously knew your alignment think it was always the new one.

The World. Today, you may gain the benefit of a long rest during one of your short rests. After this has been used, it cannot be used again until this card is drawn again.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Eidolon (HB)</name>
        <text>Your spells are cast by an avatar of your patron. When you cast a spell that matches your patron's dogma (as determined by you and your DM) the critical range for the attack becomes 19-20. Your spells no longer require verbal or somatic components, though you still need materials or an arcane focus.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Geas (HB)</name>
        <text>Your patron gifts you the ability to influence others' thoughts and actions. You gain a number of Geas uses equal to your Charisma modifier. You may expend one of the uses to cast Command as a 1st level spell. When you do so, you may expend an additional use to enhance it with one of the following:

	• You cast the spell with a bonus action, instead of a regular action.

	• You impose disadvantage on the save.

	• You cast it at your spellcasting level. (If you are a level 3 Warlock for instance, you can cast it as a 2nd level spell, as you have slots of that level.) Starting at 9th level, this enhancement also allows you to replace Command with Geas if you so choose.

You regain one expended use of Geas after a short rest, and all your expended uses after a long rest.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Looter (HB)</name>
        <text>You earned your pact not by making a deal, but by offending a being with great power. In order to make up your debt, you are expected to serve this being, and gain the following benefits and detriments to aid you in your servitude.

	• You have one valuable trinket that once belonged to your patron, and is your pact item. It must be worth 50 gold or more, such as a piece of jewelry or a fancy set of tools. While this item is not in your possession, you lose all benefits of this pact, but keep the detriments. This item can be used as a spellcasting focus.

	• You have advantage on Death Saving Throws.

	• You must actively pursue other warlocks of the same pact to kill them and/or retrieve their trinket.

	• Once per long rest while the item is in your possession, you can cast Commune without expending a spell slot.

	• You may choose one skill to gain advantage on checks for. This becomes disadvantage if you lose your trinket.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Lord (HB)</name>
        <text>You gain the service of a humanoid creature compelled to serve you by your patron. Choose the Spy, Evil Mage, or Feathergale Knight. Their alignment matches yours, and they use your action economy to attack but otherwise act on their own and have their own initiative. You can deliver touch spells through them as well.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Morning Star (HB)</name>
        <text>You can use your action to create a pact weapon in the form of a whip in your empty hand. You are proficient with it while you wield it. Your pact whip has a reach of 10 feet, counts as a finesse weapon, and deals 1d6 magical slashing damage for purposes of overcoming resistances and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.
	The whip is capable of extending up to 60 feet for utility purposes. Such purposes might include wrapping around/ pulling objects straight toward you that are not worn or carried, simple manipulations such as pulling a lever, wrapping around an anchor point you can climb to, swing from, or break a fall with, or wrapping around another creature to break their fall. The DM sets the DC and ability check for any task in which the whip is being used this way, and determines—particularly in instances of falling—whether or not any damage is still taken. The whip disappears if it is more than 5 feet away from you for one minute or more. It also disappears if you use this feature again, if you dismiss the weapon (no action required), or if you die.
	In addition, you gain the Eldritch Whip feature.

Eldritch Whip. You loose your whip toward a target, unleashing its otherworldly essence as it rushes toward them. As an action, make a ranged spell attack roll against a target that you can see within 30 feet. On a success, you deal damage equal to your whip's damage roll and modifier, plus 1d4 of extra damage. All damage dealt in this way is of a damage type associated with your patron.
	At higher levels, this feature does additional damage. The 1d4 becomes 2d4 at level 5, 3d4 at level 11, and 4d4 at level 17.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
        <roll description="Slashing Damage">1d6</roll>
        <roll description="Slashing Damage" level="3">1d4</roll>
        <roll description="Slashing Damage" level="5">2d4</roll>
        <roll description="Slashing Damage" level="11">3d4</roll>
        <roll description="Slashing Damage" level="17">4d4</roll>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Oracle (HB)</name>
        <text>Your patron gifts you the ability to see and know things others cannot. You gain a number of Sight uses equal to your Charisma modifier. You may expend one of the uses to cast one of the following spells: Detect Magic, Detect Evil and Good, Hunter's Mark, and Identify.
	You regain one expended use of the Sight after a short rest, and all your expended uses after a long rest.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Pathfinder (HB)</name>
        <text>You can use your action to create a pair of pact boots equipped on your person. You can choose the form that these boots or shoes take. You are proficient with them while you wield them. While wearing these eldritch shoes or boots, your movement speed increases by 10 feet and you add your Charisma score to your long jumps and Charisma modifier to your high jumps. In addition, while wearing these boots or shoes your unarmed strikes become 1d4 damage of your choice of piercing, slashing, or bludgeoning.
	Your pact boots disappear if they are more than 5 feet away from you for 1 minute or more. They also disappear if you use this feature again, if you dismiss the boots (no action required), or if you die.
	You can transform one magic pair of boots or shoes into your pact boots by performing a special ritual while you hold it. You perform the ritual over the course of 1 hour, which can be done during a short rest. You can then dismiss the boots, shunting them into an extradimensional space, and they appear whenever you create your pact boots thereafter. You can't affect an artifact or a sentient item in this way. The boots cease being your pact boots if you die, if you perform the 1-hour ritual on a different item, or if you use a 1-hour ritual to break your bond to them. The boots appear at your feet if they are in the extradimensional space when the bond breaks.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Shroud (HB)</name>
        <text>Your patron gifts you a shroud from its plane, an ancient garment woven with otherworldly skill, to aid your efforts by concealing your intentions and presence.
	You can wear this gifted cloak with the hood up or down, and the effects change based on how it is worn. Putting the hood up or down takes an action, just as it does with other magical cloaks.
	When the cloak's hood is down, it appears nonmagical, as though under the effects of Nystul's Magic Aura. You also gain proficiency in the Deception skill, and add an additional half your proficiency (rounded down) to any deception check you make while wearing the cloak.
	When the hood is up, your outline becomes blurry and displaced, granting you proficiency in the Stealth skill, and allowing you to add an additional half your proficiency (rounded down) to any stealth checks you make while wearing the cloak. You also gain the benefits of half cover while in dim light or darkness.
	As an action, you can summon the cloak from its plane. When it appears, you are wearing it and do not need to take further action to put it on. You may also dismiss the cloak (no action required) into its home plane. The cloak disappears if it is further than five feet from you for one minute.
	If you find a magical cloak or cape in your travels, you may entreat your patron to imbue the properties of the shroud into the new cloak by performing a 1 hour ritual. Upon completing the ritual, the new cloak has the benefits of this feature, in addition to whatever benefit it normally confers. Any cloak previously affected in this way loses its Shroud properties upon completion of the ritual.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Symbiote (HB)</name>
        <text>You become physically corrupted by your patron. They will occasionally take control of your body (as determined by your DM), but in exchange, you gain an 18 in an ability score of your choice.

Source:	DnDBeyond Unearthed Arcana (Homebrew), Additional Warlock Pacts (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
