<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <item>
    <name>Fire, Fire!</name>
    <detail>light crossbow, rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>R</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <weight>5</weight>
    <property>A,LD,2H</property>
    <dmg1>1d8</dmg1>
    <dmgType>P</dmgType>
    <range>80/320</range>
    <text>Ammo: crossbow bolt

This hollow metal crossbow was created by a team of kobolds and contains an enchanted ember at its core. While holding this magic crossbow, the ember burns brightly inside, causing flames to lick out from various gaps left along the weapon's frame. The crossbow has 3 charges and continues to burn while it has at least 1 remaining charge. While it burns, the crossbow emits bright light in a 20 foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet, and any nonmagical bolt fired from the crossbow catches fire and deals an extra 1d6 fire damage to any target it hits.
	You can expend 1 charge from the crossbow as an action to cause the flame to spew forth and send out a devastating wave of fire. Each creature in a 30-foot cone must make a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw. A creature takes 4d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. The fire ignites any flammable objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried.
	The crossbow regains 1d3 expended charges each day at dawn. If you expend the last charge, roll a d20. On a 1, the magic ember inside the crossbow dies, and the weapon becomes a nonmagical crossbow.

Ammunition: You can use a weapon that has the ammunition property to make a ranged attack only if you have ammunition to fire from the weapon. Each time you attack with the weapon, you expend one piece of ammunition. The ammunition of a firearm is destroyed upon use. Drawing the ammunition from a quiver, case, or other container is part of the attack (you need a free hand to load a one-handed weapon). At the end of the battle, you can recover half your expended ammunition by taking a minute to search the battlefield.
If you use a weapon that has the ammunition property to make a melee attack, you treat the weapon as an improvised weapon (see "Improvised Weapons").

Range: A weapon that can be used to make a ranged attack has a range shown in parentheses after the ammunition or thrown property. The range lists two numbers. The first is the weapon's normal range in feet, and the second indicates the weapon's maximum range. When attacking a target beyond normal range, you have disadvantage on the attack roll. You can't attack a target beyond the weapon's long range.

Loading: Because of the time required to load this weapon, you can fire only one piece of ammunition from it when you use an action, bonus action, or reaction to fire it, regardless of the number of attacks you can normally make.

Two-Handed: This weapon requires two hands when you attack with it.

Proficiency: simple, light crossbow
Source:	The Griffon's Saddlebag,
		Team Superhydra: The Kobolds' Cauldron</text>
    <roll description="Fire Damage">1d6</roll>
    <roll description="Fire Damage">4d6</roll>
    <roll description="Recharge">1d3</roll>
  </item>
  <!-- Fire, Fire! -->
  <item>
    <name>Talyard the Great's Wand of Power</name>
    <detail>uncommon</detail>
    <type>WD</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <weight>1</weight>
    <text>This normal looking spruce stick is actually the wand of a famous drunkard. A drunken creature that sees the stick perceives it as a magnificent, colorful wand that radiates with an awesome power.
	This wand has 3 charges and regains 1d3 expended charges each day at dusk. While you're drunk and holding the wand, you can use your action to cast the following spells from the wand, even if you are incapable of casting spells: heroism (1 charge), lesser restoration (2 charges), or thaumaturgy (no charges). If you don't have a spellcasting ability modifier, Charisma is your spellcasting ability when casting these spells (minimum 1).

Source:	The Griffon's Saddlebag,
		Team Superhydra: The Kobolds' Cauldron</text>
    <roll description="Recharge">1d3</roll>
  </item>
  <!-- Talyard the Great's Wand of Power -->
  <item>
    <name>Red Claw's Regalia</name>
    <detail>legendary (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>YES</magic>
    <text>This tough dragon scale robe is miraculously insulated and comfortable. While wearing the robe, you gain the following benefits:

	• You can withstand temperatures as low as -50 degrees F without any additional protection.
	• Your Constitution score increases by 2, to a maximum of 22.
	• You have advantage on Constitution saving throws.
	• You have resistance to fire damage.
	• You can walk on lava as if it were solid ground, without taking fire damage from it. Ending your turn on lava causes you to sink into it and take fire damage as normal.

The hem of this robe glimmers with slowly shfiting embers. While wearing this robe, your steps leave behing small motes of magical fire and scorched earth. The flames and marks left behind are harmless and disappear 1 second after they appear.

Source:	The Griffon's Saddlebag,
		Team Superhydra: The Kobolds' Cauldron</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">constitution +2</modifier>
  </item>
  <!-- Red Claw's Regalia -->
</compendium>
