<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<source>
  <name>Critical Role: Call of the Netherdeep</name>
  <abbreviation>CND</abbreviation>
  <url>https://marketplace.dndbeyond.com/category/critical-role-call-of-the-netherdeep?pid=SRC-00083</url>
  <author>Matthew Mercer, James J. Haeck, Christopher Perkins</author>
  <artist>Kate Irwin</artist>
  <publisher>Wizards of the Coast</publisher>
  <website>https://www.dndbeyond.com/</website>
  <category>Rulebook Supplements</category>
  <pubdate>2022-03-15</pubdate>
  <description>Can You Change Fate?
An epic Critical Role campaign for the world's greatest roleplaying game.

The greed of mortals has awakened a powerful entity long thought destroyed. For eons, this mighty champion of the gods has been imprisoned in the darkest depths of Exandria. His name has been forgotten, as have his heroic deeds. Languishing in despair, he calls out for new heroes to save him.

Inspired by the campaigns of the hit series Critical Role, this adventure begins in the Wastes of Xhorhas and leads to the glimmering oasis-city of Ank'Harel on the continent of Marquet, and from there into a sunken realm of gloom, corruption, and sorrow known as the Netherdeep. Above it all, the red moon of Ruidus watches, twisting the fates of those who have the power to shape the course of history.

In Critical Role: Call of the Netherdeep, you'll embark on an epic campaign taking players from levels 3-12 as they swirl through strange underwater locales, mysterious ruins, and an intrigue-filled city! Under the ill-fated red moon of Ruidius, you'll unravel truths of the greatest legends of Critical Role's world of Exandria™. This uniquely-structured adventure module pairs you alongside rival adventurers, who grow in capability alongside you. In the oasis city of Ank'Harel, secretive and powerful factions invite you into the deeper secrets of the city, and beyond. What choices will you make with the dark and tormenting knowledge you'll find in the mind-bending aquatic abyss of the Netherdeep?</description>
  <collection>
    <doc href="bestiary-cnd.xml"/>
    <doc href="items-cnd.xml"/>
    <doc href="items-magic-dmg+cnd.xml"/>
    <doc href="items-magic-erlw+cnd.xml"/>
    <doc href="items-magic-phb+cnd.xml"/>
    <doc href="items-magic-scag+cnd.xml"/>
  </collection>
</source>
