<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <!-- Ruidium Armor -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Ruidium %name%</name>
    <detail>very rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>MA,HA</type>
    <text>This magic armor has a dull, rusty color or has veins of ruidium running through it. While you wear this armor, you gain the following benefits:

	• You have resistance to psychic damage.
	• You can breathe water.
	• You gain a swimming speed equal to your walking speed.

Ruidium Corruption: When you roll a 1 on a saving throw while wearing this armor, you must make a DC 15 Charisma saving throw. On a failed save, you gain 1 level of exhaustion. If you are not already suffering from ruidium corruption, you become corrupted when you fail this save.

If Ruidium Is Destroyed: If the Apotheon is killed or redeemed, all the ruidium in Exandria is destroyed instantly, and ruidium armor becomes +1 armor.</text>
    <source>Critical Role: Call of the Netherdeep p. 215</source>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Ruidium Weapon -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Ruidium %name%</name>
    <detail>very rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>M,R</type>
    <text>This magic weapon has a dull, rusty color or has veins of ruidium running through it. While this weapon is on your person, you gain the following benefits:

	• You can breathe water.
	• You gain a swimming speed equal to your walking speed.

Ruidium Strike: A creature you hit with this weapon takes an extra 2d6 psychic damage.

Ruidium Corruption: When you roll a 1 on an attack roll made with this weapon, you must make a DC 20 Charisma saving throw. On a failed save, you gain 1 level of exhaustion. If you are not already suffering from ruidium corruption, you become corrupted when you fail this save.

If Ruidium Is Destroyed: If the Apotheon is killed or redeemed, all the ruidium in Exandria is destroyed instantly, and a ruidium weapon becomes a +2 weapon.</text>
    <source>Critical Role: Call of the Netherdeep p. 216</source>
    <roll description="Psychic Damage">2d6</roll>
  </itemtemplate>
</compendium>
