<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Warlock</name>
    <hd>8</hd>
    <proficiency>Wisdom, Charisma, Arcana, Deception, History, Intimidation, Investigation, Nature, Religion</proficiency>
    <numSkills>2</numSkills>
    <armor>Light Armor</armor>
    <weapons>Simple Weapons</weapons>
    <tools>None</tools>
    <wealth>4d4x10</wealth>
    <spellAbility>Charisma</spellAbility>
    <slotsReset>S</slotsReset>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <slots>2,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <slots>2,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
      <slots>2,0,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
      <slots>3,0,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
      <slots>3,0,0,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <slots>3,0,0,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <slots>3,0,0,0,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <slots>3,0,0,0,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <slots>3,0,0,0,0,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <slots>4,0,0,0,0,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <slots>4,0,0,0,0,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12">
      <slots>4,0,0,0,0,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <slots>4,0,0,0,0,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <slots>4,0,0,0,0,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <slots>4,0,0,0,0,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16">
      <slots>4,0,0,0,0,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <slots>4,0,0,0,0,4</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <slots>4,0,0,0,0,4</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
      <slots>4,0,0,0,0,4</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
      <slots>4,0,0,0,0,4</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>2</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>3</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>4</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>5</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>6</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>7</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>8</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>9</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>10</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>10</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>11</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>11</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>12</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>12</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>13</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>13</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>14</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>14</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>15</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
      <counter>
        <name>Spells Known</name>
        <value>15</value>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <trait>
      <name>Warlock</name>
      <text>With a pseudodragon curled on his shoulder, a young elf in golden robes smiles warmly, weaving a magical charm into his honeyed words and bending the palace sentinel to his will.
	As flames spring to life in her hands, a wizened human whispers the secret name of her demonic patron, infusing her spell with fiendish magic.
	Shifting his gaze between a battered tome and the odd alignment of the stars overhead, a wild-eyed tiefling chants the mystic ritual that will open a doorway to a distant world.
	Warlocks are seekers of the knowledge that lies hidden in the fabric of the multiverse. Through pacts made with mysterious beings of supernatural power, warlocks unlock magical effects both subtle and spectacular. Drawing on the ancient knowledge of beings such as fey nobles, demons, devils, hags, and alien entities of the Far Realm, warlocks piece together arcane secrets to bolster their own power.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Sworn and Beholden</name>
      <text>A warlock is defined by a pact with an otherworldly being. Sometimes the relationship between warlock and patron is like that of a cleric and a deity, though the beings that serve as patrons for warlocks are not gods. A warlock might lead a cult dedicated to a demon prince, an archdevil, or an utterly alien entity — beings not typically served by clerics. More often, though, the arrangement is similar to that between a master and an apprentice. The warlock learns and grows in power, at the cost of occasional services performed on the patron's behalf.
	The magic bestowed on a warlock ranges from minor but lasting alterations to the warlock's being (such as the ability to see in darkness or to read any language) to access to powerful spells. Unlike bookish wizards, warlocks supplement their magic with some facility at hand-to-hand combat. They are comfortable in light armor and know how to use simple weapons.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Delvers into Secrets</name>
      <text>Warlocks are driven by an insatiable need for knowledge and power, which compels them into their pacts and shapes their lives. This thirst drives warlocks into their pacts and shapes their later careers as well.
	Stories of warlocks binding themselves to fiends are widely known. But many warlocks serve patrons that are not fiendish. Sometimes a traveler in the wilds comes to a strangely beautiful tower, meets its fey lord or lady, and stumbles into a pact without being fully aware of it. And sometimes, while poring over tomes of forbidden lore, a brilliant but crazed student's mind is opened to realities beyond the material world and to the alien beings that dwell in the outer void.
	Once a pact is made, a warlock's thirst for knowledge and power can't be slaked with mere study and research. No one makes a pact with such a mighty patron if he or she doesn't intend to use the power thus gained. Rather, the vast majority of warlocks spend their days in active pursuit of their goals, which typically means some kind of adventuring. Furthermore, the demands of their patrons drive warlocks toward adventure.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creating a Warlock</name>
      <text>As you make your warlock character, spend some time thinking about your patron and the obligations that your pact imposes upon you. What led you to make the pact, and how did you make contact with your patron? Were you seduced into summoning a devil, or did you seek out the ritual that would allow you to make contact with an alien elder god? Did you search for your patron, or did your patron find and choose you? Do you chafe under the obligations of your pact or serve joyfully in anticipation of the rewards promised to you?
	Work with your DM to determine how big a part your pact will play in your character's adventuring career. Your patron's demands might drive you into adventures, or they might consist entirely of small favors you can do between adventures.
	What kind of relationship do you have with your patron? Is it friendly, antagonistic, uneasy, or romantic? How important does your patron consider you to be? What part do you play in your patron's plans? Do you know other servants of your patron?
	How does your patron communicate with you? If you have a familiar, it might occasionally speak with your patron's voice. Some warlocks find messages from their patrons etched on trees, mingled among tea leaves, or adrift in the clouds — messages that only the warlock can see. Other warlocks converse with their patrons in dreams or waking visions, or deal only with intermediaries.

Quick Build:
You can make a warlock quickly by following these suggestions. First, Charisma should be your highest ability score, followed by Constitution. Second, choose the charlatan background. Third, choose the eldritch blast and chill touch cantrips, along with the 1st-level spells charm person and witch bolt.</text>
    </trait>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Starting Warlock</name>
        <text>As a 1st-level Warlock, you begin play with 8 + your Constitution modifier hit points.

You are proficient with the following items, in addition to any proficiencies provided by your race or background.

	• Armor: light armor
	• Weapons: simple weapons
	• Tools: none
	• Skills: Choose 2 from Arcana, Deception, History, Intimidation, Investigation, Nature, Religion

You begin play with the following equipment, in addition to any equipment provided by your background.

	• (a) a light crossbow and crossbow bolts (20) or (b) any simple weapon
	• (a) a component pouch or (b) an arcane focus
	• (a) a scholar's pack or (b) a dungeoneer's pack
	• Leather armor, any simple weapon, and two daggers

If you forgo this starting equipment, as well as the items offered by your background, you start with 4d4 × 10 gp to buy your equipment.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Multiclass Warlock</name>
        <text>If your group uses the optional rule on multiclassing in the Player's Handbook, here's what you need to know if you choose warlock as one of your classes.

Ability Score Minimum:
As a multiclass character, you must have at least the following ability score(s) to take a level in this class, or to take a level in another class if you are already a warlock.

	• Charisma 13

Proficiencies Gained:
When you gain your first level in a class other than your initial class, you gain only some of your new class's starting proficiencies, here are the proficiencies you gain when you take your first level as a warlock.

	• Armor: light armor
	• Weapons: simple weapons
	• Tools: none

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Multiclass Features</name>
        <text>When you gain a new level in a class, you get its features for that level. You don't, however, receive the class's starting equipment, and a few features have additional rules when you're multiclassing: Channel Divinity, Extra Attack, Unarmored Defense, and Spellcasting.

Channel Divinity:
If you already have the Channel Divinity feature and gain a level in a class that also grants the feature, you gain the Channel Divinity effects granted by that class, but getting the feature again doesn't give you an additional use of it. You gain additional uses only when you reach a class level that explicitly grants them to you. For example, if you are a cleric 6/paladin 4, you can use Channel Divinity twice between rests because you are high enough level in the cleric class to have more uses. Whenever you use the feature, you can choose any of the Channel Divinity effects available to you from your two classes.

Extra Attack:
If you gain the Extra Attack class feature from more than one class, the features don't add together. You can't make more than two attacks with this feature unless it says you do (as the fighter's version of Extra Attack does).
	Similarly, the warlock's eldritch invocation Thirsting Blade doesn't give you additional attacks if you also have Extra Attack.

Unarmored Defense:
If you already have the Unarmored Defense feature, you can't gain it again from another class.

Spellcasting:
Your capacity for spellcasting depends partly on your combined levels in all your spellcasting classes and partly on your individual levels in those classes. Once you have the Spellcasting feature from more than one class, use the rules below. If you multiclass but have the Spellcasting feature from only one class, you follow the rules as described in that class.

Spells Known and Prepared:
You determine what spells you know and can prepare for each class individually, as if you were a single-classed member of that class. If you are a ranger 4/wizard 3, for example, you know three 1 st-level ranger spells based on your levels in the ranger class. As a 3rd-level wizard, you know three wizard cantrips, and your spellbook contains ten wizard spells, two of which (the two you gained when you reached 3rd level as a wizard) can be 2nd-level spells. If your Intelligence is 16, you can prepare six wizard spells from your spellbook.
	Each spell you know and prepare is associated with one of your classes, and you use the spell casting ability of that class when you cast the spell. Similarly, a spellcasting focus, such as a holy symbol, can be used only for the spells from the class associated with that focus.
	If a cantrip of yours increases in power at higher levels, the increase is based on your character level, not your level in a particular class.

Spell Slots:
You determine your available spell slots by adding together all your levels in the bard, cleric, druid, sorcerer, and wizard classes, half your levels (rounded down) in the paladin and ranger classes, and a third of your fighter or rogue levels (rounded down) if you have the Eldritch Knight or the Arcane Trickster feature. Use this total to determine your spell slots by consulting the Multiclass Spellcaster table.
	If you have more than one spellcasting class, this table might give you spell slots of a level that is higher than the spells you know or can prepare. You can use those slots, but only to cast your lower-level spells. If a lower level spell that you cast, like burning hands, has an enhanced effect when cast using a higher-level slot, you can use the enhanced effect, even though you don't have any spells of that higher level.
	For example, if you are the aforementioned ranger 4/ wizard 3, you count as a 5th-level character when determining your spell slots: you have four 1st-level slots, three 2nd-level slots, and two 3rd-level slots. However, you don't know any 3rd-level spells, nor do you know any 2nd-level ranger spells. You can use the spell slots of those levels to cast the spells you do know-and potentially enhance their effects.

Pact Magic:
If you have both the Spellcasting class feature and the Pact Magic class feature from the warlock class, you can use the spell slots you gain from the Pact Magic feature to cast spells you know or have prepared from classes with the Spellcasting class feature, and you can use the spell slots you gain from the Spellcasting class feature to cast warlock spells you know.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 164</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Pact Magic</name>
        <text>Your arcane research and the magic bestowed on you by your patron have given you facility with spells. See chapter 10 for the general rules of spellcasting and chapter 11 for the warlock spell list.

Cantrips:
You know two cantrips of your choice from the warlock spell list. You learn additional warlock cantrips of your choice at higher levels, as shown in the Cantrips Known column of the Warlock table.

Spell Slots:
The Warlock table shows how many spell slots you have to cast your warlock spells of 1st through 5th level. The table also shows what the level of those slots is; all of your spell slots are the same level. To cast one of your warlock spells of 1st level or higher, you must expend a spell slot. You regain all expended spell slots when you finish a short or long rest.
	For example, when you are 5th level, you have two 3rd-level spell slots. To cast the 1st-level spell witch bolt, you must spend one of those slots, and you cast it as a 3rd-level spell.

Spells Known of 1st Level and Higher:
At 1st level, you know two 1st-level spells of your choice from the warlock spell list.
	The Spells Known column of the Warlock table shows when you learn more warlock spells of your choice of 1st level and higher. A spell you choose must be of a level no higher than what's shown in the table's Slot Level column for your level. When you reach 6th level, for example, you learn a new warlock spell, which can be 1st, 2nd, or 3rd level.
	Additionally, when you gain a level in this class, you can choose one of the warlock spells you know and replace it with another spell from the warlock spell list, which also must be of a level for which you have spell slots.

Spellcasting Ability:
Charisma is your spellcasting ability for your warlock spells, so you use your Charisma whenever a spell refers to your spellcasting ability. In addition, you use your Charisma modifier when setting the saving throw DC for a warlock spell you cast and when making an attack roll with one.

	Spell save DC = 8 + Charisma modifier + Proficiency Bonus

	Spell attack modifier = Charisma modifier + Proficiency Bonus

Spellcasting Focus:
You can use an arcane focus as a spellcasting focus for your warlock spells.

Warlock Spells Known:
Level | Spells Known
1 | 2
2 | 3
3 | 4
4 | 5
5 | 6
6 | 7
7 | 8
8 | 9
9 | 10
10 | 10
11 | 11
12 | 11
13 | 12
14 | 12
15 | 13
16 | 13
17 | 14
18 | 14
19 | 15
20 | 15

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Otherworldly Patron</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you have struck a bargain with an otherworldly being chosen from the list of available patrons. Your choice grants you features at 1st level and again at 6th, 10th, and 14th level.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature>
        <name>Eldritch Invocations</name>
        <text>In your study of occult lore, you have unearthed eldritch invocations, fragments of forbidden knowledge that imbue you with an abiding magical ability.
	At 2nd level, you gain two eldritch invocations of your choice. When you gain certain warlock levels, you gain additional invocations of your choice. You gain an additional invocation at 5th, 7th, 9th, 12th, 15th, and 18th warlock level. A level prerequisite refers to your level in this class.
	Additionally, when you gain a level in this class, you can choose one of the invocations you know and replace it with another invocation that you could learn at that level.
	A level prerequisite in an invocation refers to warlock level, not character level.

Invocations Known:
Level | Invocations
2nd | 2
5th | 3
7th | 4
9th | 5
12th | 6
15th | 7
18th | 8

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Eldritch Invocations Known</name>
        <value>2</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature>
        <name>Pact Boon</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, your otherworldly patron bestows a gift upon you for your loyal service. You gain one of the following features of your choice.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Chain</name>
        <text>You learn the find familiar spell and can cast it as a ritual. The spell doesn't count against your number of spells known.
	When you cast the spell, you can choose one of the normal forms for your familiar or one of the following special forms: imp, pseudodragon, quasit, or sprite.
	Additionally, when you take the Attack action, you can forgo one of your own attacks to allow your familiar to use its reaction to make one attack of its own.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Blade</name>
        <text>You can use your action to create a pact weapon in your empty hand. You can choose the form that this melee weapon takes each time you create it (see chapter 5 for weapon options). You are proficient with it while you wield it. This weapon counts as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.
	Your pact weapon disappears if it is more than 5 feet away from you for 1 minute or more. It also disappears if you use this feature again, if you dismiss the weapon (no action required), or if you die.
	You can transform one magic weapon into your pact weapon by performing a special ritual while you hold the weapon. You perform the ritual over the course of 1 hour, which can be done during a short rest. You can then dismiss the weapon, shunting it into an extradimensional space, and it appears whenever you create your pact weapon thereafter. You can't affect an artifact or a sentient weapon in this way. The weapon ceases being your pact weapon if you die, if you perform the 1-hour ritual on a different weapon, or if you use a 1-hour ritual to break your bond to it. The weapon appears at your feet if it is in the extradimensional space when the bond breaks.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Tome</name>
        <text>Your patron gives you a grimoire called a Book of Shadows. When you gain this feature, choose three cantrips from any class's spell list. The cantrips do not need to be from the same spell list. While the book is on your person, you can cast those cantrips at will. They don't count against your number of cantrips known. Any cantrip you cast with this feature is considered a warlock cantrip for you. If you lose your Book of Shadows, you can perform a 1-hour ceremony to receive a replacement from your patron. This ceremony can be performed during a short or long rest, and it destroys the previous book. The book turns to ash when you die.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 4th level, and again at 8th, 12th, 16th, and 19th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
      <feature>
        <name>Additional Invocation</name>
        <text>At 5th level, you learn an additional Eldritch Invocation.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 107</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Eldritch Invocations</name>
        <value>3</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Patron Feature</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain a feature granted by your Otherworldly Patron.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature>
        <name>Additional Invocation</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn an additional Eldritch Invocation.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 107</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Eldritch Invocations</name>
        <value>4</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 8th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <feature>
        <name>Additional Invocation</name>
        <text>At 9th level, you learn an additional Eldritch Invocation.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 107</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Eldritch Invocations</name>
        <value>5</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Patron Feature</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you gain a feature granted by your Otherworldly Patron.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature>
        <name>Mystic Arcanum (6th level)</name>
        <text>At 11th level, your patron bestows upon you a magical secret called an arcanum. Choose one 6th-level spell from the warlock spell list as this arcanum.
	You can cast your arcanum spell once without expending a spell slot. You must finish a long rest before you can do so again.
	At higher levels, you gain more warlock spells of your choice that can be cast in this way: one 7th-level spell at 13th level, one 8th-level spell at 15th level, and one 9th-level spell at 17th level. You regain all uses of your Mystic Arcanum when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 12th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Additional Invocation</name>
        <text>At 12th level, you learn an additional Eldritch Invocation.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 107</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Eldritch Invocations</name>
        <value>6</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <feature>
        <name>Mystic Arcanum (7th level)</name>
        <text>At 13th level, your patron bestows upon you a magical secret called an arcanum. Choose one 7th-level spell from the warlock spell list as this arcanum.
	You can cast your arcanum spell once without expending a spell slot. You must finish a long rest before you can do so again.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Patron Feature</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain a feature granted by your Otherworldly Patron.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature>
        <name>Additional Invocation</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you learn an additional Eldritch Invocation.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 107</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Mystic Arcanum (8th level)</name>
        <text>At 15th level, your patron bestows upon you a magical secret called an arcanum. Choose one 8th-level spell from the warlock spell list as this arcanum.
	You can cast your arcanum spell once without expending a spell slot. You must finish a long rest before you can do so again.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Eldritch Invocations</name>
        <value>7</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 16th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature>
        <name>Mystic Arcanum (9th level)</name>
        <text>At 17th level, your patron bestows upon you a magical secret called an arcanum. Choose one 9th-level spell from the warlock spell list as this arcanum.
	You can cast your arcanum spell once without expending a spell slot. You must finish a long rest before you can do so again.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature>
        <name>Additional Invocation</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you learn an additional Eldritch Invocation.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 107</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Eldritch Invocations</name>
        <value>8</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 19th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
      <feature>
        <name>Eldritch Master</name>
        <text>At 20th level, you can draw on your inner reserve of mystical power while entreating your patron to regain expended spell slots. You can spend 1 minute entreating your patron for aid to regain all your expended spell slots from your Pact Magic feature. Once you regain spell slots with this feature, you must finish a long rest before you can do so again.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 105</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Eldritch Master</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Otherworldly Patron: The Archfey -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Patron: The Archfey</name>
        <text>Your patron is a lord or lady of the fey, a creature of legend who holds secrets that were forgotten before the mortal races were born. This being's motivations are often inscrutable, and sometimes whimsical, and might involve a striving for greater magical power or the settling of age-old grudges. Beings of this sort include the Prince of Frost; the Queen of Air and Darkness, ruler of the Gloaming Court; Titania of the Summer Court; her consort Oberon, the Green Lord; Hyrsam, the Prince of Fools; and ancient hags.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 108</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Expanded Spell List (The Archfey)</name>
        <text>The Archfey lets you choose from an expanded list of spells when you learn a warlock spell. The following spells are added to the warlock spell list for you.

Archfey Expanded Spells:
Spell Level | Spells
1st | faerie fire, sleep
2nd | calm emotions, phantasmal force
3rd | blink, plant growth
4th | dominate beast, greater invisibility
5th | dominate person, seeming

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 108</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Fey Presence (The Archfey)</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, your patron bestows upon you the ability to project the beguiling and fearsome presence of the fey. As an action, you can cause each creature in a 10-foot cube originating from you to make a Wisdom saving throw against your warlock spell save DC. The creatures that fail their saving throws are all charmed or frightened by you (your choice) until the end of your next turn.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 108</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Fey Presence</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
        <subclass>The Archfey</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Misty Escape (The Archfey)</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can vanish in a puff of mist in response to harm. When you take damage, you can use your reaction to turn invisible and teleport up to 60 feet to an unoccupied space you can see. You remain invisible until the start of your next turn or until you attack or cast a spell.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 108</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Misty Escape</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
        <subclass>The Archfey</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Beguiling Defenses (The Archfey)</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, your patron teaches you how to turn the mind-affecting magic of your enemies against them. You are immune to being charmed, and when another creature attempts to charm you, you can use your reaction to attempt to turn the charm back on that creature. The creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your warlock spell save DC or be charmed by you for 1 minute or until the creature takes any damage.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 108</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Dark Delirium (The Archfey)</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, you can plunge a creature into an illusory realm. As an action, choose a creature that you can see within 60 feet of you. It must make a Wisdom saving throw against your warlock spell save DC. On a failed save, it is charmed or frightened by you (your choice) for 1 minute or until your concentration is broken (as if you are concentrating on a spell). This effect ends early if the creature takes any damage.
	Until this illusion ends, the creature thinks it is lost in a misty realm, the appearance of which you choose. The creature can see and hear only itself, you, and the illusion.
	You must finish a short or long rest before you can use this feature again.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 108</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Dark Delirium</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
        <subclass>The Archfey</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Otherworldly Patron: The Fiend -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Patron: The Fiend</name>
        <text>You have made a pact with a fiend from the lower planes of existence, a being whose aims are evil, even if you strive against those aims. Such beings desire the corruption or destruction of all things, ultimately including you. Fiends powerful enough to forge a pact include demon lords such as Demogorgon, Orcus, Fraz'Urb-luu, and Baphomet; archdevils such as Asmodeus, Dispater, Mephistopheles, and Belial; pit fiends and balors that are especially mighty; and ultroloths and other lords of the yugoloths.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 109</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Expanded Spell List (The Fiend)</name>
        <text>The Fiend lets you choose from an expanded list of spells when you learn a warlock spell. The following spells are added to the warlock spell list for you.

Fiend Expanded Spells:
Spell Level | Spells
1st | burning hands, command
2nd | blindness/deafness, scorching ray
3rd | fireball, stinking cloud
4th | fire shield, wall of fire
5th | flame strike, hallow

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 109</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Dark One's Blessing (The Fiend)</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, when you reduce a hostile creature to 0 hit points, you gain temporary hit points equal to your Charisma modifier + your warlock level (minimum of 1).

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 109</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Dark One's Own Luck (The Fiend)</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can call on your patron to alter fate in your favor. When you make an ability check or a saving throw, you can use this feature to add a d10 to your roll. You can do so after seeing the initial roll but before any of the roll's effects occur.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 109</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Dark One's Luck</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
        <subclass>The Fiend</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Fiendish Resilience (The Fiend)</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, you can choose one damage type when you finish a short or long rest. You gain resistance to that damage type until you choose a different one with this feature. Damage from magical weapons or silver weapons ignores this resistance.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 109</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Hurl Through Hell (The Fiend)</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, when you hit a creature with an attack, you can use this feature to instantly transport the target through the lower planes. The creature disappears and hurtles through a nightmare landscape.
	At the end of your next turn, the target returns to the space it previously occupied, or the nearest unoccupied space. If the target is not a fiend, it takes 10d10 psychic damage as it reels from its horrific experience.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 109</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Hurl Through Hell</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>The Fiend</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Otherworldly Patron: The Great Old One -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Patron: The Great Old One</name>
        <text>Your patron is a mysterious entity whose nature is utterly foreign to the fabric of reality. It might come from the Far Realm, the space beyond reality, or it could be one of the elder gods known only in legends. Its motives are incomprehensible to mortals, and its knowledge so immense and ancient that even the greatest libraries pale in comparison to the vast secrets it holds. The Great Old One might be unaware of your existence or entirely indifferent to you, but the secrets you have learned allow you to draw your magic from it. Entities of this type include Ghaunadar, called That Which Lurks; Tharizdun, the Chained God; Dendar, the Night Serpent; Zargon, the Returner; Great Cthulhu; and other unfathomable beings.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 109</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Expanded Spell List (The Great Old One)</name>
        <text>The Great Old One lets you choose from an expanded list of spells when you learn a warlock spell. The following spells are added to the warlock spell list for you.

Great Old One Expanded Spells:
Spell Level | Spells
1st | dissonant whispers, Tasha's hideous laughter
2nd | detect thoughts, phantasmal force
3rd | clairvoyance, sending
4th | dominate beast, Evard's black tentacles
5th | dominate person, telekinesis

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 109</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Awakened Mind (The Great Old One)</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, your alien knowledge gives you the ability to touch the minds of other creatures. You can communicate telepathically with any creature you can see within 30 feet of you. You don't need to share a language with the creature for it to understand your telepathic utterances, but the creature must be able to understand at least one language.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 109</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Entropic Ward (The Great Old One)</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you learn to magically ward yourself against attack and to turn an enemy's failed strike into good luck for yourself. When a creature makes an attack roll against you, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on that roll. If the attack misses you, your next attack roll against the creature has advantage if you make it before the end of your next turn.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 109</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Entropic Ward</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
        <subclass>The Great Old One</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Thought Shield (The Great Old One)</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, your thoughts can't be read by telepathy or other means unless you allow it. You also have resistance to psychic damage, and whenever a creature deals psychic damage to you, that creature takes the same amount of damage that you do.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 109</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Create Thrall (The Great Old One)</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain the ability to infect a humanoid's mind with the alien magic of your patron. You can use your action to touch an incapacitated humanoid. That creature is then charmed by you until a remove curse spell is cast on it, the charmed condition is removed from it, or you use this feature again.
	You can communicate telepathically with the charmed creature as long as the two of you are on the same plane of existence.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 109</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
