<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Cleric</name>
    <hd>8</hd>
    <proficiency>Wisdom, Charisma, History, Insight, Medicine, Persuasion, Religion</proficiency>
    <numSkills>2</numSkills>
    <armor>Light Armor, Medium Armor, Shields</armor>
    <weapons>Simple Weapons</weapons>
    <tools>None</tools>
    <wealth>5d4x10</wealth>
    <spellAbility>Wisdom</spellAbility>
    <slotsReset>L</slotsReset>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <slots>3,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <slots>3,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
      <slots>3,4,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
      <slots>4,4,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
      <slots>4,4,3,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <slots>4,4,3,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <slots>4,4,3,3,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <slots>4,4,3,3,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <slots>4,4,3,3,3,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,3,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,3,2,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,3,2,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,3,2,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,3,2,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,3,2,1,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,3,2,1,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,3,2,1,1,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,3,3,1,1,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,3,3,2,1,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,3,3,2,2,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <trait>
      <name>Cleric</name>
      <text>Arms and eyes upraised toward the sun and a prayer on his lips, an elf begins to glow with an inner light that spills out to heal his battle-worn companions.
	Chanting a song of glory, a dwarf swings his axe in wide swaths to cut through the ranks of orcs arrayed against him, shouting praise to the gods with every foe's fall.
	Calling down a curse upon the forces of undeath, a human lifts her holy symbol as light pours from it to drive back the zombies crowding in on her companions.
	Clerics are intermediaries between the mortal world and the distant planes of the gods. As varied as the gods they serve, clerics strive to embody the handiwork of their deities. No ordinary priest, a cleric is imbued with divine magic.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 56</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Healers and Warriors</name>
      <text>Divine magic, as the name suggests, is the power of the gods, flowing from them into the world. Clerics are conduits for that power, manifesting it as miraculous effects. The gods don't grant this power to everyone who seeks it, but only to those chosen to fulfill a high calling.
	Harnessing divine magic doesn't rely on study or training. A cleric might learn formulaic prayers and ancient rites, but the ability to cast cleric spells relies on devotion and an intuitive sense of a deity's wishes.
	Clerics combine the helpful magic of healing and inspiring their allies with spells that harm and hinder foes. They can provoke awe and dread, lay curses of plague or poison, and even call down flames from heaven to consume their enemies. For those evildoers who will benefit most from a mace to the head, clerics depend on their combat training to let them wade into melee with the power of the gods on their side.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Divine Agents</name>
      <text>Not every acolyte or officiant at a temple or shrine is a cleric. Some priests are called to a simple life of temple service, carrying out their gods' will through prayer and sacrifice, not by magic and strength of arms. In some cities, priesthood amounts to a political office, viewed as a stepping stone to higher positions of authority and involving no communion with a god at all. True clerics are rare in most hierarchies.
	When a cleric takes up an adventuring life, it is usually because his or her god demands it. Pursuing the goals of the gods often involves braving dangers beyond the walls of civilization, smiting evil or seeking holy relics in ancient tombs. Many clerics are also expected to protect their deities' worshipers, which can mean fighting rampaging orcs, negotiating peace between warring nations, or sealing a portal that would allow a demon prince to enter the world.
	Most adventuring clerics maintain some connection to established temples and orders of their faiths. A temple might ask for a cleric's aid, or a high priest might be in a position to demand it.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creating a Cleric</name>
      <text>As you create a cleric, the most important question to consider is which deity to serve and what principles you want your character to embody. Appendix B includes lists of many of the gods of the multiverse. Check with your DM to learn which deities are in your campaign.
	Once you've chosen a deity, consider your cleric's relationship to that god. Did you enter this service willingly? Or did the god choose you, impelling you into service with no regard for your wishes? How do the temple priests of your faith regard you: as a champion or a troublemaker? What are your ultimate goals? Does your deity have a special task in mind for you? Or are you striving to prove yourself worthy of a great quest?

Quick Build:
You can make a cleric quickly by following these suggestions. First, Wisdom should be your highest ability score, followed by Strength or Constitution. Second, choose the acolyte background.</text>
    </trait>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Starting Cleric</name>
        <text>As a 1st-level Cleric, you begin play with 8 + your Constitution modifier hit points.

You are proficient with the following items, in addition to any proficiencies provided by your race or background.

	• Armor: light armor, medium armor, shields
	• Weapons: simple weapons
	• Tools: none
	• Skills: Choose 2 from History, Insight, Medicine, Persuasion, Religion

You begin play with the following equipment, in addition to any equipment provided by your background.

	• (a) a mace or (b) a warhammer (if proficient)
	• (a) scale mail, (b) leather armor, or (c) chain mail (if proficient)
	• (a) a light crossbow and Crossbow Bolts (20) or (b) any simple weapon
	• (a) a priest's pack or (b) an explorer's pack
	• A shield and a holy symbol

If you forgo this starting equipment, as well as the items offered by your background, you start with 5d4 × 10 gp to buy your equipment.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Multiclass Cleric</name>
        <text>If your group uses the optional rule on multiclassing in the Player's Handbook, here's what you need to know if you choose cleric as one of your classes.

Ability Score Minimum:
As a multiclass character, you must have at least the following ability score(s) to take a level in this class, or to take a level in another class if you are already a cleric.

	• Wisdom 13

Proficiencies Gained:
When you gain your first level in a class other than your initial class, you gain only some of your new class's starting proficiencies, here are the proficiencies you gain when you take your first level as a cleric.

	• Armor: light armor, medium armor, shields
	• Weapons: none
	• Tools: none

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 163</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Multiclass Features</name>
        <text>When you gain a new level in a class, you get its features for that level. You don't, however, receive the class's starting equipment, and a few features have additional rules when you're multiclassing: Channel Divinity, Extra Attack, Unarmored Defense, and Spellcasting.

Channel Divinity:
If you already have the Channel Divinity feature and gain a level in a class that also grants the feature, you gain the Channel Divinity effects granted by that class, but getting the feature again doesn't give you an additional use of it. You gain additional uses only when you reach a class level that explicitly grants them to you. For example, if you are a cleric 6/paladin 4, you can use Channel Divinity twice between rests because you are high enough level in the cleric class to have more uses. Whenever you use the feature, you can choose any of the Channel Divinity effects available to you from your two classes.

Extra Attack:
If you gain the Extra Attack class feature from more than one class, the features don't add together. You can't make more than two attacks with this feature unless it says you do (as the fighter's version of Extra Attack does).
	Similarly, the warlock's eldritch invocation Thirsting Blade doesn't give you additional attacks if you also have Extra Attack.

Unarmored Defense:
If you already have the Unarmored Defense feature, you can't gain it again from another class.

Spellcasting:
Your capacity for spellcasting depends partly on your combined levels in all your spellcasting classes and partly on your individual levels in those classes. Once you have the Spellcasting feature from more than one class, use the rules below. If you multiclass but have the Spellcasting feature from only one class, you follow the rules as described in that class.

Spells Known and Prepared:
You determine what spells you know and can prepare for each class individually, as if you were a single-classed member of that class. If you are a ranger 4/wizard 3, for example, you know three 1 st-level ranger spells based on your levels in the ranger class. As a 3rd-level wizard, you know three wizard cantrips, and your spellbook contains ten wizard spells, two of which (the two you gained when you reached 3rd level as a wizard) can be 2nd-level spells. If your Intelligence is 16, you can prepare six wizard spells from your spellbook.
	Each spell you know and prepare is associated with one of your classes, and you use the spell casting ability of that class when you cast the spell. Similarly, a spellcasting focus, such as a holy symbol, can be used only for the spells from the class associated with that focus.
	If a cantrip of yours increases in power at higher levels, the increase is based on your character level, not your level in a particular class.

Spell Slots:
You determine your available spell slots by adding together all your levels in the bard, cleric, druid, sorcerer, and wizard classes, half your levels (rounded down) in the paladin and ranger classes, and a third of your fighter or rogue levels (rounded down) if you have the Eldritch Knight or the Arcane Trickster feature. Use this total to determine your spell slots by consulting the Multiclass Spellcaster table.
	If you have more than one spellcasting class, this table might give you spell slots of a level that is higher than the spells you know or can prepare. You can use those slots, but only to cast your lower-level spells. If a lower level spell that you cast, like burning hands, has an enhanced effect when cast using a higher-level slot, you can use the enhanced effect, even though you don't have any spells of that higher level.
	For example, if you are the aforementioned ranger 4/ wizard 3, you count as a 5th-level character when determining your spell slots: you have four 1st-level slots, three 2nd-level slots, and two 3rd-level slots. However, you don't know any 3rd-level spells, nor do you know any 2nd-level ranger spells. You can use the spell slots of those levels to cast the spells you do know-and potentially enhance their effects.

Pact Magic:
If you have both the Spellcasting class feature and the Pact Magic class feature from the warlock class, you can use the spell slots you gain from the Pact Magic feature to cast spells you know or have prepared from classes with the Spellcasting class feature, and you can use the spell slots you gain from the Spellcasting class feature to cast warlock spells you know.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 164</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
        <text>As a conduit for divine power, you can cast cleric spells. See chapter 10 for the general rules of spellcasting and chapter 11 for a selection of cleric spells.

Cantrips:
At 1st level, you know three cantrips of your choice from the cleric spell list. You learn additional cleric cantrips of your choice at higher levels, as shown in the Cantrips Known column of the Cleric table.

Preparing and Casting Spells:
The Cleric table shows how many spell slots you have to cast your cleric spells of 1st level and higher. To cast one of these spells, you must expend a slot of the spell's level or higher. You regain all expended spell slots when you finish a long rest.
	You prepare the list of cleric spells that are available for you to cast, choosing from the cleric spell list. When you do so, choose a number of cleric spells equal to your Wisdom modifier + your cleric level (minimum of one spell). The spells must be of a level for which you have spell slots.
	For example, if you are a 3rd-level cleric, you have four 1st-level and two 2nd-level spell slots. With a Wisdom of 16, your list of prepared spells can include six spells of 1st or 2nd level, in any combination. If you prepare the 1st-level spell cure wounds, you can cast it using a 1st-level or 2nd-level slot. Casting the spell doesn't remove it from your list of prepared spells.
	You can change your list of prepared spells when you finish a long rest. Preparing a new list of cleric spells requires time spent in prayer and meditation: at least 1 minute per spell level for each spell on your list.

Spellcasting Ability:
Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for your cleric spells. The power of your spells comes from your devotion to your deity. You use your Wisdom whenever a cleric spell refers to your spellcasting ability. In addition, you use your Wisdom modifier when setting the saving throw DC for a cleric spell you cast and when making an attack roll with one.

	Spell save DC = 8 + Wisdom modifier + Proficiency Bonus

	Spell attack modifier = Wisdom modifier + Proficiency Bonus

Ritual Casting:
You can cast a cleric spell as a ritual if that spell has the ritual tag and you have the spell prepared.

Spellcasting Focus:
You can use a holy symbol as a spellcasting focus for your cleric spells.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Divine Domain</name>
        <text>Choose one domain related to your deity from the list of available domains. Each domain is detailed in their own feature, and each one provides examples of gods associated with it. Your choice grants you domain spells and other features when you choose it at 1st level. It also grants you additional ways to use Channel Divinity when you gain that feature at 2nd level, and additional benefits at 6th, 8th, and 17th levels.

Domain Spells:
Each domain has a list of spells—its domain spells—that you gain at the cleric levels noted in the domain description. Once you gain a domain spell, you always have it prepared, and it doesn't count against the number of spells you can prepare each day.
	If you have a domain spell that doesn't appear on the cleric spell list, the spell is nonetheless a cleric spell for you.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature>
        <name>Channel Divinity (1/rest)</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you gain the ability to channel divine energy directly from your deity, using that energy to fuel magical effects. You start with two such effects: Turn Undead and an effect determined by your domain. Some domains grant you additional effects as you advance in levels, as noted in the domain description.
	When you use your Channel Divinity, you choose which effect to create. You must then finish a short or long rest to use your Channel Divinity again.
	Some Channel Divinity effects require saving throws. When you use such an effect from this class, the DC equals your cleric spell save DC.
	Beginning at 6th level, you can use your Channel Divinity twice between rests, and beginning at 18th level, you can use it three times between rests. When you finish a short or long rest, you regain your expended uses.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain Feature</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you gain a feature from your Divine Domain.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Channel Divinity: Turn Undead</name>
        <text>As an action, you present your holy symbol and speak a prayer censuring the undead. Each undead that can see or hear you within 30 feet of you must make a Wisdom saving throw. If the creature fails its saving throw, it is turned for 1 minute or until it takes any damage.
	A turned creature must spend its turns trying to move as far away from you as it can, and it can't willingly move to a space within 30 feet of you. It also can't take reactions. For its action, it can use only the Dash action or try to escape from an effect that prevents it from moving. If there's nowhere to move, the creature can use the Dodge action.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 59</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Channel Divinity</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 4th level, and again at 8th, 12th, 16th, and 19th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
      <feature>
        <name>Destroy Undead (CR 1/2)</name>
        <text>Starting at 5th level, when an undead of CR 1/2 or lower fails its saving throw against your Turn Undead feature, the creature is instantly destroyed.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature>
        <name>Channel Divinity (2/rest)</name>
        <text>Beginning at 6th level, you can use your Channel Divinity twice between rests.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain Feature</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain a feature from your Divine Domain.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Channel Divinity</name>
        <value>2</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 8th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Destroy Undead (CR 1)</name>
        <text>Starting at 8th level, when an undead of CR 1 or lower fails its saving throw against your Turn Undead feature, the creature is instantly destroyed.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain Feature</name>
        <text>At 8th level, you gain a feature from your Divine Domain.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature>
        <name>Divine Intervention</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, you can call on your deity to intervene on your behalf when your need is great.
	Imploring your deity's aid requires you to use your action. Describe the assistance you seek, and roll percentile dice. If you roll a number equal to or lower than your cleric level, your deity intervenes. The DM chooses the nature of the intervention; the effect of any cleric spell or cleric domain spell would be appropriate.
	If your deity intervenes, you can't use this feature again for 7 days. Otherwise, you can use it again after you finish a long rest.
	At 20th level, your call for intervention succeeds automatically, no roll required.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 59</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature>
        <name>Destroy Undead (CR 2)</name>
        <text>Starting at 11th level, when an undead of CR 2 or lower or lower fails its saving throw against your Turn Undead feature, the creature is instantly destroyed.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 12th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature>
        <name>Destroy Undead (CR 3)</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, when an undead of CR 3 or lower fails its saving throw against your Turn Undead feature, the creature is instantly destroyed.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 16th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature>
        <name>Destroy Undead (CR 4)</name>
        <text>Starting at 17th level, when an undead of CR 4 or lower fails its saving throw against your Turn Undead feature, the creature is instantly destroyed.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain Feature</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you gain a feature from your Divine Domain.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature>
        <name>Channel Divinity (3/rest)</name>
        <text>Beginning at 18th level, you can use your Channel Divinity three times between rests.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Channel Divinity</name>
        <value>3</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 19th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
      <feature>
        <name>Divine Intervention Improvement</name>
        <text>At 20th level, your call for intervention succeeds automatically, no roll required.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 58</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Divine Domain: Knowledge Domain -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain: Knowledge Domain</name>
        <text>The gods of knowledge—including Oghma, Boccob, Gilean, Aureon, and Thoth—value learning and understanding above all. Some teach that knowledge is to be gathered and shared in libraries and universities, or promote the practical knowledge of craft and invention. Some deities hoard knowledge and keep its secrets to themselves. And some promise their followers that they will gain tremendous power if they unlock the secrets of the multiverse. Followers of these gods study esoteric lore, collect old tomes, delve into the secret places of the earth, and learn all they can. Some gods of knowledge promote the practical knowledge of craft and invention, including smith deities like Gond, Reorx, Onatar, Moradin, Hephaestus, and Goibhniu.

Domain Spells:
At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared. They do not count towards your limit.

Knowledge Domain Spells:
Cleric Level | Spells
1st | command, identify
3rd | augury, suggestion
5th | nondetection, speak with dead
7th | arcane eye, confusion
9th | legend lore, scrying

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 59</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Blessings of Knowledge (Knowledge Domain)</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you learn two languages of your choice. You also become proficient in your choice of two of the following skills: Arcana, History, Nature, or Religion.
	Your proficiency bonus is doubled for any ability check you make that uses either of those skills.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 59</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Knowledge of the Ages (Knowledge Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can use your Channel Divinity to tap into a divine well of knowledge. As an action, you choose one skill or tool. For 10 minutes, you have proficiency with the chosen skill or tool.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 59</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Read Thoughts (Knowledge Domain)</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you can use your Channel Divinity to read a creature's thoughts. You can then use your access to the creature's mind to command it.
	As an action, choose one creature that you can see within 60 feet of you. That creature must make a Wisdom saving throw. If the creature succeeds on the saving throw, you can't use this feature on it again until you finish a long rest.
	If the creature fails its save, you can read its surface thoughts (those foremost in its mind, reflecting its current emotions and what it is actively thinking about) when it is within 60 feet of you. This effect lasts for 1 minute.
	During that time, you can use your action to end this effect and cast the suggestion spell on the creature without expending a spell slot. The target automatically fails its saving throw against the spell.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 59</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Potent Spellcasting (Knowledge Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 8th level, you add your Wisdom modifier to the damage you deal with any cleric cantrip.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 59</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Visions of the Past (Knowledge Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 17th level, you can call up visions of the past that relate to an object you hold or your immediate surroundings. You spend at least 1 minute in meditation and prayer, then receive dreamlike, shadowy glimpses of recent events. You can meditate in this way for a number of minutes equal to your Wisdom score and must maintain concentration during that time, as if you were casting a spell.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.

Object Reading. Holding an object as you meditate, you can see visions of the object's previous owner. After meditating for 1 minute, you learn how the owner acquired and lost the object, as well as the most recent significant event involving the object and that owner. If the object was owned by another creature in the recent past (within a number of days equal to your Wisdom score), you can spend 1 additional minute for each owner to learn the same information about that creature.

Area Reading. As you meditate, you see visions of recent events in your immediate vicinity (a room, street, tunnel, clearing, or the like, up to a 50-foot cube), going back a number of days equal to your Wisdom score. For each minute you meditate, you learn about one significant event, beginning with the most recent. Significant events typically involve powerful emotions, such as battles and betrayals, marriages and murders, births and funerals. However, they might also include more mundane events that are nevertheless important in your current situation.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 60</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Divine Domain: Life Domain -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain: Life Domain</name>
        <text>The Life domain focuses on the vibrant positive energy—one of the fundamental forces of the universe—that sustains all life. The gods of life promote vitality and health through healing the sick and wounded, caring for those in need, and driving away the forces of death and undeath. Almost any non-evil deity can claim influence over this domain, particularly agricultural deities (such as Chauntea, Arawai, and Demeter), sun gods (such as Lathander, Pelor, and Re-Horakhty), gods of healing or endurance (such as Ilmater, Mishakal, Apollo, and Diancecht), and gods of home and community (such as Hestia, Hathor, and Boldrei).

Domain Spells:
At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared. They do not count towards your limit.

Life Domain Spells:
Cleric Level | Spells
1st | bless, cure wounds
3rd | lesser restoration, spiritual weapon
5th | beacon of hope, revivify
7th | death ward, guardian of faith
9th | mass cure wounds, raise dead

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 60</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bonus Proficiency (Life Domain)</name>
        <text>When you choose this domain at 1st level, you gain proficiency with heavy armor.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 60</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Disciple of Life (Life Domain)</name>
        <text>Also starting at 1st level, your healing spells are more effective. Whenever you use a spell of 1st level or higher to restore hit points to a creature, the creature regains additional hit points equal to 2 + the spell's level.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 60</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Preserve Life (Life Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can use your Channel Divinity to heal the badly injured.
	As an action, you present your holy symbol and evoke healing energy that can restore a number of hit points equal to five times your cleric level. Choose any creatures within 30 feet of you, and divide those hit points among them. This feature can restore a creature to no more than half of its hit point maximum. You can't use this feature on an undead or a construct.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 60</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Blessed Healer (Life Domain)</name>
        <text>Beginning at 6th level, the healing spells you cast on others heal you as well. When you cast a spell of 1st level or higher that restores hit points to a creature other than you, you regain hit points equal to 2 + the spell's level.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 60</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Strike (Life Domain)</name>
        <text>At 8th level, you gain the ability to infuse your weapon strikes with divine energy. Once on each of your turns when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can cause the attack to deal an extra 1d8 radiant damage to the target. When you reach 14th level, the extra damage increases to 2d8.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 60</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Supreme Healing (Life Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 17th level, when you would normally roll one or more dice to restore hit points with a spell, you instead use the highest number possible for each die. For example, instead of restoring 2d6 hit points to a creature, you restore 12.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 60</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Divine Domain: Light Domain -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain: Light Domain</name>
        <text>Gods of light—including Helm, Lathander, Pholtus, Branchala, the Silver Flame, Belenus, Apollo, and Re-Horakhty—promote the ideals of rebirth and renewal, truth, vigilance, and beauty, often using the symbol of the sun. Some of these gods are portrayed as the sun itself or as a charioteer who guides the sun across the sky. Others are tireless sentinels whose eyes pierce every shadow and see through every deception. Some are deities of beauty and artistry, who teach that art is a vehicle for the soul's improvement. Clerics of a god of light are enlightened souls infused with radiance and the power of their gods' discerning vision, charged with chasing away lies and burning away darkness.

Domain Spells:
At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared. They do not count towards your limit.

Light Domain Spells:
Cleric Level | Spells
1st | burning hands, faerie fire
3rd | flaming sphere, scorching ray
5th | daylight, fireball
7th | guardian of faith, wall of fire
9th | flame strike, scrying

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 60</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bonus Cantrip (Light Domain)</name>
        <text>When you choose this domain at 1st level, you gain the light cantrip if you don't already know it.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 61</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Warding Flare (Light Domain)</name>
        <text>Also at 1st level, you can interpose divine light between yourself and an attacking enemy. When you are attacked by a creature within 30 feet of you that you can see, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on the attack roll, causing light to flare before the attacker before it hits or misses. An attacker that can't be blinded is immune to this feature.
	You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 61</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Radiance of the Dawn (Light Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can use your Channel Divinity to harness sunlight, banishing darkness and dealing radiant damage to your foes.
	As an action, you present your holy symbol, and any magical darkness within 30 feet of you is dispelled. Additionally, each hostile creature within 30 feet of you must make a Constitution saving throw. A creature takes radiant damage equal to 2d10 + your cleric level on a failed saving throw, and half as much damage on a successful one. A creature that has total cover from you is not affected.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 61</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Improved Flare (Light Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can also use your Warding Flare feature when a creature that you can see within 30 feet of you attacks a creature other than you.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 61</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Potent Spellcasting (Light Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 8th level, you add your Wisdom modifier to the damage you deal with any cleric cantrip.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 60</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Corona of Light (Light Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 17th level, you can use your action to activate an aura of sunlight that lasts for 1 minute or until you dismiss it using another action. You emit bright light in a 60-foot radius and dim light 30 feet beyond that. Your enemies in the bright light have disadvantage on saving throws against any spell that deals fire or radiant damage.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 61</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Divine Domain: Nature Domain -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain: Nature Domain</name>
        <text>Gods of nature are as varied as the natural world itself, from inscrutable gods of the deep forests (such as Silvanus, Obad-Hai, Chislev, Balinor, and Pan) to friendly deities associated with particular springs and groves (such as Eldath). Druids revere nature as a whole and might serve one of these deities, practicing mysterious rites and reciting all-but-forgotten prayers in their own secret tongue. But many of these gods have clerics as well, champions who take a more active role in advancing the interests of a particular nature god. These clerics might hunt the evil monstrosities that despoil the woodlands, bless the harvest of the faithful, or wither the crops of those who anger their gods.

Domain Spells:
At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared. They do not count towards your limit.

Nature Domain Spells:
Cleric Level | Spells
1st | animal friendship, speak with animals
3rd | barkskin, spike growth
5th | plant growth, wind wall
7th | dominate beast, grasping vine
9th | insect plague, tree stride

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 61</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Acolyte of Nature (Nature Domain)</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you learn one druid cantrip of your choice. This cantrip counts as a cleric cantrip for you, but it doesn't count against the number of cleric cantrips you know. You also gain proficiency in one of the following skills of your choice: Animal Handling, Nature, or Survival.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bonus Proficiency (Nature Domain)</name>
        <text>Also at 1st level, you gain proficiency with heavy armor.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Charm Animals and Plants (Nature Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can use your Channel Divinity to charm animals and plants.
	As an action, you present your holy symbol and invoke the name of your deity. Each beast or plant creature that can see you within 30 feet of you must make a Wisdom saving throw. If the creature fails its saving throw, it is charmed by you for 1 minute or until it takes damage. While it is charmed by you, it is friendly to you and other creatures you designate.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Dampen Elements (Nature Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, when you or a creature within 30 feet of you takes acid, cold, fire, lightning, or thunder damage, you can use your reaction to grant resistance to the creature against that instance of the damage.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Strike (Nature Domain)</name>
        <text>At 8th level, you gain the ability to infuse your weapon strikes with divine energy. Once on each of your turns when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can cause the attack to deal an extra 1d8 cold, fire, or lightning damage (your choice) to the target. When you reach 14th level, the extra damage increases to 2d8.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 61</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Master of Nature (Nature Domain)</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you gain the ability to command animals and plant creatures. While creatures are charmed by your Charm Animals and Plants feature, you can take a bonus action on your turn to verbally command what each of those creatures will do on its next turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Divine Domain: Tempest Domain -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain: Tempest Domain</name>
        <text>Gods whose portfolios include the Tempest domain—including Talos, Umberlee, Kord, Zeboim, the Devourer, Zeus, and Thor—govern storms, sea, and sky. They include gods of lightning and thunder, gods of earthquakes, some fire gods, and certain gods of violence, physical strength, and courage. In some pantheons, a god of this domain rules over other deities and is known for swift justice delivered by thunderbolts. In the pantheons of seafaring people, gods of this domain are ocean deities and the patrons of sailors. Tempest gods send their clerics to inspire fear in the common folk, either to keep those folk on the path of righteousness or to encourage them to offer sacrifices of propitiation to ward off divine wrath.

Domain Spells:
At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared. They do not count towards your limit.

Tempest Domain Spells:
Cleric Level | Spells
1st | fog cloud, thunderwave
3rd | gust of wind, shatter
5th | call lightning, sleet storm
7th | control water, ice storm
9th | destructive wave, insect plague

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bonus Proficiencies (Tempest Domain)</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you gain proficiency with martial weapons and heavy armor.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Wrath of the Storm (Tempest Domain)</name>
        <text>Also at 1st level, you can thunderously rebuke attackers. When a creature within 5 feet of you that you can see hits you with an attack, you can use your reaction to cause the creature to make a Dexterity saving throw. The creature takes 2d8 lightning or thunder damage (your choice) on a failed saving throw, and half as much damage on a successful one.
	You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Destructive Wrath (Tempest Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can use your Channel Divinity to wield the power of the storm with unchecked ferocity.
	When you roll lightning or thunder damage, you can use your Channel Divinity to deal maximum damage, instead of rolling.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Thunderbolt Strike (Tempest Domain)</name>
        <text>At 6th level, when you deal lightning damage to a Large or smaller creature, you can also push it up to 10 feet away from you.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Strike (Tempest Domain)</name>
        <text>At 8th level, you gain the ability to infuse your weapon strikes with divine energy. Once on each of your turns when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can cause the attack to deal an extra 1d8 thunder damage to the target. When you reach 14th level, the extra damage increases to 2d8.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Stormborn (Tempest Domain)</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you have a flying speed equal to your current walking speed whenever you are not underground or indoors.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Divine Domain: Trickery Domain -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain: Trickery Domain</name>
        <text>Gods of trickery—such as Tymora, Beshaba, Olidammara, the Traveler, Garl Glittergold, and Loki—are mischief-makers and instigators who stand as a constant challenge to the accepted order among both gods and mortals. They're patrons of thieves, scoundrels, gamblers, rebels, and liberators. Their clerics are a disruptive force in the world, puncturing pride, mocking tyrants, stealing from the rich, freeing captives, and flouting hollow traditions. They prefer subterfuge, pranks, deception, and theft rather than direct confrontation.

Domain Spells:
At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared. They do not count towards your limit.

Trickery Domain Spells:
Cleric Level | Spells
1st | charm person, disguise self
3rd | mirror image, pass without trace
5th | blink, dispel magic
7th | dimension door, polymorph
9th | dominate person, modify memory

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Blessing of the Trickster (Trickery Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this domain at 1st level, you can use your action to touch a willing creature other than yourself to give it advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks. This blessing lasts for 1 hour or until you use this feature again.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Invoke Duplicity (Trickery Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can use your Channel Divinity to create an illusory duplicate of yourself.
	As an action, you create a perfect illusion of yourself that lasts for 1 minute, or until you lose your concentration (as if you were concentrating on a spell). The illusion appears in an unoccupied space that you can see within 30 feet of you. As a bonus action on your turn, you can move the illusion up to 30 feet to a space you can see, but it must remain within 120 feet of you.
	For the duration, you can cast spells as though you were in the illusion's space, but you must use your own senses. Additionally, when both you and your illusion are within 5 feet of a creature that can see the illusion, you have advantage on attack rolls against that creature, given how distracting the illusion is to the target.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 63</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Cloak of Shadows (Trickery Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can use your Channel Divinity to vanish.
	As an action, you become invisible until the end of your next turn. You become visible if you attack or cast a spell.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 63</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Strike (Trickery Domain)</name>
        <text>At 8th level, you gain the ability to infuse your weapon strikes with poison—a gift from your deity. Once on each of your turns when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can cause the attack to deal an extra 1d8 poison damage to the target. When you reach 14th level, the extra damage increases to 2d8.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 63</text>
        <roll description="Poison Damage" level="8">1d8</roll>
        <roll description="Poison Damage" level="14">2d8</roll>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Improved Duplicity (Trickery Domain)</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you can create up to four duplicates of yourself, instead of one, when you use Invoke Duplicity. As a bonus action on your turn, you can move any number of them up to 30 feet, to a maximum range of 120 feet.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 62</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Divine Domain: War Domain -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain: War Domain</name>
        <text>War has many manifestations. It can make heroes of ordinary people. It can be desperate and horrific, with acts of cruelty and cowardice eclipsing instances of excellence and courage. In either case, the gods of war watch over warriors and reward them for their great deeds. The clerics of such gods excel in battle, inspiring others to fight the good fight or offering acts of violence as prayers. Gods of war include champions of honor and chivalry (such as Torm, Heironeous, and Kiri-Jolith) as well as gods of destruction and pillage (such as Erythnul, the Fury, Gruumsh, and Ares) and gods of conquest and domination (such as Bane, Hextor, and Maglubiyet). Other war gods (such as Tempus, Nike, and Nuada) take a more neutral stance, promoting war in all its manifestations and supporting warriors in any circumstance.

Domain Spells:
At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared. They do not count towards your limit.

War Domain Spells:
Cleric Level | Spells
1st | divine favor, shield of faith
3rd | magic weapon, spiritual weapon
5th | crusader's mantle, spirit guardians
7th | freedom of movement, stoneskin
9th | flame strike, hold monster

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 63</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bonus Proficiencies (War Domain)</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you gain proficiency with martial weapons and heavy armor.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 63</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>War Priest (War Domain)</name>
        <text>From 1st level, your god delivers bolts of inspiration to you while you are engaged in battle. When you use the Attack action, you can make one weapon attack as a bonus action.
	You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 63</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Guided Strike (War Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can use your Channel Divinity to strike with supernatural accuracy. When you make an attack roll, you can use your Channel Divinity to gain a +10 bonus to the roll. You make this choice after you see the roll, but before the DM says whether the attack hits or misses.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 63</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: War God's Blessing (War Domain)</name>
        <text>At 6th level, when a creature within 30 feet of you makes an attack roll, you can use your reaction to grant that creature a +10 bonus to the roll, using your Channel Divinity. You make this choice after you see the roll, but before the DM says whether the attack hits or misses.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 63</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Strike (War Domain)</name>
        <text>At 8th level, you gain the ability to infuse your weapon strikes with divine energy. Once on each of your turns when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can cause the attack to deal an extra 1d8 damage of the same type dealt by the weapon to the target. When you reach 14th level, the extra damage increases to 2d8.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 63</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Avatar of Battle (War Domain)</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you gain resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage from nonmagical weapons.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 63</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
