<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Barbarian</name>
    <hd>12</hd>
    <proficiency>Strength, Constitution, Animal Handling, Athletics, Intimidation, Nature, Perception, Survival</proficiency>
    <numSkills>2</numSkills>
    <armor>Light Armor, Medium Armor, Shields</armor>
    <weapons>Simple Weapons, Martial Weapons</weapons>
    <tools>None</tools>
    <wealth>2d4x10</wealth>
    <slotsReset>L</slotsReset>
    <trait>
      <name>Barbarian</name>
      <text>A tall human tribesman strides through a blizzard, draped in fur and hefting his axe. He laughs as he charges toward the frost giant who dared poach his people's elk herd.
	A half-orc snarls at the latest challenger to her authority over their savage tribe, ready to break his neck with her bare hands as she did to the last six rivals.
	Frothing at the mouth, a dwarf slams his helmet into the face of his drow foe, then turns to drive his armored elbow into the gut of another.
These barbarians, different as they might be, are defined by their rage: unbridled, unquenchable, and unthinking fury. More than a mere emotion, their anger is the ferocity of a cornered predator, the unrelenting assault of a storm, the churning turmoil of the sea.
	For some, their rage springs from a communion with fierce animal spirits. Others draw from a roiling reservoir of anger at a world full of pain. For every barbarian, rage is a power that fuels not just a battle frenzy but also uncanny reflexes, resilience, and feats of strength.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 46</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Primal Instinct</name>
      <text>People of towns and cities take pride in how their civilized ways set them apart from animals, as if denying one's own nature was a mark of superiority. To a barbarian, though, civilization is no virtue, but a sign of weakness. The strong embrace their animal nature — keen instincts, primal physicality, and ferocious rage. Barbarians are uncomfortable when hedged in by walls and crowds. They thrive in the wilds of their homelands: the tundra, jungle, or grasslands where their tribes live and hunt.
	Barbarians come alive in the chaos of combat. They can enter a berserk state where rage takes over, giving them superhuman strength and resilience. A barbarian can draw on this reservoir of fury only a few times without resting, but those few rages are usually sufficient to defeat whatever threats arise.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>A Life of Danger</name>
      <text>Not every member of the tribes deemed "barbarians" by scions of civilized society has the barbarian class. A true barbarian among these people is as uncommon as a skilled fighter in a town, and he or she plays a similar role as a protector of the people and a leader in times of war. Life in the wild places of the world is fraught with peril: rival tribes, deadly weather, and terrifying monsters. Barbarians charge headlong into that danger so that their people don't have to.
	Their courage in the face of danger makes barbarians perfectly suited for adventuring. Wandering is often a way of life for their native tribes, and the rootless life of the adventurer is little hardship for a barbarian. Some barbarians miss the close-knit family structures of the tribe, but eventually find them replaced by the bonds formed among the members of their adventuring parties.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Creating a Barbarian</name>
      <text>When creating a barbarian character, think about where your character comes from and his or her place in the world. Talk with your DM about an appropriate origin for your barbarian. Did you come from a distant land, making you a stranger in the area of the campaign? Or is the campaign set in a rough-and-tumble frontier where barbarians are common?
	What led you to take up the adventuring life? Were you lured to settled lands by the promise of riches? Did you join forces with soldiers of those lands to face a shared threat? Did monsters or an invading horde drive you out of your homeland, making you a rootless refugee? Perhaps you were a prisoner of war, brought in chains to "civilized" lands and only now able to win your freedom. Or you might have been cast out from your people because of a crime you committed, a taboo you violated, or a coup that removed you from a position of authority.

Quick Build:
You can make a barbarian quickly by following these suggestions. First, put your highest ability score in Strength, followed by Constitution. Second, choose the outlander background.</text>
    </trait>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Starting Barbarian</name>
        <text>As a 1st-level Barbarian, you begin play with 12 + your Constitution modifier hit points.

You are proficient with the following items, in addition to any proficiencies provided by your race or background.

	• Armor: light armor, medium armor, shields
	• Weapons: simple weapons, martial weapons
	• Tools: none
	• Skills: Choose 2 from Animal Handling, Athletics, Intimidation, Nature, Perception and Survival

You begin play with the following equipment, in addition to any equipment provided by your background.

	• (a) a greataxe or (b) any martial melee weapon
	• (a) two handaxes or (b) any simple weapon
	• An explorer's pack, and four javelins

If you forgo this starting equipment, as well as the items offered by your background, you start with 2d4 × 10 gp to buy your equipment.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 48</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Multiclass Barbarian</name>
        <text>If your group uses the optional rule on multiclassing in the Player's Handbook, here's what you need to know if you choose barbarian as one of your classes.

Ability Score Minimum:
As a multiclass character, you must have at least the following ability score(s) to take a level in this class, or to take a level in another class if you are already a barbarian.

	• Strength 13

Proficiencies Gained:
When you gain your first level in a class other than your initial class, you gain only some of your new class's starting proficiencies, here are the proficiencies you gain when you take your first level as a barbarian.

	• Armor: shields
	• Weapons: simple weapons, martial weapons
	• Tools: none

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 163</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Multiclass Features</name>
        <text>When you gain a new level in a class, you get its features for that level. You don't, however, receive the class's starting equipment, and a few features have additional rules when you're multiclassing: Channel Divinity, Extra Attack, Unarmored Defense, and Spellcasting.

Channel Divinity:
If you already have the Channel Divinity feature and gain a level in a class that also grants the feature, you gain the Channel Divinity effects granted by that class, but getting the feature again doesn't give you an additional use of it. You gain additional uses only when you reach a class level that explicitly grants them to you. For example, if you are a cleric 6/paladin 4, you can use Channel Divinity twice between rests because you are high enough level in the cleric class to have more uses. Whenever you use the feature, you can choose any of the Channel Divinity effects available to you from your two classes.

Extra Attack:
If you gain the Extra Attack class feature from more than one class, the features don't add together. You can't make more than two attacks with this feature unless it says you do (as the fighter's version of Extra Attack does).
	Similarly, the warlock's eldritch invocation Thirsting Blade doesn't give you additional attacks if you also have Extra Attack.

Unarmored Defense:
If you already have the Unarmored Defense feature, you can't gain it again from another class.

Spellcasting:
Your capacity for spellcasting depends partly on your combined levels in all your spellcasting classes and partly on your individual levels in those classes. Once you have the Spellcasting feature from more than one class, use the rules below. If you multiclass but have the Spellcasting feature from only one class, you follow the rules as described in that class.

Spells Known and Prepared:
You determine what spells you know and can prepare for each class individually, as if you were a single-classed member of that class. If you are a ranger 4/wizard 3, for example, you know three 1 st-level ranger spells based on your levels in the ranger class. As a 3rd-level wizard, you know three wizard cantrips, and your spellbook contains ten wizard spells, two of which (the two you gained when you reached 3rd level as a wizard) can be 2nd-level spells. If your Intelligence is 16, you can prepare six wizard spells from your spellbook.
	Each spell you know and prepare is associated with one of your classes, and you use the spell casting ability of that class when you cast the spell. Similarly, a spellcasting focus, such as a holy symbol, can be used only for the spells from the class associated with that focus.
	If a cantrip of yours increases in power at higher levels, the increase is based on your character level, not your level in a particular class.

Spell Slots:
You determine your available spell slots by adding together all your levels in the bard, cleric, druid, sorcerer, and wizard classes, half your levels (rounded down) in the paladin and ranger classes, and a third of your fighter or rogue levels (rounded down) if you have the Eldritch Knight or the Arcane Trickster feature. Use this total to determine your spell slots by consulting the Multiclass Spellcaster table.
	If you have more than one spellcasting class, this table might give you spell slots of a level that is higher than the spells you know or can prepare. You can use those slots, but only to cast your lower-level spells. If a lower level spell that you cast, like burning hands, has an enhanced effect when cast using a higher-level slot, you can use the enhanced effect, even though you don't have any spells of that higher level.
	For example, if you are the aforementioned ranger 4/ wizard 3, you count as a 5th-level character when determining your spell slots: you have four 1st-level slots, three 2nd-level slots, and two 3rd-level slots. However, you don't know any 3rd-level spells, nor do you know any 2nd-level ranger spells. You can use the spell slots of those levels to cast the spells you do know-and potentially enhance their effects.

Pact Magic:
If you have both the Spellcasting class feature and the Pact Magic class feature from the warlock class, you can use the spell slots you gain from the Pact Magic feature to cast spells you know or have prepared from classes with the Spellcasting class feature, and you can use the spell slots you gain from the Spellcasting class feature to cast warlock spells you know.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 164</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Rage</name>
        <text>In battle, you fight with primal ferocity. On your turn, you can enter a rage as a bonus action.
	While raging, you gain the following benefits if you aren't wearing heavy armor:

	• You have advantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws.

	• When you make a melee weapon attack using Strength, you gain a bonus to the damage roll that increases as you gain levels as a barbarian. At 1st level, you have a +2 bonus to damage. Your bonus increases to +3 at 9th level and to +4 at 16th.

	• You have resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage.

If you are able to cast spells, you can't cast them or concentrate on them while raging.
	Your rage lasts for 1 minute. It ends early if you are knocked unconscious or if your turn ends and you haven't attacked a hostile creature since your last turn or taken damage since then. You can also end your rage on your turn as a bonus action.
	Once you have raged the maximum number of times for your barbarian level, you must finish a long rest before you can rage again. You may rage 2 times at 1st level, 3 at 3rd, 4 at 6th, 5 at 12th, and 6 at 17th.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 48</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Unarmored Defense</name>
        <text>While you are not wearing any armor, your Armor Class equals 10 + your Dexterity modifier + your Constitution modifier. You can use a shield and still gain this benefit.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 48</text>
        <special>Unarmored Defense: Constitution</special>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Rage</name>
        <value>2</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature>
        <name>Reckless Attack</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can throw aside all concern for defense to attack with fierce desperation. When you make your first attack on your turn, you can decide to attack recklessly. Doing so gives you advantage on melee weapon attack rolls using Strength during this turn, but attack rolls against you have advantage until your next turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 48</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Danger Sense</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you gain an uncanny sense of when things nearby aren't as they should be, giving you an edge when you dodge away from danger.
	You have advantage on Dexterity saving throws against effects that you can see, such as traps and spells. To gain this benefit, you can't be blinded, deafened, or incapacitated.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 48</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature>
        <name>Primal Path</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you choose a path that shapes the nature of your rage from the list of available paths. Your choice grants you features at 3rd level and again at 6th, 10th, and 14th levels.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 48</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Rage</name>
        <value>3</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 4th level, and again at 8th, 12th, 16th, and 19th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 49</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
      <feature>
        <name>Extra Attack</name>
        <text>Beginning at 5th level, you can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 49</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Fast Movement</name>
        <text>Starting at 5th level, your speed increases by 10 feet while you aren't wearing heavy armor.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 49</text>
        <modifier category="bonus">speed +10</modifier>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Path Feature</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain a feature from your Primal Path.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 46</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Rage</name>
        <value>4</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature>
        <name>Feral Instinct</name>
        <text>By 7th level, your instincts are so honed that you have advantage on initiative rolls.
	Additionally, if you are surprised at the beginning of combat and aren't incapacitated, you can act normally on your first turn, but only if you enter your rage before doing anything else on that turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 46</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 8th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM uses the optional Feats, you can instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 46</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <feature>
        <name>Brutal Critical (1 die)</name>
        <text>Beginning at 9th level, you can roll one additional weapon damage die when determining the extra damage for a critical hit with a melee attack.
	This increases to two additional dice at 13th level and three additional dice at 17th level.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 49</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Path Feature</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you gain a feature from your Primal Path.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 46</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature>
        <name>Relentless Rage</name>
        <text>Starting at 11th level, your rage can keep you fighting despite grievous wounds. If you drop to 0 hit points while you're raging and don't die outright, you can make a DC 10 Constitution saving throw. If you succeed, you drop to 1 hit point instead.
	Each time you use this feature after the first, the DC increases by 5. When you finish a short or long rest, the DC resets to 10.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 49</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 12th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM uses the optional Feats, you can instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 49</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Rage</name>
        <value>5</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <feature>
        <name>Brutal Critical (2 dice)</name>
        <text>At 13th level, you can roll two additional weapon damage dice when determining the extra damage for a critical hit with a melee attack.
	This increases to three additional dice at 17th level.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 46</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Path Feature</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain a feature from your Primal Path.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 46</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature>
        <name>Persistent Rage</name>
        <text>Beginning at 15th level, your rage is so fierce that it ends early only if you fall unconscious or if you choose to end it.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 49</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 16th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM uses the optional Feats, you can instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 49</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature>
        <name>Brutal Critical (3 dice)</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you can roll three additional weapon damage dice when determining the extra damage for a critical hit with a melee attack.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 46</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Rage</name>
        <value>6</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature>
        <name>Indomitable Might</name>
        <text>Beginning at 18th level, if your total for a Strength check is less than your Strength score, you can use that score in place of the total.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 46</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 19th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM uses the optional Feats, you can instead take a feat.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 46</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
      <feature>
        <name>Primal Champion</name>
        <text>At 20th level, you embody the power of the wilds. Your Strength and Constitution scores increase by 4. Your maximum for those scores is now 24.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 46</text>
        <modifier category="ability score">strength +4</modifier>
        <modifier category="ability score">constitution +4</modifier>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Primal Path: Path of the Berserker -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Primal Path: Path of the Berserker</name>
        <text>For some barbarians, rage is a means to an end | that end being violence. The Path of the Berserker is a path of untrammeled fury, slick with blood. As you enter the berserker's rage, you thrill in the chaos of battle, heedless of your own health or well-being.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 49</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Frenzy (Path of the Berserker)</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this path at 3rd level, you can go into a frenzy when you rage. If you do so, for the duration of your rage you can make a single melee weapon attack as a bonus action on each of your turns after this one. When your rage ends, you suffer one level of exhaustion.

Exhaustion:
Some special abilities and environmental hazards, such as starvation and the long-term effects of freezing or scorching temperatures, can lead to a special condition called exhaustion. Exhaustion is measured in six levels. An effect can give a creature one or more levels of exhaustion, as specified in the effect's description.

Exhaustion Levels:
Level | Effect
1 | Disadvantage on ability checks
2 | Speed halved
3 | Disadvantage on attack rolls and saving throws
4 | Hit point maximum halved
5 | Speed reduced to 0
6 | Death

If an already exhausted creature suffers another effect that causes exhaustion, its current level of exhaustion increases by the amount specified in the effect's description.
	A creature suffers the effect of its current level of exhaustion as well as all lower levels. For example, a creature suffering level 2 exhaustion has its speed halved and has disadvantage on ability checks.
	An effect that removes exhaustion reduces its level as specified in the effect's description, with all exhaustion effects ending if a creature's exhaustion level is reduced below 1.
	Finishing a long rest reduces a creature's exhaustion level by 1, provided that the creature has also ingested some food and drink. Also, being raised from the dead reduces a creature's exhaustion level by 1.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 49</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Mindless Rage (Path of the Berserker)</name>
        <text>Beginning at 6th level, you can't be charmed or frightened while raging. If you are charmed or frightened when you enter your rage, the effect is suspended for the duration of the rage.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 49</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Intimidating Presence (Path of the Berserker)</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, you can use your action to frighten someone with your menacing presence. When you do so, choose one creature that you can see within 30 feet of you. If the creature can see or hear you, it must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw (DC equal to 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Charisma modifier) or be frightened of you until the end of your next turn. On subsequent turns, you can use your action to extend the duration of this effect on the frightened creature until the end of your next turn. This effect ends if the creature ends its turn out of line of sight or more than 60 feet away from you.
	If the creature succeeds on its saving throw, you can't use this feature on that creature again for 24 hours.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 49</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Retaliation (Path of the Berserker)</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, when you take damage from a creature that is within 5 feet of you, you can use your reaction to make a melee weapon attack against that creature.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 49</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Primal Path: Path of the Totem Warrior -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Primal Path: Path of the Totem Warrior</name>
        <text>The Path of the Totem Warrior is a spiritual journey, as the barbarian accepts a spirit animal as guide, protector, and inspiration. In battle, your totem spirit fills you with supernatural might, adding magical fuel to your barbarian rage.
	Most barbarian tribes consider a totem animal to be kin to a particular clan. In such cases, it is unusual for an individual to have more than one totem animal spirit, though exceptions exist.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Spirit Seeker (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>Yours is a path that seeks attunement with the natural world, giving you a kinship with beasts. At 3rd level when you adopt this path, you gain the ability to cast the beast sense and speak with animals spells, but only as rituals, as described in chapter 10.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Totem Spirit (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, when you adopt this path, you choose a totem spirit and gain its feature. You must make or acquire a physical totem object—an amulet or similar adornment—that incorporates fur or feathers, claws, teeth, or bones of the totem animal. At your option, you also gain minor physical attributes that are reminiscent of your totem spirit. For example, if you have a bear totem spirit, you might be unusually hairy and thick-skinned, or if your totem is the eagle, your eyes turn bright yellow.
	Your totem animal might be an animal related to those listed here but more appropriate to your homeland. For example, you could choose a hawk or vulture in place of an eagle.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bear (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>While raging, you have resistance to all damage except psychic damage. The spirit of the bear makes you tough enough to stand up to any punishment.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Eagle (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>While you're raging and aren't wearing heavy armor, other creatures have disadvantage on opportunity attack rolls against you, and you can use the Dash action as a bonus action on your turn. The spirit of the eagle makes you into a predator who can weave through the fray with ease.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Wolf (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>While you're raging, your friends have advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature within 5 feet of you that is hostile to you. The spirit of the wolf makes you a leader of hunters.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Aspect of the Beast (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain a magical benefit based on the totem animal of your choice. You can choose the same animal you selected at 3rd level or a different one.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Aspect of the Bear (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>You gain the might of a bear. Your carrying capacity (including maximum load and maximum lift) is doubled, and you have advantage on Strength checks made to push, pull, lift, or break objects.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Aspect of the Eagle (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>You gain the eyesight of an eagle. You can see up to 1 mile away with no difficulty, able to discern even fine details as though looking at something no more than 100 feet away from you. Additionally, dim light doesn't impose disadvantage on your Wisdom (Perception) checks.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Aspect of the Wolf (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>You gain the hunting sensibilities of a wolf. You can track other creatures while traveling at a fast pace, and you can move stealthily while traveling at a normal pace.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Spirit Walker (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you can cast the commune with nature spell, but only as a ritual. When you do so, a spiritual version of one of the animals you chose for Totem Spirit or Aspect of the Beast appears to you to convey the information you seek.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Totemic Attunement (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain a magical benefit based on a totem animal of your choice. You can choose the same animal you selected previously or a different one.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bear (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>While you're raging, any creature within 5 feet of you that's hostile to you has disadvantage on attack rolls against targets other than you or another character with this feature. An enemy is immune to this effect if it can't see or hear you or if it can't be frightened.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Eagle (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>While raging, you have a flying speed equal to your current walking speed. This benefit works only in short bursts; you fall if you end your turn in the air and nothing else is holding you aloft.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Wolf (Path of the Totem Warrior)</name>
        <text>While you're raging, you can use a bonus action on your turn to knock a Large or smaller creature prone when you hit it with melee weapon attack.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 50</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
