<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Agonizing Blast</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: Eldritch Blast cantrip

When you cast eldritch blast, add your Charisma modifier to the damage it deals on a hit.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 110</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Armor of Shadows</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>You can cast mage armor on yourself at will, without expending a spell slot or material components.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 110</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Ascendant Step</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 9th level Warlock

You can cast levitate on yourself at will, without expending a spell slot or material components.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 110</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Beast Speech</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>You can cast speak with animals at will, without expending a spell slot.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 110</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Beguiling Influence</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>You gain proficiency in the Deception and Persuasion skills.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 110</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Bewitching Whispers</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 7th level Warlock

You can cast compulsion once using a warlock spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 110</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Book of Ancient Secrets</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: Pact of the Tome feature

You can now inscribe magical rituals in your Book of Shadows. Choose two 1st-level spells that have the ritual tag from any class's spell list (the two needn't be from the same list). The spells appear in the book and don't count against the number of spells you know. With your Book of Shadows in hand, you can cast the chosen spells as rituals. You can't cast the spells except as rituals, unless you've learned them by some other means. You can also cast a warlock spell you know as a ritual if it has the ritual tag.
	On your adventures, you can add other ritual spells to your Book of Shadows. When you find such a spell, you can add it to the book if the spell's level is equal to or less than half your warlock level (rounded up) and if you can spare the time to transcribe the spell. For each level of the spell, the transcription process takes 2 hours and costs 50 gp for the rare inks needed to inscribe it.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 110</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Chains of Carceri</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 15th level, Pact of the Chain

You can cast hold monster at will-targeting a celestial, fiend, or elemental-without expending a spell slot or material components. You must finish a long rest before you can use this invocation on the same creature again.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 110</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Devil's Sight</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>You can see normally in darkness, both magical and nonmagical, to a distance of 120 feet.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 110</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Dreadful Word</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 7th level Warlock

You can cast confusion once using a warlock spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 110</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Eldritch Sight</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>You can cast detect magic at will, without expending a spell slot.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 110</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Eldritch Spear</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: Eldritch Blast cantrip

When you cast eldritch blast, its range is 300 feet.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Eyes of the Rune Keeper</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>You can read all writing.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Fiendish Vigor</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>You can cast false life on yourself at will as a 1st-level spell, without expending a spell slot or material components.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Gaze of Two Minds</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>You can use your action to touch a willing humanoid and perceive through its senses until the end of your next turn. As long as the creature is on the same plane of existence as you, you can use your action on subsequent turns to maintain this connection, extending the duration until the end of your next turn. While perceiving through the other creature's senses, you benefit from any special senses possessed by that creature, and you are blinded and deafened to your own surroundings.

Blinded:
	• A blinded creature can't see and automatically fails any ability check that requires sight.
	• Attack rolls against the creature have advantage, and the creature's attack rolls have disadvantage.

Deafened:
	• A deafened creature can't hear and automatically fails any ability check that requires hearing.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Lifedrinker</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 12th level, Pact of the Blade

When you hit a creature with your pact weapon, the creature takes extra necrotic damage equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum 1).

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Mask of Many Faces</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>You can cast disguise self at will, without expending a spell slot.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Master of Myriad Forms</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 15th level Warlock

You can cast alter self at will, without expending a spell slot.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Minions of Chaos</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 9th level Warlock

You can cast conjure elemental once using a warlock spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Mire the Mind</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 5th level Warlock

You can cast slow once using a warlock spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Misty Visions</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>You can cast silent image at will, without expending a spell slot or material components.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: One with Shadows</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 5th level Warlock

When you are in an area of dim light or darkness, you can use your action to become invisible until you move or take an action or a reaction.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Otherworldly Leap</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 9th level Warlock

You can cast jump on yourself at will, without expending a spell slot or material components.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Repelling Blast</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: Eldritch Blast cantrip

When you hit a creature with eldritch blast, you can push the creature up to 10 feet away from you in a straight line.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Sculptor of Flesh</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 7th level Warlock

You can cast polymorph once using a warlock spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Sign of Ill Omen</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 5th level Warlock

You can cast bestow curse once using a warlock spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Thief of Five Fates</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>You can cast bane once using a warlock spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Thirsting Blade</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 5th level, Pact of the Blade

You can attack with your pact weapon twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Visions of Distant Realms</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 15th level Warlock

You can cast arcane eye at will, without expending a spell slot.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Voice of the Chain Master</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: Pact of the Chain

You can communicate telepathically with your familiar and perceive through your familiar's senses as long as you are on the same plane of existence. Additionally, while perceiving through your familiar's senses, you can also speak through your familiar in your own voice, even if your familiar is normally incapable of speech.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Whispers of the Grave</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 9th level Warlock

You can cast speak with dead at will, without expending a spell slot.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Invocation: Witch Sight</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Eldritch Invocations</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 15th level Warlock

You can see the true form of any shapechanger or creature concealed by illusion or transmutation magic while the creature is within 30 feet of you and within line of sight.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 111</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Breath of Winter</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self (60-foot cone)</range>
    <components>V, S, M (6 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 17th level Monk

You can spend 6 ki points to cast cone of cold.

Cone of Cold:
A blast of cold air erupts from your hands. Each creature in a 60-foot cone must make a Constitution saving throw. A creature takes 8d8 cold damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.
	A creature killed by this spell becomes a frozen statue until it thaws.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
    <roll description="Cold Damage, 6 Ki Points">8d8</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Clench of the North Wind</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EN</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>60 feet</range>
    <components>V, S, M (3 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 6th level Monk

You can spend 3 ki points to cast hold person.

Hold Person:
Choose a humanoid that you can see within range. The target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or be paralyzed for the duration. At the end of each of its turns, the target can make another Wisdom saving throw. On a success, the spell ends on the target.

Additional Ki Points: When you cast this spell using 4 or more ki points, you can target on additional humanoid for each ki point above 3. The humanoids must be within 30 feet of each other when you target them.

Paralyzed:
	• A paralyzed creature is incapacitated, meaning it can't take actions or reactions, and can't move or speak.
	• The creature automatically fails Strength and Dexterity saving throws.
	• Attack rolls against the creature have advantage.
	• Any attack that hits the creature is a critical hit if the attacker is within 5 feet of the creature.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Elemental Attunement</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>T</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>30 feet</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>1 hour</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>You can use your action to briefly control elemental forces within 30 feet of you, causing one of the following effects of your choice:

	• Create a harmless, instantaneous sensory effect related to air, earth, fire, or water, such as a shower of sparks, a puff of wind, a spray of light mist, or a gentle rumbling of stone.

	• Instantaneously light or snuff out a candle, a torch, or a small campfire.

	• Cause earth, fire, water, or mist that can fit within a 1-foot cube to shape itself into a crude form you designate for 1 minute.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Eternal Mountain Defense</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>A</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V, S, M (5 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 hour</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 17th level Monk

You can spend 5 ki points to cast stoneskin, targeting yourself.

Stoneskin:
This spell turns your flesh as hard as stone. Until the spell ends, you have resistance to nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Fangs of the Fire Snake</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>10 feet</range>
    <components>V, S, M (1 ki point)</components>
    <duration>1 turn</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>When you use the Attack action on your turn, you can spend 1 ki point to cause tendrils of flame to stretch out from your fists and feet. Your reach with your unarmed strikes increases by 10 feet for that action, as well as the rest of the turn. A hit with such an attack deals fire damage instead of bludgeoning damage, and if you spend 1 ki point when the attack hits, it also deals an extra 1d10 fire damage.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
    <roll description="Fire Damage, 1 Ki Point">1d10</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Fist of Four Thunders</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self (15-foot cube)</range>
    <components>V, S, M (2 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>You can spend 2 ki points to cast thunderwave.

Thunderwave:
A wave of thunderous force sweeps out from you. Each creature in a 15-foot cube originating from you must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 2d8 thunder damage and is pushed 10 feet away from you. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage and isn't pushed.
	In addition, unsecured objects that are completely within the area of effect are automatically pushed 10 feet away from you by the spell's effect, and the spell emits a thunderous boom audible out to 300 feet.

Additional Ki Points: When you cast this spell by spending 3 or more ki points, the damage increases by 1d8 for each ki point above 2.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
    <roll description="Thunder Damage, 2 Ki Points">2d8</roll>
    <roll description="Thunder Damage, 3 Ki Points">3d8</roll>
    <roll description="Thunder Damage, 4 Ki Points">4d8</roll>
    <roll description="Thunder Damage, 5 Ki Points">5d8</roll>
    <roll description="Thunder Damage, 6 Ki Points">6d8</roll>
    <roll description="Damage Increase">1d8</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Fist of Unbroken Air</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>30 feet</range>
    <components>V, S, M (2 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>You can create a blast of compressed air that strikes like a mighty fist. As an action, you can spend 2 ki points and choose a creature within 30 feet of you. That creature must make a Strength saving throw. On a failed save, the creature takes 3d10 bludgeoning damage, plus an extra 1d10 bludgeoning damage for each additional ki point you spend, and you can push the creature up to 20 feet away from you and knock it prone. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage, and you don't push it or knock it prone.

Prone:
	• A prone creature's only movement option is to crawl, unless it stands up and thereby ends the condition.
	• The creature has disadvantage on attack rolls.
	• An attack roll against the creature has advantage if the attacker is within 5 feet of the creature. Otherwise, the attack roll has disadvantage.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
    <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage, 2 Ki Points">3d10</roll>
    <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage, 3 Ki Points">4d10</roll>
    <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage, 4 Ki Points">5d10</roll>
    <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage, 5 Ki Points">6d10</roll>
    <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage, 6 Ki Points">7d10</roll>
    <roll description="Damage Increase">1d10</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Flames of the Phoenix</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>150 feet</range>
    <components>V, S, M (4 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 11th level Monk

You can spend 4 ki points to cast fireball.

Fireball:
A bright streak flashes from your pointing finger to a point you choose within range then blossoms with a low roar into an explosion of flame. Each creature in a 20-foot radius must make a Dexterity saving throw. A target takes 8d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.
	The fire spreads around corners. It ignites flammable objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried.

Additional Ki Points: When you cast this spell by spending 5 or more ki points, the damage increases by 1d6 for each ki point above 4.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
    <roll description="Fire Damage, 4 Ki Points">8d6</roll>
    <roll description="Fire Damage, 5 Ki Points">9d6</roll>
    <roll description="Fire Damage, 6 Ki Points">10d6</roll>
    <roll description="Damage Increase">1d6</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Gong of the Summit</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>60 feet</range>
    <components>V, S, M (3 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 6th level Monk

You can spend 3 ki points to cast shatter.

Shatter:
A sudden loud ringing noise, painfully intense, erupts from a point of your choice within range. Each creature in a 10-foot-radius sphere centered on that point must make a Constitution saving throw. A creature takes 3d8 thunder damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. A creature made of inorganic material such as stone, crystal, or metal has disadvantage on this saving throw.
	A nonmagical object that isn't being worn or carried also takes the damage if it's in the spell's area.

Additional Ki Points: When you cast this spell using 4 or more ki points, the damage increases by 1d8 for each ki point above 3.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
    <roll description="Thunder Damage, 3 Ki Points">3d8</roll>
    <roll description="Thunder Damage, 4 Ki Points">4d8</roll>
    <roll description="Thunder Damage, 5 Ki Points">5d8</roll>
    <roll description="Thunder Damage, 6 Ki Points">6d8</roll>
    <roll description="Damage Increase">1d8</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Mist Stance</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>T</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V, S, M (4 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 hour</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 11th level Monk

You can spend 4 ki points to cast gaseous form, targeting yourself.

Gaseous Form:
You transform yourself, along with everything you're wearing and carrying, into a misty cloud for the duration. The spell ends if you drop to 0 hit points.
	While in this form, your only method of movement is a flying speed of 10 feet. You can enter and occupy the space of another creature. You have resistance to nonmagical damage, and you have advantage on Strength, Dexterity, and Constitution saving throws. You can pass through small holes, narrow openings, and even mere cracks, though you treat liquids as though they were solid surfaces. You can't fall and remains hovering in the air even when stunned or otherwise incapacitated.
	While in the form of a misty cloud, you can't talk or manipulate objects, and any objects you were carrying or holding can't be dropped, used, or otherwise interacted with. You can't attack or cast spells.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Ride the Wind</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>T</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V, S, M (4 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 10 minutes</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 11th level Monk

You can spend 4 ki points to cast fly, targeting yourself.

Fly:
You gain a flying speed of 60 feet for the duration. When the spell ends, you fall if you are still aloft, unless you can stop the fall.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: River of Hungry Flame</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>120 feet</range>
    <components>V, S, M (5 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 17th level Monk

You can spend 5 ki points to cast wall of fire.

Wall of Fire:
You create a wall of fire on a solid surface within range. You can make the wall up to 60 feet long, 20 feet high, and 1 foot think, or a ringed wall up to 20 feet in diameter, 20 feet high, and 1 foot think. The wall is opaque and lasts for the duration.
	When the wall appears, each creature within its area must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 5d8 fire damage, or half as much damage on a successful save.
	One side of the wall, selected by you when you cast this spell, deals 5d8 fire damage to each creature that ends its turn within 10 feet of that side or inside the wall. A creature takes the same damage when it enters the wall for the first time on a turn or ends its turn there. The other side of the wall deals no damage.

Additional Ki Points: When you cast this spell using 6 ki points, the damage increases to 6d8.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
    <roll description="5 Ki Points">5d8</roll>
    <roll description="6 Ki Points">6d8</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Rush of the Gale Spirits</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self (60-foot line)</range>
    <components>V, S, M (2 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>You can spend 2 ki points to cast gust of wind.

Gust of Wind:
A line of strong wind 60 feet long and 10 feet wide blasts from you in a direction you choose for the spell's duration. Each creature that starts its turn in the line must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be pushed 15 feet away from you in a direction following the line.
	Any creature in the line must spend 2 feet of movement for every 1 foot it moves when moving closer to you.
	The gust disperses gas or vapor, and it extinguishes candles, torches, and similar unprotected flames in the area. It causes protected flames, such as those of lanterns, to dance wildly and has a 50 percent chance to extinguish them.
	As a bonus action on each of your turns before the spell ends, you can change the direction in which the line blasts from you.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Shape of the Flowing River</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>T</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>120 feet</range>
    <components>(1 ki point)</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>As an action, you can spend 1 ki point to choose an area of ice or water no larger than 30 feet on a side within 120 feet of you. You can change water to ice within the area and vice versa, and you can reshape ice in the area in any manner you choose. You can raise or lower the ice's elevation, create or fill in a trench, erect or flatten a wall, or form a pillar. The extent of any such changes can't exceed half the area's largest dimension. For example, if you affect a 30-foot square, you can create a pillar up to 15 feet high, raise or lower the square's elevation by up to 15 feet, dig a trench up to 15 feet deep, and so on. You can't shape the ice to trap or injure a creature in the area.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Sweeping Cinder Strike</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self (15-foot cone)</range>
    <components>V, S, M (2 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>You can spend 2 ki points to cast burning hands.

Burning Hands:
As you hold your hands with thumbs touching and fingers spread, a thin sheet of flames shoots forth from your outstretched fingertips. Each creature in a 15-foot cone must make a Dexterity saving throw. A creature takes 3d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.
	The fire ignites any flammable objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried.

Additional Ki Points: When you cast this spell using 3 or more ki points, the damage increases by 1d6 for each ki point above 2.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
    <roll description="Fire Damage, 2 Ki Points">3d6</roll>
    <roll description="Fire Damage, 3 Ki Points">4d6</roll>
    <roll description="Fire Damage, 4 Ki Points">5d6</roll>
    <roll description="Fire Damage, 5 Ki Points">6d6</roll>
    <roll description="Fire Damage, 6 Ki Points">7d6</roll>
    <roll description="Damage Increase">1d6</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Water Whip</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>30 feet</range>
    <components>(2 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>You can spend 2 ki points as an action to create a whip of water that shoves and pulls a creature to unbalance it. A creature that you can see that is within 30 feet of you must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, the creature takes 3d10 bludgeoning damage, plus an extra 1d10 bludgeoning damage for each additional ki point you spend, and you can either knock it prone or pull it up to 25 feet closer to you. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage, and you don't pull it or knock it prone.

Prone:
	• A prone creature's only movement option is to crawl, unless it stands up and thereby ends the condition.
	• The creature has disadvantage on attack rolls.
	• An attack roll against the creature has advantage if the attacker is within 5 feet of the creature. Otherwise, the attack roll has disadvantage.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
    <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage, 2 Ki Points">3d10</roll>
    <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage, 3 Ki Points">4d10</roll>
    <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage, 4 Ki Points">5d10</roll>
    <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage, 5 Ki Points">6d10</roll>
    <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage, 6 Ki Points">7d10</roll>
    <roll description="Damage Increase">1d10</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Elemental Discipline: Wave of Rolling Earth</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>120 feet</range>
    <components>V, S, M (6 ki points)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 10 minutes</duration>
    <classes>Monk (Way of the Four Elements)</classes>
    <text>Prerequisite: 17th level Monk

You can spend 6 ki points to cast wall of stone.

Wall of Stone:
A nonmagical wall of solid stone springs into existence at a point you choose within range. The wall is 6 inches thick and is composed of ten 10-foot-by-10-foot panels. Each panel must be contiguous with at least on other panel. Alternatively, you can create 10-foot-by-20-foot panels that are only 3 inches thick.
	If the wall cuts through a creature's space when it appears, the creature is pushed to one side of the wall (your choice). If a creature would be surrounded on all sides by the wall (or the wall and another solid surface), that creature can make a Dexterity saving throw. On a success, it can use its reaction to move up to its speed so that it is no longer enclosed by the wall.
	The wall can have any shape you desire, though it can't occupy the same space as a creature or object. the wall doesn't need to be vertical or resting on any firm foundation. It must, however, merge with and be solidly supported by existing stone. Thus you can use this spell to bridge a chasm or create a ramp.
	If you create a span greater than 20 feet in length, you must halve the size of each panel to create supports. You can crudely shape the wall to create crenellations, battlements, and so on.
	The wall is an object made of stone that can be damaged and thus breached. Each panel has AC 15 and 30 hit points per inch of thickness. Reducing a panel to 0 hit points destroys it and might cause connected panels to collapse at the DM's discretion.
	If you maintain your concentration on this spell for its whole duration, the wall becomes permanent and can't be dispelled. Otherwise, the wall disappears when the spell ends.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 81</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Commander's Strike</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When you take the Attack action on your turn, you can forgo one of your attacks and use a bonus action to direct one of your companions to strike. When you do so, choose a friendly creature who can see or hear you and expend one superiority die. That creature can immediately use its reaction to make one weapon attack, adding the superiority die to the attack's damage roll.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Disarming Attack</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend one superiority die to attempt to disarm the target, forcing it to drop one item of your choice that it's holding. You add the superiority die to the attack's damage roll, and the target must make a Strength saving throw. On a failed save, it drops the object you choose. The object lands at its feet.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Distracting Strike</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend one superiority die to distract the creature, giving your allies an opening. You add the superiority die to the attack's damage roll. The next attack roll against the target by an attacker other than you has advantage if the attack is made before the start of your next turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Evasive Footwork</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When you move, you can expend one superiority die, rolling the die and adding the number rolled to your AC until you stop moving.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Feinting Attack</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <time>1 bonus action</time>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>You can expend one superiority die and use a bonus action on your turn to feint, choosing one creature within 5 feet of you as your target. You have advantage on your next attack roll against that creature this turn. If that attack hits, add the superiority die to the attack's damage roll.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Goading Attack</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend one superiority die to attempt to goad the target into attacking you. You add the superiority die to the attack's damage roll, and the target must make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the target has disadvantage on all attack rolls against targets other than you until the end of your next turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Lunging Attack</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When you make a melee weapon attack on your turn, you can expend one superiority die to increase your reach for that attack by 5 feet. If you hit, you add the superiority die to the attack's damage roll.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Maneuvering Attack</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend one superiority die to maneuver one of your comrades into a more advantageous position. You add the superiority die to the attack's damage roll, and you choose a friendly creature who can see or hear you. That creature can use its reaction to move up to half its speed without provoking opportunity attacks from the target of your attack.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Menacing Attack</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend one superiority die to attempt to frighten the target. You add the superiority die to the attack's damage roll, and the target must make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, it is frightened of you until the end of your next turn.

Frightened:
	• A frightened creature has disadvantage on ability checks and attack rolls while the source of its fear is within line of sight.
	• The creature can't willingly move closer to the source of its fear.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Parry</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <time>1 reaction</time>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When another creature damages you with a melee attack, you can use your reaction and expend one superiority die to reduce the damage by the number you roll on your superiority die + your Dexterity modifier.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Precision Attack</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When you make a weapon attack roll against a creature, you can expend one superiority die to add it to the roll. You can use this maneuver before or after making the attack roll, but before any effects of the attack are applied.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Pushing Attack</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend one superiority die to attempt to drive the target back. You add the superiority die to the attack's damage roll, and if the target is Large or smaller, it must make a Strength saving throw. On a failed save, you push the target up to 15 feet away from you.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Rally</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <time>1 bonus action</time>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>On your turn, you can use a bonus action and expend one superiority die to bolster the resolve of one of your companions. When you do so, choose a friendly creature who can see or hear you. That creature gains temporary hit points equal to the superiority die roll + your Charisma modifier.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Riposte</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <time>1 reaction</time>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When a creature misses you with a melee attack, you can use your reaction and expend one superiority die to make a melee weapon attack against the creature. If you hit, you add the superiority die to the attack's damage roll.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Sweeping Attack</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When you hit a creature with a melee weapon attack, you can expend one superiority die to attempt to damage another creature with the same attack. Choose another creature within 5 feet of the original target and within your reach. If the original attack roll would hit the second creature, it takes damage equal to the number you roll on your superiority die. The damage is of the same type dealt by the original attack.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Maneuver: Trip Attack</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Maneuver Options</classes>
    <text>When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend one superiority die to attempt to knock the target down. You add the superiority die to the attack's damage roll, and if the target is Large or smaller, it must make a Strength saving throw. On a failed save, you knock the target prone.

Prone:
	• A prone creature's only movement option is to crawl, unless it stands up and thereby ends the condition.
	• The creature has disadvantage on attack rolls.
	• An attack roll against the creature has advantage if the attacker is within 5 feet of the creature. Otherwise, the attack roll has disadvantage.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 74</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Metamagic: Careful Spell</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <components>(1 sorcery point)</components>
    <classes>Metamagic Options</classes>
    <text>When you cast a spell that forces other creatures to make a saving throw, you can protect some of those creatures from the spell's full force. To do so, you spend 1 sorcery point and choose a number of those creatures up to your Charisma modifier (minimum of one creature). A chosen creature automatically succeeds on its saving throw against the spell.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 102</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Metamagic: Distant Spell</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <components>(1 sorcery point)</components>
    <classes>Metamagic Options</classes>
    <text>When you cast a spell that has a range of 5 feet or greater, you can spend 1 sorcery point to double the range of the spell.
	When you cast a spell that has a range of touch, you can spend 1 sorcery point to make the range of the spell 30 feet.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 102</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Metamagic: Empowered Spell</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <components>(1 sorcery point)</components>
    <classes>Metamagic Options</classes>
    <text>When you roll damage for a spell, you can spend 1 sorcery point to reroll a number of the damage dice up to your Charisma modifier (minimum of one). You must use the new rolls.
	You can use Empowered Spell even if you have already used a different Metamagic option during the casting of the spell.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 102</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Metamagic: Extended Spell</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <components>(1 sorcery point)</components>
    <classes>Metamagic Options</classes>
    <text>When you cast a spell that has a duration of 1 minute or longer, you can spend 1 sorcery point to double its duration, to a maximum duration of 24 hours.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 102</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Metamagic: Heightened Spell</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <components>(3 sorcery points)</components>
    <classes>Metamagic Options</classes>
    <text>When you cast a spell that forces a creature to make a saving throw to resist its effects, you can spend 3 sorcery points to give one target of the spell disadvantage on its first saving throw made against the spell.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 102</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Metamagic: Quickened Spell</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <components>(2 sorcery points)</components>
    <classes>Metamagic Options</classes>
    <text>When you cast a spell that has a casting time of 1 action, you can spend 2 sorcery points to change the casting time to 1 bonus action for this casting.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 102</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Metamagic: Subtle Spell</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <components>(2 sorcery points)</components>
    <classes>Metamagic Options</classes>
    <text>When you cast a spell, you can spend 1 sorcery point to cast it without any somatic or verbal components.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 102</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Metamagic: Twinned Spell</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <components>(1 sorcery point or more)</components>
    <classes>Metamagic Options</classes>
    <text>When you cast a spell that targets only one creature and doesn't have a range of self, you can spend a number of sorcery points equal to the spell's level to target a second creature in range with the same spell (1 sorcery point if the spell is a cantrip).
	To be eligible, a spell must be incapable of targeting more than one creature at the spell's current level. For example, magic missile and scorching ray aren't eligible, but ray of frost and chromatic orb are.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 102</text>
  </spell>
  <feat>
    <name>Fighting Style: Archery</name>
    <prerequisite>Fighting Style Feature</prerequisite>
    <text>You gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls you make with ranged weapons.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 72</text>
    <special>fighting style archery</special>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Fighting Style: Defense</name>
    <prerequisite>Fighting Style Feature</prerequisite>
    <text>While you are wearing armor, you gain a +1 bonus to AC.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 72</text>
    <special>fighting style defense</special>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Fighting Style: Dueling</name>
    <prerequisite>Fighting Style Feature</prerequisite>
    <text>When you are wielding a melee weapon in one hand and no other weapons, you gain a +2 bonus to damage rolls with that weapon.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 72</text>
    <special>fighting style dueling</special>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Fighting Style: Great Weapon Fighting</name>
    <prerequisite>Fighting Style Feature</prerequisite>
    <text>When you roll a 1 or 2 on a damage die for an attack you make with a melee weapon that you are wielding with two hands, you can reroll the die and must use the new roll, even if the new roll is a 1 or a 2. The weapon must have the two-handed or versatile property for you to gain this benefit.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 72</text>
    <special>fighting style great weapon fighting</special>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Fighting Style: Protection</name>
    <prerequisite>Fighting Style Feature</prerequisite>
    <text>When a creature you can see attacks a target other than you that is within 5 feet of you, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on the attack roll. You must be wielding a shield.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 72</text>
    <special>fighting style protection</special>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Fighting Style: Two-Weapon Fighting</name>
    <prerequisite>Fighting Style Feature</prerequisite>
    <text>When you engage in two-weapon fighting, you can add your ability modifier to the damage of the second attack.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 72</text>
    <special>fighting style two-weapon fighting</special>
  </feat>
</compendium>
