<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <monster>
    <name>Aerosaur</name>
    <sortname>Dinosaur, Aerosaur</sortname>
    <ancestry>Dinosaur</ancestry>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>monstrosity (dinosaur)</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>155 (10d20+50)</hp>
    <speed>20 ft., fly 120 ft.</speed>
    <str>26</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages/>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The aerosaur has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The aerosaur makes one Bite attack and one Talons attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 27 (3d12 + 8) piercing damage. If the target is a Huge or smaller creature, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 18). Until this grapple ends, the target has the restrained condition, and the aerosaur can't Bite another target.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+12|3d12+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Talons</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 24 (3d10 + 8) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+12|3d10+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Wing Gusts (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The aerosaur beats its wings, creating bursts of thunderous force. Each creature within 10 feet of the aerosaur must make a DC 20 Strength saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 38 (7d10) thunder damage, is pushed up to 30 feet horizontally from the aerosaur, and has the prone condition. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage and is pushed up to 15 feet horizontally from the aerosaur.</text>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||7d10</attack>
    </action>
    <description>A pterosaur the size of the most ancient dragons, an aerosaur boasts a wingspan of nearly 200 feet. Elemental energy traces patterns like lightning across its scales, giving additional thunderous power to the beating of its enormous wings.

Dinosaurs:
Dinosaurs, or behemoths, are among the oldest reptiles in the world. Predatory dinosaurs are savage, territorial hunters. Herbivorous dinosaurs are less aggressive, but they might attack to defend their young, or if startled or harassed.
	Dinosaurs come in many sizes and shapes. Larger varieties often have drab coloration, while smaller dinosaurs have colorful markings akin to birds. Dinosaurs roam rugged and isolated areas that humanoids seldom visit, including remote mountain valleys, inaccessible plateaus, tropical islands, and deep fens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 128</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Altisaur</name>
    <sortname>Dinosaur, Altisaur</sortname>
    <ancestry>Dinosaur</ancestry>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>monstrosity (dinosaur)</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>198 (12d20+72)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>28</str>
    <dex>6</dex>
    <con>23</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Perception +11</skill>
    <passive>21</passive>
    <languages/>
    <cr>13</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+5</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The altisaur has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The altisaur makes one Stomp attack and one Tail attack. The altisaur can't make both attacks against the same target.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Stomp</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 33 (7d6 + 9) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Huge or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 22 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+14|7d6+9</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 45 (8d8 + 9) bludgeoning damage, and the target is pushed up to 20 feet horizontally from the altisaur.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+14|8d8+9</attack>
    </action>
    <description>The altisaur is a titanic sauropod often likened to a walking mountain, with craggy spines, patterns of elemental energy that glow in its hide like streams of lava, and eight massive legs the size of ancient trees. It creates gullies where its tail drags along the ground. Clouds often seem to gather around its head, which can reach as high as 150 feet off the ground.

Dinosaurs:
Dinosaurs, or behemoths, are among the oldest reptiles in the world. Predatory dinosaurs are savage, territorial hunters. Herbivorous dinosaurs are less aggressive, but they might attack to defend their young, or if startled or harassed.
	Dinosaurs come in many sizes and shapes. Larger varieties often have drab coloration, while smaller dinosaurs have colorful markings akin to birds. Dinosaurs roam rugged and isolated areas that humanoids seldom visit, including remote mountain valleys, inaccessible plateaus, tropical islands, and deep fens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 129</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Bag Jelly</name>
    <sortname>Ooze, Bag Jelly</sortname>
    <ancestry>Ooze</ancestry>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>ooze</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>8</ac>
    <hp>42 (5d8+20)</hp>
    <speed>10 ft., climb 10 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>6</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>7</wis>
    <cha>2</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages/>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>acid, bludgeoning</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (can't see beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Amorphous</name>
      <text>The bag jelly can move through a space as narrow as 1 inch without squeezing.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The bag jelly makes two Pseudopod attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Pseudopod</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 8 (2d6 + 1) acid damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 11). Ability checks made to escape this grapple have disadvantage.</text>
      <attack>Acid Damage|+3|2d6+1</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Bag jellies are olive-hued oozes similar to the dungeon scavengers described in the Monster Manual. As their name suggests, though, these creatures are most often found in the bags carried by giants, where they feed on whatever organic material they find. Bag jellies are resistant to squishing, which helps them survive when a giant throws the bag, sits on it, or uses it as a makeshift bludgeon.
	Some giants keep their bags scrupulously clean to avoid attracting bag jellies, but others actually use these scavengers to hinder thieves. Many would-be thieves who rummage through a sleeping giant's bag find themselves stuck to a bag jelly's adhesive surface and unable to flee as the sound of their struggle wakes the giant.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 120</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Barrowghast</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>12 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>138 (12d12+60)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>21</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>9</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>necrotic, poison</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Stench</name>
      <text>Any creature that starts its turn within 10 feet of the barrowghast must make a DC 16 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the creature has the poisoned condition for 1 minute. While poisoned this way, the creature can't regain hit points. On a successful save, the creature is immune to the Stench of all barrowghasts for 24 hours.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The barrowghast makes two Slam attacks. It can replace one Slam attack with a Life Drain attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 18 (2d12 + 5) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+8|2d12+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Life Drain</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one creature. Hit: 9 (1d8 + 5) necrotic damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 16 Constitution saving throw or its hit point maximum is reduced by an amount equal to the damage taken. This reduction lasts until the target finishes a long rest. The target dies if this effect reduces its hit point maximum to 0.
	A Humanoid slain by this attack immediately rises as a zombie (see the Monster Manual). The zombie acts as an ally of the barrowghast but isn't under its control.</text>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage|+8|1d8+5</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Noxious Wound</name>
      <text>Immediately after the barrowghast takes piercing or slashing damage, poisonous ichor sprays from the wound. Each creature within 5 feet of the barrowghast must make a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw, taking 10 (3d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Poison Damage||3d6</attack>
    </reaction>
    <description>A hill giant who dies with an empty stomach, full of rage and regret, might become suffused with energy from the Negative Plane and rise as a barrowghast. Though it looks like little more than an animated corpse, a barrowghast is filled with necrotic energy and driven by spite and malice. Its blood is a thick and toxic ichor that gives the barrowghast a noxious stench.
	Barrowghasts no longer hunger for physical food and instead crave life energy drained from living creatures. They often target former family members and allies, but they feast indiscriminately on any creatures they encounter. When barrowghasts drain Humanoids' life energy, those Humanoids rise as zombies.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 121</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Cairnwight</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>138 (12d12+60)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save>Wis +5, Con +9</save>
    <skill>Stealth +8, Athletics +10, Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, petrified</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The cairnwight makes two Slam attacks or two Rock attacks, and it uses its Petrifying Touch if available.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 22 (3d10 + 6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+10|3d10+6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rock</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, range 60/240 ft., one target. Hit: 19 (3d8 + 6) bludgeoning damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 17 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+10|3d8+6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Petrifying Touch (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The cairnwight touches one creature it can see within 10 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 17 Constitution saving throw or take 26 (4d12) force damage and have the restrained condition as it begins to turn to stone. The affected target must repeat the saving throw at the end of its next turn. On a successful save, the effect ends on the target. On a failed save, the target has the petrified condition instead of the restrained condition.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage||4d12</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Stone giants believe the god Skoraeus Stonebones inspires artists to create their finest stone carvings. Sometimes a giant pursues this divine inspiration to the exclusion of all other tasks, retreating into a spacious cavern and blocking out all distractions. Creating a masterwork can become such a driving obsession that death can't stop it: a giant who dies while creating art might rise as a cairnwight and continue the work. Once the artwork is completed, the cairnwight remains as its undying guardian.
	A cairnwight looks much like an emaciated stone giant. Its form is caked with lichens and mineral deposits, which help it blend with its cavern tomb. Should a creature attempt to interfere with the completion of the cairnwight's project, damage the art, or steal from the cairnwight, the giant petrifies the creature, places the resulting statue outside as a warning, then reseals its cavern vault.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 122</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Ceratops</name>
    <sortname>Dinosaur, Ceratops</sortname>
    <ancestry>Dinosaur</ancestry>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>monstrosity (dinosaur)</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>139 (9d20+45)</hp>
    <speed>50 ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>4</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages/>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The ceratops has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The ceratops makes one Gore attack and one Stomp attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Gore</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 29 (4d10 + 7) piercing damage. If the ceratops moved at least 20 feet in a straight line toward the target immediately before the hit, the target takes an extra 11 (2d10) piercing damage; if the target is a creature, it also must succeed on a DC 19 Strength saving throw or be pushed up to 20 feet from the ceratops and have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+11|4d10+7</attack>
      <attack>Piercing Damage||2d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Stomp</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 29 (4d10 + 7) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+11|4d10+7</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Stretching over 200 feet from the tip of its enormous nose horn to the end of its spiky tail, a ceratops gleams with lines of vibrant green energy in its thickly scaled hide. Its horn alone is larger than most giants, and the ceratops can trample ancient forests under its feet when it becomes enraged.

Dinosaurs:
Dinosaurs, or behemoths, are among the oldest reptiles in the world. Predatory dinosaurs are savage, territorial hunters. Herbivorous dinosaurs are less aggressive, but they might attack to defend their young, or if startled or harassed.
	Dinosaurs come in many sizes and shapes. Larger varieties often have drab coloration, while smaller dinosaurs have colorful markings akin to birds. Dinosaurs roam rugged and isolated areas that humanoids seldom visit, including remote mountain valleys, inaccessible plateaus, tropical islands, and deep fens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 129</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Cinder Hulk</name>
    <sortname>Hulk, Cinder</sortname>
    <ancestry>Hulk</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>84 (8d10+40)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Wis +5, Con +8, Dex +4</save>
    <skill>Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Ignan</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>fire, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Death Burst</name>
      <text>When the cinder hulk dies, it leaves behind a cloud of cinders and smoke that fills a 10-foot-radius sphere centered on its space. The sphere is heavily obscured. Any creature that moves into the area for the first time on a turn or starts its turn there must succeed on a DC 16 Constitution saving throw or take 10 (3d6) fire damage. The cloud lasts for 1 minute or until it is dispersed by strong wind.</text>
      <attack>Fire Damage||3d6</attack>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The cinder hulk makes two Slam attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 16 (2d10 + 5) bludgeoning damage plus 10 (3d6) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+8|(2d10+5)+(3d6)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+8|2d10+5</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Wave of Cinders (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The cinder hulk emits a wave of smoldering ash from its face, hands, or chest in a 30-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 31 (7d8) fire damage and has the blinded condition until the end of its next turn. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.

Blinded:
	• A blinded creature can't see and automatically fails any ability check that requires sight.
	• Attack rolls against the creature have advantage, and the creature's attack rolls have disadvantage.</text>
      <attack>Fire Damage||7d8</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Cinder hulks are distant descendants of fire giants who isolated themselves from the world and steeped themselves in the energy of the Elemental Planes. Over the course of centuries, these giants were transformed into Elementals made of smoke and cinders. Half the size of their giant ancestors, cinder hulks maintain the basic physical shape of fire giants, but ash and embers billow around their barely cohesive physical forms.
	Cinder hulks live in isolated enclaves in fiery locations on the Material Plane, in the Elemental Planes of Air and Fire, and especially in the Great Conflagration, the border region between those two planes. They retain none of the skills and motivation of their giant ancestors; they simply want to burn as much as they can until their own flames are extinguished. When a cinder hulk dies, it collapses into a billowing cloud of searing smoke.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 123</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Cloud Giant Destiny Gambler</name>
    <sortname>Cloud Giant, Destiny Gambler</sortname>
    <ancestry>Cloud Giant</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant (bard)</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>337 (27d12+162)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft., fly 40 ft.(hover), canHover true ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>19</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>22</cha>
    <save>Wis +9, Con +12, Cha +12, Int +10</save>
    <skill>Insight +9, Deception +18, Perception +9</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>19</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>thunder</immune>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>truesight 30 ft. (requires cloud rune)</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Cloud Rune</name>
      <text>The giant has a cloud rune inscribed on a mask in its possession. While holding or wearing the mask bearing the rune, the giant has truesight within a range of 30 feet and can use its Thunderous Clap action and Negate Spell reaction.
	The mask bearing the cloud rune has AC 15; 45 hit points; and immunity to necrotic, poison, and psychic damage. The mask regains all its hit points at the end of every turn, but it turns to dust if reduced to 0 hit points or when the giant dies. If the rune is destroyed, the giant can inscribe a cloud rune on a mask in its possession when it finishes a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes three Flying Staff attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Flying Staff</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 10 ft. or range 30/90 ft., one target. Hit: 18 (3d6 + 8) bludgeoning damage plus 16 (3d10) thunder damage. Hit or Miss: The staff magically returns to the giant's hand immediately after a ranged attack.</text>
      <attack>Flying Staff|+14|(3d6+8)+(3d10)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+14|3d6+8</attack>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||3d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The giant casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Charisma as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 20):

	• At will: detect magic, fog cloud, light, minor illusion
	• 1/Day each: dream (as an action), gaseous form, major image</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Thunderous Clap (Requires Cloud Rune)</name>
      <text>The giant magically summons a thundercloud that fills a 30-foot-radius sphere centered on a point the giant can see within 60 feet of itself. The cloud spreads around corners. Each creature in that area must make a DC 20 Constitution saving throw as the cloud emits a thunderous boom. On a failed save, a creature takes 52 (8d12) thunder damage and has the prone condition. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only. The thunderclap is audible within 300 feet of the cloud's center point.
	The cloud's area is heavily obscured. The cloud lingers until the start of the giant's next turn or until a strong wind disperses it.</text>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||8d12</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Negate Spell (Requires Cloud Rune)</name>
      <text>When the giant sees a creature within 60 feet of itself casting a spell, the giant tries to interrupt it. If the creature is casting a spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or lower, the spell fails and has no effect. If the creature is casting a spell of 4th level or higher, it must succeed on a DC 18 Intelligence saving throw, or the spell fails and has no effect.</text>
    </reaction>
    <spells>detect magic, fog cloud, light, minor illusion, dream, gaseous form, major image</spells>
    <description>Cloud giants rise in the ordning by amassing valuable and beautiful treasures-often by gambling. While many cloud giants are content with risking their wealth in games with each other, those who aim for the top of their ordning challenge all manner of beings in games of chance and wit. A destiny gambler is a cloud giant who has won increasingly high-stakes wagers against other giants, smaller folk, and even beings from the Outer Planes.
	Destiny gamblers wear half masks that cover their eyes. The masks' runic magic allows these giants not only to see normally, but also to see through illusions, invisibility, darkness, and other forms of magical trickery.
	Years of successful wagers make destiny gamblers so confident in their ability to win any challenge that they invite potential rivals to name the terms of a wager. Those who are foolish enough to issue a combat challenge quickly find these giants' magical prowess is nearly unmatched.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 124</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Cloud Giant of Evil Air</name>
    <sortname>Cloud Giant, Evil Air</sortname>
    <ancestry>Cloud Giant</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>200 (16d12+96)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>19</cha>
    <save>Wis +7, Con +10, Cha +8</save>
    <skill>Insight +7, Stealth +4, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Auran, Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Flyby</name>
      <text>The giant doesn't provoke an opportunity attack when it flies out of an enemy's reach.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes two Scimitar attacks and one Storm Boomerang attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Scimitar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 18 (3d6 + 8) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+12|3d6+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Storm Boomerang</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, range 60/240 ft., one target. Hit: 15 (3d4 + 8) bludgeoning damage plus 7 (2d6) thunder damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 16 Constitution saving throw or have the stunned condition until the end of its next turn. Hit or Miss: The boomerang magically returns to the giant's hand immediately after the attack.</text>
      <attack>Storm Boomerang|+12|(3d4+8)+(2d6)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+12|3d4+8</attack>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The giant casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Charisma as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 16):

	• At will: detect magic, fog cloud, light
	• 1/Day: gaseous form
	• 2/Day: telekinesis</text>
    </action>
    <spells>detect magic, fog cloud, light, gaseous form, telekinesis</spells>
    <description>Given their inherent link to elemental air, cloud giants who turn from the gods of the Ordning often gravitate to the service of Yan-C-Bin, Prince of Evil Air. These giants' cunning, charisma, and sheer physical and magical might make them well suited to leadership positions in the cults of Elemental Evil. A cult with a cloud giant at its head can be a formidable force of corruption and destruction in the world. As if that weren't enough, cloud giants often bring tremendous wealth with them, swelling the cult's coffers to finance more far-reaching operations.
	A cloud giant dedicated to Evil Air wears a magic vest adorned with wings made from roc feathers and enchanted with elemental air, allowing the giant to fly. The vest functions only for the giant who wears it.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 125</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Cradle of the Fire Scion</name>
    <sortname>Scion of Surtur, Cradle of the Fire Scion</sortname>
    <ancestry>Scion of Surtur</ancestry>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful evil</alignment>
    <ac>20 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>555 (30d20+240)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>28</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>27</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>20</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>25</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, lightning; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>fire, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+8</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Awakening of the Scion</name>
      <text>The cradle is a container for the scion of Surtur. When the cradle drops to 0 hit points, its body hardens and crumbles to ash. The scion instantly appears in the space the cradle occupied and uses the cradle's initiative count.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (5/Day)</name>
      <recharge>5/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the cradle fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The cradle has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The cradle deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The cradle makes three Slam or Hurl Lava attacks in any combination.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +17 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 31 (4d10 + 9) bludgeoning damage plus 14 (4d6) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+17|(4d10+9)+(4d6)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+17|4d10+9</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||4d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Hurl Lava</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +17 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 27 (4d8 + 9) fire damage. If the target is a creature or a flammable object, it ignites. Until a creature within 5 feet of the fire takes an action to douse the fire, the target takes 10 (3d6) fire damage at the start of each of its turns.</text>
      <attack>Fire Damage|+17|4d8+9</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Erupting Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The cradle exhales flames and volcanic gases in a 90-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 24 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 55 (10d10) fire damage and has the poisoned condition for 1 minute. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.
	A creature poisoned in this way can make a DC 24 Constitution saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Fire Damage||10d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Lava Geyser (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The cradle causes lava to erupt from a point on the ground it can see within 120 feet of itself. Each creature in a 20-foot-radius, 50-foot-high cylinder centered on that point must succeed on a DC 21 Dexterity saving throw or take 14 (4d6) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Fire Damage||4d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Scion of Surtur:
A scion of Surtur slumbering at the peak of a volcano causes an unending plume of smoke to rise, sometimes lit from below by fiery bursts of lava. As the scion dreams of battle-perhaps a battle to rouse Annam from seclusion by uniting the giants or a war to conquer all in Surtur's name-the volcano rumbles and spews molten rage.
	If intruders disturb its resting place, the fire scion's cradle rises as a bipedal juggernaut of molten rock. Sometimes miners risk their lives to find rich veins of ore in a scion's volcano, or misguided fire cultists offer sacrifices meant to appease or awaken the volcano, and the awakened cradle defies all their expectations. Like a living volcano, the cradle hurls balls of magma at intruders, exhales fiery gases, and causes molten stone to erupt from the ground around it.
	If the cradle is destroyed, the scion of Surtur inside it awakens. Standing 60 feet tall, the scion's form is shrouded in a continual cloud of billowing ash and smoke. The awakened scion forms a blade of lava in its mighty hand and schemes to resume its ancient campaigns of conquest, preferably at the head of a fire giant army.

Scions of Giants' Gods:
Giants are descended from the All-Father, Annam, and his children. But scions of giants' gods boast a greater claim: they are Annam's grandchildren, and they occupy a privileged place among giants. On some worlds, these scions ruled the first empires of giants until Annam retreated into seclusion. On other worlds, the scions guard their birthplaces (which are rich in elemental magic) or hold the substance of the world together. (See "Giants of Myth" in chapter 3 for additional inspiration.)
	Scions of giants' gods are enormously powerful beings who infuse the world around them with primeval magic. In many worlds, they slumber and have become part of the landscape. In this case, each scion is enclosed in stasis inside a powerful Elemental called a cradle. The cradle protects the slumbering scion and follows its subconscious wishes, including driving off intruders. But if the cradle dies, the scion within fully awakens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 172</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Cradle of the Frost Scion</name>
    <sortname>Scion of Thrym, Cradle of the Frost Scion</sortname>
    <ancestry>Scion of Thrym</ancestry>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>20 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>499 (27d20+216)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>26</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>19</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Wis +11, Cha +10</save>
    <skill/>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>24</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>fire, lightning; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>cold, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+7</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Awakening of the Scion</name>
      <text>The cradle is a container for the scion of Thrym. When the cradle drops to 0 hit points, its body shatters into shards of ice. The scion instantly appears in the space the cradle occupied and uses the cradle's initiative count.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (5/Day)</name>
      <recharge>5/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the cradle fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The cradle has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The cradle deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The cradle makes two Slam or Hurl Icicle attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 30 (4d10 + 8) bludgeoning damage plus 11 (2d10) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+15|(4d10+8)+(2d10)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+15|4d10+8</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||2d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Hurl Icicle</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 26 (4d8 + 8) piercing damage plus 9 (2d8) cold damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 23 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Hurl Icicle|+15|(4d8+8)+(2d8)</attack>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+15|4d8+8</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Freezing Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The cradle exhales a blast of frost in a 90-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 23 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 52 (8d12) cold damage, and its speed is reduced to 0 until the end of its next turn. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only. If this damage would reduce the target to 0 hit points, the target drops to 1 hit point instead and has the petrified condition, turning into a frozen statue.
	If the statue takes bludgeoning damage, it shatters, killing the frozen creature. If the statue would take fire damage, it instead takes no damage and thaws, ending the petrification.</text>
      <attack>Cold Damage||8d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Chilling Mist (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The cradle magically conjures a cloud of chilling mist that fills a 30-foot-radius sphere centered on a point it can see within 90 feet of itself. The mist spreads around corners. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 19 Constitution saving throw or take 28 (8d6) cold damage and be unable to use reactions until the start of its next turn. The mist vanishes at the end of the cradle's turn.</text>
      <attack>Cold Damage||8d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Scion of Thrym:
A slumbering scion of Thrym encased in its cradle is functionally identical to a glacier or iceberg, nestled in an alpine valley or drifting in a polar sea. In its wintry seclusion, the scion dreams of battle and glory.
	If it is disturbed, the scion's cradle animates as a bipedal figure formed of ice and snow. It smashes intruders with its icy fists or hurls shards of its own icy substance at them, and it can exhale a blast of frigid air to freeze foes in place.
	If the cradle is destroyed, its icy body shatters to reveal the awakened scion of Thrym inside it. Forming a double-bladed axe in its hand, the 7O-foot-tall scion rushes at any foe that dares to challenge it. Emulating sagas of Thrym, the scion can achieve a tremendous feat of strength: creating a glacier in the ground and hurling it skyward, along with any creatures standing on it.

Scions of Giants' Gods:
Giants are descended from the All-Father, Annam, and his children. But scions of giants' gods boast a greater claim: they are Annam's grandchildren, and they occupy a privileged place among giants. On some worlds, these scions ruled the first empires of giants until Annam retreated into seclusion. On other worlds, the scions guard their birthplaces (which are rich in elemental magic) or hold the substance of the world together. (See "Giants of Myth" in chapter 3 for additional inspiration.)
	Scions of giants' gods are enormously powerful beings who infuse the world around them with primeval magic. In many worlds, they slumber and have become part of the landscape. In this case, each scion is enclosed in stasis inside a powerful Elemental called a cradle. The cradle protects the slumbering scion and follows its subconscious wishes, including driving off intruders. But if the cradle dies, the scion within fully awakens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 174</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Cradle of the Hill Scion</name>
    <sortname>Scion of Grolantor, Cradle of the Hill Scion</sortname>
    <ancestry>Scion of Grolantor</ancestry>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>402 (23d20+161)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>24</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Wis +10, Cha +7</save>
    <skill/>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>22</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire, lightning; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+7</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Awakening of the Scion</name>
      <text>The cradle is a container for the scion of Grolantor. When the cradle drops to 0 hit points, its body crumbles to dirt and moss. The scion instantly appears in the space the cradle occupied and uses the cradle's initiative count.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (5/Day)</name>
      <recharge>5/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the cradle fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The cradle has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The cradle deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The cradle makes three Slam or Spit Rock attacks in any combination and one Grasping Root attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 33 (4d12 + 7) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+14|4d12+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spit Rock</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 25 (4d8 + 7) bludgeoning damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 22 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+14|4d8+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Grasping Root</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 30 ft., one creature not grappled by the cradle. Hit: the target has the grappled condition (escape DC 17). Until the grapple ends, the target takes 29 (4d10 + 7) bludgeoning damage at the start of each of its turns. The root has AC 19 and can be severed by dealing 15 or more slashing damage to it on one attack. Cutting the root doesn't hurt the cradle but ends the grapple.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+14|4d10+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rolling Hills (Recharge 6)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>The cradle magically creates a wave of dirt that extends from a point on the ground within 120 feet of itself. The wave is up to 30 feet long, up to 30 feet tall, and up to 30 feet wide. Each creature in the wave must make a DC 22 Strength saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 58 (9d12) bludgeoning damage, has the prone condition, and is buried under dirt. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.
	A buried creature has the restrained condition, has total cover, and can't breathe. As an action, a creature buried in this way, or another creature within 5 feet of it that isn't buried, can make a DC 17 Strength (Athletics) check. On a successful check, the buried creature no longer has the prone or restrained conditions.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage||9d12</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Scion of Grolantor:
A slumbering scion of Grolantor is often mistaken for a hill, and sometimes people erect standing stones, a village. or a city on a scion's back, unaware of the mighty power beneath them. Such settlements can thrive for centuries, as the scion's magic causes crops to flourish and livestock to thrive in the surrounding region. An ancient tree towers from the crest of the hill.
	When roused, a cradle of the hill scion rises as a mass of dirt, stone, and roots with two massive arms. The cradle uses tree roots and waves of dirt to entangle and entomb foes.
	If the cradle is destroyed, the scion of Grolantor inside it awakens. Standing 50 feet tall, the scion devours everything within reach to satiate its hunger. Its powerful lungs can suck food straight into its gullet. The scion uses a great tree to bat foes far into the distance.

Scions of Giants' Gods:
Giants are descended from the All-Father, Annam, and his children. But scions of giants' gods boast a greater claim: they are Annam's grandchildren, and they occupy a privileged place among giants. On some worlds, these scions ruled the first empires of giants until Annam retreated into seclusion. On other worlds, the scions guard their birthplaces (which are rich in elemental magic) or hold the substance of the world together. (See "Giants of Myth" in chapter 3 for additional inspiration.)
	Scions of giants' gods are enormously powerful beings who infuse the world around them with primeval magic. In many worlds, they slumber and have become part of the landscape. In this case, each scion is enclosed in stasis inside a powerful Elemental called a cradle. The cradle protects the slumbering scion and follows its subconscious wishes, including driving off intruders. But if the cradle dies, the scion within fully awakens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 164</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Cradle of the Stone Scion</name>
    <sortname>Scion of Skoraeus, Cradle of the Stone Scion</sortname>
    <ancestry>Scion of Skoraeus</ancestry>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>20 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>455 (26d20+182)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>26</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>24</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Wis +11, Cha +7</save>
    <skill/>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>23</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire, lightning; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>acid, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>tremorsense 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+7</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Awakening of the Scion</name>
      <text>The cradle is a container for the scion of Skoraeus. When the cradle drops to 0 hit points, its body crumbles to dust. The scion instantly appears in the space the cradle occupied and uses the cradle's initiative count.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (5/Day)</name>
      <recharge>5/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the cradle fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The cradle has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The cradle deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The cradle makes two Slam or Spit Rock attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 30 (4d10 + 8) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+15|4d10+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spit Rock</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 24 (3d10 + 8) bludgeoning damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 23 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+15|3d10+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shattering Roar (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The cradle lets out a painfully load roar. Each creature within 60 feet of the cradle must make a DC 23 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 33 (6d10) thunder damage and has the incapacitated condition until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||6d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Crystal Flare (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The cradle causes the crystals on its body to flare with light. Each creature within 30 feet of the cradle must succeed on a DC 22 Constitution saving throw or take 21 (6d6) radiant damage and have the blinded condition until the end of the cradle's next turn.

Blinded:
	• A blinded creature can't see and automatically fails any ability check that requires sight.
	• Attack rolls against the creature have advantage, and the creature's attack rolls have disadvantage.</text>
      <attack>Radiant Damage||6d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Stone Spikes (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The cradle causes the ground in a 20-foot square within 90 feet of itself to sprout crystal spikes until the start of its next turn. The area becomes difficult terrain for the duration. A creature takes 10 (3d6) piercing damage for each 5 feet it moves on this terrain.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Scion of Skoraeus:
A scion of Skoraeus typically slumbers deep in the heart of a towering mountain, almost becoming one with the earth. While the scion dreams, the mountain's minerals are transformed into fine carving stones and brilliant gems.
	If a miner tunnels too close to the heart of the mountain, the cradle awakens as a bipedal mass of stone and crystals. It brings the weight of the mountain down on the intruder's head and unleashes an earsplitting roar that can collapse mine tunnels.
	If the cradle is destroyed, the scion of Skoraeus inside it awakens. At nearly 70 feet tall, it towers over most other creatures and wields a mass of crystal as a club. Once awakened, the scion continues to pursue the art that ornamented its dreams, seeking to mold and shape stone into beautiful elegance. If it needs more raw materials, the scion can transform a living creature in its palm into stone.

Scions of Giants' Gods:
Giants are descended from the All-Father, Annam, and his children. But scions of giants' gods boast a greater claim: they are Annam's grandchildren, and they occupy a privileged place among giants. On some worlds, these scions ruled the first empires of giants until Annam retreated into seclusion. On other worlds, the scions guard their birthplaces (which are rich in elemental magic) or hold the substance of the world together. (See "Giants of Myth" in chapter 3 for additional inspiration.)
	Scions of giants' gods are enormously powerful beings who infuse the world around them with primeval magic. In many worlds, they slumber and have become part of the landscape. In this case, each scion is enclosed in stasis inside a powerful Elemental called a cradle. The cradle protects the slumbering scion and follows its subconscious wishes, including driving off intruders. But if the cradle dies, the scion within fully awakens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 168</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Cradle of the Storm Scion</name>
    <sortname>Scion of Stronmaus, Cradle of the Storm Scion</sortname>
    <ancestry>Scion of Stronmaus</ancestry>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic good</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>682 (35d20+315)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft., fly 60 ft.(hover), canHover true ft., swim 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>30</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>29</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>23</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>27</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire, thunder; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>lightning, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained, stunned</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+8</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Awakening of the Scion</name>
      <text>The cradle is a container for the scion of Stronmaus. When the cradle drops to 0 hit points, its body bursts into light. The scion instantly appears in the space the cradle occupied and uses the cradle's initiative count.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (5/Day)</name>
      <recharge>5/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the cradle fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The cradle has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The cradle deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The cradle makes three Slam or Spit Hailstone attacks in any combination.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 36 (4d12 + 10) bludgeoning damage plus 19 (3d12) lightning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+18|(4d12+10)+(3d12)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+18|4d12+10</attack>
      <attack>Lightning Damage||3d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spit Hailstone</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 32 (4d10 + 10) bludgeoning damage plus 14 (4d6) cold damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 26 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Spit Hailstone|+18|(4d10+10)+(4d6)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+18|4d10+10</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||4d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Lightning Barrage (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The cradle hurls multiple magical lightning bolts at up to two creatures it can see within 500 feet of itself. Each target must make a DC 22 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, the target takes 71 (11d12) lightning damage and has the stunned condition until the end of its next turn. On a successful save, the target takes half as much damage only.</text>
      <attack>Lightning Damage||11d12</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Booming Step</name>
      <text>Immediately after taking damage, the cradle cracks with thunder and then magically teleports up to 60 feet to an unoccupied space it can see. Each creature within 10 feet of the space the cradle left must make a DC 22 Constitution saving throw, taking 14 (4d6) thunder damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||4d6</attack>
    </reaction>
    <description>Scion of Stronmaus:
A scion of Stronmaus often slumbers high in the sky or deep in the ocean, where the tumult caused by the scion's restless sleep has little effect on the world. If it drifts too near the ground or the ocean surface, it causes mighty storms or fierce maelstroms. A scion's slumber is filled with dreams ranging from inspiring visions of Annam's return to melancholy prophecies of inevitable decline, from joyful glimpses of an idyllic past to horrific nightmares of torment and devastation.
	A cradle of the storm scion stirs into action not only when the scion is threatened but also if the scion's sleep is troubled by nightmares. When roused, the cradle takes on a vaguely giant-shaped form consisting of air, water, and ice whirling in fury.
	If the cradle is destroyed, the scion of Stronmaus inside it awakens. Among the mightiest creatures of all giant kind, the scion stands 80 feet tall. It often finds some relief in waking and being freed from its troubling dreams, so it doesn't necessarily lash out in violence when emerging from its cradle. But it's not particularly interested in Humanoids or other little creatures-either in conversing with them or in protecting them from harm it might cause.
	If the scion is threatened, it unleashes elemental might like few other forces in the multiverse can muster: blades of lightning, boulder-sized hailstones, and a storm of churning elements.

Scions of Giants' Gods:
Giants are descended from the All-Father, Annam, and his children. But scions of giants' gods boast a greater claim: they are Annam's grandchildren, and they occupy a privileged place among giants. On some worlds, these scions ruled the first empires of giants until Annam retreated into seclusion. On other worlds, the scions guard their birthplaces (which are rich in elemental magic) or hold the substance of the world together. (See "Giants of Myth" in chapter 3 for additional inspiration.)
	Scions of giants' gods are enormously powerful beings who infuse the world around them with primeval magic. In many worlds, they slumber and have become part of the landscape. In this case, each scion is enclosed in stasis inside a powerful Elemental called a cradle. The cradle protects the slumbering scion and follows its subconscious wishes, including driving off intruders. But if the cradle dies, the scion within fully awakens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 170</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Cradle of the Cloud Scion</name>
    <sortname>Scion of Memnor, Cradle of the Cloud Scion</sortname>
    <ancestry>Scion of Memnor</ancestry>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic neutral</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>624 (32d20+288)</hp>
    <speed>0 ft., fly 90 ft.(hover), canHover true ft.</speed>
    <str>29</str>
    <dex>21</dex>
    <con>28</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>22</wis>
    <cha>19</cha>
    <save>Cha +12, Int +10</save>
    <skill/>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>26</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire, lightning; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>poison, thunder</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained, stunned</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+8</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Awakening of the Scion</name>
      <text>The cradle is a container for the scion of Memnor. When the cradle drops to 0 hit points, its body dissipates into cloud wisps. The scion instantly appears in the space the cradle occupied and uses the cradle's initiative count.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Flyby</name>
      <text>The cradle doesn't provoke opportunity attacks when it flies out of an enemy's reach.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (5/Day)</name>
      <recharge>5/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the cradle fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The cradle has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The cradle deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The cradle makes three Slam or Wind Javelin attacks in any combination.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +17 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 31 (4d10 + 9) bludgeoning damage plus 19 (3d12) thunder damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+17|(4d10+9)+(3d12)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+17|4d10+9</attack>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||3d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Wind Javelin</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +17 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 27 (4d8 + 9) bludgeoning damage plus 10 (3d6) thunder damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 25 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Wind Javelin|+17|(4d8+9)+(3d6)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+17|4d8+9</attack>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Vortex (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The cradle conjures a vortex of wind at a point it can see within 90 feet of itself. The wind vortex is a 30-foot-radius, 100-foot-high cylinder centered on that point. Each creature other than the cradle in that area must make a DC 25 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 71 (11d12) bludgeoning damage and has the restrained condition within the vortex. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage and is pushed to the nearest unoccupied space outside the cylinder. The vortex lasts until the start of the cradle's next turn. A creature with the restrained condition falls prone when the vortex ends.
	A creature with the restrained condition can use its action to try to escape the vortex. The creature makes a DC 19 Strength (Athletics) or Dexterity (Acrobatics) check. On a successful check, the creature escapes and moves 3d6 × 10 feet away from the vortex in a random direction.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage||11d12</attack>
      <attack>Feet||3d6x10</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Thunderclap</name>
      <text>Immediately after taking damage, the cradle unleashes a thunderclap in a 30-foot-radius sphere centered on itself. All other creatures in that area must succeed on a DC 25 Constitution saving throw or take 18 (4d8) thunder damage and have the deafened condition for 1 minute.</text>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||4d8</attack>
    </reaction>
    <description>Scion of Memnor:
A slumbering scion of Memnor appears as a dense, slowly drifting tower of clouds that never dissipates. Often, this cloud lingers over a remote valley, creating a constantly overcast sky. Sapient creatures who live beneath this cloud often display superstitious and duplicitous behavior, almost unconsciously leaving gifts for "rain spirits" while playing mischievous pranks on each other.
	When roused, a cradle of the cloud scion manifests as a titanic air elemental made of fierce winds and wisps of cloud. It wields air and thunder to knock enemies from the sky.
	If the cradle is destroyed, the scion of Memnor emerges from the dissipating cloud, often laughing as if it just heard a great joke. Incredibly tall and lanky, the scion towers 75 feet tall and wields a morningstar made from magically dense clouds. It tends to regard other creatures as toys rather than serious threats, and it uses its illusion magic to manipulate creatures into fighting each other. If seriously threatened, it wields thunder and wind to demolish its enemies.

Scions of Giants' Gods:
Giants are descended from the All-Father, Annam, and his children. But scions of giants' gods boast a greater claim: they are Annam's grandchildren, and they occupy a privileged place among giants. On some worlds, these scions ruled the first empires of giants until Annam retreated into seclusion. On other worlds, the scions guard their birthplaces (which are rich in elemental magic) or hold the substance of the world together. (See "Giants of Myth" in chapter 3 for additional inspiration.)
	Scions of giants' gods are enormously powerful beings who infuse the world around them with primeval magic. In many worlds, they slumber and have become part of the landscape. In this case, each scion is enclosed in stasis inside a powerful Elemental called a cradle. The cradle protects the slumbering scion and follows its subconscious wishes, including driving off intruders. But if the cradle dies, the scion within fully awakens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 166</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Death Giant Reaper</name>
    <sortname>Death Giant, Reaper</sortname>
    <ancestry>Death Giant</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>172 (15d12+75)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>18</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Wis +7, Con +9, Cha +7, Int +8</save>
    <skill>Stealth +6, Arcana +8, History +8, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>necrotic</immune>
    <conditionImmune>frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes two Scythe or Soul Bolt attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Scythe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: 21 (3d8 + 8) slashing damage plus 11 (2d10) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Scythe|+12|(3d8+8)+(2d10)</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+12|3d8+8</attack>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage||2d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Soul Bolt</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +8 to hit, range 120 ft., one creature. Hit: 26 (4d10 + 4) necrotic damage. If the target has the frightened condition, the giant gains temporary hit points equal to the damage dealt.</text>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage|+8|4d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Frightening Teleport (Recharge 4-6) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>D4</recharge>
      <text>The giant magically teleports, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying, up to 40 feet to an unoccupied space it can see. Each creature within 10 feet of the location the giant left must succeed on a DC 16 Wisdom saving throw or have the frightened condition until the end of that creature's next turn.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Death giant reapers wield massive scythes and wear armor that resembles the carapaces of giant insects. They wield the magic of shadow, which lets them take on a ghastly appearance and disappear, as well as twist shadow into terrifying bolts of energy that drain the vigor of their victims.

Death Giant:
Long ago, a large band of cloud giants traveled to the Shadowfell in search of a way to preserve their collapsing empire. Desperate to save themselves and their way of life, they collectively made a bet with the Raven Queen, a mysterious god of death and memory who dwells on that plane. Accounts of that bet and its outcome vary: some say the Raven Queen answered every riddle the giants posed until the giants collapsed from exhaustion, while others describe a series of increasingly improbable events favoring the Raven Queen in every wager. What is certain is that the giants severely underestimated the Raven Queen. When they lost their wager, the Shadowfell became their home, and they have grudgingly served the Raven Queen ever since.
	Over time, the Shadowfell transformed these giants; their bodies shriveled, and their complexions took on a deep-purple hue. They became the first death giants, and their descendants haunt the Shadowfell to this day, searching both that plane and the Material Plane for souls that might please their divine queen.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 126</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Death Giant Shrouded One</name>
    <sortname>Death Giant, Shrouded One</sortname>
    <ancestry>Death Giant</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant (wizard)</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>195 (17d12+85)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>23</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Wis +8, Con +10, Cha +8, Int +11</save>
    <skill>Stealth +7, Arcana +11, Perception +8</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>15</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>necrotic</immune>
    <conditionImmune>frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+5</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Death Rune</name>
      <text>The giant has a death rune inscribed on a giant's skull in its possession. While holding or wearing the skull bearing the rune, the giant can use its Reaping Scythe action and Shroud of Souls bonus action.
	The skull bearing the death rune has AC 18; 35 hit points; and immunity to necrotic, poison, and psychic damage. The skull regains all its hit points at the end of every turn, but it turns to dust if reduced to 0 hit points or when the giant dies. If the rune is destroyed, the giant can inscribe a death rune on another skull in its possession when it finishes a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes three Soul Burst attacks. Alternatively, if the giant has its death rune, it can make three Reaping Scythe attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Soul Burst</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Spell Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft. or range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 28 (4d10 + 6) necrotic damage. If the target has the frightened condition, the giant gains temporary hit points equal to the damage dealt.</text>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage|+11|4d10+6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Reaping Scythe (Requires Death Rune)</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +11 to hit, reach 15 ft., one creature. Hit: 38 (7d10) necrotic damage, and the target can't regain hit points until the end of its next turn. The target dies if it is reduced to 0 hit points by this attack.</text>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage|+11|7d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The giant casts one of the following spells, using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability:

	• At will: detect magic, mage armor
	• 3/Day each: speak with dead, Tenser's floating disk</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Frightening Teleport (Recharge 4-6) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>D4</recharge>
      <text>The giant magically teleports, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying, up to 40 feet to an unoccupied space it can see. Each creature within 10 feet of the location the giant left must succeed on a DC 19 Wisdom saving throw or have the frightened condition until the end of that creature's next turn.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shroud of Souls (Requires Death Rune) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The giant shrouds itself in a torrent of souls. While the giant is shrouded, each creature that starts its turn within 5 feet of the giant must succeed on a DC 19 Wisdom saving throw or have disadvantage on saving throws until the end of that creature's next turn. The shroud disappears after 1 minute, when the giant dies, when the giant uses this bonus action again, or when the giant's death rune is destroyed.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>detect magic, mage armor, speak with dead, tenser's floating disk</spells>
    <description>A death giant shrouded one has learned the secrets of death magic-some say from the Raven Queen herself. A shrouded one collects the skulls of fallen kin and inscribes the death rune on a prized skull from this grisly collection. Abandoning armor in favor of gloomy robes, the shrouded one uses rune magicto create a shadowy scythe blade at the end of a staff and to conjure an aura of tormented souls for protection.

Death Giant:
Long ago, a large band of cloud giants traveled to the Shadowfell in search of a way to preserve their collapsing empire. Desperate to save themselves and their way of life, they collectively made a bet with the Raven Queen, a mysterious god of death and memory who dwells on that plane. Accounts of that bet and its outcome vary: some say the Raven Queen answered every riddle the giants posed until the giants collapsed from exhaustion, while others describe a series of increasingly improbable events favoring the Raven Queen in every wager. What is certain is that the giants severely underestimated the Raven Queen. When they lost their wager, the Shadowfell became their home, and they have grudgingly served the Raven Queen ever since.
	Over time, the Shadowfell transformed these giants; their bodies shriveled, and their complexions took on a deep-purple hue. They became the first death giants, and their descendants haunt the Shadowfell to this day, searching both that plane and the Material Plane for souls that might please their divine queen.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 127</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Dust Hulk</name>
    <sortname>Hulk, Dust</sortname>
    <ancestry>Hulk</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic neutral</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>68 (8d10+24)</hp>
    <speed>0 ft., fly 30 ft.(hover), canHover true ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>19</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Terran</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Air Form</name>
      <text>The dust hulk can enter a hostile creature's space and stop there. It can move through a space as narrow as 1 inch without squeezing.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Death Burst</name>
      <text>When the dust hulk dies, it explodes in a burst of dust that fills a 10-foot-radius sphere centered on itself. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 14 Constitution saving throw or have the blinded condition for 1 minute. An affected creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The dust hulk makes three Slam attacks. It can replace one of these attacks with Stinging Dust.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 13 (2d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+7|2d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Stinging Dust</name>
      <text>One creature of the dust hulk's choice inside its space must make a DC 14 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the creature takes 10 (3d6) bludgeoning damage and has the blinded condition until the end of its next turn. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage only.

Blinded:
	• A blinded creature can't see and automatically fails any ability check that requires sight.
	• Attack rolls against the creature have advantage, and the creature's attack rolls have disadvantage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Dust hulks are descended from enclaves of stone giants who lived in extreme environments, isolated from others. Elemental energy from the Plane of Air eroded their physical forms and slowly transformed them into Elementals. They are little more than clouds of gravel and dust, barely maintaining a cohesive form. When a dust hulk dies, it disperses into a cloud of dust.
	Dust hulks retain their ancestors' passion for artistry, but instead of carving stone, they view their bodies as living works of art. As they fly, coursing along wind currents or blowing through underground tunnels like living sandstorms, they create mesmerizing dances with their ever-shifting forms.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 131</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Echo of Demogorgon</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>fiend (demon)</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>85 (10d10+30)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>22</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Str +9, Cha +5</save>
    <skill>Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Giant, Orc</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire, lightning</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The echo has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Wakeful</name>
      <text>When one of the echo's heads is asleep, its other head is awake.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The echo makes two Tentacle attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tentacle</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 13 (2d6 + 6) bludgeoning damage plus 9 (2d8) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Tentacle|+9|(2d6+6)+(2d8)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+9|2d6+6</attack>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage||2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Discordant Screams (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The echo directs its frenzied howls at one creature it can see within 60 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 13 Wisdom saving throw or suffer one of the following effects of the echo's choice:

Confused Reaction: The target must use its reaction to make a melee attack against another creature of the echo's choice that the echo can see.

Psychic Torment: The target takes 13 (2d12) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Damage||2d12</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Some legends claim the first ettins were orcs transformed by Demogorgon, the Prince of Demons, while others tie their origin to Grolantor or another god of the Ordning. Whatever the truth of their origin, ettins sometimes recognize a kindred soul in the two-headed Demogorgon and devote themselves to his service. Those who prove exceptionally valuable to Demogorgon's purposes in the Material Plane are rewarded with a "blessing" that transforms them into monstrous echoes of their demon patron.
	The arms of an echo of Demogorgon transform into powerful tentacles, and the heads take on a more bestial appearance. The transformation leaves the echo frenzied with rage; the two heads shout and howl at each other with a fury that resounds with demonic magic, sowing discord and confusion around them. As the echo's monstrous heads roar and bite at each other, nearby creatures are racked with psychic pain or join in the ruckus, attacking their allies.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 132</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Ettin Ceremorph</name>
    <sortname>Ettin, Ceremorph</sortname>
    <ancestry>Ettin</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>104 (11d10+44)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>18</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Wis +5, Int +7</save>
    <skill>Perception +8</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages>Deep Speech, Giant, telepathy 60 ft., Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>psychic</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The ceremorph has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The ceremorph makes one Slam attack and one Tentacles attack. The ceremorph can replace one of the attacks with a Mind Bolt attack, if available.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 22 (4d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+7|4d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tentacles</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 10 ft., one creature. Hit: 15 (2d10 + 4) psychic damage. If the target is Large or smaller, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 14) and must succeed on a DC 15 Intelligence saving throw or have the stunned condition until this grapple ends.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Damage|+7|2d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Extract Brain</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one incapacitated Humanoid grappled by the ceremorph. Hit: 55 (10d10) piercing damage. If this damage reduces the target to 0 hit points, the ceremorph kills the target by extracting and devouring its brain.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+7|10d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Mind Bolt (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +7 to hit, range 120 ft., one creature. Hit: 17 (2d12 + 4) psychic damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 15 Intelligence saving throw or have the stunned condition until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Damage|+7|2d12+4</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Mind flayers, which are described in the Monster Manual, are created through ceremorphosis, a process that begins with the implantation of an illithid tadpole in the brain of a Humanoid host. Mind flayers have subjected giants to this process in an effort to create larger, stronger mind flayers, but those experiments all ended in failure: a giant's body is simply too large for a single tadpole to take over.
	Ettins, however, proved to be perfect subjects. An ettin's two brains provide sufficient food for two tadpoles, and the two tadpoles are able to transform the entirety of the ettin's body, creating an ettin ceremorph. As part of the transformation process, one of the ettin's heads sinks into the body, with that brain focused on controlling the body. The other head focuses on cogitation and psionic power, though its power is not as great as a mind flayer's.
	Ettin ceremorphs serve mind flayer colonies, protecting the elder brains that rule the communities and guarding their treasures. They retain no memory of their previous existence as ettins.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 133</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Fensir Devourer</name>
    <sortname>Fensir, Devourer</sortname>
    <ancestry>Fensir</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic neutral</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>138 (12d12+60)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Survival +8, Perception +8</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Death Curse</name>
      <text>When the fensir starts its turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate, it releases a curse on those around it. Each creature within 30 feet of the fensir when it dies must succeed on a DC 13 Charisma saving throw or be cursed for the next 24 hours.
	While cursed in this way, an affected creature gains no benefit from finishing a short or long rest. At the end of every hour, the creature must succeed on a DC 13 Charisma saving throw or take 11 (2d10) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Damage||2d10</attack>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>The fensir regains 10 hit points at the start of its turn if it isn't in sunlight. If the fensir takes acid or fire damage, this trait doesn't function at the start of the fensir's next turn. The fensir dies only if it starts its turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Sunlight Hypersensitivity</name>
      <text>When the fensir starts its turn in sunlight, it must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or have the petrified condition until the fensir is no longer in sunlight.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The fensir makes two attacks, using Rend, Boulder, or a combination of them.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rend</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 21 (3d10 + 5) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+8|3d10+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Boulder</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, range 60/240 ft., one target. Hit: 18 (2d12 + 5) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 16 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition. After the fensir throws the boulder, roll a d6; on a roll of 4 or lower, the fensir has no more boulders to throw.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+8|2d12+5</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Some fensirs undergo a transformation after living in Ysgard for at least a thousand years. They grow rapidly to a height of 25 feet, fueled by an insatiable hunger. These fensir devourers use their great size and strength to overwhelm foes. They can also issue a baleful curse in their final moments.

Fensirs:
Long ago, a band of frost giants led trolls in a campaign to win Annam's favor by conquering the outer plane of Ysgard. The campaign's aspirations of conquest quickly failed, but the raiders discovered a key feature ofYsgard: creatures slain on that plane return to life the next dawn. Thus, the giants' incursion became a part of the eternal battle that rages across the plane. The trolls, whose fundamental nature was altered by constant regeneration and rebirth amid the energy of Ysgard, slowly changed into entirely new creatures: fensirs.
	Fensirs' troll ancestry is hardly apparent in their appearance. They retain prominent noses and a hint of green in their skin but otherwise resemble relatively small frost or stone giants. They use armor and weapons similar to what other combatants on Ysgard use in the eternal battle.
	The transformation that created fensirs left them with an odd quirk to their regenerative powers: their regeneration doesn't function in sunlight, and in fact, sunlight can turn these creatures to stone.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 135</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Fensir Skirmisher</name>
    <sortname>Fensir, Skirmisher</sortname>
    <ancestry>Fensir</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (chain shirt)</ac>
    <hp>94 (9d10+45)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Wis +3, Int +5</save>
    <skill>Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>The fensir regains 10 hit points at the start of its turn if it isn't in sunlight. If the fensir takes acid or fire damage, this trait doesn't function at the start of the fensir's next turn. The fensir dies only if it starts its turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Sunlight Hypersensitivity</name>
      <text>When the fensir starts its turn in sunlight, it must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or have the petrified condition until the fensir is no longer in sunlight.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The fensir makes three Battleaxe attacks or two Magic Stone attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Battleaxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 13 (2d8 + 4) slashing damage, or 15 (2d10 + 4) slashing damage if used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+7|2d8+4</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage (Two-Handed)|+7|2d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Magic Stone</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +5 to hit, range 60 ft., one target. Hit: 15 (2d12 + 2) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+5|2d12+2</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Mud to Stone (Recharge 6)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>The fensir lobs a magical mass of mud that splashes all creatures in a 30-foot-radius sphere centered on a point the fensir can see within 60 feet of itself. Each non-fensir creature in that area must succeed on a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw or take 13 (3d8) bludgeoning damage and have the restrained condition as the mud begins to turn to stone. An affected creature must repeat the saving throw at the end of its next turn. On a successful save, the effect ends on the creature. On a failed save, the creature has the petrified condition for 24 hours.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage||3d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The fensir casts one of the following spells, using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability:

	• 1/Day each: create or destroy water, detect magic, pass without trace</text>
    </action>
    <spells>create or destroy water, detect magic, pass without trace</spells>
    <description>Fensir skirmishers boast great skill in battle, honed over centuries of endless conflict on the battlefields of Ysgard. They also wield elemental magic of earth and stone. True to their giant heritage, they can transform even a pinch of mud or gravel into a boulder suitable for hurling, and the thrown stone grows in flight to knock its target flat on impact.

Fensirs:
Long ago, a band of frost giants led trolls in a campaign to win Annam's favor by conquering the outer plane of Ysgard. The campaign's aspirations of conquest quickly failed, but the raiders discovered a key feature ofYsgard: creatures slain on that plane return to life the next dawn. Thus, the giants' incursion became a part of the eternal battle that rages across the plane. The trolls, whose fundamental nature was altered by constant regeneration and rebirth amid the energy of Ysgard, slowly changed into entirely new creatures: fensirs.
	Fensirs' troll ancestry is hardly apparent in their appearance. They retain prominent noses and a hint of green in their skin but otherwise resemble relatively small frost or stone giants. They use armor and weapons similar to what other combatants on Ysgard use in the eternal battle.
	The transformation that created fensirs left them with an odd quirk to their regenerative powers: their regeneration doesn't function in sunlight, and in fact, sunlight can turn these creatures to stone.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 135</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Firbolg Primeval Warden</name>
    <sortname>Firbolg, Primeval Warden</sortname>
    <ancestry>Firbolg</ancestry>
    <npc>YES</npc>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (druid)</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (hide armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>65 (10d8+20)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Wis +5, Int +3</save>
    <skill>Nature +3, Medicine +5, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Common, Druidic, Giant</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The firbolg makes two Spear or Fire Lance attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. Hit: 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage plus 9 (2d8) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+5|(1d6+3)+(2d8)</attack>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Fire Lance</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +5 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 14 (2d10 + 3) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Fire Damage|+5|2d10+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The firbolg casts one of the following spells, using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 13):

	• At will: entangle, speak with animals, speak with plants
	• 1/Day each: commune with nature (as an action), detect magic, disguise self</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Hidden Step (2/Day) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>2/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The firbolg magically turns invisible until the start of its next turn, until it makes an attack roll, or until it forces someone to make a saving throw.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>entangle, speak with animals, speak with plants, commune with nature, detect magic, disguise self</spells>
    <description>Like giant priests of Hiatea, firbolgs who serve her fall into two distinct roles that parallel Hiatea's dual nature. At home, primeval wardens tend the hearths and tutor the young. Primeval wardens who patrol the borders of firbolg communities are fierce hunters who guard against external threats and incursions.

Firbolgs:
Distant cousins of giants, the first firbolgs wandered the primeval forests of the multiverse, and the magic of those forests entwined itself with the firbolgs' souls. Ages later, that magic still thrums inside firbolgs.
	Firbolgs are often drawn to the service or emulation of the gods Diancastra and Hiatea. Firbolgs'
innate magic of obscurement and trickery resonates with Diancastra's wily resourcefulness. A traditional emphasis on community and harmony leads many firbolgs to pledge themselves to Hiatea's service.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 136</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Firbolg Wanderer</name>
    <sortname>Firbolg, Wanderer</sortname>
    <ancestry>Firbolg</ancestry>
    <npc>YES</npc>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (cleric)</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (breastplate)</ac>
    <hp>90 (12d8+36)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Dex +5, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Persuasion +6, Stealth +5, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The firbolg makes two attacks using Longsword, Bewitching Bolt, or a combination of them.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d8 + 3) slashing damage, or 8 (1d10 + 3) slashing damage if used with two hands, plus 9 (2d8) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Longsword|+6|(1d8+3)+(2d8)</attack>
      <attack>Longsword (Two-Handed)|+6|(1d10+3)+(2d8)</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+6|1d8+3</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage (Two-Handed)|+6|1d10+3</attack>
      <attack>Psychic Damage||2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bewitching Bolt</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +6 to hit, range 60 ft., one creature. Hit: 10 (2d6 + 3) psychic damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 14 Charisma saving throw or have the charmed condition until the start of the target's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Damage|+6|2d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The firbolg casts one of the following spells, using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 14):

	• At will: mage hand, minor illusion, Tasha's hideous laughter
	• 1/Day each: detect magic, disguise self, dispel magic, polymorph</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Duplicitous Movement (1/Day) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>1/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The firbolg projects an illusory duplicate of itself in an unoccupied space it can see within 30 feet of itself. The firbolg can then swap places with the illusion. The illusion vanishes after 1 minute, if the firbolg is incapacitated, or if the illusion is more than 120 feet from the firbolg.
	As a bonus action on later turns, the firbolg can move the illusion up to 30 feet and can then swap places with it.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>mage hand, minor illusion, tasha's hideous laughter, detect magic, disguise self, dispel magic, polymorph</spells>
    <description>Firbolgs inspired by the saga of Diancastra embark on adventures to create their own legends. These wanderers use their magic for trickery and disguise to emulate Diancastra.

Firbolgs:
Distant cousins of giants, the first firbolgs wandered the primeval forests of the multiverse, and the magic of those forests entwined itself with the firbolgs' souls. Ages later, that magic still thrums inside firbolgs.
	Firbolgs are often drawn to the service or emulation of the gods Diancastra and Hiatea. Firbolgs'
innate magic of obscurement and trickery resonates with Diancastra's wily resourcefulness. A traditional emphasis on community and harmony leads many firbolgs to pledge themselves to Hiatea's service.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 137</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Fire Giant Forgecaller</name>
    <sortname>Fire Giant, Forgecaller</sortname>
    <ancestry>Fire Giant</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant (cleric)</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>312 (25d12+150)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., fly 30 ft.(hover), canHover true ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>23</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>21</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Wis +11, Dex +6, Int +9</save>
    <skill>Athletics +13, Perception +11</skill>
    <passive>21</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>18</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>fire</immune>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the giant fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Fire Rune</name>
      <text>The giant has a fire rune inscribed on a medallion or some other object in its possession. While holding or wearing the object bearing the rune, the giant can use its Magma Wave action and Furnace Armor bonus action.
	The object bearing the rune has AC 15; 40 hit points; and immunity to necrotic, poison, and psychic damage. The object regains all its hit points at the end of every turn, but it turns to dust if reduced to 0 hit points or when the giant dies. If the rune is destroyed, the giant can inscribe a fire rune on an object in its possession when it finishes a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes three Forge Hammer attacks or two Heated Rock attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Forge Hammer</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 24 (5d6 + 7) bludgeoning damage. Hit or Miss: The giant can cause the hammer to emit a burst of heat in a 30-foot-radius sphere centered on the target. Metal objects in that area glow red-hot until the start of the giant's next turn. Any creature in physical contact with a heated object at the start of its turn must make a DC 19 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the creature takes 10 (3d6) fire damage and has disadvantage on attack rolls until the start of its next turn unless it has immunity to fire damage. The hammer can emit heat in this way only once per turn.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+13|5d6+7</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Heated Rock</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, range 60/240 ft., one target. Hit: 23 (3d10 + 7) bludgeoning damage plus 19 (3d12) fire damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 21 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition. After the giant throws the rock, roll a d6; on a roll of 3 or lower, the giant has no more rocks to throw.</text>
      <attack>Heated Rock|+13|(3d10+7)+(3d12)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+13|3d10+7</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||3d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Magma Wave (Requires Fire Rune)</name>
      <text>The giant emits a wave of magma from its fire rune in a 30-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 19 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 36 (8d8) fire damage and has the restrained condition. As an action, a creature can make a DC 19 Strength (Athletics) check, freeing itself or a creature within its reach from the rock on a success. The rock restraining each creature has AC 17; 20 hit points; and immunity to fire, poison, and psychic damage. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.</text>
      <attack>Fire Damage||8d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Furnace Armor (Requires Fire Rune) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The giant causes smoke and cinders to billow from its armor, filling a 30-foot-radius sphere centered on the giant. While the armor is billowing smoke, the giant has half cover. The armor stops billowing smoke after 1 minute, when the giant dies, when the giant uses a bonus action to end the effect, or when the giant's fire rune is destroyed.</text>
    </action>
    <description>A fire giant who masters traditional rune magic can control the heat of a volcanic environment and conjure raw elemental energy of fire and magma. In a fire giant community, these forgecallers oversee both forges and the community's defense, often in Surtur's name. Some forgecallers prefer to live and work in isolation, seeking the hottest fires in volcanoes' hearts or the Elemental Plane of Fire to pursue their own crafts and studies.
	A forgecaller is a walking furnace, clad head to toe in plate armor that seems to barely contain intense heat and billowing smoke. They conjure waves of magma and can fly by jetting magical fire from their legs and body.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 138</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Fire Giant of Evil Fire</name>
    <sortname>Fire Giant, Evil Fire</sortname>
    <ancestry>Fire Giant</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>150 (12d12+72)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>23</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>19</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Wis +8, Con +10, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +11, Perception +8</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant, Ignan</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>fire</immune>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Shrapnel Explosion</name>
      <text>When the giant drops to 0 hit points, its armor explodes, destroying the giant's body and scattering the armor as shrapnel. Creatures within 10 feet of the giant when its armor explodes must make a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw, taking 21 (6d6) piercing damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage||6d6</attack>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes two Searing Scepter attacks or two Bolt of Imix attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Searing Scepter</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 17 (3d6 + 7) bludgeoning damage plus 9 (2d8) fire damage, and the target is magically branded. While branded in this way, the target becomes visible if it's invisible, can't become invisible, and sheds dim light in a 5-foot radius. The brand disappears after 24 hours, or it can be removed from a creature or an object by any spell that ends a curse.</text>
      <attack>Searing Scepter|+11|(3d6+7)+(2d8)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+11|3d6+7</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bolt of Imix</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +8 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 20 (3d10 + 4) fire damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 16 Wisdom saving throw or have the frightened condition until the end of the target's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Fire Damage|+8|3d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <description>A fire giant is born around flame. works with flame, and lives among flames, but a fire giant who gazes into flames too deeply may see the Prince of Evil Fire, Imix, gazing back. Giants who fa1l to Imix's corruption might leave their homes to join with likeminded cultists, but others remain within their communities to pursue Imix's destructive agenda.
	A fire giant of Evil Fire forges a set of armor and weapons in flames blessed by Imix. The giant can then call on these magical flames to strike the foes of the Eternal Flame. The armor forged in these flames welds to the flesh. so while the giant isn't burned, the armor can't be removed once donned. When the giant dies, the armor explodes as a final gift from the All-Consuming Fire.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 139</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Fire Hellion</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>fiend (devil)</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>175 (14d12+84)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>23</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>21</cha>
    <save>Wis +6, Cha +9</save>
    <skill>Arcana +7, Athletics +11, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>11</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>fire</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The hellion has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Soul Taker</name>
      <text>A Giant or a Humanoid that is reduced to 0 hit points by the hellion dies, and its soul rises as a lemure (see the Monster Manual) on Avernus, one of the Nine Hells, in 1d4 hours. If the creature isn't revived before then, it can be restored to life only by a wish spell or by killing the lemure and casting true resurrection on the creature's original body.</text>
      <attack>Hours||1d4</attack>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The hellion makes two Morningstar attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Morningstar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 20 (3d8 + 7) piercing damage plus 11 (2d10) fire damage. If the target is a creature, it can't regain hit points until the start of the hellion's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Morningstar|+11|3d8+7</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||2d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Infernal Orb</name>
      <text>The hellion hurls a magical ball of fire that explodes in a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on a point the hellion can see within 120 feet of itself. The sphere spreads around corners. Each creature in that area must make a DC 17 Dexterity saving throw. A creature takes 18 (4d8) fire damage and 18 (4d8) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Infernal Orb||(4d8)+(4d8)</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||4d8</attack>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage||4d8</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Fire giants study war in its many forms across the multiverse, which sometimes leads the giants to a fascination with the Blood War-the endless conflict between demons and devils across the Lower Planes. Such a giant might enter into a pact with a powerful devil, hoping to learn tactics the devils have fine-tuned over millennia and to acquire magical gifts to help the giant rise in the ordning.
	Over time, the giant is corrupted, becoming a Fiend in its own right. The devil teaches the giant how to forge with infernal iron and hellfire, enabling the giant to craft weapons that can funnel the souls of the slain to Avernus, the first layer of the Nine Hells. In this way, the devil stands to gain a constant supply of souls from the giant's enemies, as well as the promise that the giant will serve the devil as a smith in the Nine He11s after death.
	The corrupted fire giant takes on fiendish features, including horns, cloven hooves for feet, and a forked tail.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 140</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Firegaunt</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (damaged plate)</ac>
    <hp>175 (14d12+84)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>7</dex>
    <con>23</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save>Con +10, Dex +2, Cha +5</save>
    <skill>Athletics +11, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>11</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>necrotic</resist>
    <immune>fire, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Fire Blood</name>
      <text>Whenever a creature within 5 feet of the firegaunt hits the firegaunt with a melee attack that deals piercing or slashing damage, that creature takes 5 (1d10) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Fire Damage||1d10</attack>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The firegaunt makes two Heated Maul attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Heated Maul</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 23 (3d10 + 7) bludgeoning damage. The firegaunt can cause the maul to erupt with crimson flames, and the target must succeed on a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw or take 10 (3d6) fire damage and 10 (3d6) necrotic damage. The maul can erupt with flames in this way only once per turn.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+11|3d10+7</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||3d6</attack>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Crimson Rays (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The firegaunt emits beams of fire from its eyes, mouth, and wounds in a 30-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw, taking 31 (7d8) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. On a success or failure, that creature catches fire. Until the burning creature or another creature that can reach it takes an action to extinguish the fire, the burning creature can't regain hit points and takes 5 (1d10) fire damage at the start of each of its turns.</text>
      <attack>Fire Damage||7d8</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||1d10</attack>
    </action>
    <description>A fire giant whose burning hatred prevents it from moving on to the afterlife rises as a firegaunt. Spawned from deep rancor, the firegaunt seeks out living creatures to destroy. Like a specter, it doesn't seek redemption; it just hopes to cause as much destruction as possible before attaining its final oblivion.
	A firegaunt looks like a severely burned corpse. Supernatural crimson flames flow through its veins, erupting from its wounds and its mouth.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 137</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Flesh Colossus</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>280 (16d20+112)</hp>
    <speed>60 ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>24</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands Giant but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>20</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>lightning, poison, psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Berserk</name>
      <text>If the core inside the colossus is destroyed, the colossus goes berserk. On each of its turns while berserk, the colossus attacks the nearest creature it can see. If no creature is near enough to move to and attack, the colossus attacks an object. Once the colossus goes berserk, it remains berserk until it is destroyed.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The colossus is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The colossus has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The colossus deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The colossus makes two Fist attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Fist</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit (with advantage if the colossus is berserk), reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 17 (3d6 + 7) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, it is pulled up to 15 feet toward the colossus, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 17), and it has the restrained condition until this grapple ends. The colossus can have up to two creatures grappled this way at a time.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+13|3d6+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Elemental Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The colossus exhales a cloud swirling with elemental energy in a 90-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 21 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 40 (9d8) damage of a type of the colossus's choosing: acid, cold, fire, or lightning. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage.
	At the same time as the colossus releases this exhalation, creatures inside the colossus's chest cavity take 40 (9d8) force damage from churning elemental energy.</text>
      <attack>Acid, Cold, Fire, or Lightning Damage||9d8</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage||9d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 5 ft., one Large or smaller creature grappled by the colossus. Hit: 20 (3d8 + 7) bludgeoning damage, and the creature is swallowed. A swallowed creature has the restrained condition, has total cover against attacks and other effects outside the colossus, and takes 10 (3d6) force damage at the start of each of the colossus's turns.
	The colossus's chest cavity can hold up to two creatures at a time. Inside its chest cavity is its core, which is a Large object with AC 16 that is immune to lightning, poison, and psychic damage. It has 140 hit points and sheds dim light in a 10-foot radius. If the core is destroyed, the colossus regurgitates all swallowed creatures, each of which falls in a space within 10 feet of the colossus and has the prone condition, and the colossus can no longer swallow a creature. If the colossus dies, any swallowed creature no longer has the restrained condition and can escape from the corpse using 10 feet of movement, exiting with the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+13|3d8+7</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>During the dawn of the giants' empires, twisted minds sought to make their fallen comrades continue their service. Wizard giants stitched and wove the flesh of various giants over an adamantine skeleton, creating a grisly colossal construct. Inside the flesh colossus's chest is a stone sphere infused with spirits from each elemental plane acting as its core.
	To this day, some of these ancient flesh colossi guard abandoned ruins, sites sacred to giants, and lost treasures-and possibly the procedure to create new examples of their kind.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 141</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Fomorian Deep Crawler</name>
    <sortname>Fomorian, Deep Crawler</sortname>
    <ancestry>Fomorian</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>184 (16d12+80)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Stealth +6, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Contortionist</name>
      <text>The fomorian can enter a space large enough for a Large creature without squeezing.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Crawling Stance</name>
      <text>While the fomorian has the prone condition, crawling does not cost it extra movement. In addition, the prone condition does not grant advantage on attack rolls against the fomorian.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>The fomorian can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The fomorian makes two Slam attacks and uses Crawling Hex if it is available.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 22 (3d10 + 6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+10|3d10+6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Crawling Hex (Recharge 4-6)</name>
      <recharge>D4</recharge>
      <text>The fomorian targets one creature it can see within 60 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 15 Wisdom saving throw or take 31 (7d8) psychic damage, have the prone condition, and become cursed for 1 hour. While cursed this way, the target can't stand up and end the prone condition on itself.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Damage||7d8</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Deep crawlers are fomorians whose bodies are adapted to crawling through the tunnels of the Underdark, perhaps in imitation or in honor of Karontor, "the king that crawls." Their limbs are long and sinuous, and their grip is strong enough for them to climb walls and ceilings.

Fomorians:
Descended from Annam's son Karontor, fomorians once occupied a place in the giants' ordning between hill and stone giants. In ancient times, they were scholars of magic known for their keen intellect-but also for their inflated egos and sense of entitlement. Karontor exploited these qualities, tempting them with promises of higher standing in the ordning, and incited his descendants to launch an assault on the Feywild. When the assault failed, the fomorians were banished to the Underdark and their god was consigned to a subterranean prison. Subjected to the strange magic of the Underdark, the fomorians' bodies and souls twisted until they became the fomorians of today.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 142</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Fomorian Noble</name>
    <sortname>Fomorian, Noble</sortname>
    <ancestry>Fomorian</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant (wizard)</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (17 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>253 (22d12+110)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>19</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Wis +7, Cha +8, Int +9</save>
    <skill>Stealth +9, Arcana +14, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Giant plus any three languages</languages>
    <cr>15</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>charmed</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+5</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The fomorian makes three Rod attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rod</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 16 (3d6 + 6) bludgeoning damage plus 11 (2d10) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Rod|+11|(3d6+6)+(2d10)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+11|3d6+6</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage||2d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The fomorian casts one of the following spells, using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 17):

	• At will: mage armor (self only), mage hand, prestidigitation
	• 1/Day each: chain lightning, cone of cold (6th-level version), fireball (6th-level version), fly, plane shift (self only)</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Beguiling Presence (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The fomorian targets a creature it can see within 60 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw or have the charmed condition for 1 minute. An affected target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns and whenever it takes damage, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a target's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the target becomes immune to all fomorians' Beguiling Presence for the next 24 hours.</text>
    </action>
    <spells>mage armor, mage hand, prestidigitation, chain lightning, cone of cold, fireball, fly, plane shift</spells>
    <description>Before their banishment to the Underdark, fomorians ordered themselves based on achievements of knowledge and magical power. Before Karontor urged his descendants into an ill-fated assault against the Feywild, some of the most ambitious, inquisitive, and power-hungry fomorians felt they had already learned all theycould from the Material Plane, and they departed to the Inner Planes, where they could continue their journeys of knowledge unopposed.
	In their arrogance, these fomorian nobles unknowingly escaped the dreadful fate of their kin, and they remain unchanged in their remote enclaves. Occasionally they return to the Material Plane to survey the world they left. With angular features and apparently ageless faces, these fomorians resemble gigantic elves.

Fomorians:
Descended from Annam's son Karontor, fomorians once occupied a place in the giants' ordning between hill and stone giants. In ancient times, they were scholars of magic known for their keen intellect-but also for their inflated egos and sense of entitlement. Karontor exploited these qualities, tempting them with promises of higher standing in the ordning, and incited his descendants to launch an assault on the Feywild. When the assault failed, the fomorians were banished to the Underdark and their god was consigned to a subterranean prison. Subjected to the strange magic of the Underdark, the fomorians' bodies and souls twisted until they became the fomorians of today.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 143</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Fomorian Warlock of the Dark</name>
    <sortname>Fomorian, Warlock of the Dark</sortname>
    <ancestry>Fomorian</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>207 (18d12+90)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Wis +6, Cha +8</save>
    <skill>Stealth +5, Arcana +3, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Blood Rune</name>
      <text>The fomorian has a blood rune inscribed on an effigy or some other object in its possession. While holding or wearing the object bearing the rune, the giant can use its Corrupting Hex action and Poisoning Rebuke reaction.
	The object bearing the blood rune has AC 15; 30 hit points; and immunity to necrotic, poison, and psychic damage. The object regains all its hit points at the end of every turn, but it turns to dust if reduced to 0 hit points or when the fomorian dies. If the rune is destroyed, the fomorian can inscribe a blood rune on an object in its possession when it finishes a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Devil's Sight</name>
      <text>Magical darkness doesn't impede the fomorian's darkvision.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the fomorian fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The fomorian makes three Greatclub attacks. If the fomorian has its blood rune, it can replace one of these attacks with a use of Corrupting Hex.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Greatclub</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: 19 (3d8 + 6) bludgeoning damage plus 7 (2d6) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Greatclub|+10|(3d8+6)+(2d6)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+10|3d8+6</attack>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage||2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Corrupting Hex (Requires Blood Rune)</name>
      <text>The fomorian targets one creature it can see within 60 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 16 Charisma saving throw or take 27 (6d8) necrotic damage and become cursed for 24 hours. While cursed this way, the target's speed is reduced by half, and if it tries to cast a spell, it must first succeed on a DC 16 Intelligence check or the spell fails and is wasted.</text>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage||6d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Eldritch Burst</name>
      <text>Magical energy explodes in a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on a point the fomorian can see within 120 feet of itself. Each creature in that area must make a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 32 (5d12) force damage and has the prone condition. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage||5d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The fomorian casts one of the following spells, using Charisma as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 16):

	• At will: detect magic, levitate, mage hand, prestidigitation
	• 1/Day each: detect thoughts, suggestion, telekinesis</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Creeping Gloom (Recharge 6) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>The fomorian momentarily conjures grasping darkness in a 30-foot-radius sphere centered on a point it can see within 120 feet of itself. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 16 Constitution saving throw or take 11 (2d10) necrotic damage and have the blinded condition until the end of its next turn.

Blinded:
	• A blinded creature can't see and automatically fails any ability check that requires sight.
	• Attack rolls against the creature have advantage, and the creature's attack rolls have disadvantage.</text>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage||2d10</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Poisoning Rebuke (Requires Blood Rune)</name>
      <text>In response to being damaged by a creature the fomorian can see within 60 feet of itself, the fomorian forces that creature to make a DC 16 Constitution saving throw; on a failed save, the creature has the poisoned condition until the end of its next turn.</text>
    </reaction>
    <spells>detect magic, levitate, mage hand, prestidigitation, detect thoughts, suggestion, telekinesis</spells>
    <description>Some fomorians search for the arcane glory their kind possessed before their banishment into the Underdark. They forge magical pacts with entities of the dark-perhaps powerful Fey of the Gloaming Court or eldritch entities buried deep in the Underdark. Their pacts give these fomorians power over shadows, allowing them to mold and shape darkness like clay.

Fomorians:
Descended from Annam's son Karontor, fomorians once occupied a place in the giants' ordning between hill and stone giants. In ancient times, they were scholars of magic known for their keen intellect-but also for their inflated egos and sense of entitlement. Karontor exploited these qualities, tempting them with promises of higher standing in the ordning, and incited his descendants to launch an assault on the Feywild. When the assault failed, the fomorians were banished to the Underdark and their god was consigned to a subterranean prison. Subjected to the strange magic of the Underdark, the fomorians' bodies and souls twisted until they became the fomorians of today.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 144</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Frost Giant Ice Shaper</name>
    <sortname>Frost Giant, Ice Shaper</sortname>
    <ancestry>Frost Giant</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant (cleric)</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (chain mail)</ac>
    <hp>310 (27d12+135)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>19</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Str +12, Wis +10, Con +11, Cha +9</save>
    <skill>Athletics +12, Perception +10</skill>
    <passive>20</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>17</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>cold</immune>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Frost Rune</name>
      <text>The giant has a frost rune inscribed on a chunk of ice or some other object in its possession. While holding or wearing the object bearing the rune, the giant can use its Ice Wolves action and Ice Armor reaction.
	The object bearing the rune has AC 16; 40 hit points; and immunity to necrotic, poison, and psychic damage. The object regains all its hit points at the end of every turn, but it turns to dust if reduced to 0 hit points or when the giant dies. If the rune is destroyed, the giant can inscribe a frost rune on an object in its possession when it finishes a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the giant fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes three attacks using Greataxe, Freezing Ray, or a combination of them.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Greataxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 22 (3d10 + 6) slashing damage plus 9 (2d8) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Greataxe|+12|(3d10+6)+(2d8)</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+12|3d10+6</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Freezing Ray</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +10 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 17 (3d8 + 4) cold damage, and the target must make a DC 18 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the target has the restrained condition until the end of its next turn. On a successful save, the target's speed is reduced by 10 feet until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Cold Damage|+10|3d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ice Wolves (Requires Frost Rune)</name>
      <text>The giant magically summons 1d4 wolves made of ice (use the winter wolf stat block in the Monster Manual to represent them, but they are Elementals instead of Monstrosities). The wolves appear in unoccupied spaces the giant can see within 30 feet of itself. The wolves take their turn immediately after the giant on the same initiative count, and they obey the giant's commands. The wolves gain a +6 bonus to their attack and damage rolls while they are within 30 feet of the giant. The wolves disappear after 1 minute, when the giant dies, or when the giant uses this action again.</text>
      <attack>Wolves||1d4</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Ice Armor (Requires Frost Rune)</name>
      <text>When a creature the giant can see makes an attack roll against it, the giant can form a coat of ice around itself, granting it a +6 bonus to its AC against that attack. After the attack hits or misses, the ice shatters, and each creature within 5 feet of the giant must succeed on a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw or take 13 (3d8) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Cold Damage||3d8</attack>
    </reaction>
    <description>Frost giants who master rune magic are known as ice shapers, and their sheer power typically contributes to a meteoric rise in the giants' ordning. Many of them end up as jarls, leading their communities, or as advisers to jarls-often the true power behind the throne. They are usually devoted to Thrym.
	True to their name, these ice shapers manipulate the raw elemental energy of air and water to wield ice in both offense and defense. They summon ice elementals in the shape of wolves, cloak themselves in icy armor, and just as quickly turn that armor into a hail of deadly ice shards.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 145</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Frost Giant of Evil Water</name>
    <sortname>Frost Giant, Evil Water</sortname>
    <ancestry>Frost Giant</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (scale mail)</ac>
    <hp>172 (15d12+75)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Wis +6, Con +9, Dex +7</save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +10, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Aquan, Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>11</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>cold</immune>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The giant can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes two Battleaxe attacks and one Harpoon attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Battleaxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 19 (3d8 + 6) slashing damage, or 22 (3d10 + 6) slashing damage if used with two hands, plus 7 (2d6) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Battleaxe|+10|(3d8+6)+(2d6)</attack>
      <attack>Battleaxe (Two-Handed)|+10|(3d10+6)+(2d6)</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+10|3d8+6</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage (Two-Handed)|+10|3d10+6</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Harpoon</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, range 50/200 ft., one creature. Hit: 14 (2d10 + 3) piercing damage, and the target has the grappled condition (escape DC 16). While the target is grappled this way, its speed isn't reduced, but it can't move farther from the giant. The target takes 5 (1d10) slashing damage if it escapes from the grapple or if it tries and fails. The giant can grapple only one target at a time with its harpoon.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+7|2d10+3</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage||1d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Reel In (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The giant pulls the target grappled by its Harpoon up to 20 feet toward itself.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Though primordials of frost and ice do exist (most notably Cryonax, who is sometimes considered almost the equal of the four Princes of Elemental Evil), frost giants who turn from the gods of the Ordning to embrace Elemental Evil are more likely to serve Olhydra, the Princess of Evil Water. To these giants, water is a cruel and destructive force that finds its ultimate expression in ice. These cultists of Evil Water often hide their allegiance as long as possible while urging their communities to ever increasing depths of cruelty and violence, but if the cultists' apostasy is revealed and they are exiled, they often end up as leaders of Olhydra's cults in colder regions.
	Olhydra grants these frost giants the ability to breathe underwater, and they wield armor and weapons that reflect their commitment to the cult. Their armor is outfitted with enormous crossbows that can launch barbed harpoons, which the giants use to drag enemies into or through the water.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 146</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Frostmourn</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>195 (17d12+85)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Wis +4, Con +9</save>
    <skill>Athletics +10, Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>cold, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The frostmourn makes one Freezing Touch attack and one Icy Axe attack. It can replace one of these attacks with a Polar Ray attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Freezing Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. Hit: 18 (4d8) cold damage plus 18 (4d8) necrotic damage. If this damage would reduce the target to 0 hit points, the target drops to 1 hit point instead and has the petrified condition, turning into a frozen statue.
	If the statue takes bludgeoning damage, it shatters, killing the frozen creature. If the statue would take fire damage, it instead takes no damage and thaws, ending the petrification.</text>
      <attack>Freezing Touch|+10|(4d8)+(4d8)</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage|+10|4d8</attack>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage||4d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Icy Axe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 19 (3d8 + 6) slashing damage plus 7 (2d6) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Icy Axe|+10|(3d8+6)+(2d6)</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+10|3d8+6</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Polar Ray</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +8 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 31 (5d10 + 4) cold damage, and the target's speed is reduced by 10 feet until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Cold Damage|+8|5d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Blizzard Escape</name>
      <text>Immediately after a creature the frostmourn can see hits it with an attack roll, the frostmourn momentarily dissolves into a blizzard, reducing the damage to itself by half. The frostmourn can then magically teleport to an unoccupied space it can see within 30 feet of itself.</text>
    </reaction>
    <description>When a frost giant is murdered in a dishonorable manner perhaps poisoned, stabbed in the back, or killed while sleeping the slain giant can rise as a frostmourn. Driven by its desire for vengeance, the frostmourn can turn the living into frozen statues with a touch or blast enemies with frigid wind. Achieving vengeance is not always enough to grant these creatures rest; often, their hatred and loathing of the living is sufficient to keep them roaming the wilds for years after their murderers are slain.
	A frostmourn looks like a desiccated corpse mummified by exposure to bitter cold. It carries the marks of its death on its body: a wound that seeps frosty vapor or vibrant, purple veins showing the ravages of poison. It can momentarily dissolve its body into a swirling blizzard to avoid harm, reforming at a distance to continue its assault.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 147</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Fury of Kostchtchie</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>fiend (demon)</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>216 (16d12+112)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>26</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>25</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Wis +6, Con +12</save>
    <skill>Athletics +13, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Giant</languages>
    <cr>14</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>fire, lightning, poison</resist>
    <immune>cold</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+5</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Chilling Aura</name>
      <text>A creature that starts its turn within 10 feet of the fury must succeed on a DC 20 Constitution saving throw or take 11 (2d10) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Cold Damage||2d10</attack>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The fury has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The fury makes two Fist or Rock attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Fist</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 17 (2d8 + 8) bludgeoning damage plus 10 (3d6) cold damage, or 17 (5d6) cold damage if the target took damage from the fury's Chilling Aura since the end of the fury's last turn.</text>
      <attack>Fist|+13|(2d8+8)+(3d6)</attack>
      <attack>Fist (Damaged Before)|+13|(2d8+8)+(5d6)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+13|2d8+8</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||3d6</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||5d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rock</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, range 60/240 ft., one target. Hit: 30 (4d10 + 8) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+13|4d10+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Charge (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The fury can move up to its speed toward an enemy it can see.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Frost giants who struggle to rise in their ordning, along with those who reject Annam and his children, sometimes turn to the worship of the demon lord Kostchtchie. In the myths of these giants, Kostchtchie was once a frost giant of such tremendous might that he slew a demon lord in single combat, claimed its Abyssal realm for himself and now waits for other frost giants to join him in conquering the rest of the Abyss.
	When Kostchtchie answers the pleas of giants, he gives them supernatural strength and ferocious bloodlust. The giants' muscles expand, their arms extend past their knees, and bitter cold surrounds them. The demon lord's gifts come at a cost, though, as the giants' souls slowly burn away to fuel these newfound powers. Over time, the sensation of burning in the chest intensifies, driving these giants into a frenzy. The newly transformed Fiends quickly find that only combat can numb the burning.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 148</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Gargantua</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic neutral</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>388 (21d20+168)</hp>
    <speed>60 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>26</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Wis +10, Dex +7, Int +6</save>
    <skill/>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>21</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>force, psychic</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+7</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Weird Aura</name>
      <text>At the start of each of the gargantua's turns, each creature of the gargantua's choice within 30 feet of it must make a DC 19 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, a target sees the gargantua as a manifestation of the target's worst fears; it takes 17 (5d6) psychic damage and has the frightened condition until the start of the target's next turn. On a successful save, a target is immune to this gargantua's Weird Aura for 24 hours.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Damage||5d6</attack>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The gargantua makes two Slam or Rock attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 27 (3d12 + 8) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+15|3d12+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rock</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. Hit: 24 (3d10 + 8) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+15|3d10+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Baleful Hex (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The gargantua curses one creature it can see within 120 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 19 Wisdom saving throw or have the incapacitated condition until the end of its next turn.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Teleport (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The gargantua teleports, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying, to an unoccupied space that it can see within 120 feet of itself.</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Flick</name>
      <text>Immediately after the gargantua takes damage from a Large or smaller creature it can see within 20 feet of itself, it attempts to flick the creature away. The target must succeed on a DC 23 Strength saving throw, or the target takes 18 (3d6 + 8) bludgeoning damage, is pushed horizontally up to 100 feet away from the gargantua, and has the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage||3d6+8</attack>
    </reaction>
    <reaction>
      <name>Spell Mimicry (1/Day)</name>
      <recharge>1/DAY</recharge>
      <text>Immediately after a creature the gargantua can see casts a spell of 5th level or lower, the gargantua tries to copy the spell. That creature must succeed on a DC 19 Charisma saving throw, or the gargantua immediately casts the same spell at the same level (+11 to hit with spell attacks, spell save DC 19), requiring no material components and choosing the spell's targets.</text>
      <attack>Spell Mimicry|+11|</attack>
    </reaction>
    <description>From time to time-perhaps once a generation, under a particular configuration of stars and planets, or at the whim of some malicious god-a gargantua is born to giant parents. Though the child appears like any other of its kind, the creature's true nature manifests upon reaching adulthood: its complexion turns purplish and horns sprout from its head. The gargantua grows rapidly, eventually towering over other giants at a height of 40 feet or more.
	Most gargantuas do not feel at home in giant communities and end up searching for homes large enough to hold their enormous frames. They might find a suitable home in an ancient forest, a deep canyon, or an immense cavern in the Underdark. Some gargantuas seek only peace and solitude, while others lash out fiercely at a world that fears them.
	Giants tell a variety of stories to explain the existence of gargantuas. One tale connects their origin to an ancient enclave's pact with an entity from the Far Realm. Another claims that Karontor, "the banished son" of Annam, creates gargantuas in retaliation for his imprisonment. A third blames Annam, claiming the All-Father of the giants is disgusted with his descendants and seeks to destroy them.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 149</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Giant Child</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>4 (1d8)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Club</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 4 (1d4 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+4|1d4+2</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Generally, it's a good idea to avoid situations where you treat a giant child as a monster. While even giant toddlers can be dangerous, they're no match for adventurers who can handle giant parents. Young giants are no more inherently evil than any other free-willed creature, so fighting and killing them can raise abundant moral questions for good-aligned characters. At minimum, make sure all your players are comfortable with that kind of quandary before presenting it in your game.
	lf you need a stat block for a giant who is less than full grown, use the following guidelines (inspired by the examples presented in the Storm King's Thunder adventure).
	For a giant child, use the commoner stat block. Change the creature type to Giant, increase the Strength to l4 (+2), and choose Giant as the child's one language. The child attacks at +4 and deals 4 (1d4 + 2) bludgeoning damage with a club (which might be a toy or anything else the child picks up to use as a weapon).
	For a giant teenager, use the ogre stat block. Increase the intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma scores to l0 or match the parents' scores, whichever is lower. (This increases the teenager's passive Perception score to 10 as well.) Remove darkvision (unless the teenager is a stone giant) and adjust the teenager's weapons and armor as you see fit.
	For a young adult giant, use the stat block of a giant lower in the ordning. For example, Storm King's Thunder includes young cloud giants that use the hill giant stat block with several adjustments. You can craft the stat block as you see fit to match the challenge rating you're aiming for.
	For a giant child of any age, you can further modify one ofthese stat blocks by adding the parents' damage immunities and resistances (if any) and any inherent traits.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 34</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Giant Goose</name>
    <sortname>Giant Animal, Goose</sortname>
    <ancestry>Giant Animal, Goose</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>60 (8d10+16)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., fly 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>understands Giant and Sylvan but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The goose makes one Beak attack and two Wing attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Beak</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 9 (2d6 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+4|2d6+2</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Wing</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d10 + 2) bludgeoning damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 12 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+4|1d10+2</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Thunderous Honk (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The goose honks with ear-splitting volume. Each other creature within 30 feet of the goose must make a DC 12 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 16 (3d10) thunder damage and has the deafened condition until the start of the goose's next turn. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only. The honk can be heard within 300 feet.</text>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||3d10</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Giants keep geese as livestock for eggs and because geese make excellent sentries, protecting the giants' property with their keen senses and loud voices. Not only are giant geese from fey stock significantly larger than ordinary geese, but they also have two magical properties that make them even more valuable: their honk is a powerful defense against intruders, and they can lay eggs with shells of pure gold.
	When commanded by its keeper, a giant goose lays a golden egg-a hollow shell of gold, 1 foot long and weighing 2 pounds. The shell is worth 100 gp. Sometimes, the egg inexplicably contains some kind of small trinket or minor magic item. Once it lays a golden egg, a giant goose can't do so again for a year and a day.
	You can use the Goose Egg Trinket table to determine the contents of a golden egg. A giant goose's egg can be a great way to give characters an item that's important to the story of an adventure or your campaign.

Goose Egg Trinket:
d12 | Egg Contents
1 | The egg is empty, but the inside of the shell is inscribed with a poem or an intricate illustration.
2 | The gold shell encloses a candy egg.
3 | The egg holds a small toy goose that makes a loud honking noise when squeezed.
4 | The egg contains a potion of giant strength (hill giant) with no container.
5 | The egg holds a pearl of power.
6 | The egg contains a brooch of shielding.
7 | The egg contains a fgurine of wondrous power (silver raven) that activates automatically as the egg is opened, releasing what appears to be a living bird.
8-12 | The egg is empty.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 150</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Giant Lynx</name>
    <sortname>Giant, Lynx</sortname>
    <ancestry>Giant Animal, Lynx</ancestry>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>14</ac>
    <hp>22 (4d8+4)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Stealth +6, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>truesight 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Lynx's Sight (1/Day)</name>
      <recharge>1/DAY</recharge>
      <text>The lynx can cast clairvoyance, requiring no spell components and using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Woodland Camouflage</name>
      <text>The lynx has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide in undergrowth or snowy terrain.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 8 (1d8 + 4) slashing damage. If the lynx moved at least 20 feet straight toward the target immediately before the hit, the target must succeed on a DC 12 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition. If the target has the prone condition, the lynx can make another Claws attack against it as a bonus action.</text>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+6|1d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <spells>Clairvoyance</spells>
    <description>Though they're often mistaken for mundane cats, giant lynxes are magical creatures with origins in the snowy woodlands of the Feywild. Their coats grow lighter in winter, helping to camouflage them in their favored habitats even when the landscape is draped in snow.
	Giant lynxes are crafty hunters, cooperating in small groups to trap prey and occasionally using a magical gift to scout likely hunting locations. They're also smart enough to outwit many of the hunters who seek to trap them for their fur, and they're fond of disabling any trappers' snares they find in their territories.
	Frost and cloud giants sometimes befriend giant lynxes and treat them as beloved pets. As long as the lynxes' intelligence and independence are respected, the creatures are happy to share their divination magic with their giant companions.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 151</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Giant Ox</name>
    <sortname>Giant, Ox</sortname>
    <ancestry>Giant Animal, Ox</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>105 (10d12+40)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>22</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>4</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands Giant and Sylvan but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Beast of Burden</name>
      <text>The ox is considered to be one size larger for the purpose of determining its carrying capacity.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Gore</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 13 (2d6 + 6) piercing damage. If the ox moved at least 20 feet straight toward the target immediately before the hit, the target takes an extra 7 (2d6) piercing damage, and it must succeed on a DC 16 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+8|2d6+6</attack>
      <attack>Piercing Damage||2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Giant oxen labor as beasts of burden for giants of all kinds, pulling plows, hauling oversized carts, and performing similar tasks well suited to their tremendous strength. These cattle are covered in thick, shaggy hide, often in vibrant colors, such as sky blue or deep violet.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 152</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Giant Ram</name>
    <sortname>Giant, Ram</sortname>
    <ancestry>Giant Animal, Ram</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>28 (3d10+12)</hp>
    <speed>50 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages/>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire, lightning</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The ram has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Ram</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 9 (2d4 + 4) bludgeoning damage plus 3 (1d6) force damage. If the ram moved at least 20 feet straight toward the target immediately before the hit, the target must succeed on a DC 14 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Ram|+6|(2d4+4)+(1d6)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+6|2d4+4</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage||1d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Force Bolt</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +4 to hit, range 30 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (2d6) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage|+4|2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Absorbent Fleece (Recharge 6)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>Immediately after the ram succeeds on a saving throw against a spell or a spell's attack misses it, the ram can make one Force Bolt attack.</text>
    </reaction>
    <description>Giant rams are prized livestock among giants. The rams' fleece stores magical energy by absorbing ambient magic and drawing power from spells. While a ram is alive and unshorn, it uses its fleece's magic for self-defense, channeling the power it absorbs into a magical blast to drive off predators.
	If the fleece is shorn from the ram without damaging the creature, it can be made into a protective magical garment. When woven into cloth, the fleece serves as a cloak of protection It can also be woven into the lining of armor to make armor of resistance that protects against cold, fire, or lightning damage.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 153</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Giant Tick</name>
    <sortname>Giant, Tick</sortname>
    <ancestry>Giant Animal, Tick</ancestry>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>52 (7d8+21)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>2</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages/>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Proboscis</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. Hit: 10 (2d6 + 3) piercing damage, and the tick attaches to the target. While attached, the tick can't make Proboscis attacks. The tick can detach itself by spending 5 feet of its movement. As an action, a creature within reach of the tick can try to detach the tick, doing so with a successful DC 13 Strength check.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+5|2d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Blood Drain</name>
      <text>The tick deals 10 (2d6 + 3) necrotic damage to one creature it is physically attached to, provided that creature isn't a Construct or an Undead, or 17 (4d6 + 3) necrotic damage if the creature is a Giant. The tick regains hit points equal to the damage dealt.</text>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage||2d6+3</attack>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage (Giant)||4d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Ticks the size ofboars have feasted on the blood of giants for countless ages. Though these parasites are painful nuisances to giants, they can be terrible threats to smaller folk, since a hungry tick will consume the blood of any creature it can catch.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 153</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Gigant</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>325 (21d20+105)</hp>
    <speed>50 ft., fly 80 ft., burrow 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Wis +8, Dex +8</save>
    <skill>Perception +8</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages/>
    <cr>20</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spell-Resistant Carapace</name>
      <text>The gigant has advantage on saving throws against spells, and any creature that makes a spell attack against the gigant has disadvantage on the attack roll.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The gigant makes one Mandibles attack and two Talons attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Mandibles</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 10 ft., one creature. Hit: 21 (4d6 + 7) slashing damage, and the target has the grappled condition (escape DC 17). Until the grapple ends, the target takes 21 (4d6 + 7) slashing damage at the start of each of the gigant's turns. While the gigant is grappling a target, it can't use Mandibles against other targets.</text>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+13|4d6+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Talons</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 17 (3d6 + 7) slashing damage, and the target is pulled 10 feet straight toward the gigant.</text>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+13|3d6+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Scale Dust (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The gigant releases magical dust from its wings in a 30-foot cube. Each creature in that area must make a DC 19 Constitution saving throw, taking 45 (10d8) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. On a success or failure, the creature has the poisoned condition for 1 hour. While poisoned this way, the creature can't regain hit points.</text>
      <attack>Poison Damage||10d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Drone (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The gigant produces a horrid droning sound by rapidly beating its wings. Each creature within 10 feet of the gigant must succeed on a DC 19 Constitution saving throw or take 10 (3d6) thunder damage and have the incapacitated condition until the end of its next turn. The gigant can then fly up to half its flying speed.</text>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>A gigant is a towering insectile creature variously regarded as a harbinger of doom, a defender of nature, and a divine messenger of mysterious purpose. Giants regard them as a plague, since gigants prefer giants over other food. Some giants claim gigants are created by the weird magical aura that surrounds a gargantua (described earlier in this chapter).
	A gigant resembles an enormous beetle with legs ending in sharp talons. It uses its talons to bring creatures to its enormous mandibles, which are strong enough to carry a giant to the gigant's nest to be devoured.
	A gigant's wings are usually folded under its carapace, but the speedy flier can also beat its wings to create a horrible sound or to spread a toxic dust.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 154</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Goliath Giant-Kin</name>
    <npc>YES</npc>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (half plate, shield)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d8+27)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Survival +3, Athletics +6, Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The goliath makes two Spear attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage, or 8 (1d8 + 4) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+6|1d6+4</attack>
      <attack>Piercing Damage (Two-Handed)|+6|1d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Giant's Strikes (Recharge 5-6) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>Until the end of its turn, the goliath's melee attacks each deal an extra 7 (2d6) damage of a type determined by the goliath's giant community: cold (frost giant), fire (fire giant), force (stone giant), lightning (storm giant), piercing (hill giant), or thunder (cloud giant).</text>
      <attack>Giant's Strikes||2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Goliaths are Humanoids distantly related to giants. Infused with the supernatural essence of their ancestors' mountainous home, goliaths have the strength and fortitude to garner a giant's respect. Communities of goliaths who live in close relationship with giants emulate them and are recognized by the giants as kin. These goliath giant-kin often act as liaisons between giant clans and other Humanoids.
	Though they rarely stand more than 8 feet tall, goliaths can hold their own in contests of strength with ogres. Goliath giant-kin can also channel the magic of their giant relatives into mighty melee attacks.
	Though they are not part of the ordning. goliath giant-kin often revere the divine ancestors of the giants, with a particular affinity for Annam's daughters: Diancastra, Hiatea, and Iallanis. They also tend to extol the same virtues as the giants they live alongside, so goliath giant-kin dwelling near frost giants boast of their might, while those dweliing with stone giants cherish artistry.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 155</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Grinning Cat</name>
    <sortname>Cat, Grinning</sortname>
    <ancestry>Cat</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic neutral</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>45 (7d10+7)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft., climb 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Stealth +6, Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The grinning cat has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 7 (1d10 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+4|1d10+2</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 9 (2d6 + 2) slashing damage. If the grinning cat was invisible before it attacked, the target must succeed on a DC 12 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition. If the target has the prone condition, the cat can make a Bite attack against it as a bonus action.</text>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+4|2d6+2</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Fade Away</name>
      <text>The grinning cat magically becomes invisible for 1 hour or until it attacks, gradually fading away over the course of its turn. It can choose to leave part of its body visible, such as its tail, its head, or its grinning mouth. Any equipment the cat wears or carries is invisible with it.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Fade Back (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The grinning cat becomes visible or makes part of its body visible. Any equipment the cat wears or carries on a visible part of its body also becomes visible.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Grinning Step (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The grinning cat teleports, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying, up to 60 feet to an unoccupied space it can see.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Grinning cats are mischievous Fey who delight in pestering and misleading travelers. They resemble oversized domestic cats with long, needlelike claws, but they're distinguished by the wide, toothy smiles that give them their name.
	Grinning cats often dwell in or near giants' enclaves. They spend much of their time invisible, lounging on tree branches until prey-or a potential conversation partner-wanders by. While trading riddles or witticisms, a cat often decides to reveal its grin, its tail, or sometimes its whole head to confuse or intimidate the creature it's talking to.
	A grinning cat can be persuaded to bestow one of its whiskers as a gift. A creature holding a whisker can use it to cast the misty step spell once, then the whisker turns to smoke and is destroyed. If a grinning cat is slain, 2d12 of its whiskers can be retrieved for this purpose.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 156</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Hill Giant Avalancher</name>
    <sortname>Giant, Hill Avalancer</sortname>
    <ancestry>Giant</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant (druid)</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>220 (21d12+84)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>21</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Str +9, Wis +8, Con +8</save>
    <skill>Nature +7, Perception +8</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Hill Rune</name>
      <text>The giant has a hill rune inscribed on a rock or some other object in its possession. While holding or wearing the object bearing the rune, the giant can use its Stone Avalanche action and Hill Rebuff reaction.
	The object bearing the rune has AC 15; 20 hit points; and immunity to necrotic, poison, and psychic damage. The object regains all its hit points at the end of every turn, but it turns to dust if reduced to 0 hit points or when the giant dies. If the rune is destroyed, the giant can inscribe a hill rune on an object in its possession when it finishes a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the giant fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes one Greatclub attack and uses Stone Bolas.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Greatclub</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 18 (3d8 + 5) bludgeoning damage plus 9 (2d8) thunder damage.</text>
      <attack>Greatclub|+9|(3d8+5)+(2d8)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+9|3d8+5</attack>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Stone Bolas</name>
      <text>The giant conjures three stone balls connected by lines of magical force and throws them at one creature it can see within 60 feet of itself. The target must make a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, the target has the restrained condition until the start of the giant's next turn, and the stones erupt in a burst of thunderous energy that deals 14 (4d6) thunder damage to the target and each creature within 10 feet of the target. On a successful save, the stones vanish without erupting.</text>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||4d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The giant casts one of the following spells, using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 16):

	• At will: druidcraft, guidance
	• 1/Day each: stone shape, wall of stone</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Stone Avalanche (Requires Hill Rune)</name>
      <text>The giant conjures a hail of rocks in a 20-foot-radius, 40-foot-high cylinder centered on a point on the ground it can see within 120 feet of itself. Each creature in that area must make a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 28 (8d6) bludgeoning damage and has the prone condition. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.
	The rocks turn the ground in that area into difficult terrain until the start of the giant's next turn, when the rocks vanish.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage||8d6</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Hill Rebuff (Requires Hill Rune)</name>
      <text>Immediately after the giant takes damage from a creature it can see within 10 feet of itself, that creature must succeed on a DC 16 Constitution saving throw or take 10 (3d6) force damage and be pushed horizontally 10 feet away from the giant.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage||3d6</attack>
    </reaction>
    <spells>druidcraft, guidance, stone shape, wall of stone</spells>
    <description>Hill giants who master rune magic discover a close connection to the natural forces of earth and stone. Their magic, combined with their size and strength, helps them quickly rise to positions of leadership.
	These hill giants drape themselves in rocks attached to chains or ropes, then use their magic to knock down and pummel their foes with these stones. This magic, combined with their ability to defeat and devour their prey as quickly as a torrent of boulders cascades down a mountain, leads other giants to call them avalanchers.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 157</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Lightning Hulk</name>
    <sortname>Hulk, Lightning</sortname>
    <ancestry>Hulk</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic neutral</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>102 (12d10+36)</hp>
    <speed>0 ft., fly 90 ft.(hover), canHover true ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>21</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Wis +6, Con +7, Dex +9, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Auran, Giant</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, thunder; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>lightning, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Illumination</name>
      <text>The lightning hulk sheds bright light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Lightning Form</name>
      <text>The lightning hulk can enter a hostile creature's space and stop there. The first time the lightning hulk enters a creature's space on a turn, or if it begins its turn in a creature's space, that creature takes 7 (2d6) lightning damage. The hulk can also move through a space as narrow as 1 inch without squeezing. A creature that touches the lightning hulk or hits it with a melee attack while within 5 feet of it takes 7 (2d6) lightning damage.</text>
      <attack>Lightning Damage||2d6</attack>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Arc Lightning</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 10 ft. or range 60 ft., one target. Hit: 18 (4d8) lightning damage. If the target is a creature, it can't take reactions until the start of its next turn, and lightning jumps from the target to another creature of the lightning hulk's choice that it can see within 30 feet of the target. The second creature must succeed on a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw or take 18 (4d8) lightning damage.</text>
      <attack>Lightning Damage|+9|4d8</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Lightning hulks are the descendants of storm giants who retreated from the world in ages past. Over the course of centuries, the elemental nature of these giants-aided by infusions of energy from the Elemental Planes grew to dominate these giants, eventually freeing them from the limitations of flesh.
	A lightning hulk is essentially a living bolt of lightning, with the one lasting vestige of its former nature being a vague face that appears at the head of the bolt as it streams through the air. In rare moments, the hulk coalesces into a bipedal shape resembling a storm giant, but these moments are as fleeting as a lightning strike. At other times, particularly when near metal or solid earth, the hulk seems on the verge of dispersing entirely, losing its last shreds of cohesion as a single entity. Its mental state is similarly incoherent: a lightning hulk rushes from one place to another with little sense of purpose and no hint of the contemplation that occupies its distant cousin giants.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 158</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Maw of Yeenoghu</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>fiend (demon)</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>161 (14d12+70)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>8</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Con +9, Cha +4</save>
    <skill>Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Giant</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The maw has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The maw makes two Bite or Fang Fling attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 19 (2d12 + 6) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+10|2d12+6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Fang Fling</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, range 30/90 ft., one target. Hit: 11 (1d10 + 6) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+10|1d10+6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Gorging Charge (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The maw moves up to its speed without provoking opportunity attacks and can move through the spaces of Large or smaller creatures. Each time the maw enters a creature's space for the first time during this move, that creature must succeed on a DC 18 Strength saving throw or take 25 (3d12 + 6) piercing damage and have the grappled condition (escape DC 16); if a creature is already grappled this way, it has the prone condition. Until this grapple ends, the target has the restrained condition. The maw can have only one creature grappled in this way at a time.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage||3d12+6</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Fanged Rebuke</name>
      <text>In response to taking damage, the maw makes one Bite attack against a random creature within 10 feet of itself. If no creature is within reach, the maw can make two Fang Fling attacks.</text>
    </reaction>
    <description>Hill giants are known for their voracious appetites, which can attract the attention of the demon lord Yeenoghu, known as the Beast ofButchery. A cruel hill giant sometimes turns to Yeenoghu for help in expanding the reach of its malevolence. Occasionally a hill giant consumes an evil artifact that transforms the giant into a fiendish form. Once in a while, Yeenoghu whispers promises of power in the dreams of a giant whose hunger surpasses other giants'. In any case, the result is a ravenous monster called a maw of Yeenoghu, which is wholly devoted to the demon lord.
	A maw of Yeenoghu grows a mane of hair and hunches over like a gnoll. Its jaw grows and widens, and its mouth fills with multiple rows of sharp teeth. These teeth constantly grow, driving the maw to bite and chew on anything within reach. Some maws desperately rip the teeth from their mouth for relief, but the teeth quickly regrow. Cunning maws use this phenomenon as a ready supply of weaponry, throwing clusters of teeth at their foes.
	A maw of Yeenoghu charges at its prey on all fours with its mouth wide open, scraping the ground like a plow.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 159</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Mist Hulk</name>
    <sortname>Hulk, Mist</sortname>
    <ancestry>Hulk</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic neutral</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>94 (9d10+45)</hp>
    <speed>0 ft., fly 40 ft.(hover), canHover true ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>21</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Wis +4, Con +8, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Stealth +8, Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Auran, Giant</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>thunder</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, paralyzed, poisoned, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Air Form</name>
      <text>The mist hulk can enter another creature's space and stop there. It can move through a space as narrow as 1 inch without squeezing.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Death Burst</name>
      <text>When the mist hulk dies, it bursts in a wave of water. Each creature within 10 feet of it must make a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 11 (2d10) bludgeoning damage and has the prone condition. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage||2d10</attack>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The mist hulk makes two Slam attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 16 (2d10 + 5) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Cold Damage|+8|2d10+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Hideous Wailing (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The mist hulk releases a wail infused with magical anguish. Each creature within 30 feet of it must make a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw. A creature in the mist hulk's space has disadvantage on the saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 14 (4d6) psychic damage and has the incapacitated condition for 1 minute. The affected creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Damage||4d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Descended from ancient cloud giants, mist hulks are Elementals that embody their ancestors' mixed elemental nature of Air and Water. After countless ages of isolation-often on one of the Elemental Planes or some hidden demiplane-they retain the barest hint of their ancestors' physical form, and even less of the giants' culture.
	A mist hulk resembles a bipedal figure made of dark rain clouds. Parts of its body seem more solid than others, but these parts are transparent enough that the churning vapors of the hulk's substance are visible inside. Wisps of cloud constantly leak from the creature, as if it might dissolve completely at any time. When it is slain, its misty form condenses into a torrent of water.
	A mist hulk's mood is always gloomy, and when threatened, it often howls in infectious misery. All who hear this wail are magically reminded of past regrets, real or imagined.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 160</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Mud Hulk</name>
    <sortname>Hulk, Mud</sortname>
    <ancestry>Hulk</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>68 (8d10+24)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>9</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Terran</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>acid</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, paralyzed</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Amorphous</name>
      <text>The mud hulk can move through a space as narrow as 1 inch without squeezing.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Sticky Mud</name>
      <text>The ground within 15 feet of the mud hulk is difficult terrain for other creatures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Enveloping Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 9 (1d12 + 3) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or be pulled into the mud hulk's space and be engulfed by the mud hulk. While engulfed, the target can't breathe, has the restrained condition, and takes 6 (1d12) acid damage at the start of each of its turns. When the mud hulk moves, the engulfed target moves with it. The mud hulk can have only one target engulfed at a time. While a creature is engulfed, the mud hulk can't use its Amorphous trait.
	An engulfed target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns. On a successful save, the target escapes and enters the nearest unoccupied space.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+5|1d12+3</attack>
      <attack>Acid Damage||1d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Mud Splash</name>
      <text>The mud hulk lobs a mass of mud that splashes in a 10-foot-radius sphere centered on a point within 30 feet of the mud hulk. Each creature in that area must make a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw, taking 10 (2d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. The affected area is difficult terrain until the start of the mud hulk's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage||2d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <description>The ancestors of mud hulks were hill giants who, living in isolation, ate everything within reach until they were forced to subsist on the earth itself. The giants' elemental nature asserted itself and transformed them into creatures of living mud.
	A mud hulk vaguely resembles its ancestors, but its body consists of wet mud that constantly sloughs off around it, creating thick pools of the stuff everywhere the creature goes. It retains the hunger of a hill giant, enveloping anything even vaguely edible and directly absorbing it into its body. When threatened, it huds masses of mud at its enemies to make sure they stay in place long enough for the mud hulk to consume them

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 161</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Regisaur</name>
    <sortname>Dinosaur, Regisaur</sortname>
    <ancestry>Dinosaur</ancestry>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>monstrosity (dinosaur)</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>181 (11d20+66)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>23</con>
    <int>4</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages/>
    <cr>14</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+5</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The regisaur has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The regisaur makes one Bite attack and one Tail attack. The regisaur can't target the same creature with both attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 47 (6d12 + 8) piercing damage, and the target has the grappled condition (escape DC 18). Until this grapple ends, the target has the restrained condition, and the regisaur can't Bite another target.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+13|6d12+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 26 (4d8 + 8) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+13|4d8+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Swallow (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 5 ft., one Huge or smaller creature grappled by the regisaur. Hit: The regisaur swallows the target, and the grapple ends. A swallowed creature has the blinded and restrained conditions, it has total cover against attacks and other effects outside the regisaur, and it takes 7 (2d6) acid damage at the start of each of its turns. The regisaur can have up to two creatures swallowed at a time.
	If the regisaur takes 25 damage or more on a single turn from a swallowed creature, the regisaur must succeed on a DC 16 Constitution saving throw at the end of that turn or regurgitate the creature, which falls in a space within 5 feet of the regisaur and has the prone condition; the creature no longer has the blinded and restrained conditions.</text>
      <attack>Acid Damage|+13|2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Aptly called "the ruler of dinosaurs," a regisaur is an enormous predator large enough to swallow a giant whole. Fieryveins of elemental energy course through its skin and glow in its eye-s and nostrils.

Dinosaurs:
Dinosaurs, or behemoths, are among the oldest reptiles in the world. Predatory dinosaurs are savage, territorial hunters. Herbivorous dinosaurs are less aggressive, but they might attack to defend their young, or if startled or harassed.
	Dinosaurs come in many sizes and shapes. Larger varieties often have drab coloration, while smaller dinosaurs have colorful markings akin to birds. Dinosaurs roam rugged and isolated areas that humanoids seldom visit, including remote mountain valleys, inaccessible plateaus, tropical islands, and deep fens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 130</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Rime Hulk</name>
    <sortname>Hulk, Rime</sortname>
    <ancestry>Hulk</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>85 (9d10+36)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>8</int>
    <wis>9</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages>Aquan, Giant</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune>cold, poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Death Burst</name>
      <text>When the rime hulk dies, it explodes in a 10-foot-radius sphere of frigid air and frost centered on itself. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or take 10 (3d6) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Cold Damage||3d6</attack>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The rime hulk makes two Slam attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 9 (1d10 + 4) bludgeoning damage plus 9 (2d8) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+7|(1d10+4)+(2d8)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+7|1d10+4</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Trail of Frost (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The rime hulk moves up to its speed without provoking opportunity attacks and can move through the space of any Medium or smaller creature. Each time the rime hulk enters another creature's space for the first time during this move, that creature must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the creature takes 22 (4d10) cold damage, and its speed is reduced by 10 feet until the start of the rime hulk's next turn. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage only.</text>
      <attack>Cold Damage||4d10</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Rime hulks are a withered branch of the frost giant family tree, descended from ancient giants who withdrew from the wodd and succumbed to their elemental nature. Most rime hulks dwell in the Frostfell, the "plane of ice" that forms the border between the Elemental Planes of Air and Water. Others lurk in isolated rifts in enormous polar glaciers.
	Smaller and weaker than their ancestors, rime hulks are roughly formed masses of frost and ice. Their vaguely giant-shaped physical forms are unstable, constantly breaking apart and reforming as clouds of frost billow off them. As a rime hulk moves, it leaves a trail of ice that can freeze enemies in place. When it dies, a rime hulk explodes in a burst of frost.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 162</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Runic Colossus</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>20 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>315 (18d20+126)</hp>
    <speed>60 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>24</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands Giant but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>21</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>acid, cold, fire, lightning</resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+7</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The colossus is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The colossus has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The colossus deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The colossus makes two Slam attacks and then uses Stomp.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 26 (3d12 + 7) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+14|3d12+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Stomp</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 29 (4d10 + 7) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Huge or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 22 Dexterity saving throw or have the prone condition. Until the colossus uses its Stomp again or moves, the creature has the restrained condition. The restrained creature or another creature within 5 feet of it can use its action to make a DC 22 Strength check. On a successful check, the affected creature relocates to an unoccupied space of its choice within 5 feet of the colossus and is no longer restrained.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+14|4d10+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Arcane Beam (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The colossus fires a beam of magical force from its chest, hands, or head in a 150-foot line that is 10 feet wide. Each creature in that area must make a DC 22 Dexterity saving throw, taking 58 (9d12) force damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage||9d12</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Spell Reflection (2/Day)</name>
      <recharge>2/DAY</recharge>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +14 to hit, range 120 ft., one creature casting a spell of 5th level or lower. Hit: 26 (4d12) force damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 15 Intelligence saving throw or the spell fails and has no effect.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage|+14|4d12</attack>
    </reaction>
    <description>According to The Sa§a of the Dra§on Queller, told by giants on some worlds, a disparate group of giants combined their efforts to protect their ancient empire from a particularly vicious dragon. Stone and hill giants hewed a mighty form from living stone. Cloud and frost giants gathered rare metals, and fire giants shaped them into flexible joints and plated armor. Storm giants inscribed runes into the inert form to give it the semblance of life. The fruit of these labors was an everlasting guardian: the first runic colossus.
	A runic colossus stands 30 feet tall. It regards all non-giants as a threat, and unless it has other orders, it attacks such creatures on sight.
	The art of crafting a runic colossus is lost to modern giants, but many tales suggest the instructions might be buried deep in ruins from ancient giants' empires.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 163</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Scion of Grolantor</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>giant (titan)</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>402 (23d20+161)</hp>
    <speed>60 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>25</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>21</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Wis +12, Cha +11</save>
    <skill>Perception +12</skill>
    <passive>22</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>22</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire, lightning; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, paralyzed, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+7</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (6/Day)</name>
      <recharge>6/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the scion fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The scion has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The scion deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The scion makes one Great Tree Club attack and two Slam attacks, or it makes three Boulder attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Great Tree Club</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, reach 30 ft., one target. Hit: 30 (4d10 + 8) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 23 Strength saving throw or be pushed horizontally up to 100 feet straight away from the scion and have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+15|4d10+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 26 (4d8 + 8) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage|+15|4d8+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Boulder</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. Hit: 27 (3d12 + 8) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+15|3d12+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Inhale (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The scion inhales a vortex of air in a 120-foot line that is 15 feet wide. Each creature in that area that is Huge or smaller must succeed on a DC 23 Strength saving throw or be pulled up to 120 feet straight toward the scion and be swallowed. A swallowed creature has the restrained condition, has total cover against attacks and other effects outside the scion, and takes 24 (7d6) force damage at the start of each of the scion's turns.
	The scion's stomach can hold up to two creatures at a time. If the scion takes 60 damage or more on a single turn from a creature inside it, the scion must succeed on a DC 17 Constitution saving throw at the end of that turn or regurgitate all swallowed creatures, each of which falls in a space within 10 feet of the scion and has the prone condition. If the scion dies, any swallowed creature no longer has the restrained condition and can escape from the corpse using 15 feet of movement, exiting with the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage||7d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Earth-Shaking Movement (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The scion moves up to its speed and then sends a shock wave through the ground in a 60-foot-radius circle centered on itself. Each creature on the ground in that area that is concentrating must succeed on a DC 23 Constitution saving throw or lose concentration.</text>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Feed</name>
      <text>Immediately after taking damage, if it has at least one creature swallowed, the scion deals 10 (3d6) force damage to each swallowed creature and regains 10 hit points.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage||3d6</attack>
    </reaction>
    <legendary category="lair">
      <name>Regional Effects</name>
      <text>The region surrounding a scion of Grolantor is altered by the giant's magic, creating one or more of the following effects:

	• Abundant Food: Crops and domestic animals grow and reproduce quickly within 6 miles of the scion.

	• Empowered Hill Giants: Hill giants within 1,000 feet of the scion gain a +7 bonus to attack and damage rolls.

	• FarmingWeather: The weather within 6 miles of the scion is always ideal for farming: sunny and warm with occasional showers.

If the scion dies, these effects end immediately.</text>
    </legendary>
    <description>Scion of Grolantor:
A slumbering scion of Grolantor is often mistaken for a hill, and sometimes people erect standing stones, a village. or a city on a scion's back, unaware of the mighty power beneath them. Such settlements can thrive for centuries, as the scion's magic causes crops to flourish and livestock to thrive in the surrounding region. An ancient tree towers from the crest of the hill.
	When roused, a cradle of the hill scion rises as a mass of dirt, stone, and roots with two massive arms. The cradle uses tree roots and waves of dirt to entangle and entomb foes.
	If the cradle is destroyed, the scion of Grolantor inside it awakens. Standing 50 feet tall, the scion devours everything within reach to satiate its hunger. Its powerful lungs can suck food straight into its gullet. The scion uses a great tree to bat foes far into the distance.

Scions of Giants' Gods:
Giants are descended from the All-Father, Annam, and his children. But scions of giants' gods boast a greater claim: they are Annam's grandchildren, and they occupy a privileged place among giants. On some worlds, these scions ruled the first empires of giants until Annam retreated into seclusion. On other worlds, the scions guard their birthplaces (which are rich in elemental magic) or hold the substance of the world together. (See "Giants of Myth" in chapter 3 for additional inspiration.)
	Scions of giants' gods are enormously powerful beings who infuse the world around them with primeval magic. In many worlds, they slumber and have become part of the landscape. In this case, each scion is enclosed in stasis inside a powerful Elemental called a cradle. The cradle protects the slumbering scion and follows its subconscious wishes, including driving off intruders. But if the cradle dies, the scion within fully awakens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 165</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Scion of Memnor</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>giant (titan)</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic neutral</alignment>
    <ac>20 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>656 (32d20+320)</hp>
    <speed>60 ft., fly 80 ft.(hover), canHover true ft.</speed>
    <str>30</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>30</con>
    <int>24</int>
    <wis>22</wis>
    <cha>26</cha>
    <save>Dex +12, Cha +16</save>
    <skill>Arcana +15, Perception +14</skill>
    <passive>24</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>26</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire, lightning; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>thunder</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, paralyzed, petrified</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+8</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Flyby</name>
      <text>The scion doesn't provoke opportunity attacks when it flies out of an enemy's reach.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (6/Day)</name>
      <recharge>6/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the scion fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The scion has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The scion deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The scion makes one attack using Cloud Morningstar or Wind Javelin, as well as two Slam attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Cloud Morningstar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, reach 30 ft., one target. Hit: 32 (4d10 + 10) force damage plus 22 (4d10) thunder damage.</text>
      <attack>Cloud Morningstar|+18|(4d10+10)+(4d10)</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage|+18|4d10+10</attack>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||4d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Wind Javelin</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. Hit: 42 (5d12 + 10) thunder damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 26 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Thunder Damage|+18|5d12+10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 28 (4d8 + 10) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage|+18|4d8+10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Thunderous Vortex (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The scion magically creates a vortex of wind in a 60-foot-radius sphere centered on a point it can see within 120 feet of itself. Each creature in the sphere must succeed on a DC 24 Strength saving throw or be pulled straight toward the sphere's center, ending in an unoccupied space as close as possible to the center. Then a burst of thunder erupts in a 30-foot-radius sphere centered on the same point. Each creature in that area takes 52 (8d12) thunder damage and must succeed on a DC 24 Constitution saving throw or have the stunned condition until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||8d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Fog of Deception (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The scion conjures a magical cloud that fills a 30-foot-radius sphere centered on a point it can see within 90 feet of itself. Each creature in that area must make a DC 24 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, a creature has the charmed condition until the end of its next turn. While it has the charmed condition, the creature must use its action to make a melee attack against a creature other than itself of the scion's choice. If no creature is within its reach, the affected creature makes a ranged attack against a creature of the scion's choice, throwing its weapon if necessary. On a successful save, a creature is immune to the scion's Fog of Deception for the next 24 hours.</text>
    </action>
    <legendary category="lair">
      <name>Regional Effects</name>
      <text>The region surrounding a scion of Memnor is altered by the giant's magic, creating one or more of the following effects:

	• Compulsory Offering: The first time a sapient creature comes within 6 miles of the scion, the creature must succeed on a DC 15 Wisdom saving throw or feel an overwhelming compulsion to leave an offering worth at least 5 gp stashed in an out-of-the-way place. Cloud giants within 6 miles of the cradle or scion immediately sense the location of this gift. A creature can be affected only once by this compulsion.

	• Empowered Cloud Giants: Cloud giants within 1,000 feet of the scion gain a +8 bonus to attack and damage rolls.

	• Mischievous Whispers: Whispers can be heard on the wind within 1 mile of the scion. The words are indistinct, but a creature with an Intelligence score of 5 or higher interprets them as instructions for a prank they can play on others.

If the scion dies, these effects end immediately.</text>
    </legendary>
    <description>Scion of Memnor:
A slumbering scion of Memnor appears as a dense, slowly drifting tower of clouds that never dissipates. Often, this cloud lingers over a remote valley, creating a constantly overcast sky. Sapient creatures who live beneath this cloud often display superstitious and duplicitous behavior, almost unconsciously leaving gifts for "rain spirits" while playing mischievous pranks on each other.
	When roused, a cradle of the cloud scion manifests as a titanic air elemental made of fierce winds and wisps of cloud. It wields air and thunder to knock enemies from the sky.
	If the cradle is destroyed, the scion of Memnor emerges from the dissipating cloud, often laughing as if it just heard a great joke. Incredibly tall and lanky, the scion towers 75 feet tall and wields a morningstar made from magically dense clouds. It tends to regard other creatures as toys rather than serious threats, and it uses its illusion magic to manipulate creatures into fighting each other. If seriously threatened, it wields thunder and wind to demolish its enemies.

Scions of Giants' Gods:
Giants are descended from the All-Father, Annam, and his children. But scions of giants' gods boast a greater claim: they are Annam's grandchildren, and they occupy a privileged place among giants. On some worlds, these scions ruled the first empires of giants until Annam retreated into seclusion. On other worlds, the scions guard their birthplaces (which are rich in elemental magic) or hold the substance of the world together. (See "Giants of Myth" in chapter 3 for additional inspiration.)
	Scions of giants' gods are enormously powerful beings who infuse the world around them with primeval magic. In many worlds, they slumber and have become part of the landscape. In this case, each scion is enclosed in stasis inside a powerful Elemental called a cradle. The cradle protects the slumbering scion and follows its subconscious wishes, including driving off intruders. But if the cradle dies, the scion within fully awakens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 167</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Scion of Skoraeus</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>giant (titan)</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>444 (24d20+192)</hp>
    <speed>60 ft.</speed>
    <str>29</str>
    <dex>20</dex>
    <con>26</con>
    <int>19</int>
    <wis>24</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Wis +14, Dex +12</save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +12, Perception +14</skill>
    <passive>24</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>23</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire, lightning; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>acid</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, paralyzed, petrified</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+7</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (6/Day)</name>
      <recharge>6/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the scion fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The scion has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The scion deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The scion makes one Crystal Club attack and two Slam attacks, then uses Entombing Grasp if available. Alternatively, the scion makes two Runic Boulder attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Crystal Club</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +16 to hit, reach 30 ft., one target. Hit: 35 (4d12 + 9) bludgeoning damage. Hit or Miss: The scion can cause the club to flare with bright light, and the target must succeed on a DC 22 Constitution saving throw or take 18 (4d8) radiant damage and have the blinded condition until the start of the scion's next turn.

Blinded:
	• A blinded creature can't see and automatically fails any ability check that requires sight.
	• Attack rolls against the creature have advantage, and the creature's attack rolls have disadvantage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+16|4d12+9</attack>
      <attack>Radiant Damage||4d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +16 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 31 (4d10 + 9) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage|+16|4d10+9</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Runic Boulder</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +16 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. Hit: 27 (4d8 + 9) bludgeoning damage. Hit or Miss: The boulder explodes. The target and each creature within 30 feet of it must make a DC 22 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 19 (3d12) force damage and has the prone condition. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+16|4d8+9</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage||3d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Entombing Grasp (Recharge 6)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>The scion wreathes its hand in petrifying magic and touches one Huge or smaller creature it can see within 20 feet of itself. The target must succeed on a DC 24 Dexterity saving throw or take 28 (8d6) force damage and have the grappled condition (escape DC 19). At the start of the scion's next turn, if the target is still grappled, the target has the petrified condition.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage||8d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Earth-Shaking Movement (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The scion moves up to its speed and then sends a shock wave through the ground in a 60-foot radius circle centered on itself. Each creature on the ground in that area that is concentrating must succeed on a DC 24 Constitution saving throw or lose concentration.</text>
    </action>
    <legendary category="lair">
      <name>Regional Effects</name>
      <text>The region surrounding a scion of Skoraeus is altered by the giant's magic, creating one or more of the following effects:

	• Abundant Stone and Minerals: Smooth stones and gems grow within 6 miles of the scion.

	• Edible Moss: Carpets of golden moss that stone giants find tasty grow on cavern walls within 6 miles of the scion.

	• Empowered Stone Giants: Stone giants within 1,000 feet of the scion gain a +7 bonus to attack and damage rolls.

If the scion dies, the Empowered Stone Giants effect ends immediately. The other effects cease to produce new moss and minerals, and existing moss dies within 1d10 days.</text>
      <attack>Days||1d10</attack>
    </legendary>
    <description>Scion of Skoraeus:
A scion of Skoraeus typically slumbers deep in the heart of a towering mountain, almost becoming one with the earth. While the scion dreams, the mountain's minerals are transformed into fine carving stones and brilliant gems.
	If a miner tunnels too close to the heart of the mountain, the cradle awakens as a bipedal mass of stone and crystals. It brings the weight of the mountain down on the intruder's head and unleashes an earsplitting roar that can collapse mine tunnels.
	If the cradle is destroyed, the scion of Skoraeus inside it awakens. At nearly 70 feet tall, it towers over most other creatures and wields a mass of crystal as a club. Once awakened, the scion continues to pursue the art that ornamented its dreams, seeking to mold and shape stone into beautiful elegance. If it needs more raw materials, the scion can transform a living creature in its palm into stone.

Scions of Giants' Gods:
Giants are descended from the All-Father, Annam, and his children. But scions of giants' gods boast a greater claim: they are Annam's grandchildren, and they occupy a privileged place among giants. On some worlds, these scions ruled the first empires of giants until Annam retreated into seclusion. On other worlds, the scions guard their birthplaces (which are rich in elemental magic) or hold the substance of the world together. (See "Giants of Myth" in chapter 3 for additional inspiration.)
	Scions of giants' gods are enormously powerful beings who infuse the world around them with primeval magic. In many worlds, they slumber and have become part of the landscape. In this case, each scion is enclosed in stasis inside a powerful Elemental called a cradle. The cradle protects the slumbering scion and follows its subconscious wishes, including driving off intruders. But if the cradle dies, the scion within fully awakens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 169</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Scion of Stronmaus</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>giant (titan)</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic good</alignment>
    <ac>20 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>656 (32d20+320)</hp>
    <speed>60 ft., fly 80 ft.(hover), canHover true ft., swim 80 ft.</speed>
    <str>30</str>
    <dex>20</dex>
    <con>30</con>
    <int>26</int>
    <wis>28</wis>
    <cha>24</cha>
    <save>Dex +13, Int +16</save>
    <skill>Arcana +16, History +16, Perception +17</skill>
    <passive>27</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>27</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>lightning, thunder</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+8</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Flyby</name>
      <text>The scion doesn't provoke opportunity attacks when it flies out of an enemy's reach.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (6/Day)</name>
      <recharge>6/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the scion fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The scion has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The scion deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The scion makes one attack using Lightning Sword or Hailstone, as well as two Slam attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Lightning Sword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, reach 30 ft., one target. Hit: 36 (4d12 + 10) force damage plus 22 (4d10) lightning damage.</text>
      <attack>Lightning Sword|+18|(4d12+10)+(4d10)</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage|+18|4d12+10</attack>
      <attack>Lightning Damage||4d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Hailstone</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. Hit: 32 (4d10 + 10) bludgeoning damage plus 18 (4d8) cold damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 26 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Hailstone|+18|(4d10+10)+(4d8)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+18|4d10+10</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||4d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 36 (4d12 + 10) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage|+18|4d12+10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Vengeful Storm (Recharge 6) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>The scion conjures a churning storm cloud in a 30-foot-radius, 10-foot-tall cylinder centered on a point within 120 feet of itself. The cloud's area is heavily obscured. The cloud lasts for 1 minute, until the scion dies, or when the scion uses this bonus action again.
	When the cloud appears, and as a bonus action on later turns, the scion can move the cloud up to 30 feet and cause one of the following effects in a 30-foot-radius, 120-foot-high cylinder directly below it; the scion can't choose the same effect two rounds in a row:</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Acid Rain (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The cloud rains acid. Each creature in the cylinder must succeed on a DC 25 Constitution saving throw or be covered in acid for 1 minute or until a creature uses its action to remove the acid from itself or another creature. A creature covered in the acid takes 26 (4d12) acid damage at the start of each of its turns.</text>
      <attack>Acid Damage||4d12</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Freezing Storm (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>Shards of ice pelt down, and freezing wind fills the area. Each creature in the cylinder must succeed on a DC 25 Dexterity saving throw or take 28 (8d6) cold damage and be hindered by ice formations for 1 minute or until it or another creature within reach of it uses an action to break away the ice. A creature hindered by ice has its speed reduced to 0.</text>
      <attack>Cold Damage||8d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Lightning Bolts (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>Bolts of lightning strike down. Each creature in the cylinder must succeed on DC 25 Dexterity saving throw or take 18 (4d8) lightning damage and have the stunned condition until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Lightning Damage||4d8</attack>
    </action>
    <legendary category="lair">
      <name>Regional Effects</name>
      <text>The region surrounding a scion of Stronmaus is altered by the giant's magic, creating one or more of the following effects:

	• Elemental Portals: Two-way portals to the Elemental Plane of Air (if the scion is in the sky) or the Elemental Plane of Water (if the scion is in the ocean) form within 1 mile of the cradle or scion, allowing elemental creatures into the world.

	• Empowered Storm Giants: Storm giants within 1,000 feet of the scion gain a +8 bonus to attack and damage rolls.

	• Extreme Weather: The weather within 1 mile of the scion dramatically shifts day to day, ranging from pleasantly sunny to brutal hailstorms.

If the scion dies, these effects end immediately.</text>
    </legendary>
    <description>Scion of Stronmaus:
A scion of Stronmaus often slumbers high in the sky or deep in the ocean, where the tumult caused by the scion's restless sleep has little effect on the world. If it drifts too near the ground or the ocean surface, it causes mighty storms or fierce maelstroms. A scion's slumber is filled with dreams ranging from inspiring visions of Annam's return to melancholy prophecies of inevitable decline, from joyful glimpses of an idyllic past to horrific nightmares of torment and devastation.
	A cradle of the storm scion stirs into action not only when the scion is threatened but also if the scion's sleep is troubled by nightmares. When roused, the cradle takes on a vaguely giant-shaped form consisting of air, water, and ice whirling in fury.
	If the cradle is destroyed, the scion of Stronmaus inside it awakens. Among the mightiest creatures of all giant kind, the scion stands 80 feet tall. It often finds some relief in waking and being freed from its troubling dreams, so it doesn't necessarily lash out in violence when emerging from its cradle. But it's not particularly interested in Humanoids or other little creatures-either in conversing with them or in protecting them from harm it might cause.
	If the scion is threatened, it unleashes elemental might like few other forces in the multiverse can muster: blades of lightning, boulder-sized hailstones, and a storm of churning elements.

Scions of Giants' Gods:
Giants are descended from the All-Father, Annam, and his children. But scions of giants' gods boast a greater claim: they are Annam's grandchildren, and they occupy a privileged place among giants. On some worlds, these scions ruled the first empires of giants until Annam retreated into seclusion. On other worlds, the scions guard their birthplaces (which are rich in elemental magic) or hold the substance of the world together. (See "Giants of Myth" in chapter 3 for additional inspiration.)
	Scions of giants' gods are enormously powerful beings who infuse the world around them with primeval magic. In many worlds, they slumber and have become part of the landscape. In this case, each scion is enclosed in stasis inside a powerful Elemental called a cradle. The cradle protects the slumbering scion and follows its subconscious wishes, including driving off intruders. But if the cradle dies, the scion within fully awakens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 171</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Scion of Surtur</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>giant (titan)</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful evil</alignment>
    <ac>20 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>546 (28d20+252)</hp>
    <speed>60 ft.</speed>
    <str>30</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>28</con>
    <int>21</int>
    <wis>24</wis>
    <cha>20</cha>
    <save>Dex +11, Cha +13</save>
    <skill>Athletics +18, Perception +15</skill>
    <passive>25</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>25</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, lightning; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>fire</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+8</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (6/Day)</name>
      <recharge>6/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the scion fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The scion has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The scion deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The scion makes one attack using Lava Blade or Lava Ball, as well as two Slam attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Lava Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, reach 30 ft., one target. Hit: 32 (4d10 + 10) slashing damage plus 18 (4d8) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Lava Blade|+18|(4d10+10)+(4d8)</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+18|4d10+10</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||4d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Lava Ball</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. Hit: 29 (3d12 + 10) bludgeoning damage plus 10 (3d6) fire damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 26 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Lava Ball|+18|(3d12+10)+(3d6)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+18|3d12+10</attack>
      <attack>Fire Damage||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 28 (4d8 + 10) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage|+18|4d8+10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Lava Wave (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The scion emits a wave of lava from its blade, hands, or mouth in a 90-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 25 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 60 (11d10) fire damage and has the restrained condition from being embedded in hardening rock. A creature can make a DC 25 Strength (Athletics) check as an action, freeing itself or a creature within reach from the rock on a success. The rock has AC 17 and 40 hit points, and it is immune to fire, poison, and psychic damage. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.</text>
      <attack>Fire Damage||11d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Earth-Shaking Movement (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The scion moves up to its speed and then sends a shock wave through the ground in a 60-foot-radius circle centered on itself. Each creature on the ground in that area that is concentrating must succeed on a DC 26 Constitution saving throw or lose concentration.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Incendiary Smoke (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The scion causes smoke and white-hot embers to billow from its skin, filling a 30-foot-radius sphere centered on itself that moves with it. While the scion's skin billows smoke, ranged attacks against the scion are made with disadvantage. A creature that moves into the smoke for the first time on a turn or starts its turn there must succeed on a DC 25 Constitution saving throw or take 14 (4d6) fire damage. The scion's skin stops billowing smoke after 1 minute, when the scion dies, or when the scion uses this bonus action to stop the smoke.</text>
      <attack>Fire Damage||4d6</attack>
    </action>
    <legendary category="lair">
      <name>Regional Effects</name>
      <text>The region surrounding a scion of Surtur is altered by the giant's magic, creating one or more of the following effects:

	• Abundant Ore: Veins of precious metals and ore are more common within 6 miles of the scion.

	• Desertification: Precipitation is almost nonexistent within 6 miles of the scion, parching the land and withering most plant 1ife.

	• Empowered Fire Giants: Fire giants within 1,000 feet of the scion gain a *8 bonus to attack and damage rolls.

If the scion dies, existing ore remains, but new veins of ore stop forming. The other effects end immediately.</text>
    </legendary>
    <description>Scion of Surtur:
A scion of Surtur slumbering at the peak of a volcano causes an unending plume of smoke to rise, sometimes lit from below by fiery bursts of lava. As the scion dreams of battle-perhaps a battle to rouse Annam from seclusion by uniting the giants or a war to conquer all in Surtur's name-the volcano rumbles and spews molten rage.
	If intruders disturb its resting place, the fire scion's cradle rises as a bipedal juggernaut of molten rock. Sometimes miners risk their lives to find rich veins of ore in a scion's volcano, or misguided fire cultists offer sacrifices meant to appease or awaken the volcano, and the awakened cradle defies all their expectations. Like a living volcano, the cradle hurls balls of magma at intruders, exhales fiery gases, and causes molten stone to erupt from the ground around it.
	If the cradle is destroyed, the scion of Surtur inside it awakens. Standing 60 feet tall, the scion's form is shrouded in a continual cloud of billowing ash and smoke. The awakened scion forms a blade of lava in its mighty hand and schemes to resume its ancient campaigns of conquest, preferably at the head of a fire giant army.

Scions of Giants' Gods:
Giants are descended from the All-Father, Annam, and his children. But scions of giants' gods boast a greater claim: they are Annam's grandchildren, and they occupy a privileged place among giants. On some worlds, these scions ruled the first empires of giants until Annam retreated into seclusion. On other worlds, the scions guard their birthplaces (which are rich in elemental magic) or hold the substance of the world together. (See "Giants of Myth" in chapter 3 for additional inspiration.)
	Scions of giants' gods are enormously powerful beings who infuse the world around them with primeval magic. In many worlds, they slumber and have become part of the landscape. In this case, each scion is enclosed in stasis inside a powerful Elemental called a cradle. The cradle protects the slumbering scion and follows its subconscious wishes, including driving off intruders. But if the cradle dies, the scion within fully awakens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 173</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Scion of Thrym</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>giant (titan)</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>499 (27d20+216)</hp>
    <speed>60 ft.</speed>
    <str>30</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>27</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>20</wis>
    <cha>21</cha>
    <save>Wis +12, Cha +12</save>
    <skill>Athletics +17, Perception +12</skill>
    <passive>22</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>24</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>fire, lightning; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>cold</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+7</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (6/Day)</name>
      <recharge>6/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the scion fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The scion has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The scion deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The scion makes one Ice Axe and two Slam attacks, or it makes two Glacier Throw attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ice Axe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +17 to hit, reach 30 ft., one target. Hit: 36 (4d12 + 10) force damage plus 18 (4d8) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Ice Axe|+17|(4d12+10)+(4d8)</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage|+17|4d12+10</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||4d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +17 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. Hit: 32 (4d10 + 10) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage|+17|4d10+10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Glacier Throw</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +17 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. Hit: 36 (4d12 + 10) bludgeoning damage plus 14 (4d6) cold damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 25 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition.</text>
      <attack>Glacier Throw|+17|(4d12+10)+(4d6)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+17|4d12+10</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||4d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Glacial Upheaval (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The scion digs its hands into the ground at a point it can see within 30 feet of itself and launches a magically conjured mass of ice into the air. Each creature other than the scion in a 30-foot-radius, 100-foot-high cylinder centered on that point must make a DC 25 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 36 (8d8) bludgeoning damage plus 19 (3d12) cold damage and is pushed vertically to the top of the cylinder, at which point the creature falls. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage and is pushed to the nearest unoccupied space outside the cylinder with no additional effects.
	At the start of the scion's next turn, a mass of ice plummets to the ground on a point the scion can see within 60 feet of the point the scion dug its hands into. Each creature in a 30-foot-radius, 100-foot-high cylinder centered on that point must succeed on a DC 25 Dexterity saving throw or take 18 (4d8) bludgeoning damage plus 18 (4d8) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage||8d8</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||3d12</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage||4d8</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||4d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Earth-Shaking Movement (Bonus Action)</name>
      <text>The scion moves up to its speed and sends a shock wave through the ground in a 60-foot-radius circle centered on itself. Each creature on the ground in that area that is concentrating must succeed on a DC 25 Constitution saving throw or lose concentration.</text>
    </action>
    <legendary category="lair">
      <name>Regional Effects</name>
      <text>The region surrounding a scion of Thrym is altered by the giant's magic, creating one or more of the following effects:

	• Biting Chill: Extreme cold envelops the land within 6 miles of the scion (see the Dun§eon Master's Guide for rules on extreme cold). If the climate in the area already features extreme cold, the cold is numbing-creatures in the area without immunity or resistance to cold damage have disadvantage on Strength and Dexterity checks.

	• Empowered Frost Giants: Frost giants within 1,000 feet of the scion gain a +7 bonus to attack and damage rolls.

	• Thriving Wildlife: Beasts reproduce rapidly and thrive within 6 miles of the scion.

If the scion dies, these effects end immediately.</text>
    </legendary>
    <description>Scion of Thrym:
A slumbering scion of Thrym encased in its cradle is functionally identical to a glacier or iceberg, nestled in an alpine valley or drifting in a polar sea. In its wintry seclusion, the scion dreams of battle and glory.
	If it is disturbed, the scion's cradle animates as a bipedal figure formed of ice and snow. It smashes intruders with its icy fists or hurls shards of its own icy substance at them, and it can exhale a blast of frigid air to freeze foes in place.
	If the cradle is destroyed, its icy body shatters to reveal the awakened scion of Thrym inside it. Forming a double-bladed axe in its hand, the 7O-foot-tall scion rushes at any foe that dares to challenge it. Emulating sagas of Thrym, the scion can achieve a tremendous feat of strength: creating a glacier in the ground and hurling it skyward, along with any creatures standing on it.

Scions of Giants' Gods:
Giants are descended from the All-Father, Annam, and his children. But scions of giants' gods boast a greater claim: they are Annam's grandchildren, and they occupy a privileged place among giants. On some worlds, these scions ruled the first empires of giants until Annam retreated into seclusion. On other worlds, the scions guard their birthplaces (which are rich in elemental magic) or hold the substance of the world together. (See "Giants of Myth" in chapter 3 for additional inspiration.)
	Scions of giants' gods are enormously powerful beings who infuse the world around them with primeval magic. In many worlds, they slumber and have become part of the landscape. In this case, each scion is enclosed in stasis inside a powerful Elemental called a cradle. The cradle protects the slumbering scion and follows its subconscious wishes, including driving off intruders. But if the cradle dies, the scion within fully awakens.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 175</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Spectral Cloud</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>189 (18d12+72)</hp>
    <speed>0 ft., fly 40 ft.(hover), canHover true ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Cha +8</save>
    <skill>Perception +8</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>13</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, necrotic; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>poison, thunder</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+5</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Blurred Form</name>
      <text>Attack rolls against the spectral cloud are made with disadvantage unless the attacker is within 15 feet of the spectral cloud or the spectral cloud is incapacitated.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Incorporeal Movement</name>
      <text>The spectral cloud can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. It takes 5 (1d10) force damage if it ends its turn inside an object.</text>
      <attack>Force Damage||1d10</attack>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The spectral cloud makes two Spectral Touch attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spectral Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 20 (3d8 + 7) force damage plus 10 (3d6) necrotic damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 20 Constitution saving throw, or its hit point maximum is reduced by an amount equal to the necrotic damage taken. This reduction lasts until the target finishes a long rest. The target dies if its hit point maximum is reduced to 0.
	A Humanoid slain by this attack immediately rises as a miniature spectral cloud (use the specter stat block in the Monster Manual). The miniature spectral cloud acts as an ally of its creator but isn't under its control.</text>
      <attack>Spectral Touch|+12|(3d8+7)+(3d6)</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage|+12|3d8+7</attack>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Chilling Winds (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The spectral cloud emits intensely cold wind in a 60-foot line that is 10 feet wide. Each creature in that area must make a DC 20 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 38 (7d10) cold damage and has the incapacitated condition for 1 minute. The affected creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.
	If a creature's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, that creature is immune to this spectral cloud's Chilling Winds for the next 24 hours.</text>
      <attack>Cold Damage||7d10</attack>
    </action>
    <description>A cloud giant that dies through an act of betrayal or an ill-fated wager sometimes returns as a spectral cloud. While this Undead seems to be merely a thick cloud or fog bank, observers can sometimes spot a shadowy bipedal figure lurking within. At the heart of the cloud, the figure's appearance becomes clear: a skeletal cloud giant corpse.
	Tales suggest cloud giants sometimes seek this fate rather than accept the end of their naturally long lives. In such stories, a cloud giant undergoes a ritual in which its heart is transplanted into a cloud, causing the giant's body to dissolve and its spirit to animate the cloud.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 176</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Spotted Lion</name>
    <sortname>Lion, Spotted</sortname>
    <ancestry>Lion</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>66 (7d12+21)</hp>
    <speed>60 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill>Stealth +6, Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages/>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The lion has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the lion's allies is within 5 feet of the target and the ally doesn't have the incapacitated condition.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Rend</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 15 (2d8 + 6) piercing damage. If the lion moved at least 20 feet straight toward the target immediately before the hit, the target must succeed on a DC 16 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition. If the target has the prone condition, the lion can make another Rend attack against it as a bonus action.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+8|2d8+6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Roughly twice the size of a common lion, a spotted lion has a dusky coat and mane, both speckled with charcoal-colored spots. Spotted lions gather in prides to hunt enormous prey ranging from giant elk to mammoths. Stone and cloud giants often keep these massive beasts as pets and hunting companions.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 177</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Stalker of Baphomet</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>fiend (demon)</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>200 (16d12+96)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Wis +7, Dex +7</save>
    <skill>Stealth +11, Athletics +15, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Giant</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Labyrinthine Recall</name>
      <text>The stalker can perfectly recall any path it has traveled.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The stalker has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The stalker makes two Glaive attacks or two Rock attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Glaive</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: 18 (2d10 + 7) slashing damage plus 9 (2d8) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Glaive|+11|(2d10+7)+(2d8)</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+11|2d10+7</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage||2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rock</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, range 60/240 ft., one target. Hit: 23 (3d10 + 7) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 19 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition. After the stalker throws the rock, roll a d6; on a roll of 3 or lower, the stalker has no more rocks to throw.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+11|3d10+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Erupting Horns (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The stalker causes the earth to churn at a point on the ground it can see within 60 feet of itself. Six horn-shaped stones erupt in a 30-foot-radius, 30-foot-high cylinder centered on that point and then crumble to dust.
	Each creature in that area must make a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 33 (6d10) piercing damage and is pushed up to 30 feet upward and then falls. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage||6d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The stalker casts one of the following spells, requiring no spell components and using Wisdom as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 15):

	• 1/Day each: meld into stone, stone shape, wall of stone</text>
    </action>
    <spells>meld into stone, stone shape, wall of stone</spells>
    <description>Demon worship is rare among stone giants; the destructive tendency of demons is the antithesis of the artistry that drives the stone giant's ordning. The Horned King, Baphomet, is an exception. Though he is a merciless hunter, the Prince of Beasts also crafts complex mazes as his hunting grounds. Stone giants can become mesmerized by the demon lord's mazes and enter his service. These giants can continue pursuing art by crafting mazes, while satiating their bloodlust by hunting in them.
	Baphomet rewards his most faithful cultists with transformation into demonic stalkers. Such a giant grows an elaborate crown of six horns, and Baphomet gives the stone giant a magic glaive and the ability to call up horns of stone from the earth.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 178</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Stone Giant of Evil Earth</name>
    <sortname>Stone Giant, Evil Earth</sortname>
    <ancestry>Stone Giant</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>typically neutral evil</alignment>
    <ac>20 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>137 (11d12+66)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save>Str +10, Con +10</save>
    <skill>Athletics +14, Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant, Terran</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes two Thundering Stone Club or Boulder attacks in any combination.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Thundering Stone Club</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: 16 (3d6 + 6) bludgeoning damage. The giant can cause the club to emit a burst of thunderous energy that deals 10 (3d6) thunder damage to each creature, other than the giant, within 30 feet of the target. The club can emit a burst this way only once per turn.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+10|3d6+6</attack>
      <attack>Thunder Damage||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Boulder</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, range 60/240 ft., one target. Hit: 19 (3d8 + 6) bludgeoning damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 18 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition. After the giant throws the boulder, roll a d6; on a roll of 3 or lower, the giant has no more boulders to throw.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+10|3d8+6</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Unyielding</name>
      <text>In response to failing a saving throw to avoid being moved, having the prone condition, or both, the giant succeeds instead.</text>
    </reaction>
    <description>Stone giants with a bent toward cruelty and destruction might reject the gods of the Ordning and turn to the worship of Ogrdmoch, the Prince of Evil Earth. These giants view the surface world not as a realm of dream but as a nightmare worthy only of destruction, so they lend their strength to cults that plan to reduce the world to rubble.

Outfitted in heavy armor crafted to resemble the cult's patron, stone giants of Evil Earth wield weapons that pulse with thunderous energy. These giants serve as the muscle for the cult, wielding their might to destroy the surface world in the name of Ogrdmoch.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 179</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Stone Giant Rockspeaker</name>
    <sortname>Stone Giant, Rockspeaker</sortname>
    <ancestry>Stone Giant</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant (wizard)</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>276 (24d12+120)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>19</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Wis +7, Con +10, Dex +7, Int +9</save>
    <skill>History +9, Athletics +16, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant, Terran</languages>
    <cr>16</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+5</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the giant fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Stone Rune</name>
      <text>The giant has a stone rune inscribed on a mineral object in its possession. While holding or wearing the object bearing the rune, the giant can use its Prismatic Rays action.
	The object bearing the rune has AC 18; 30 hit points; and immunity to necrotic, poison, and psychic damage. The object regains all its hit points at the end of every turn, but it turns to dust if reduced to 0 hit points or when the giant dies. If the rune is destroyed, the giant can inscribe a stone rune on an object in its possession when it finishes a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes three Prism Staff attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Prism Staff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 16 (3d6 + 6) bludgeoning damage plus 13 (3d8) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Prism Staff|+11|(3d6+6)+(3d8)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+11|3d6+6</attack>
      <attack>Radiant Damage||3d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Exploding Geode</name>
      <text>The giant throws a geode at a point within 60 feet of itself, and the geode explodes in a dazzling flash. Each creature in a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on that point must make a DC 17 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 13 (3d8) piercing damage plus 13 (3d8) radiant damage and has the blinded condition until the end of its next turn. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only. After the giant throws the geode, roll a d6; on a roll of 4 or lower, the giant has no more geodes to throw.

Blinded:
	• A blinded creature can't see and automatically fails any ability check that requires sight.
	• Attack rolls against the creature have advantage, and the creature's attack rolls have disadvantage.</text>
      <attack>Exploding Geode||(3d8)+(3d8)</attack>
      <attack>Piercing Damage||3d8</attack>
      <attack>Radiant Damage||3d8</attack>
      <attack>Geodes||1d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Prismatic Rays (Requires Stone Rune)</name>
      <text>The giant's stone rune emits beams of light that form a 60-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 17 Dexterity saving throw. For each creature in that area, roll a d6 to determine what ray affects it:

1-2: Blazing Red: On a failed save, the creature takes 35 (10d6) radiant damage and has the blinded condition until the end of the giant's next turn. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage only.

3-4: Dreadful Blue: On a failed save, the creature takes 35 (10d6) necrotic damage and has the frightened condition until the end of the giant's next turn. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage only.

5-6: Sapping Green: On a failed save, the creature takes 35 (10d6) force damage and has the incapacitated condition until the end of the giant's next turn. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage only.

Blinded:
	• A blinded creature can't see and automatically fails any ability check that requires sight.
	• Attack rolls against the creature have advantage, and the creature's attack rolls have disadvantage.</text>
      <attack>Prismatic Rays||1d6</attack>
      <attack>Radiant Damage||10d6</attack>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage||10d6</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage||10d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Stone giants practice rune magic more than other giants do, perhaps because of these giants' interest in and aptitude for carving stone. Stone giants who combine this magic with prodigious artistic skill are called rockspeakers. Within their communities, they act as leaders and oracles.
	Rockspeakers incorporate crystals and stones into their clothing and embed them in their skin. By invoking the power of their stone runes, these giants can turn these crystals into scintillating works of art. In combat, rockspeakers can use this same magic to cause their crystals to emit brilliantly colored, intense beams of light than can sear flesh and inhibit enemies.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 180</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Storm Crab</name>
    <sortname>Crab, Storm</sortname>
    <ancestry>Crab</ancestry>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>155 (10d20+50)</hp>
    <speed>40 ft., swim 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save>Str +10, Con +9</save>
    <skill>Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>understands Giant but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>11</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, fire, lightning</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+4</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The crab can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The crab makes two Claw attacks and one Stinger attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: 19 (3d8 + 6) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Huge or smaller creature, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 16). The crab has four claws, each of which can grapple one target.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+10|3d8+6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Stinger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one creature. Hit: 22 (3d10 + 6) piercing damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 17 Constitution saving throw or have the poisoned and paralyzed conditions for 1 minute. The affected creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending both the poisoned and paralyzed conditions on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+10|3d10+6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Water Jet (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The crab exhales water in a 150-foot line that is 10 feet wide. Each creature in that area must make a DC 17 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 27 (6d8) bludgeoning damage, is pushed up to 30 feet from the crab, and has the prone condition. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage||6d8</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Storm crabs are colossal crustaceans with four monstrous claws and a poisonous stinger. Equally adept underwater or on shore, they can exhale a jet of pressurized water to crush foes.
	Giants on some worlds claim Stronmaus or one of his children created storm crabs in the early years of an ancient empire. Just as behirs were created to fight dragons on land and rocs to challenge dragons' mastery of the sky, storm crabs were meant to battle dragon turtles, bronze dragons, and other aquatic foes. On many worlds, these creatures fiercely guard the underwater strongholds of storm giants, as well as the ruined keeps giants have abandoned.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 181</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Storm Giant Tempest Caller</name>
    <sortname>Storm Giant, Tempest Caller</sortname>
    <ancestry>Storm Giant</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant (sorcerer)</type>
    <alignment>any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>310 (27d12+135)</hp>
    <speed>50 ft., fly 50 ft.(hover), canHover true ft., swim 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>29</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>21</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>25</cha>
    <save>Str +15, Wis +10, Con +11, Cha +13</save>
    <skill>Arcana +17, Athletics +15, Perception +10</skill>
    <passive>20</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>20</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold</resist>
    <immune>lightning, thunder</immune>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alert</name>
      <text>The giant can't be surprised, and it has advantage on initiative rolls.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The giant can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the giant fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Scrying (Requires Storm Rune)</name>
      <text>The giant can use its crystal ball to cast the scrying spell (save DC 17).</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Storm Rune</name>
      <text>The giant has a storm rune inscribed on a crystal ball. While the object bearing the rune is embedded in its body, the giant can use its Tempest Call action and its Scrying trait.
	The object bearing the storm rune has AC 17; 50 hit points; and immunity to necrotic, poison, and psychic damage. The object regains all its hit points at the end of every turn, but it turns to dust if reduced to 0 hit points or when the giant dies. If the rune is destroyed, the giant can inscribe a storm rune on another crystal ball in its possession when it finishes a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes three Lightning Blade or Lightning Lance attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Lightning Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 22 (3d8 + 9) slashing damage plus 16 (3d10) lightning damage.</text>
      <attack>Lightning Blade|+15|(3d8+9)+(3d10)</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+15|3d8+9</attack>
      <attack>Lightning Damage||3d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Lightning Lance</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +13 to hit, range 500 ft., one target. Hit: 39 (5d12 + 7) lightning damage.</text>
      <attack>Lightning Damage|+13|5d12+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The giant casts one of the following spells, requiring no material components and using Charisma as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 21, +13 to hit with spell attacks):

	• At will: detect magic, detect thoughts
	• 1/Day each: control water, control weather (as an action), dispel magic, plane shift, sending, time stop</text>
      <attack>Spellcasting|+13|</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tempest Call (Requires Storm Rune)</name>
      <text>The giant creates an elemental vortex that fills a 60-foot-radius sphere centered on itself. Each creature in that area other than the giant must make a DC 21 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 43 (8d8 + 7) damage of a type of the giant's choosing: cold, lightning, or thunder. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage.</text>
      <attack>Cold, Lightning or Thunder Damage||8d8+7</attack>
    </action>
    <spells>detect magic, detect thoughts, control water, control weather, dispel magic, plane shift, sending, time stop</spells>
    <description>While most storm giants care little for the intricate details of ranking in the ordning, tempest callers proudly claim a position at the pinnacle of that ranking-and few dare to challenge them. Wielding the power of rune magic in addition to the innate magic that courses through them, these storm giants are highly respected. If any giant can draw Annam's attention to the world, it would likely be a tempest caller.
	Tempest callers implant crystal balls inscribed with the storm rune into their foreheads or eye sockets, allowing them to see through magical deception. They can also create a momentary vortex of freezing winds and storm clouds around themselves, engulfing their foes in elemental fury.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 182</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Storm Herald</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>typically lawful evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>287 (23d12+138)</hp>
    <speed>50 ft., swim 100 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>24</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Wis +10, Cha +10</save>
    <skill>Deception +10, Arcana +13, Perception +10</skill>
    <passive>20</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>17</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, psychic</resist>
    <immune>lightning, thunder</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The herald can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The herald has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The herald makes one Claw attack, one Tentacles attack, and one Trident attack.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 18 (3d6 + 8) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+14|3d6+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tentacles</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 21 (3d8 + 8) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, it has the grappled condition (escape DC 18). It also has the restrained condition and takes 16 (3d10) psychic damage at the start of each of its turns until this grapple ends. The herald can have only one creature grappled this way at a time.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+14|3d8+8</attack>
      <attack>Psychic Damage||3d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Trident</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 18 (3d6 + 8) piercing damage or 21 (3d8 + 8) piercing damage if used with two hands, plus 13 (3d8) lightning damage.</text>
      <attack>Trident|+14|(3d6+8)+(3d8)</attack>
      <attack>Trident (Two-Handed)|+14|(3d8+8)+(3d8)</attack>
      <attack>Piercing Damage|+14|3d6+8</attack>
      <attack>Piercing Damage (Two-Handed)|+14|3d8+8</attack>
      <attack>Lightning Damage||3d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Psychic Wave (Recharge 6)</name>
      <recharge>D6</recharge>
      <text>The herald unleashes a blast of psionic energy into the minds of up to three creatures it can see within 90 feet of itself. Each target must make a DC 21 Intelligence saving throw. On a failed save, a target takes 23 (3d10 + 7) psychic damage and has the stunned condition for 1 minute. On a successful save, a target takes half as much damage only. An affected creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.
	If a creature is reduced to 0 hit points by this psychic damage, it dies and its head explodes if it has one.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Damage||3d10+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>The herald casts one of the following spells, requiring no spell components and using Intelligence as the spellcasting ability (spell save DC 21):

	• At will: detect magic, detect thoughts, mage hand (the hand is invisible)
	• 1/Day each: control water, control weather (as an action), sending</text>
    </action>
    <spells>detect magic, detect thoughts, mage hand, control water, control weather, sending</spells>
    <description>Ancient and alien beings dwell or slumber in ocean depths, awaiting some cosmic circumstance that signals their time to rise. In their retreat from the world, storm giants sometimes stray into the orbit of such creatures, perhaps while seeking insight into some omen, vision, or prophecy. Krakens, aboleths, and Great Old Ones delight in corrupting storm giants to their service, transforming them into storm heralds.
	A storm herald grows fins and tentacles, giving it a monstrous appearance. Its mind is wholly under its master's sway, and the herald gains fearsome psychic powers to use in advancing its master's plans. When the herald dies, it reverts to its previous appearance.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 183</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Tempest Spirit</name>
    <sortname>Spirit, Tempest</sortname>
    <ancestry>Spirit</ancestry>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>195 (17d12+85)</hp>
    <speed>0 ft., fly 60 ft.(hover), canHover true ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>19</cha>
    <save>Wis +9, Con +10, Cha +9, Int +8</save>
    <skill>Arcana +8, Perception +9</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>15</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>cold, necrotic, poison; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>lightning, thunder</immune>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+5</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Incorporeal Movement</name>
      <text>The spirit can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. The spirit takes 5 (1d10) force damage if it ends its turn inside an object.</text>
      <attack>Incorporeal Movement||1d10</attack>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the spirit fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The spirit makes two Lightning Fist or Hailstone attacks in any combination.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Lightning Fist</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 25 (4d8 + 7) lightning damage.</text>
      <attack>Lightning Damage|+12|4d8+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Hailstone</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, range 90/180 ft., one target. Hit: 17 (3d6 + 7) bludgeoning damage plus 7 (2d6) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Hailstone|+12|(3d6+7)+(2d6)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+12|3d6+7</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Death Bolt (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The spirit hurls a magical lightning bolt in a 120-foot line that is 10 feet wide. Each creature in that area must make a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw, taking 27 (6d8) lightning damage plus 16 (3d10) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. On a success or failure, an affected creature's hit point maximum is reduced by an amount equal to the necrotic damage taken. This reduction lasts until the creature finishes a long rest. The creature dies if its hit point maximum is reduced to 0.</text>
      <attack>Death Bolt||(6d8)+(3d10)</attack>
      <attack>Lightning Damage||6d8</attack>
      <attack>Necrotic Damage||3d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Hailstorm (Recharge 4-6) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>D4</recharge>
      <text>The spirit conjures a hailstorm in a 20-foot-radius, 40-foot-high cylinder centered on a point it can see within 120 feet of itself. Each creature in that area must make a DC 17 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 10 (3d6) bludgeoning damage plus 10 (3d6) cold damage and has the prone condition. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.</text>
      <attack>Hailstorm||(3d6)+(3d6)</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage||3d6</attack>
      <attack>Cold Damage||3d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>A storm giant can escape death through a mystical ritual that transforms the giant into a semiconscious storm. However, if the giant performs the ritual in a place where the barrier between the Material Plane and the Shadowfell is thin, the seeping negative energy drastically alters the ritual's outcome. The giant's soul becomes infused with negative energy and doesn't disperse into the elements. Rather, it absorbs the elemental energy around it, and its lower body becomes a storm cloud. The resulting tempest spirit is similar in appearance to a djinni and is sometimes mistaken for one by adventurers.
	Some tempest spirits cannot accept their new form and seek to undo the transformation in solitude. Others are overcome with rage and hew a path of destruction. Massive hailstones and lightning infused with necrotic energy rain from tempest spirits on those that get too close to them.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 184</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Titanothere</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>136 (13d12+52)</hp>
    <speed>50 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save/>
    <skill/>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages/>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses/>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Beast of Burden</name>
      <text>The titanothere is considered to be one size larger for the purpose of determining its carrying capacity.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Stomp</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. Hit: 20 (3d8 + 7) bludgeoning damage. If the titanothere moved at least 20 feet straight toward the target immediately before the hit, the target takes an extra 13 (3d8) bludgeoning damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 18 Strength saving throw or have the prone condition if it is a creature.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+10|3d8+7</attack>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage||3d8</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Titanotheres are a family of enormous mammals related to rhinoceroses. Some of them lack any horns on the face, while others have one, two, or more horns of various shapes and sizes. Some have rough, almost stony skin; some have horny plates; and some have thick, shaggy fur. These creatures are united by their tremendous stature, their herding behavior, and their irritable disposition.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 185</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Troll Amalgam</name>
    <sortname>Troll, Amalgam</sortname>
    <ancestry>Troll</ancestry>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>217 (14d20+70)</hp>
    <speed>60 ft., climb 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save>Wis +9, Con +11</save>
    <skill>Perception +9</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>Giant, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>17</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist>poison; bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+6</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>If the amalgam fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The amalgam has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>The amalgam regains 15 hit points at the start of its turn. If the amalgam takes acid or fire damage, it regains only 5 hit points at the start of its next turn. The amalgam dies only if it takes 20 or more acid or fire damage while it has 0 hit points.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The amalgam makes three Rend attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rend</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: 25 (4d8 + 7) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+13|4d8+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Fling Limb (3/Day) (Bonus Action)</name>
      <recharge>3/DAY</recharge>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, range 60/240 ft., one target. Hit: 11 (1d8 + 7) bludgeoning damage. If the limb hits a Medium or smaller creature, that creature has the grappled condition (escape DC 17). The limb has the statistics of a troll amalgam, except for the following: it is Medium, it has 45 hit points, its speed is 30 ft., it doesn't have a challenge rating or Legendary Resistance, and the only action it can take is the Attack action, which it can use only to grapple.
	Until this grapple ends, the target has the restrained condition and takes 25 (4d8 + 7) slashing damage at the start of each of its turns. If the limb is not destroyed within 24 hours of being flung, roll a d12; on a roll of 12, the limb regenerates into a troll (see the Monster Manual). Otherwise, the limb withers away.</text>
      <attack>Bludgeoning Damage|+13|1d8+7</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage||4d8+7</attack>
    </action>
    <description>A troll amalgam forms when multiple trolls fuse together during regeneration. This sometimes occurs when many trolls are slain in a single battle, when troll parts are thrown into charnel pits or mass graves, or through twisted rituals of wicked spellcasters. Sometimes troll worshipers of Vaprak hear a call to gather in the Underdark and perform a gruesome rite that fuses them into an amalgam that is regarded as an avatar of their fearsome god.
	A troll amalgam is a misshapen mass of rubbery flesh, claws, and faces. If a creature tries to attack it from beyond its reach or to escape through a small tunnel, the troll amalgam tears offa piece of its own body and hurls it at the creature. These body parts eventually regenerate into full trolls, and sometimes they regather and combine into a new troll amalgam.

Trolls:
The dwarven tale titled The Sa§a of Gnarldan Steelshield claims the god Vaprak the Destroyer came into being when Annam was injured and his blood spilled on the ground. The saga further claims that trolls were born similarly when Vaprak's blood was spilled. Whatever the truth of their origin, trolls embody life's steadfast determination to grow and thrive despite all obstacles.
	Trolls' rapid healing makes them subject to bizarre mutations, particularly when they regenerate in unusual environments or heal from extraordinary magical wounds. Troll amalgams and troll mutates are two examples of such strangely mutated forms.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 186</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Troll Mutate</name>
    <sortname>Troll, Mutate</sortname>
    <ancestry>Troll</ancestry>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>typically chaotic evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>95 (10d10+40)</hp>
    <speed>30 ft., fly 30 ft.(winged form only)</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>9</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Con +7, Int +6</save>
    <skill>Stealth +4, Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Giant, telepathy 60 ft.</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <vulnerable/>
    <resist/>
    <immune/>
    <conditionImmune/>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Proficiency Bonus</name>
      <text>+3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Mutation</name>
      <text>When the troll mutate is created, it gains one of four possible body mutations at random: 1, Elastic Body; 2, Psionic Mirror; 3, Spell Scarred; or 4, Winged Form. This mutation determines certain traits in this stat block.</text>
      <attack>Mutation||1d4</attack>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>The mutate regains 10 hit points at the start of its turn. If the mutate takes acid or fire damage, this trait doesn't function at the start of the mutate's next turn. The mutate dies only if it starts its turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate. If the mutate starts its turn with 0 hit points and regenerates, it randomly gains a mutation it doesn't already have (up to a maximum of four mutations).</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Amorphous (Elastic Body Only)</name>
      <text>The mutate can move through a space as narrow as 1 inch without squeezing.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance (Spell Scarred Only)</name>
      <text>The mutate has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Psychic Rebuke (Psionic Mirror Only)</name>
      <text>If the mutate takes psychic damage, each creature within 20 feet of it takes that damage as well.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The mutate makes two Rend attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rend</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft. (or 15 ft. if the mutate has the Elastic Body mutation), one target. Hit: 15 (2d10 + 4) slashing damage plus 9 (2d8) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Rend|+7|(2d10+4)+(2d8)</attack>
      <attack>Slashing Damage|+7|2d10+4</attack>
      <attack>Force Damage||2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Psychic Burst (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <recharge>D5</recharge>
      <text>The mutate unleashes a wave of psychic energy. Each creature within 30 feet of the mutate must make a DC 14 Intelligence saving throw, taking 28 (8d6) psychic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Damage||8d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>When exposed to corrupting alien energy, such as that found near a gate to the Far Realm or the strange magic that emanates through the Underdark, a regenerating troll undergoes strange mutations. Among the most common mutations are wings, stretchable bodies, resistance to magic, and a strange reflective psychic property. Many troll mutates also have small additional limbs and eyes, externalized organs, and other varjations.

Trolls:
The dwarven tale titled The Sa§a of Gnarldan Steelshield claims the god Vaprak the Destroyer came into being when Annam was injured and his blood spilled on the ground. The saga further claims that trolls were born similarly when Vaprak's blood was spilled. Whatever the truth of their origin, trolls embody life's steadfast determination to grow and thrive despite all obstacles.
	Trolls' rapid healing makes them subject to bizarre mutations, particularly when they regenerate in unusual environments or heal from extraordinary magical wounds. Troll amalgams and troll mutates are two examples of such strangely mutated forms.

Source:	Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 187</description>
    <environment/>
  </monster>
</compendium>
