<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <!-- Bloodshed Blade -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Bloodshed %name%</name>
    <detail>very rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <match>Double-Bladed Scimitar,Greatsword,Longsword,Rapier,Scimitar,Shortsword</match>
    <text>The hilt of this sword bears a carnelian engraved with the blood rune.

You can add your Constitution modifier (minimum of +1) to the damage rolls of attacks made with this weapon.

Invoking the Rune: When you target a creature with an attack using this weapon, you can invoke the sword's rune, causing it to flare with crimson light and infusing your attack with bloodthirsty precision. You then spend and roll one of your unspent Hit Dice and add the number rolled to the attack roll. You can choose to invoke the rune after rolling the d20.

If this attack hits, you can also spend and roll any number of your unspent Hit Dice and add the total rolled to the weapon's damage.

Once the rune has been invoked, it can't be invoked again until the next dawn.</text>
    <source>Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 111</source>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Armor of Safeguarding-->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>%name% of Safeguarding</name>
    <detail>very rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>HA</type>
    <text>Set in the center of this armor's chest is a citrine engraved with the shield rune.

While wearing this armor, your hit point maximum increases by an amount equal to 10 + your level.

Invoking the Rune: As an action, you can invoke the armor's rune to cast the beacon of hope spell with it; the spell has a duration of 1 minute and doesn't require concentration. Once the rune has been invoked, it can't be invoked again until the next dawn.</text>
    <source>Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 111</source>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Zephyr Armor -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Zephyr %name%</name>
    <detail>rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>LA</type>
    <text>This fine set of white-and-silver armor bears the wind rune upon its chest.

While wearing this armor, you have advantage on Dexterity (Acrobatics) checks and Dexterity saving throws as your movements are bolstered by gentle currents of wind.

Invoking the Rune: As an action, you can invoke the armor's rune to cast the wind wall spell (save DC 15) with it. Once the rune has been invoked, it can't be invoked again until the next dawn.</text>
    <source>Bigby Presents: Glory of the Giants p. 117</source>
  </itemtemplate>
</compendium>
