<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <spell>
    <name>Antagonize</name>
    <level>3</level>
    <school>EN</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>30 feet</range>
    <components>V, S, M (a playing card depicting a rogue)</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>School: Enchantment, Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Fighter (Eldritch Knight), Rogue (Arcane Trickster)</classes>
    <text>You whisper magical words that antagonize one creature of your choice within range. The target must make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the target takes 4d4 psychic damage and must immediately use its reaction to make a melee attack against another creature of your choice that you can see. If the target can't make this attack (for example, because there is no one within its reach or because its reaction is unavailable), the target instead has disadvantage on the next attack roll it makes before the start of your next turn. On a successful save, the target takes half as much damage only.

At Higher Levels: When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the damage increases by 1d4 for each slot level above 3rd.

Source:	The Book of Many Things p. 50</text>
    <roll description="3">4d4</roll>
    <roll description="4">5d4</roll>
    <roll description="5">6d4</roll>
    <roll description="6">7d4</roll>
    <roll description="7">8d4</roll>
    <roll description="8">9d4</roll>
    <roll description="9">10d4</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Spirit of Death</name>
    <level>4</level>
    <school>N</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>60 feet</range>
    <components>V, S, M (a gilded playing card worth at least 400 gp and depicting an avatar of death)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 hour</duration>
    <classes>School: Necromancy, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Fighter (Eldritch Knight), Rogue (Arcane Trickster)</classes>
    <text>You call forth a spirit that embodies death. The spirit manifests in an unoccupied space you can see within range and uses the reaper spirit stat block. The spirit disappears when it is reduced to 0 hit points or when the spell ends.
	The spirit is an ally to you and your companions. In combat, the spirit shares your initiative count and takes its turn immediately after yours. It obeys your verbal commands (no action required by you). If you don't issue the spirit any commands, it takes the Dodge action and uses its movement to avoid danger.

At Higher Levels: When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, use the higher level wherever the spell's level appears in the reaper spirit stat block.

Source:	The Book of Many Things p. 50</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Spray of Cards</name>
    <level>2</level>
    <school>C</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self (15-foot cone)</range>
    <components>V, S, M (a deck of cards)</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>School: Conjuration, Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Fighter (Eldritch Knight), Rogue (Arcane Trickster)</classes>
    <text>You spray a 15-foot cone of spectral cards. Each creature in that area must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 2d10 force damage and has the blinded condition until the end of its next turn. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage only.

At Higher Levels: When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the damage increases by 1d10 for each slot level above 2nd.

Blinded:
	• A blinded creature can't see and automatically fails any ability check that requires sight.
	• Attack rolls against the creature have advantage, and the creature's attack rolls have disadvantage.

Source:	The Book of Many Things p. 50</text>
    <roll description="2">2d10</roll>
    <roll description="3">3d10</roll>
    <roll description="4">4d10</roll>
    <roll description="5">5d10</roll>
    <roll description="6">6d10</roll>
    <roll description="7">7d10</roll>
    <roll description="8">8d10</roll>
    <roll description="9">9d10</roll>
  </spell>
</compendium>
