<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <!-- Antimagic Armor -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Antimagic %name%</name>
    <detail>very rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>LA,MA,HA</type>
    <text>While wearing this armor, you can use your reaction to give yourself advantage on a saving throw you make against a spell. Once this property is used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.
	In addition, while you wear this armor, you can use it to cast Antimagic Field, requiring no spell components. Once this property is used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 65</source>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Weapon of Throne's Command -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>%name% of Throne's Command</name>
    <detail>very rare</detail>
    <type>M,R</type>
    <text>This weapon is bedecked in ornate gold filigree and deep-blue and maroon jewels. You gain a +1 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with this weapon. Additionally, you gain proficiency in the Intimidation and Persuasion skills if you don't already have it.

Spellcasting: The weapon has 5 charges. You can use a bonus action and expend 1 or more of its charges to cast one of the following spells (save DC 16): Command (1 charge), Zone of Truth (2 charges), Compulsion (4 charges), Banishment (4 charges), or Dominate Person (5 charges).
	The weapon regains 1d4 expended charges daily at dawn.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 39</source>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon attacks +1</modifier>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon damage +1</modifier>
    <roll description="Recharge">1d4</roll>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Bloodseeker Ammunition -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Bloodseeker %name%</name>
    <detail>very rare</detail>
    <type>A</type>
    <text>Ranged attack rolls made with this ammunition have advantage against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 66</source>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Medium Armor of Fungal Spores -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>%name% of Fungal Spores</name>
    <detail>uncommon</detail>
    <type>MA</type>
    <text>While wearing this armor, you can take a bonus action to make the armor emit poisonous spores, which fill a 10-foot-radius sphere centered on yourself. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or have the poisoned condition until the end of your next turn. Once this property is used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 65</source>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Armor of the Fallen -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>%name% of the Fallen</name>
    <detail>uncommon (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>MA,HA</type>
    <text>While wearing this armor, you can use it to cast either Speak with Dead or Animate Dead. Once the armor has cast a spell in this way, it can't cast either spell until the next dawn.
	Your soul keeps this armor together. If you die while you are attuned to the armor, the armor is destroyed.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 65</source>
    <ac>14</ac>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Armor of Weightlessness -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>%name% of Weightlessness</name>
    <detail>uncommon (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>LA,MA,HA</type>
    <text>This armor has 5 charges. While you wear it, you can use a bonus action to expend 1 or more charges to cast one of the following spells from the armor, targeting yourself: Jump (1 charge) or Levitate (2 charges).
	This armor regains 1d4 + 1 expended charges daily at dawn.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 65</source>
    <roll description="Recharge">1d4+1</roll>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Clockwork Heavy Armor-->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Clockwork %name%</name>
    <detail>very rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>HA</type>
    <text>The outside surface and internal joints of this armor whir with interlocking gears, drawing on the orderly magic of the plane of Mechanus.
	The armor has 4 charges. If you make a d20 roll while wearing this armor, you can expend 1 charge to change the number rolled to a 10. The armor regains 1d4 expended charges daily at dawn.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 67</source>
    <roll description="Recharge">1d4</roll>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Sword of the Planes -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>%name% of the Planes</name>
    <detail>legendary (requires attunement)</detail>
    <match>Double-Bladed Scimitar,Greatsword,Longsword,Rapier,Scimitar,Shortsword</match>
    <text>You gain a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with this magic sword.
	This sword can tear the fabric of reality, creating a temporary rift between planes. You can use your action to choose a different plane of existence from the one you're on and slice through an unoccupied space within 5 feet of yourself, creating a rift to that other plane. The rift can be up to 10 feet high and 10 feet wide, and it lasts for 1 minute. Once this property is used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.
	You can specify a target destination, such as the City of Brass on the Elemental Plane of Fire or the palace of Dispater on the second layer of the Nine Hells, and the rift opens in or near that destination (DM's discretion). If you are trying to reach the City of Brass, for example, the rift might appear on the Street of Steel, before the Gate of Ashes, or facing the city from across the Sea of Fire, at the DM's discretion.

Anything that enters the rift is instantly transported to the other plane, appearing in the unoccupied space nearest to the rift.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 68</source>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon attacks +3</modifier>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon damage +3</modifier>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Dried Leech Ammunition -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Dried Leech %name%</name>
    <detail>uncommon</detail>
    <type>A</type>
    <text>This leech has been dried and imbued with a mote of animating magic. If you hit a creature with a ranged attack roll using this ammunition, the leech springs to life and sinks its teeth into the target, dealing 1d4 piercing damage at the start of each of the target's turns. If the leech deals at least 10 damage or the target dies, the leech falls off. A creature, including the target, can use its action to detach the leech. Once a leech is no longer attached to its target, the leech dies and is no longer magical.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 67</source>
    <roll description="Piercing Damage">1d4</roll>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Feywrought Armor-->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Feywrought %name%</name>
    <detail>rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>LA,MA,HA</type>
    <text>This colorful, flowery armor was forged in the Feywild and is infused with that plane's captivating magic.
	While wearing this armor, you have advantage on saving throws you make to avoid or end the charmed condition on yourself.
	This armor has 3 charges. You can use an action to expend a charge to cast the Compulsion spell (save DC 15) from this armor. The armor regains 1d3 expended charges daily at dawn.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 67</source>
    <roll>1d3</roll>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Fool's Blade -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Fool's %name%</name>
    <detail>very rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <match>Double-Bladed Scimitar,Greatsword,Longsword,Rapier,Scimitar,Shortsword</match>
    <text>This weapon appears ordinary, but it bears strong illusion magic that allows its wielder to skillfully deceive opponents.
	You have a +2 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with this magic weapon. While wielding it, you also gain the following benefits:

Fool's Feint: As a bonus action, you can feint, choosing a creature within 5 feet of you as your target. Until the start of your next turn, you have advantage on attack rolls against the target. Once this bonus action is used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.

Misdirect: When a creature within 60 feet of you targets you with an attack roll, you can use your reaction to require that creature to make a DC 15 Intelligence saving throw. On a failed save, the attack instead targets another creature of your choice that is within the attacker's reach. Once this reaction has been used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 36</source>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon attacks +2</modifier>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon damage +2</modifier>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Forcebreaker Weapon -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Forcebreaker %name%</name>
    <detail>very rare</detail>
    <match>Club,Flail,Greatclub,Light Hammer,Mace,Maul,Quarterstaff,Sling,Staff,Warhammer,Wooden Staff</match>
    <text>You gain a +2 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with this magic weapon.
	This weapon was crafted to destroy structures made of force, such as those created by Forcecage or Wall of Force. Striking a Large or smaller structure of magical force with this weapon automatically shatters that structure. If the target is a Huge or larger structure of force, this weapon shatters a 20-foot-cube portion of it.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 67</source>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon attacks +2</modifier>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon damage +2</modifier>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Glimmering Moonbow -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Glimmering Moon %name%</name>
    <detail>rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <match>Longbow,Shortbow</match>
    <text>This silver-and-black bow is engraved with the phases of the moon. You gain a +1 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with this magic weapon.
	When you hit with a ranged attack roll using this magic bow, the target takes an extra 1d6 radiant damage. If you load no ammunition in the weapon, it produces its own, automatically creating one piece of magic ammunition when you make a ranged attack with it. The ammunition created by the bow vanishes the instant after it hits or misses a target.
	While wielding this magic bow, you can use a bonus action to enter a semi-incorporeal state until the start of your next turn. While semi-incorporeal, you have resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage. Once this bonus action is used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 36</source>
    <roll>1d6</roll>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon attacks +1</modifier>
    <modifier category="bonus">weapon damage +1</modifier>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Gloomwrought Armor -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Gloomwrought %name%</name>
    <detail>rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <type>LA,MA,HA</type>
    <text>This intricate grayscale armor was forged in the Shadowfell and is infused with that plane's gloom.
	While you're wearing this armor, you have advantage on saving throws you make to avoid or end the frightened condition on yourself.
	This armor has 3 charges. You can expend a charge to cast the Calm Emotions spell (save DC 15) from the armor. This armor regains 1d3 expended charges daily at dawn.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 67</source>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Bow of Conflagration -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>%name% of Conflagration</name>
    <detail>rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <match>Longbow,Shortbow</match>
    <text>Ammunition fired from this bow blazes brightly. When you hit with an attack roll using this bow, the target takes an extra 1d6 fire damage. If the target is a flammable, nonmagical object, it catches fire, taking 1d6 fire damage at the start of each of your turns until a creature uses an action to extinguish the flames.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 66</source>
    <roll>1d6</roll>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Bow of Melodies-->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>%name% of Melodies</name>
    <detail>very rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <match>Longbow,Shortbow</match>
    <text>This bow has multiple strings and resembles a lyre or small harp. By strumming the strings while setting an arrow to the bow, you imbue the arrow with magic.
	You can play one of the following melodies when you use the bow to make a ranged weapon attack. You must choose to do so before you make the attack roll, and you can play only one melody per attack.

Melody of Precision: If you're proficient in Performance, you gain a +1 bonus to the attack roll. If you have expertise in Performance, you gain a +2 bonus instead.

Melody of Reverberation: The melody you strum echoes loudly. On a hit, the target takes extra thunder damage equal to your Charisma modifier.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 66</source>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Starshot Crossbow -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Starshot %name%</name>
    <detail>rare (requires attunement)</detail>
    <match>Crossbow,Hand Crossbow,Heavy Crossbow,Light Crossbow,Light Repeating Crossbow</match>
    <text>This crossbow is crafted from blackened wood, and its limbs bear pearl inlays depicting constellations. You ignore the loading property with this crossbow. If you load no ammunition in the weapon, it produces its own, automatically creating one piece of magic ammunition when you make a ranged attack with it. The ammunition created by the weapon vanishes the instant after it hits or misses a target. The crossbow has 3 charges and regains 1d3 expended charges daily at dawn.

Constellations: The crossbow is decorated with three constellations. As a bonus action, you can tap one of the constellations to invoke it, expending 1 charge and producing one of the following effects:

Balance: The next time you hit a creature with a ranged attack roll using this crossbow before the end of your next turn, you or another creature of your choice within 30 feet of you can regain hit points equal to 1d8 plus your proficiency bonus.

Flames: Until the end of your next turn, when you hit a creature with a ranged attack roll using this crossbow, the attack deals an additional 2d8 fire damage.

Rogue: Until the end of your next turn, you have the invisible condition, and anything you are wearing or carrying is also invisible.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 38</source>
    <roll description="Recharge">1d3</roll>
    <roll description="Heal">1d8+%0</roll>
    <roll description="Fire Damage">2d8</roll>
  </itemtemplate>

  <!-- Winged Ammunition -->
  <itemtemplate>
    <name>Winged %name%</name>
    <detail>uncommon</detail>
    <type>A</type>
    <text>Ranged weapon attack rolls made with this ammunition ignore half and three-quarters cover. In addition, attacking at long range doesn't impose disadvantage on ranged weapon attack rolls made with this ammunition.</text>
    <source>The Book of Many Things p. 66</source>
  </itemtemplate>
</compendium>
