<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Warlock</name>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <counter>
        <name>Dreamer's Whisper</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <counter>
        <name>Sound Lance</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Otherworldly Patron: Goat (HB) -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Patron: Goat (HB)</name>
        <text>Your patron is a goat. A magical goat? Possibly. An alien goat? Could be. The greatest of all time? Conceivably. Whatever its origins, that higher power you've created a pact with is a garbage-eating, sure-footed, frog-eyed, head-butting, stubborn-ass goat.
	As a warlock of the goat, you are imbued with the might of the goat as well as its lack of decorum and finesse. You do not fear rushing head first (literally) at enemies. Magic sword? No thanks. But it looks like it'd taste good on a sandwich. Stuck door? Stand back and hold my potions, lads.

Source:	DMDave - Goat Patron</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Expanded Spell List (Goat (HB))</name>
        <text>The goat lets you choose from an expanded list of spells when you learn a warlock spell. The following spells are added to the warlock spell list for you.

Goat Spells:
Warlock Level | Spells
1st | compelled duel, wrathful smite
3rd | barkskin, enlarge/reduce
5th | protection from energy, stinking cloud
7th | staggering smite, stoneskin
9th | destructive wave, planar binding

Source:	DMDave - Goat Patron</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Headbutt (Goat (HB))</name>
        <text>When you select this otherworldly patron at 1st level, your dense skull is a natural weapon, which you can use to make unarmed strikes. If you hit with it, you deal bludgeoning damage equal to 1d4 + your Strength or Charisma modifier (your choice).
	At 5th level, the damage die increases to 1d6, and then again at 11th level to 1d8, and 17th level to 1d10.

Source:	DMDave - Goat Patron</text>
        <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage" level="1">1d4+%1</roll>
        <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage" level="5">1d6+%1</roll>
        <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage" level="11">1d8+%1</roll>
        <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage" level="17">1d10+%1</roll>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Headbutt of the Goat (Goat (HB))</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you gain the ability to channel the power of the goat to deal extra damage with your headbutt attacks. You have a pool of d6s that you spend to fuel this damage. The number of dice in the pool equals 1 + your warlock level.
	Once per turn, you can use one or more dice from the pool to deal extra damage to one creature you hit with your headbutt attack. The maximum number of dice you can spend at once equals your Charisma modifier (minimum of one die). Roll the dice you spend and add it to your headbutt's normal damage roll.
	Your pool regains all expended dice when you finish a long rest.

Source:	DMDave - Goat Patron</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Magic Headbutt (Goat (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, your headbutt attack counts as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.

Source:	DMDave - Goat Patron</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Garbage Mouth (Goat (HB))</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you can eat mundane objects in order to gain temporary hit points. Choose one or more Tiny nonmagical objects with an AC of 15 or lower (see page 246 of the DMG for object ACs). You spend 2 minutes per pound of weight the object has eating it. For each pound of objects consumed in this manner, you gain 1d6 temporary hit points. The total amount of weight in objects that you can eat equals one pound per your Charisma modifier (minimum of one). At 17th level, the amount you can eat increases to one pound per twice your Charisma modifier (minimum of one).
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	DMDave - Goat Patron</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Garbage Mouth</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>Goat (HB)</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Butthead (Goat (HB))</name>
        <text>At 10th level, your stubbornness is difficult to overcome. You gain proficiency in Intelligence saving throws. In addition, you are immune to being charmed, and when another creature attempts to charm you, you can use your reaction to force the creature to succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC, taking 2d8 psychic damage on a failed save or half as much damage on a successful one.

Source:	DMDave - Goat Patron</text>
        <roll description="Psychic Damage">2d8</roll>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Greatest of All Time (Goat (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, once you start charging, nothing can stand in your way. As long as you have not yet moved on your turn, you can use your action to choose a direction. You then charge 60 feet straight in that direction with your head down.
	Each creature in your path must make a Strength saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the creature takes damage from your headbutt attack as if you had hit it with a critical hit and falls prone in its space. On a successful saving throw, the creature takes the normal damage from your headbutt attack and doesn't fall prone.
	Your headbutt automatically destroys any Medium or smaller nonmagical object not being worn or carried in your path if its AC is 17 or less, and any Medium or smaller nonmagical object with an AC of 18 or more is pushed 5 feet out of the path of your charge. If a nonmagical object in your path is Large or larger with an AC of 17 or less and no thicker than 2 feet, such a stone wall or wooden door, you destroy a 5-foot portion of it and continue your charge.
	While charging, your movement is unaffected by difficult terrain, and spells and other magical effects can neither reduce your speed nor cause you to be paralyzed or restrained. You may also run across any liquid surface-such as water, acid, mud, snow, quicksand, or lava-as if it were harmless solid ground (you still take damage from the heat of crossing molten lava). If you are on a liquid surface when your charge ends, you become submerged.
	Your charge ends if you move the full 60 feet, a creature succeeds on its saving throw, or you hit an object that you can't break through. After your charge, your movement speed becomes 0 until the start of your next turn.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	DMDave - Goat Patron</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Greatest of All Time</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>Goat (HB)</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Otherworldly Patron: Great Dreamer (HB) -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Patron: Great Dreamer (HB)</name>
        <text>The Great Dreamer is an enormous spacegoing cetacean that is apparently responsible for the occurrence of whales and other cetaceans, both in space and on worlds with plentiful water. They travel through space in a spherical envelope of airy water, so large that weather patterns occur on its surface, creating the image of an immense elemental whale swimming through the cosmos.
	The lucky few warlocks who are awarded the might of the Great Dreamer experience many of the benefits that their cetacean favorites do, including advanced magics involving thunder damage and, eventually, immortality.

Source:	DMDave - Great Dreamer Patron</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Expanded Spell List (Great Dreamer (HB))</name>
        <text>The Great Dreamer lets you choose from an expanded list of spells when you learn a warlock spell. The following spells are added to the warlock spell list for you.

Greater Dreamer Spells:
Warlock Level | Spells
1st | sleep, thunderwave
3rd | augury, gust of wind
5th | clairvoyance, spirit guardians
7th | conjure minor elementals, control water
9th | conjure elemental, modify memory

Source:	DMDave - Great Dreamer Patron</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Dreamer's Whisper (Great Dreamer (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level when you choose the Great Dreamer patron, you can cast sleep without expending a spell slot. Once you cast sleep using this feature, you can't do so again until you complete a long rest. In addition, when you cast sleep using this feature or a warlock spell slot, you roll d12s instead of d8s to determine the number of hits points of creatures that the spell affects.

Source:	DMDave - Great Dreamer Patron</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Deep Space Resilience (Great Dreamer (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you have resistance to cold damage. In addition, you can hold your breath indefinitely.

Source:	DMDave - Great Dreamer Patron</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sound Amplifier (Great Dreamer (HB))</name>
        <text>Also at 6th level, when you cast a spell that deals thunder damage, you can add your Charisma modifier to one thunder damage roll of that spell against one of its targets.

Source:	DMDave - Great Dreamer Patron</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Great Dreamer's Blessing (Great Dreamer (HB))</name>
        <text>At 10th level, your patron bestows you with the gift of immortality. You suffer none of the drawbacks of old age, you can't be aged magically, and you make death saving throws with advantage. In addition, if a spell, such as raise dead, has the sole effect of restoring you to life (but not undeath), the caster doesn't need material components to cast the spell on you.

Source:	DMDave - Great Dreamer Patron</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sound Lance (Great Dreamer (HB))</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you can emit a blast of thunderous energy in a 30-foot cone. Each creature in the area must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC or it is stunned until the start of your next turn. Creatures immune to thunder damage automatically pass their saving throws. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you complete a long rest.

Source:	DMDave - Great Dreamer Patron</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Sound Lance</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>Great Dreamer (HB)</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
  <spell>
    <name>Sleep</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Great Dreamer (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Thunderwave</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Great Dreamer (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Augury</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Great Dreamer (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Gust of Wind</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Great Dreamer (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Clairvoyance</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Great Dreamer (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Spirit Guardians</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Great Dreamer (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Conjure Minor Elementals</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Great Dreamer (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Control Water</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Great Dreamer (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Conjure Elemental</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Great Dreamer (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Modify Memory</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Great Dreamer (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Compelled Duel</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Goat (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Wrathful Smite</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Goat (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Barkskin</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Goat (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Enlarge/Reduce</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Goat (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Protection from Energy</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Goat (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Stinking Cloud</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Goat (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Staggering Smite</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Goat (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Stoneskin</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Goat (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Destructive Wave</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Goat (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Planar Binding</name>
    <classes>Warlock (Goat (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
</compendium>
