<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Monk</name>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Fighting Stances (HB)</name>
        <text>With this optional rule, when you take on levels in the Monk class, you adopt fighting stances which you can switch to change your combat dynamic. While you are in a particular fighting stance, the fighting stance's features and drawbacks replace those normally offered by the Martial Arts feature.

Learning Fighting Stances.
You learn the balanced stance at first level as well as two more fighting stances of your choice which are detailed below. You learn one additional fighting stance of your choice at 5th, 11th, and 17th level. Each time you learn a new fighting stance, you can also replace one fighting stance you know with a different one. You can not replace the balanced stance.

Starting Stance and Changing Stance in Combat.
When you roll initiative, you automatically assume the balanced stance. At the start of each of your turns, you can switch to another fighting stance that you know. The benefits and drawbacks of your chosen fighting style replace your monk Martial Arts feature until the start of your next turn, if you are incapacitated, or if you die. At the start of your next turn, you can choose another fighting stance or continue using the same one.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Balanced Stance (HB)</name>
        <text>This is your default stance.

While in the balanced fighting stance, your Martial Arts feature offers the normal benefits and drawbacks detailed in the PHB.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Clever Leopard Stance (HB)</name>
        <text>The leopard uses its superior intellect to engage its opponents, standing back and observing, always looking for the right moment to strike.

While you are in this stance, you gain the following benefits and drawbacks while you are unarmed or wielding only monk weapons and you aren't wearing armor or wielding a shield. These benefits and drawbacks replace those normally offered by your monk Martial Arts feature:

	• You can use Dexterity or Intelligence instead of Strength for the attack and damage rolls of your unarmed strikes and monk weapons.

	• You can roll a d4 in place of the normal damage of your unarmed strike or monk weapons. This die changes as you gain monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table.

	• When you use the Ready action in order to use your reaction to make an attack with your unarmed strike or monk weapon (regardless of the triggering event), you make your attack roll with advantage.

	• You can take the Dash action as a bonus action on each of your turns.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Constricting Snake Stance (HB)</name>
        <text>The snake fighter is a close combatant, utilizing fast attacks that target an opponent's weak points such as the eyes, groin, and joints.

While you are in this stance, you gain the following benefits and drawbacks while you are unarmed or wielding only monk weapons and you aren't wearing armor or wielding a shield. These benefits and drawbacks replace those normally offered by your monk Martial Arts feature:

	• You can use Dexterity instead of Strength for the attack and damage rolls of your unarmed strikes and monk weapons.

	• You can roll a d4 in place of the normal damage of your unarmed strike or monk weapons. This die changes as you gain monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table.

	• If you do not move more than 5 feet on your turn, your unarmed strike and monk weapon attacks score a critical hit on a roll of 19-20.

	• If you use your reaction to make an attack of opportunity when a hostile creature that you can see moves out of your reach, you gain a +2 bonus to your attack rolls made with your unarmed strike or monk weapons against that creature.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Dancing Crane Stance (HB)</name>
        <text>The crane fighter is a dancer, using their entire form to bewilder and deftly move around their opponents. Cranes prefer not to use weapons.

While you are in this stance, you gain the following benefits and drawbacks while you are unarmed or wielding only monk weapons and you aren't wearing armor or wielding a shield. These benefits and drawbacks replace those normally offered by your monk Martial Arts feature:

	• You can use Dexterity instead of Strength for the attack and damage rolls of your unarmed strikes and monk weapons.

	• You can roll a d4 in place of the normal damage of your unarmed strike or monk weapons. This die changes as you gain monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table.

	• When you use the Attack action with an unarmed strike on your turn, you can take the Disengage action as a bonus action.

	• You can use your reaction to deflect a weapon when you are hit by a melee weapon attack. When you do so, the damage you take from the attack is reduced by your monk die + your Dexterity modifier.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Great Dragon Stance (HB)</name>
        <text>The dragon attacks with blows intended to dispatch and kill. It is a powerful fighting stance, reserved only for the most aggressive warriors.

While you are in this stance, you gain the following benefits and drawbacks while you are unarmed or wielding only monk weapons and you aren't wearing armor or wielding a shield. These benefits and drawbacks replace those normally offered by your monk Martial Arts feature:

	• You can roll a d4 in place of the normal damage of your unarmed strike or monk weapons. This die changes as you gain monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table.

	• You gain a +2 bonus to damage rolls made with your unarmed strike and monk weapon attacks.

	• If you use your Attack action to make a grapple, when you roll your Strength (Athletics) check, you can treat a d20 roll of 9 or lower as a 10. You may only use this benefit if you are proficient in the Athletics skill.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Fierce Tiger Stance (HB)</name>
        <text>The fierce tiger is a quick and powerful fighter, striking hard and fast.

While you are in this stance, you gain the following benefits and drawbacks while you are unarmed or wielding only monk weapons and you aren't wearing armor or wielding a shield. These benefits and drawbacks replace those normally offered by your monk Martial Arts feature:

	• You can use Dexterity instead of Strength for the attack and damage rolls of your unarmed strikes and monk weapons.

	• You can roll a d4 in place of the normal damage of your unarmed strike or monk weapons. This die changes as you gain monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table.

	• Once on each of your turns, if you move at least 20 feet straight towards a creature you can use your bonus action to shove the creature.

	• When you use the Attack action against a creature that is prone and score a critical hit with an unarmed strike or monk weapon on your turn, you can roll your martial arts die one additional time and add it to the extra damage of the critical hit.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Laughing Monkey Stance (HB)</name>
        <text>Those who fight in the style of the monkey are fast, cheeky opponents, and masters of the quarterstaff.

While you are in this stance, you gain the following benefits and drawbacks while you are unarmed or wielding only monk weapons and you aren't wearing armor or wielding a shield. These benefits and drawbacks replace those normally offered by your monk Martial Arts feature:

	• You can use Dexterity instead of Strength for the attack and damage rolls of your unarmed strikes and monk weapons.

	• You can roll a d4 in place of the normal damage of your unarmed strike or monk weapons. This die changes as you gain monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table.

	• When you use the Attack action with a quarterstaff on your turn or use the Dodge action, you can make one additional attack with your quarterstaff as a bonus action. You do not add your ability modifier to the damage of the bonus attack unless that modifier is negative.

	• When you take the Dodge action, you gain a +1 bonus to AC.

	• You have advantage on Dexterity (Acrobatics) checks.

	• You have disadvantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Proud Wolf Stance (HB)</name>
        <text>The wolf sticks to its pack, gaining power from its allies.

While you are in this stance, you gain the following benefits and drawbacks while you are unarmed or wielding only monk weapons and you aren't wearing armor or wielding a shield. These benefits and drawbacks replace those normally offered by your monk Martial Arts feature:

	• You can use Dexterity instead of Strength for the attack and damage rolls of your unarmed strikes and monk weapons.

	• You can roll a d4 in place of the normal damage of your unarmed strike or monk weapons. This die changes as you gain monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table.

	• When one of your allies attacks a hostile creature within 5 feet of you, you can use your reaction to make an unarmed strike or monk weapon attack against that creature.

	• When you use your Attack action with an unarmed strike or a monk weapon on your turn, instead of dealing damage you can attempt to knock the target prone. The target must make a Strength saving throw against a DC of 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength modifier or fall prone in its space.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sly Raven Stance (HB)</name>
        <text>The raven watches its opponent carefully. Then, much to its opponent's surprise, the raven learns its moves.

While you are in this stance, you gain the following benefits and drawbacks while you are unarmed or wielding only monk weapons and you aren't wearing armor or wielding a shield. These benefits and drawbacks replace those normally offered by your monk Martial Arts feature:

	• You can use Dexterity instead of Strength for the attack and damage rolls of your unarmed strikes and monk weapons.

	• You can roll a d4 in place of the normal damage of your unarmed strike or monk weapons. This die changes as you gain monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table.

	• When you use the Help action to aid a friendly creature in attacking a creature within 5 feet of you, you can make one unarmed strike as a bonus action.

	• When you take damage from a creature that is within 5 feet of you, you can use your reaction to adjust your defenses. Once you do, the creature has disavantage on its attacks against you until you take damage from the creature again or you change your fighting stance.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Thrashing Mantis Stance (HB)</name>
        <text>The mantis attacks violently without regard to itself, attacking to defend, hitting and smashing hardly and firmly.

While you are in this stance, you gain the following benefits and drawbacks while you are unarmed or wielding only monk weapons and you aren't wearing armor or wielding a shield. These benefits and drawbacks replace those normally offered by your monk Martial Arts feature:

	• You can use Dexterity instead of Strength for the attack and damage rolls of your unarmed strikes and monk weapons.

	• You can roll a d4 in place of the normal damage of your unarmed strike or monk weapons. This die changes as you gain monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table.

	• You gain 2 temporary hit points for each level you have in this class. You lose these temporary hit points if you change your fighting stance.

	• Before you use the Attack action with an unarmed strike or monk weapon attack on your turn, you can choose to take a -2 penalty to your AC which lasts until the start of your next turn. If the attack hits, you add +5 to the attack's damage.

	• When you take damage from a creature that is within 5 feet of you, you can use your reaction to take make an unarmed strike or monk weapon attack against that creature.

	• *You can't switch to this fighting stance again until you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Monastic Tradition: Way of the Moon Soul (HB) -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Moon Soul (HB)</name>
        <text>Monks of the way of the moon soul are strong, capable warriors, who use their cycle style of fighting to chain powerful attacks. Their stoic nature keeps them in a calm state of constant meditation, allowing them to be unflappable in the face of danger.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.15 (Jan 2019)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Fist of the New Moon (Way of the Moon Soul (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you can catch enemies off guard with a powerful opening strike. Whenever you hit a creature that hasn't taken a turn in combat yet with one of the attacks granted by your Flurry of Blows, the first hit you score using it against that creature is a critical hit.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.15</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Crescent Kick (Way of the Moon Soul (HB))</name>
        <text>At 6th level, your powerful opening strikes can be used to expose your enemy to the rest of your attacks. When you use the Attack action with an unarmed strike or monk weapon on your turn against a creature within 5 feet of you, you can spend 1 ki point to give yourself advantage against that creature until the end of your turn.

Source:	EVIL p.15</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Moonlight Warrior (Way of the Moon Soul (HB))</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you have become proficient at fighting in the dark. You gain darkvision out to 60 feet. If you already have darkvision out to 60 feet, your darkvision's range increases to 120 feet. In addition, if you are blinded, you can use your action to end the condition.

Source:	EVIL p.15</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Full Moon Strike (Way of the Moon Soul (HB))</name>
        <text>At 11th level, if you move at least 10 feet straight toward a target and then hit it with an unarmed strike or monk weapon on the same turn, you can spend 1 ki point to have the target take an extra 1d10 damage from the attack.
	You can increase the strike's damage by spending ki points. Each point you spend increases the damage by 1d10. The maximum number of ki points (the first 1 plus the additional points) that you can spend on the feature is 6.
	You can use this feature only once on each of your turns.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.15</text>
        <roll description="Extra Damage">1d10</roll>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Enemy of Lycanthropes (Way of the Moon Soul (HB))</name>
        <text>Also at 11th level, your knowledge of the moon and its minions makes you a formidable combatant against lyncanthropes. You automatically pass saving throws to avoid contracting a lycanthrope's curse.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.15</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Lunar Eclipse (Way of the Moon Soul (HB))</name>
        <text>At 17th level, when a creature targets you with an attack, as a reaction you can mark that target. While the target is marked, you have a +2 bonus to your AC, attack rolls, and damage rolls against that target. The target remains marked for 24 hours, until it dies, you are incapacitated, or you mark another creature using this feature.

Source:	EVIL p.15</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
