<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Rogue</name>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <counter>
        <name>Fade</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <counter>
        <name>Free Jack</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Roguish Archetype: Demolitionist (HB) -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Roguish Archetype: Demolitionist (HB)</name>
        <text>The smell of gun powder and sulfur, soot-covered clothing, and a missing finger or two (which is how they earned their dwarven names "haritzfingrumm" which literally translates to "gone fingers") are the traits of the dwarven demolitionist. Considered "rogues" by their mountain-dwelling brethren, these bomb tossing dwarves are a unique twist on the classic rogue.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.18</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Restriction: Dwarves Only (Demolitionist (HB))</name>
        <text>Only dwarves can join the ranks of Dwarven Demolitionists. The demolitionist fills a particular niche in dwarven society and culture.
	Your GM can lift this restriction to better suit the campaign.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.18</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Demolitionists' Tools (Demolitionist (HB))</name>
        <text>You gain proficiency in demolitionists' tools (costs and weighs the same as alchemist's supplies).
	In order to craft explosive devices using the Bomb Craft or Quick Bomb features, you must have a set of demolitionists' tools available. The demolitionists' tools have enough supplies to create 10 explosive devices. Once you've created 10 explosive devices with your demolitionists' tools, you will need to replace them before you create another explosive device.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.18</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bomb Craft (Demolitionist (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting when you select this roguish archetype at 3rd level, you can create explosives to assist you in your adventures. The bombs that you can create are detailed in the "Bomb Designs" section below.
	You conduct an hour-long ritual that crafts up to 2 explosive devices of your choice, selected from the list of "Bomb Designs" below. The creation is completed at the end of the hour, coalescing in an unoccupied space of your choice on a surface within 5 feet of you. After you use this feature, you can't use it again until you complete a long rest.

Using an Explosive Device. Unless the bomb design's description says otherwise, you must use your action to use an explosive device. Once you use the device, it is destroyed and cannot be used again. If another creature attempts to use one of your explosive devices, it must make a DC 10 Intelligence check using demolitionists tools. On a success, the creature can use the device. On a failure, it explodes in their space.

Bombcrafting Ability. Intelligence is your bomb crafting ability for your explosive devices. You use your Intelligence whenever a bomb refers to your bomb crafting ability. In addition, you use your Intelligence modifier when setting the saving throw DC for an explosive device you use. If another creature uses your explosive device, it still uses your bomb save DCs when setting the saving throw.

	Bomb save DC = 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence modifier.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.18</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Quick Bomb (Demolitionist (HB))</name>
        <text>Beginning at 3rd level, as a bonus action, you can quickly assemble a small, unstable explosive device to use in combat. The construction of this device does not count towards the 2 explosive devices your Bomb Craft feature limits you to. However, it does use up supplies from your demolitionists' tools as normal.
	You must use an action to throw this explosive device as a ranged weapon attack at a target you can see within 30 feet of you before the end of your next turn; otherwise, the quick bomb loses its potency and the materials spent creating it are wasted. On a hit, the bomb deals 2d6 fire damage. When you reach certain levels in this class, the damage increases: 3d6 at 7th level, 4d6 at 13th level, and 5d6 at 19th level.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.18</text>
        <roll description="Fire Damage" level="3">2d6</roll>
        <roll description="Fire Damage" level="7">3d6</roll>
        <roll description="Fire Damage" level="13">4d6</roll>
        <roll description="Fire Damage" level="19">5d6</roll>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bomb Designs (Demolitionist (HB))</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you have learned how to create a variety of explosive devices using your Bomb Craft feature.
	The bomb designs are presented here in alphabetical order. If a bomb design requires a level, you must be that level in this class to learn the design.

Boom Bucket. You can throw this explosive device at a point you can see within 30 feet of you. On impact, it explodes in a 5-foot sphere centered on that point. Each creature in the area must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw against your bomb craft DC, taking 3d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. The fire ignites any flammable objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried. When you reach certain levels in this class, the damage increases: 4d6 at 7th level, 5d6 at 13th level, and 6d6 at 19th level.

Concussion Grenade. You can throw this explosive device at a point you can see within 30 feet of you. On impact, it explodes in a 5-foot radius sphere centered on that point.
	Each creature in the area must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against your bomb craft DC, taking 2d8 thunder damage and is pushed 10 feet away from the point of explosion. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage and isn't pushed. In addition, unsecured objects that are completely within the area of effect are automatically pushed 10 feet away from you by the explosive device's effect. When you reach certain levels in this class, the damage increases: 3d8 at 7th level, 4d8 at 13th level, and 5d8 at 19th level.

Door Knocker (7th Level Required). You can place this explosive device on a locking mechanism, hinge, or other functional parts of a closed door, window, gate, or chest andlight the fuse. At the end of your current turn, the explosive device explodes.
	After the explosion, the object is easier to break or force open; the DC to break it or pick any locks on it decreases by 10. If this reduces the DC to 0 or less, the object automatically opens. If this explosive device is accidentally triggered by someone other than you trying to use it, it deals 4d6 piercing damage to the creature holding it.

Dragon Fist (7th Level Required). You can throw this explosive device as a ranged weapon attack at a target you can see within 30 feet of you. On a hit, the bomb deals 6d6 fire damage. When you reach certain levels in this class, the damage increases: 8d6 at 13th level and 10d6 at 19th level.

Fire Cyclone (19th Level Required). You throw this explosive device at a point you can see within 30 feet of you. At the end of your current turn, the device erupts into a 20-foot radius sphere of whirling air and fire centered on that point. The sphere remains for 1 minute. Each creature in the sphere when it appears or that ends its turn there must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take 4d6 fire damage on a failed saving throw or half as much damage on a successful one.

Fireworks (7th Level Required). You throw this explosive device at a point you can see within 30 feet of you. The device erupts into brilliant fireworks at the end of your current turn. Each creature within 10 feet of the fireworks must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against your bomb craft DC or become blinded until the end of your next turn.

Flame Thrower (7th Level Required). The flame thrower is an apparatus that requires both hands to use. As a bonus action, you can activate the flame thrower. Once activated, the flame thrower spews a 15-foot cone of fire from the end of the flame thrower's nozzle. At the start of each of your turns, you decide which way the cone faces. Each creature that you hit with the fire or starts its turn in that area must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw, taking 3d6 fire damage on a failed saving throw, or half as much damage on a successful one. When you reach certain levels in this class, the damage increases: 4d6 at 13th level and 5d6 at 19th level.
	An activated flame thrower stops spewing flame after 1 minute or if you use your bonus action to deactivate it. Once it is deactivated, the flame thrower is destroyed even if you did not use it for its entire duration.
	While the flame thrower is activated, your speed becomes 0 and you can't use actions or reactions, and you can only use your bonus action to deactivate the flame thrower.
	If you are hit by a critical hit while the flame throw is activated, it explodes. When it explodes, you must make a DC 10 Dexterity saving throw, taking 6d6 fire damage on a failed save or half as much damage on a successful one.

Glue Bomb (7th Level Required). You can throw this explosive device at a point you can see within 30 feet of you. On impact, a mess of sticky glue fills a 20-foot cube from that point. The glue is difficult terrain. Each creature caught in the glue explosion must make a Dexterity saving throw against your bomb craft DC. On a failed save, the creature takes one level of exhaustion and is restrained as long as it remains in the glue or until it breaks free. A creature restrained by the glue can use its action to make a Strength check against your bomb craft DC. If it succeeds, it is no longer restrained.

Room Clearer (13th Level Required). You can throw this explosive device at a point that you can see within 30 feet of you. The device explodes in a 20-foot radius sphere centered on that point at the end of your current turn. Each creature in the area must make a Dexterity saving throw. A target takes 8d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. The fire spreads around corners. It ignites flammable objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried. When you reach 19th level in this class, the damage increases to 9d6.

Smoke Bomb. You can throw this explosive device at a point that you can see within 30 feet of you. On impact, it emits a 20-foot radius sphere of smoke centered on that point. The sphere spreads around corners and its area is heavily obscured. It lasts for the duration or until a wind of moderate or greater speed (at least 10 miles per hour) disperses it. When you reach certain levels in this class, the radius of the sphere increases: 40 feet at 7th level, 60 feet at 13th level, and 80 feet at 19th level.

Stink Bomb (13th Level Required).You can throw this explosive device at a point that you can see within 30 feet of you. At the end of your current turn, the explosive device emits a 20-foot radius sphere of yellow, nauseating gas centered on that point. The cloud spreads around corners, and its area is heavily obscured. The cloud lingers in the air for 1 minute. Each creature that is completely within the cloud at the start of its turn must make a Constitution saving throw versus your bomb craft DC. On a failed save, the creature spends its action that turn retching and reeling. Creatures that don't need to breathe or are immune to poison automatically succeed on this saving throw. A moderate wind (at least 10 miles per hour) disperses the cloud after 4 rounds. A strong wind (at least 20 miles per hour) disperses it after 1 round.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.18</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Demolitionist Specialization (Demolitionist (HB))</name>
        <text>At 9th level, you gain one of the following features of your choice.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.18</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Specialization: Dead Eye (Demolitionist (HB))</name>
        <text>You gain a +2 bonus to ranged attack rolls you make with your explosive devices.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.18</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Specialization: Gatherer (Demolitionist (HB))</name>
        <text>You have a knack for finding the supplies you need to create explosives. When you are traveling underground, you can forage for supplies for your explosives. Make a DC 10 Intelligence (Nature) check. On a successful roll, you find enough supplies to restock your demolitionists' tools.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.18</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Specialization: Lobber (Demolitionist (HB))</name>
        <text>The range you can throw explosive devices increases by 30 feet.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.18</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Trick Bombs (Demolitionist (HB))</name>
        <text>At 13th level, your quick bombs pack a punch. When you hit a creature with one of your quick bombs, the creature is shaken until the end of its next turn. While shaken, its attacks and ability checks are made with disadvantage and attacks against it are made with advantage.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.18</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Powerful Bombs (Demolitionist (HB))</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you can add your Intelligence modifier to one damage roll of any explosive device you use.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.18</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Roguish Archetype: Gatecrasher (HB) -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Roguish Archetype: Gatecrasher (HB)</name>
        <text>Gatecrashers view themselves as cosmic free agents, totally liberated from the laws and ethics that bind all planes of existence. They claim that they have the power to influence all creatures they meet on their travels as well as the very dynamic forces of magic itself. Consummate tricksters, they move from plane to plane, testing the mettle of the valiant, depravity of the egotistical, and resolve of the powerful.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bonus Proficiencies (Gatecrasher (HB))</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in the Arcana and History skills if you don't have already have it. Your proficiency bonus is doubled for any ability check you make that uses either of those proficiencies.You also learn one additional language of your choice.

Source:	DMDave</text>
        <proficiency>arcana, history</proficiency>
        <modifier category="skill">arcana +%0</modifier>
        <modifier category="skill">history +%0</modifier>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Disabling Strike (Gatecrasher (HB))</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, when you hit a creature with an attack that deals Sneak Attack damage, you can use your bonus action to force the target to make a Charisma saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence modifier). On a failed saving throw, until the end of the target's next turn, the target's movement speed is reduced to 0, and it can't cast spells or use features that allow it to instantly move from one location to another, such as the misty step and teleport spells, or a blink dog's teleport feature.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Warp Sense (Gatecrasher (HB))</name>
        <text>Also at 3rd level, you gain the ability to magically detect nearby portals and gates. As an action, you can open your awareness to detect these effects. Until the end of your next turn, you know the location of any gate or portal within 60 feet of you. You do not know where the portal leads or who created it, only that it exists. You can use this feature a number of times equal to 1 + your Intelligence modifier(minimum of once). When you finish a long rest, you regain all expended uses.
	At 13th level, this sense improves. When you discover a portal using your Warp Sense, you can make an Intelligence check with a DC equal to the portal creator's spellcasting ability (or DC 15 if the portal was not created by a spellcaster). On a success, you know where the portal leads and who created it (if anyone).

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Surelock (Gatecrasher (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 9th level, you can use your action to magically close all magical portals in a 60-foot radius sphere centered on a point that you can see within 120 feet of you. For the duration, all portals in that area that link to different planes of existence close, and spells that transport creatures to another plane of existence—such as plane shift and banishment—fail when cast in this area. Spells and effects that allow a creature to enter the ethereal plane, such as etherealness, also fail (including your own Fade feature, detailed below). However, spells used to move from one point to another on the same plane of existence, such as misty step and teleport, still function. The effect ends in 1 hour or until you use your action or bonus action to end it. Permanent portals temporarily closed by this effect return to the space that they previously occupied.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Fade (Gatecrasher (HB))</name>
        <text>Beginning at 13th level, you can use your action to magically enter the Ethereal Plane, and remain there for 1 hour or until you use your action to return. You return to the plane you originated from in the spot you currently occupy. If you occupy the same spot as a solid object or creature when this happens, you are immediately shunted to the nearest unoccupied space that you can occupy and take force damage equal to twice the number of feet you moved. Other than its duration, this feature works exactly like the etherealness spell. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you complete a long rest.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Fade</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>Gatecrasher (HB)</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Free Jack (Gatecrasher (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 17th level, you can cast the gate, and you do not require the material components when you cast it using this feature. Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for this spell (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence modifier). Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you complete a long rest.

Source:	DMDave</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Free Jack</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>Gatecrasher (HB)</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
