<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Fighter</name>
    <!-- Martial Archetype: Planar Champion (HB) -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Martial Archetype: Planar Champion (HB)</name>
        <text>Guardians of the Beyond, Warriors of Destiny, Blades of the Other—Planar Champions travel through the Cosmos to lend their blade wherever it is needed. Some planar champions intrude on the battles that rage between demons and devils, while another might make its presence known in the planes of elemental energy. Others still focus on balance, turning their attention to the neutral planes.

Source:	DMDave - Fighter Archetype Planar Champion</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bonus Proficiency (Planar Champion (HB))</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in one of the following skills of your choice: Arcana, History, Nature, or Survival.

Source:	DMDave - Fighter Archetype Planar Champion</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Favored Plane (Planar Champion (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you become intimately familiar with a plane of existence that you have traveled to before (speak with your GM about what options are available). You have advantage on Wisdom (Survival) checks made to track creatures from that plane, as well as on Intelligence checks to recall information about them. You also learn one language of your choice that is spoken by creatures from the plane.
	Additionally, when you hit a creature native to your favored plane with a weapon attack, you can add a bonus to your damage roll equal to your proficiency bonus.
	These benefits only work on creatures native to the chosen plane, but not against similar creatures from different realms. For example, if you choose the plane of earth as your favored plane, the benefits only work against earth elementals from the plane of earth and not earth elementals native to the Real.
	You choose one additional favored plane, as well as an associated language, at the 7th and 15th level. As you gain levels, your choices should reflect the types of planes you have traveled to on your adventures.

Source:	DMDave - Fighter Archetype Planar Champion</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>See Invisibility (Planar Champion (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 7th level, you can see invisible creatures and objects as if they were visible, and you can see into the Ethereal Plane. Ethereal creatures and objects appear ghostly and translucent.

Source:	DMDave - Fighter Archetype Planar Champion</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Attack Ethereal (Planar Champion (HB))</name>
        <text>Also at 7th level, you can use your bonus action to imbue your weapon with force energy, allowing you to make attacks against creatures that you can see in the Ethereal Plane as if they were on the same plane of existence as you. This benefit lasts until the end of your current turn.

Source:	DMDave - Fighter Archetype Planar Champion</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Favored Plane (2nd) (Planar Champion (HB))</name>
        <text>You choose one additional favored plane, as well as an associated language, at the 7th and 15th level. As you gain levels, your choices should reflect the types of planes you have traveled to on your adventures.

Source:	DMDave - Fighter Archetype Planar Champion</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Banishing Critical (Planar Champion (HB))</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, when you score a critical hit on an attack roll against a creature native to one of your favored planes, in addition to the damage normal for a critical hit, you can force the creature to make a Charisma saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Charisma modifier). On a failed saving throw, the target is banished. This effect otherwise works the same as the banishment spell.

Source:	DMDave - Fighter Archetype Planar Champion</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Planar Traveler (Planar Champion (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, you learn the plane shift spell. If you use this feature's spell to travel anywhere other than one of your favored planes of existence, you can't use this feature again until you finish a long rest. You do not require material components when you use this feature's spell to travel to your favored planes.

Source:	DMDave - Fighter Archetype Planar Champion</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Favored Plane (3rd) (Planar Champion (HB))</name>
        <text>You choose one additional favored plane, as well as an associated language, at the 7th and 15th level. As you gain levels, your choices should reflect the types of planes you have traveled to on your adventures.

Source:	DMDave - Fighter Archetype Planar Champion</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sunder Portal (Planar Champion (HB))</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you can permanently destroy a portal through sheer force of will. As an action, choose a portal that you can see within 30 feet of you, such a one created by the gate spell, and make a Charisma check with a DC equal to the portal creator's spell save DC (or DC 15 if the portal was created by other means). You have advantage on this check if the portal leads to one of your favored planes. On a successful saving throw, the portal permanently closes. If you use this featureand fail your check, you can't try to close the same portal again until you complete a long rest.

Source:	DMDave - Fighter Archetype Planar Champion</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
