<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Cleric</name>
    <!-- Divine Domain: Baking Domain (HB) -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain: Baking Domain (HB)</name>
        <text>Gods of baking are those who put their faith into flour, yeast, and water, roll it up, stick it in an oven, and share its warm rewards with the rest of the world. Whether it's bread, cakes, rolls, cookies, or even donuts, clerics who follow the tenets of the baking domain sow their magic into food, using it to assist companions and others in need.
	In Wandrossa, the gods who offer baking as domain include the Jade Panda, Avelynn, and even Coram Krulak. In fact, there is a new divine bakery in Port Mathis that offers enchanted cookies for weary patrons.

Domain Spells:
At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared. They do not count towards your limit.

Baking Domain Spells:
Cleric Level | Spells
1st | goodberry, purify food and drink
3rd | calm emotions, heat metal
5th | create food and water, aura of vitality
7th | aura of purity, wall of fire
9th | mass cure wounds, greater restoration

Source:	DMDave - Baking Divine Domain (Mar 2019)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bonus Proficiencies (Baking Domain (HB))</name>
        <text>When you choose this domain at 1st level, you gain proficiency with cook's utensils.

Source:	DMDave - Baking Divine Domain</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Baked Goods (Baking Domain (HB))</name>
        <text>At 1st level, whenever you cast goodberry, you can choose to have four biscuits, cookies, donuts, or other baked goods appear in your hand instead of berries. Eating the baked goods restores 3 hit points instead of the 1 normally provided by goodberry.
	When you reach 5th level in this class, the amount of healing your baked good provides increases by 2 hit points at 5th level (5), 11th level (7), and 17th level (9).

Source:	DMDave - Baking Divine Domain</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Good Smells (Baking Domain (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can use your Channel Divinity to help revitalize your wounded allies during a short rest through baking. If you or any friendly creatures who can smell your baked goods regain hit points at the end of the short rest by spending one or more Hit Dice, each of those creatures gains extra hit points equal to your proficiency bonus.

Source:	DMDave - Baking Divine Domain</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Good Natured Cook (Baking Domain (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, your pleasant demeanor and attitude grant you special abilities:

	• You are immune to being frightened.

	• When taking damage, you have advantage on Constitution saving throws to maintain your concentration on spells.

	• You can cast create food and water without expending a spell slot and the food you create is always delicious. Once you cast create food and water in this way, you can't do so again until you complete a long rest.

Source:	DMDave - Baking Divine Domain</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Potent Spellcasting (Baking Domain (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 8th level, you add your Wisdom modifier to the damage you deal with any cleric cantrip.

Source:	DMDave - Baking Divine Domain</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Saint of the Oven (Baking Domain (HB))</name>
        <text>At 17th level, your skill in the kitchen is rarely contested. Instead of the healing effects offered by the food you create with your Baked Goods feature, you can choose to imbue the baked goods with the effects of one of the following spells instead: enhance ability (choose the ability type when you bake the goods), lesser restoration, protection from energy (choose the damage type when you bake the goods). All four baked goods must have the same effect. After a creature eats the baked good, the spell takes effect as if you had cast it upon it.

Source:	DMDave - Baking Divine Domain</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Divine Domain: Space Domain (HB) -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain: Space Domain (HB)</name>
        <text>GThe multiverse is an endless infinity of worlds, planes, dimensions, and everything in between. As such, the gods have learned that magical means of travel are much more effective and efficient than traditional, physical means. Therefore, having control over space is a necessity for nearly all divine beings.
	Space domain clerics are awarded the instantaneous travel and communication powers of their deities. Capable of traversing great distances, space domain clerics are master tacticians as well as an invaluable asset to those they adventure with.

Domain Spells:
At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared. They do not count towards your limit.

Space Domain Spells:
Cleric Level | Spells
1st | expeditious retreat, jump
3rd | levitate, misty step
5th | haste, sending
7th | banishment, dimension door
9th | contact other plane, teleportation circle

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.11 (Jan 2019)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bonus Cantrip (Space Domain (HB))</name>
        <text>When you choose this domain at 1st level, you gain the message cantrip if you don't already know it and you may cast it as a bonus action on each of your turns.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.11</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Incidental Teleportation (Space Domain (HB))</name>
        <text>At 1st level, when you select this Domain, you can use your action to target an inanimate object not being worn or held by another creature that you can see within 120 feet of you. This object can be no larger than 3 feet on a side and weigh no more than 10 pounds, and its form must be that of a nonmagical object.The object disappears from its present location and reappears into your hand or on the ground in an unoccupied space that you can see within 10 feet of you.
	You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Accelerate (Space Domain (HB))</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you can call upon your god's power to increase the movement speed others around you. As an action, you can use your Channel Divinity to choose a number of creatures within 60 feet of you that you can see equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of one). Each creature can use its bonus action to take the Dash action until the end of its next turn.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Zone Shift (Space Domain (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, when a creature that you can see within 60 feet of you ends its turn, you can use your reaction to teleport the creature 30 feet from its starting position to an unoccupied space you can see, using your Channel Divinity. An unwilling creature that succeeds on a Charisma saving throw versus your spell save DC is unaffected.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Potent Spellcasting (Space Domain (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 8th level, you add your Wisdom modifier to the damage you deal with any cleric cantrip.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Portal Priest (Space Domain (HB))</name>
        <text>At 17th level, your mastery of dimensional travel becomes exceptional. You gain the following benefits:

	• When you cast the haste spell on yourself, you gain a +4 bonus to your AC instead of the +2 normally offered by the spell. In addition, when the spell ends, you can move and take actions as normal.

	• Immediately after you teleport using the misty step spell, you can enable one creature within 60 feet of you to use its reaction to gain the benefits of the misty step spell.

	• When you cast the dimension door spell, the spell's range increases to 1000 feet and you can bring with you a number of willing creatures your size or smaller equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of two).

	• Your casting time for teleportation circle is 1 round instead of 1 minute. In addition, you can create a permanent teleportation circle by casting the spell in the same location every day for one month instead of one year.

	• Whenever you take damage while you are concentrating on the banishment or levitation spells, you make your Constitution saving throw to maintain your concentration with advantage.

Source:	DMDave - EVIL p.11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
  <spell>
    <name>Goodberry</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Baking Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Purify Food and Drink</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Baking Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Calm Emotions</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Baking Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Heat Metal</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Baking Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Create Food and Water</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Baking Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Aura of Vitality</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Baking Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Aura of Purity</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Baking Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Wall of Fire</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Baking Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Mass Cure Wounds</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Baking Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Greater Restoration</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Baking Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Expeditious Retreat</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Space Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Jump</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Space Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Levitate</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Space Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Misty Step</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Space Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Haste</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Space Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Sending</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Space Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Banishment</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Space Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Dimension Door</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Space Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Contact Other Plane</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Space Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Teleportation Circle</name>
    <classes>Cleric (Space Domain (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
</compendium>
