<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Paladin</name>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <counter>
        <name>Stone Defender</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Sacred Oath: Oath of the Stonearm (HB) -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sacred Oath: Oath of the Stonearm (HB)</name>
        <text>When a Castlegrapsian soldier proves his or herself during training, demonstrating immeasurable virtue, they are encouraged to take the March of the Stonearms. The soldier must enter the first mine and seek the dao Gasta-Harrak. From there, he or she must kneel before the dao and offer his or herself to the dao just as the first Khan did two-hundred years prior. If Gasta-Harrak detects the spirit of the Khan within the soldier, they are granted her blessing—an arm of stone. However, if she senses any impurity within the soldier's heart, she commands the earth to devour them.

Tenets of the Stonearm:

Protect the City. Whether as a member of the city's fighting forces or an outbound agent, you must always work in the best interests of the city.

Bring Justice to the Lawless. Those who seek to unravel the foundations of civilization must be stopped.

Fight until the Eighth. Nothing short of death will stop you from your mission.

Respect the Land. The earth is your final home. You must respect and honor for it as you would your own parents.

Oath Spells:
You gain oath spells at the paladin levels listed.

Oath of the Stonearm Spells:
Paladin Level | Spells
3rd | expeditious retreat, shield
5th | enhance ability, enlarge/reduce
9th | beacon of hope, meld into stone
13th | stone shape, stone skin
17th | animate objects, passwall

Source:	DMDave - Paladin: Oath of the Stonearm</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Blessing of the Earth (Oath of the Stonearm (HB))</name>
        <text>As an action, you can grant yourself temporary hit points equal to 5 times your Charisma modifier (minimum of +1).

Source:	DMDave - Paladin: Oath of the Stonearm</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Stone Blade (Oath of the Stonearm (HB))</name>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can imbue one piercing or slashing weapon that you are holding with magic drawn from the earth itself. For 1 minute, the weapon you enchant counts as magical for the purposes of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage. Additionally, a living creature made of flesh that takes damage from your weapon must make a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed saving throw, the creature's flesh starts to harden. The creature takes one level of exhaustion. If a creature takes a sixth level of exhaustion from this feature, instead of dying, it becomes petrified.

Source:	DMDave - Paladin: Oath of the Stonearm</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Aura of Stone (Oath of the Stonearm (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 7th, you exude an aura that weakens your enemies. The aura extends 10 feet from you in all directions, but not through total cover. Each creature of your choice within this aura has disadvantage on its Constitution saving throws.
	When you reach 18th level in this class, the range of the aura increases to 30 feet.

Source:	DMDave - Paladin: Oath of the Stonearm</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Stone Defender (Oath of the Stonearm (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, you no longer have a need for mundane armor or shields. While you are not wearing armor or carrying a shield, your AC becomes 19. In addition, you can use this feature to cast the stoneskin spell without expending a spell slot. When you do, you must target yourself. After you use this feature to cast the spell, you can't do so again until you complete a long rest.

Source:	DMDave - Paladin: Oath of the Stonearm</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Stone Defender</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>Oath of the Stonearm (HB)</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Champion of Grasta-Harrak (Oath of the Stonearm (HB))</name>
        <text>At 20th level, you are an avatar for the dao symbiote, which gives you the following benefits:

	• When you use your Stone Defender to cast stoneskin on yourself, the duration becomes 8 hours and no longer requires concentration.

	• When you hit a creature using your stone blade feature, the creature takes two levels of exhaustion on a failed saving throw instead of one.

Source:	DMDave - Paladin: Oath of the Stonearm</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
  <spell>
    <name>Expeditious Retreat</name>
    <classes>Paladin (Stonearm (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Shield</name>
    <classes>Paladin (Stonearm (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Enhance Ability</name>
    <classes>Paladin (Stonearm (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Enlarge/Reduce</name>
    <classes>Paladin (Stonearm (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Beacon of Hope</name>
    <classes>Paladin (Stonearm (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Meld Into Stone</name>
    <classes>Paladin (Stonearm (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Stone Shape</name>
    <classes>Paladin (Stonearm (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Stoneskin</name>
    <classes>Paladin (Stonearm (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Animate Objects</name>
    <classes>Paladin (Stonearm (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Passwall</name>
    <classes>Paladin (Stonearm (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
</compendium>
