<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <background>
    <name>Knight Of Solamnia (UA)</name>
    <proficiency>Athletics, Survival</proficiency>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>You have trained to be a valorous warrior known as a Knight of Solamnia. Strict rules guide your every action, and you work to uphold them as you strive to defend the weak and oppose evil. Your honor is as important to you as your life.

	• Skill Proficiencies: Athletics, Survival.
	• Tool Proficiencies: One type of musical instrument.
	• Languages: Two of your choice.
	• Equipment: An insignia of rank, a deck of cards, a set of common clothes, and a pouch containing 10 gp.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 2</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Squire Of Solamnia</name>
      <text>You gain the Squire of Solamnia feat (presented later in this document).
	In addition, the Knights of Solamnia provide you free, modest lodging and food at any of their fortresses or encampments.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
      <text>Adventurers who dedicate themselves to protecting the innocent and upholding honorable virtues are welcomed among the Knights of Solamnia. The Knight of Solamnia Personality Traits table suggests various traits you might adopt for your character.

d6 | Personality Trait
1 | I pledge my sword to the greater good. If I must perish in pursuit of that good, so be it.
2 | My comrades-in-arms are my family. I'll do whatever it takes to keep them safe.
3 | The protection of innocent people comes first. All other concerns come second.
4 | I joined the knights for the free meals, but their lessons grew on me over time.
5 | I wish my deeds to become the stuff of legends—just like those of the knighthood's heroic founders.
6 | A dishonorable act drove me to become a knight. I have acted with honor ever since.</text>
      <roll description="Personality Trait">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Knight of Solamnia Trinkets</name>
      <text>When you make your character, you may roll once on the Knight of Solamnia Trinkets table, instead of on the Trinkets table in the Player's Handbook, for your starting trinket.

Knight of Solamnia Trinkets:
d6 | Trinket
1 | A flat silver disk you record your heroics upon
2 | A piece of a fallen knight's armor
3 | A pendant featuring a crown, a rose, a sword, or combination of all three
4 | The pommel of your mentor's sword
5 | A meaningful favor from someone you defended—perhaps a handkerchief or glove
6 | A brass locket with a sketch of a silver dragon inside</text>
      <roll description="Trinket">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
  <background>
    <name>Mage Of High Sorcery (UA)</name>
    <proficiency>Arcana, History</proficiency>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Your talent for magic came to the attention of the Mages of High Sorcery, an organization of spellcasters that study magic and prevent its misuse. You've trained among the Mages, but whether or not you'll face the dangerous tests required to become a true member of the group remains to be determined. Your passion for studying magic has likely already predisposed you toward one of the organization's three orders: the benevolent Order of the White Robes, the balance-pursuing Order of the Red Robes, or the ruthless Order of the Black Robes.
	In the world of Krynn, many refer to the Mages of High Sorcery as the Wizards of High Sorcery. The organization accepts more than wizards, though, with sorcerers, warlocks, and other spellcasters included among their ranks.

	• Skill Proficiencies: Arcana, History.
	• Languages: Two of your choice.
	• Equipment: A bottle of colored ink, an ink pen, a set of common clothes, and a pouch containing 10 gp.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 3</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Initiate Of High Sorcery</name>
      <text>You gain the Initiate of High Sorcery feat (presented later in this document).
	In addition, the Mages of High Sorcery provide you with free, modest lodging and food indefinitely at any occupied Tower of High Sorcery and for one night at the home of an organization member.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
      <text>The study of magic drives the Mages of High Sorcery. Consider which of the group's three orders you aspire to join. The Mage of High Sorcery Personality Traits table suggests traits you might adopt for your character.

d6 | Personality Trait
1 | I wish to use my knowledge of magic to better people's lives.
2 | My study of magic might reveal all manner of secrets.
3 | Magic is a means to power, and I will use it to pursue my ambitions.
4 | I learned magic so I'd be able to protect those I care about.
5 | I use my magic to maintain the balance between all things.
6 | Whether in the past, present, or future, I will be the greatest mage ever known.</text>
      <roll description="Personality Trait">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Mage of High Sorcery Trinkets</name>
      <text>When you make your character, you may roll once on the Mage of High Sorcery Trinkets table, instead of on the Trinkets table in the Player's Handbook, for your starting trinket.

Mage of High Sorcery Trinkets:
d6 | Trinket
1 | An unopened letter from your first teacher
2 | A broken wand made of black, red, or white wood
3 | A scroll bearing an incomprehensible formula
4 | A purposeless device covered in colored stones that can fold into various enigmatic shapes
5 | A pouch or spell book emblazoned with the triple moon symbol of the Mages of High Sorcery
6 | A lens through which you can see Krynn's invisible black moon, Nuitari</text>
      <roll description="Trinket">1d6</roll>
    </trait>
  </background>
  <feat>
    <name>Adept Of The Black Robes (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Initiate of High Sorcery (Nuitari) Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>You chose the moon Nuitari to influence your magic, and your ambition and loyalty to the Order of the Black Robes has been recognized, granting you these benefits:

Ambitious Magic. You learn one 2nd-level spell of your choice. The 2nd-level spell must be from the enchantment or necromancy school of magic. You can cast this feat's 2nd-level spell without a spell slot, and you must finish a long rest before you can cast it in this way again. You can also cast this spell using spell slots you have of the appropriate level. The spell's spellcasting ability is the one chosen when you gained the Initiate of High Sorcery feat.

Life Channel. You can channel your lifeforce into the power of your magic. When a creature you can see within 60 feet of you fails a saving throw against a spell that deals damage that you cast, you can expend a number of Hit Dice equal to the level of the spell. Roll the expended Hit Dice and add them together. The damage that the creature takes increases by an amount equal to that total.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 4</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Adept Of The Red Robes (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Initiate of High Sorcery (Lunitari) Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>You chose the moon Lunitari to influence your magic, and your dedication to maintaining the balance between all things has been recognized by the Order of the Red Robes, granting you these benefits:

Insightful Magic. You learn one 2nd-level spell of your choice. The 2nd-level spell must be from the illusion or transmutation school of magic. You can cast this feat's 2nd-level spell without a spell slot, and you must finish a long rest before you can cast it in this way again. You can also cast this spell using spell slots you have of the appropriate level. The spell's spellcasting ability is the one chosen when you gained the Initiate of High Sorcery feat.

Magical Balance. When you make an attack roll or an ability check and roll a 9 or lower on the d20, you can balance fate and treat the roll as a 10. You can balance fate in this way a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 4</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Adept Of The White Robes (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Initiate of High Sorcery (Solinari) Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>You chose the moon Solinari to influence your magic, and your oath to use magic to make the world a better place has been recognized by the Order of the White Robes, granting you these benefits: Protective

Protective Magic. You learn one 2nd-level spell of your choice. The 2nd-level spell must be from the abjuration or divination school of magic. You can cast this feat's 2nd-level spell without a spell slot, and you must finish a long rest before you can cast it in this way again. You can also cast this spell using spell slots you have of the appropriate level. The spell's spellcasting ability is the one chosen when you gained the Initiate of High Sorcery feat.

Protective Ward. When you or a creature you can see within 30 feet of you takes damage, you can use your reaction to expend a spell slot and weave protective magic around the target. Roll a number of d6s equal to the level of the spell slot expended and reduce the damage the target takes by the total rolled on those dice + your spellcasting ability modifier.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 4</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Divinely Favored (UA)</name>
    <text>A god has chosen you to carry a spark of their divine power.
	You learn one cantrip of your choice from the cleric spell list and one 1st-level spell based on the alignment of your character, as specified in the Alignment Spells table below. You also learn the augury spell.
	You can cast the chosen 1st-level spell and the augury spell without a spell slot, and you must finish a long rest before you can cast either of these spells in this way again. You can also cast these spells using spell slots you have of the appropriate level.
	Your spellcasting ability for this feat's spells is Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma (choose when you select this feat).

Alignment Spells:
Alignment | 1st-level Spell
Evil | Choose one 1st-level warlock spell.
Good | Choose one 1st-level cleric spell.
Neutral | Choose one 1st-level druid spell.

In addition, you can use a holy symbol as a spellcasting focus for any spell you cast that uses the spellcasting ability you choose when you select this feat.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 4</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Initiate Of High Sorcery (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Sorcerer or Wizard Class or Mage of High Sorcery Background</prerequisite>
    <text>You've received training from magic-users affiliated with the Mages of High Sorcery.
	Choose one of the three moons of Krynn to influence your magic: the black moon, Nuitari; the red moon, Lunitari; or the white moon Solinari. You learn one cantrip of your choice from the wizard spell list and two 1st-level spells based on the moon you choose, as specified in the Lunar Spells table.
	You can cast each of the chosen 1st-level spells without a spell slot, and you must finish a long rest before you can cast it in this way again. You can also cast the spells using any spell slots you have.
	Your spellcasting ability for this feat's spells is Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma (choose when you select this feat).

Lunar Spells:
Moon | 1st-level Spell
Nuitari | Choose two from dissonant whispers, false life, hex, and ray of sickness
Lunitari | Choose two from color spray, disguise self, feather fall, and longstrider
Solinari | Choose two from comprehend languages, detect evil and good, protection from evil and good, and shield

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 4</text>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Knight Of The Crown (UA) (Strength)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Squire of Solamnia Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>You are a Knight of Solamnia aligned with the Order of the Crown, a group that extols the virtues of cooperation, loyalty, and obedience. You excel in group combat and gain these benefits:

Ability Score Increase. Increase your Strength or Dexterity score by 1, to a maximum of 20.

Crown Maneuvers. You learn the Distracting Strike or the Goading Attack maneuver from the Battle Master subclass of the fighter in the Player's Handbook (choose the maneuver when you gain this feat). If the maneuver requires a saving throw, the save's DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength or Dexterity modifier (your choice). Whenever you finish a long rest, you can replace the maneuver you learned from this feat with the other maneuver offered by it.

Superiority Dice. You gain two superiority dice, which you add to the dice you have from the Squire of Solamnia feat. All the dice are now d8s.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 5</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">strength +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Knight Of The Crown (UA) (Dexterity)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Squire of Solamnia Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>You are a Knight of Solamnia aligned with the Order of the Crown, a group that extols the virtues of cooperation, loyalty, and obedience. You excel in group combat and gain these benefits:

Ability Score Increase. Increase your Strength or Dexterity score by 1, to a maximum of 20.

Crown Maneuvers. You learn the Distracting Strike or the Goading Attack maneuver from the Battle Master subclass of the fighter in the Player's Handbook (choose the maneuver when you gain this feat). If the maneuver requires a saving throw, the save's DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength or Dexterity modifier (your choice). Whenever you finish a long rest, you can replace the maneuver you learned from this feat with the other maneuver offered by it.

Superiority Dice. You gain two superiority dice, which you add to the dice you have from the Squire of Solamnia feat. All the dice are now d8s.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 5</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">dexterity +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Knight Of The Sword (UA) (Intelligence)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Squire of Solamnia Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>You are a Knight of Solamnia aligned with the Order of the Sword, a group devoted to heroism and courage. Bravery steels your spirit, granting you these benefits:

Ability Score Increase. Increase your Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20.

Sword Maneuvers. You learn the Maneuvering Attack or the Menacing Attack maneuver from the Battle Master subclass of the fighter in the Player's Handbook (choose the maneuver when you gain this feat). If the maneuver requires a saving throw, the save's DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength or Dexterity modifier (your choice). Whenever you finish a long rest, you can replace the maneuver you learned from this feat with the other maneuver offered by it.

Superiority Dice. You gain two superiority dice, which you add to the dice you have from the Squire of Solamnia feat. All the dice are now d8s.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 5</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">intelligence +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Knight Of The Sword (UA) (Wisdom)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Squire of Solamnia Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>You are a Knight of Solamnia aligned with the Order of the Sword, a group devoted to heroism and courage. Bravery steels your spirit, granting you these benefits:

Ability Score Increase. Increase your Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20.

Sword Maneuvers. You learn the Maneuvering Attack or the Menacing Attack maneuver from the Battle Master subclass of the fighter in the Player's Handbook (choose the maneuver when you gain this feat). If the maneuver requires a saving throw, the save's DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength or Dexterity modifier (your choice). Whenever you finish a long rest, you can replace the maneuver you learned from this feat with the other maneuver offered by it.

Superiority Dice. You gain two superiority dice, which you add to the dice you have from the Squire of Solamnia feat. All the dice are now d8s.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 5</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">wisdom +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Knight Of The Sword (UA) (Charisma)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Squire of Solamnia Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>You are a Knight of Solamnia aligned with the Order of the Sword, a group devoted to heroism and courage. Bravery steels your spirit, granting you these benefits:

Ability Score Increase. Increase your Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20.

Sword Maneuvers. You learn the Maneuvering Attack or the Menacing Attack maneuver from the Battle Master subclass of the fighter in the Player's Handbook (choose the maneuver when you gain this feat). If the maneuver requires a saving throw, the save's DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength or Dexterity modifier (your choice). Whenever you finish a long rest, you can replace the maneuver you learned from this feat with the other maneuver offered by it.

Superiority Dice. You gain two superiority dice, which you add to the dice you have from the Squire of Solamnia feat. All the dice are now d8s.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 5</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">charisma +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Knight Of The Rose (UA) (Constitution)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Squire of Solamnia Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>You are a Knight of Solamnia aligned with the Order of the Rose, a group known for leadership, justice, and wisdom. Your resolve grants you these benefits:

Ability Score Increase. Increase your Constitution or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20.

Rose Maneuvers. You learn the Commander's Strike or Rally maneuver from the Battle Master subclass of the fighter in the Player's Handbook (choose the maneuver when you gain this feat). Whenever you finish a long rest, you can replace the maneuver you learned from this feat with the other maneuver offered by it.

Superiority Dice. You gain two superiority dice, which you add to the dice you have from the Squire of Solamnia feat. All the dice are now d8s.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 5</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">constitution +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Knight Of The Rose (UA) (Charisma)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Squire of Solamnia Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>You are a Knight of Solamnia aligned with the Order of the Rose, a group known for leadership, justice, and wisdom. Your resolve grants you these benefits:

Ability Score Increase. Increase your Constitution or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20.

Rose Maneuvers. You learn the Commander's Strike or Rally maneuver from the Battle Master subclass of the fighter in the Player's Handbook (choose the maneuver when you gain this feat). Whenever you finish a long rest, you can replace the maneuver you learned from this feat with the other maneuver offered by it.

Superiority Dice. You gain two superiority dice, which you add to the dice you have from the Squire of Solamnia feat. All the dice are now d8s.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 5</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">charisma +1</modifier>
  </feat>
  <feat>
    <name>Squire Of Solamnia (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Fighter or Paladin Class or Knight of Solamnia Background</prerequisite>
    <text>Your training in the ways of the Knights of Solamnia grants you these benefits:

Mount Up. Mounting or dismounting costs you only 5 feet of movement.

Squire Maneuvers. You learn the Lunging Attack, Precision Attack, or Pushing Attack maneuver from the Battle Master subclass of the fighter in the Player's Handbook (choose the maneuver when you gain this feat). If the maneuver requires a saving throw, the save's DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength or Dexterity modifier (your choice). Whenever you finish a long rest, you can replace the maneuver you learned from this feat with another one from the list above.

Superiority Dice. You gain a number of superiority dice equal to your proficiency bonus. These dice are d6s, and you can use them only with the maneuver you gain from this feat and with any maneuvers you gain from feats that have this feat as a prerequisite. A superiority die is expended when you use it, and you regain all expended superiority dice when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Heroes of Krynn Revisited p. 5</text>
  </feat>
</compendium>
