<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <race>
    <name>Dragonborn, Chromatic (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>The dragonborn walk proudly through a world that greets them with fearful incomprehension. Shaped by the dragons themselves, dragonborn originally hatched from dragon eggs as a unique race, combining the best attributes of dragons and humanoids.

Dragonborn with chromatic ancestry claim the raw elemental power of the chromatic dragons. The vibrant colors of the chromatics—black, blue, green, red, and white—gleam in their scaled skin and in the deadly energy of their breath weapons. Theirs is the raw elemental fury of the volcano, of biting arctic winds, of raging lightning storms; theirs also is the subtle whisper of swamp and forest, corrosive and toxic.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 78: Draconic Options</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different one by 1, or you increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Young dragonborn grow quickly. They walk hours after hatching, attain the size and development of a 10-year-old human child by the age of 3, and reach adulthood by 15. They live to be around 80.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Dragonborn tend towards extremes, making a conscious choice for one side or the other in the cosmic war between Good and Evil (represented by Bahamut and Tiamat, respectively). More side with Bahamut than Tiamat (whose non-dragon followers are mostly kobolds), but villainous dragonborn can be quite terrible indeed. Some rare few choose to devote themselves to lesser dragon deities, such as Chronepsis (Neutral), and fewer still choose to worship Io, the Ninefold Dragon, who is all alignments at once.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Dragonborn are taller and heavier than humans, standing well over 6 feet tall and averaging almost 250 pounds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 5 feet + 6 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 175 + (2d6 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Chromatic Ancestry</name>
      <text>You trace your ancestry to a chromatic dragon, granting you a special magical affinity. Choose one type of dragon from the Chromatic Ancestry table. This determines the damage type for your other traits as shown in the table.

Chromatic Ancestry:
Dragon | Damage Type
Black | Acid
Blue | Lightning
Green | Poison
Red | Fire
White | Cold</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Breath Weapon</name>
      <text>When you take the Attack action, you can replace one of your attacks with an exhalation of a magical energy in a 30-foot line that is 5 feet wide. Each creature in the area must make a Dexterity saving throw against a DC equal to 8 + your Constitution modifier + your proficiency bonus. A creature takes 2d8 damage of the type associated with your Chromatic Ancestry on a failed save, and half as much damage on a successful one. This damage increases by 1d8 when you reach 5th level (3d8), 11th level (4d8), and 17th level (5d8).
	You can use this trait a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
      <roll description="Chromatic Damage" level="0">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Chromatic Damage" level="5">3d8</roll>
      <roll description="Chromatic Damage" level="11">4d8</roll>
      <roll description="Chromatic Damage" level="17">5d8</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Draconic Resistance</name>
      <text>You have resistance to the damage type associated with your Chromatic Ancestry.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Chromatic Warding</name>
      <text>Starting at 3rd level, as an action, you can channel your draconic energies to protect yourself. For 10 minutes, you become immune to the damage type associated with your Chromatic Ancestry.
	Once you use this trait, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Draconic. Draconic is thought to be one of the oldest languages and is often used in the study of magic. The language sounds harsh to most other creatures and includes numerous hard consonants and sibilants.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Dragonborn, Metallic (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>The dragonborn walk proudly through a world that greets them with fearful incomprehension. Shaped by the dragons themselves, dragonborn originally hatched from dragon eggs as a unique race, combining the best attributes of dragons and humanoids.

Dragonborn with metallic ancestry lay claim to the unflinching tenacity of the metallic dragons—brass, bronze, copper, gold, and silver—whose hues glint in their scales. Theirs is the fire of hearth and forge, the cold of high mountain air, the spark of inspiration, and the scouring touch of acid that cleanses and purifies.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 78: Draconic Options</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different one by 1, or you increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Young dragonborn grow quickly. They walk hours after hatching, attain the size and development of a 10-year-old human child by the age of 3, and reach adulthood by 15. They live to be around 80.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Dragonborn tend towards extremes, making a conscious choice for one side or the other in the cosmic war between Good and Evil (represented by Bahamut and Tiamat, respectively). More side with Bahamut than Tiamat (whose non-dragon followers are mostly kobolds), but villainous dragonborn can be quite terrible indeed. Some rare few choose to devote themselves to lesser dragon deities, such as Chronepsis (Neutral), and fewer still choose to worship Io, the Ninefold Dragon, who is all alignments at once.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Dragonborn are taller and heavier than humans, standing well over 6 feet tall and averaging almost 250 pounds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 5 feet + 6 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 175 + (2d6 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Metallic Ancestry</name>
      <text>You trace your ancestry to a metallic dragon, granting you a special magical affinity. Choose one type of dragon from the Metallic Ancestry table. This determines the damage type for your other traits as shown in the table.

Metalli Ancestry:
Dragon | Damage Type
Brass | Fire
Bronze | Lightning
Copper | Acid
Gold | Fire
Silver | Cold</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Breath Weapon</name>
      <text>When you take the Attack action, you can replace one of your attacks with an exhalation of a magical energy in a 15-foot cone. Each creature in the area must make a Dexterity saving throw against a DC equal to 8 + your Constitution modifier + your proficiency bonus. A creature takes 2d8 damage of the type associated with your Metallic Ancestry on a failed save, and half as much damage on a successful one. This damage increases by 1d8 when you reach 5th level (3d8), 11th level (4d8), and 17th level (5d8).
	You can use this trait a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
      <roll description="Damage" level="0">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Damage" level="5">3d8</roll>
      <roll description="Damage" level="11">4d8</roll>
      <roll description="Damage" level="17">5d8</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Draconic Resistance</name>
      <text>You have resistance to the damage type associated with your Metallic Ancestry.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Metallic Breath Weapon</name>
      <text>At 3rd level you gain a second breath weapon. When you take the Attack action, you can replace one of your attacks with an exhalation of a magical gas in a 15-foot cone. The save DC for this breath is 8 + your Constitution modifier + your proficiency bonus. When you use this ability, choose one:

	• Each creature in the area must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be pushed 20 feet away from you and be knocked prone.

	• Each creature in the area must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or become incapacitated until the start of your next turn.

Once you use your Metallic Breath Weapon, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Draconic. Draconic is thought to be one of the oldest languages and is often used in the study of magic. The language sounds harsh to most other creatures and includes numerous hard consonants and sibilants.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Dragonborn, Gem (UA)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>The dragonborn walk proudly through a world that greets them with fearful incomprehension. Shaped by the dragons themselves, dragonborn originally hatched from dragon eggs as a unique race, combining the best attributes of dragons and humanoids.

Dragonborn with gem ancestry partake of the heritage of all gem dragons, who claim to be heirs of the ruby dragon, Sardior—the firstborn of all creation, made by Bahamut and Tiamat in the first days of the First World. The colors and mysterious powers of the gem dragons—amethyst, crystal, emerald, sapphire, and topaz—gleam in their scaled skin and course through their veins. Theirs are the wonders of the mind, the force of will, the brilliant light of insight, the resounding echo of discovery, and the desiccation of despair.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana 78: Draconic Options</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different one by 1, or you increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Young dragonborn grow quickly. They walk hours after hatching, attain the size and development of a 10-year-old human child by the age of 3, and reach adulthood by 15. They live to be around 80.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Dragonborn tend towards extremes, making a conscious choice for one side or the other in the cosmic war between Good and Evil (represented by Bahamut and Tiamat, respectively). More side with Bahamut than Tiamat (whose non-dragon followers are mostly kobolds), but villainous dragonborn can be quite terrible indeed. Some rare few choose to devote themselves to lesser dragon deities, such as Chronepsis (Neutral), and fewer still choose to worship Io, the Ninefold Dragon, who is all alignments at once.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Dragonborn are taller and heavier than humans, standing well over 6 feet tall and averaging almost 250 pounds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 5 feet + 6 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 175 + (2d6 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Gem Ancestry</name>
      <text>You trace your ancestry to a gem dragon, granting you a special magical affinity. Choose one type of dragon from the Gem Ancestry table. This determines the damage type for your other traits as shown in the table.

Gem Ancestry:
Dragon | Damage Type
Amethyst | Force
Crystal | Radiant
Emerald | Psychic
Sapphire | Thunder
Topaz | Necrotic</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Breath Weapon</name>
      <text>When you take the Attack action, you can replace one of your attacks with an exhalation of a magical energy in a 15-foot cone. Each creature in the area must make a Dexterity saving throw against a DC equal to 8 + your Constitution modifier + your proficiency bonus. A creature takes 2d8 damage of the type associated with your Gem Ancestry on a failed save, and half as much damage on a successful one. This damage increases by 1d8 when you reach 5th level (3d8), 11th level (4d8), and 17th level (5d8).
	You can use this trait a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
      <roll description="Damage" level="0">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Damage" level="5">3d8</roll>
      <roll description="Damage" level="11">4d8</roll>
      <roll description="Damage" level="17">5d8</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Draconic Resistance</name>
      <text>You have resistance to the damage type associated with your Gem Ancestry.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Psionic Mind</name>
      <text>You can telepathically speak to any creature you can see within 30 feet of you. You don't need to share a language with the creature, but the creature must be able to understand at least one language. Your communication doesn't give the creature the ability to respond to you telepathically.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Gem Flight</name>
      <text>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your bonus action to temporarily summon an array of spectral gems that match your Gem Ancestry in the shape of wings that last for 1 minute. For the duration, you gain a flying speed equal to your walking speed and can hover. Once you use this trait, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Draconic. Draconic is thought to be one of the oldest languages and is often used in the study of magic. The language sounds harsh to most other creatures and includes numerous hard consonants and sibilants.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Kobold (UA)</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Some of the smallest draconic creatures to walk the planes, kobolds display their draconic ancestry in the glint of their scales and in their roars. Legends tell of the first kobolds emerging from the Underdark near the lairs of the earliest dragons. In some lands, kobolds serve chromatic or metallic dragons—even worshiping them as divine beings. In other places, kobolds know too well how dangerous those dragons can be and help others defend against draconic destruction.
	Whatever their relationship to dragons, kobold scales tend to be rust colored, although the occasional kobold sports scale color more akin to that of a chromatic or a metallic dragon. The roar of a kobold can express a range of emotion: anger, resolve, elation, fear, and more. Regardless of the emotion the kobold expresses, the roar resonates with draconic power.

Source:	Volo's Guide to Monsters p. 119,
		Unearthed Arcana 78: Draconic Options</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ability Score Increases</name>
      <text>Increase one ability score by 2 and increase a different one by 1, or you increase three different scores by 1.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Kobolds reach adulthood at age 6 and can live up to 120 years but rarely do so.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Kobolds are fundamentally selfish, making them evil, but their reliance on the strength of their group makes them trend toward law.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Kobolds are between 2 and 3 feet tall and weigh between 25 and 35 pounds. Your size is Small.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Draconic Legacy</name>
      <text>The kobold connection to dragons can manifest in unpredictable ways in an individual kobold. Choose one of the following legacy options when you select this race:

	• You have advantage on saving throws to avoid or end the frightened condition on yourself.

	• You know one cantrip of your choice from the sorcerer spell list. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for that cantrip (choose when you select this race).

	• You can make unarmed strikes with your tail. When you hit with it, the strike deals 1d6 + your Strength modifier bludgeoning damage, instead of the bludgeoning damage normal for an unarmed strike.</text>
      <roll description="Bludgeoning Damage">1d6+%1</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Draconic Roar</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, you let out a draconic roar at your enemies within 10 feet of you. Until the end of your next turn, you and your allies have advantage on attack rolls against any of those enemies who could hear the roar. You can use this trait a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Draconic.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
</compendium>
