<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <item>
    <name>Elemental Shroom, Boom</name>
    <detail>flora, dark blue mushroom, uncommon</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <value>50.0</value>
    <text>Power rumbles within this dark blue mushroom. When you consume a Boom Shroom, you suffer 1d4 thunder damage but gain resistance to thunder damage for 24 hours.

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
    <roll description="Thunder Damage">1d4</roll>
  </item>
  <!-- Elemental Shroom, Boom (Thunder) -->
  <item>
    <name>Elemental Shroom, Corrosive</name>
    <detail>flora, dark purple mushroom, uncommon</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <value>50.0</value>
    <text>A sizzling puddle of acid pools around this dark purple mushroom. When you consume a Corrosive Shroom, you suffer 1d4 acid damage but gain resistance to acid damage for 24 hours.

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
    <roll description="Acid Damage">1d4</roll>
  </item>
  <!-- Elemental Shroom, Corrosive (Acid) -->
  <item>
    <name>Elemental Shroom, Frost</name>
    <detail>flora, freezing mushroom, uncommon</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <value>50.0</value>
    <text>A thin sheen of ice covers this freezing mushroom. When you consume a Frost Shroom, you suffer 1d4 cold damage but gain resistance to cold damage for 24 hours.

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
    <roll description="Cold Damage">1d4</roll>
  </item>
  <!-- Elemental Shroom, Frost (Cold) -->
  <item>
    <name>Elemental Shroom, Magma</name>
    <detail>flora, fiery mushroom, uncommon</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <value>50.0</value>
    <text>Scalding lava drips from the cap of this fiery mushroom. When you consume a Magma Shroom, you suffer 1d4 fire damage but gain resistance to fire damage for 24 hours.

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
    <roll description="Fire Damage">1d4</roll>
  </item>
  <!-- Elemental Shroom, Magma (Fire) -->
  <item>
    <name>Elemental Shroom, Spark</name>
    <detail>flora, yellow mushroom, uncommon</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <value>50.0</value>
    <text>Electricity dances along this yellow mushroom. When you consume a Spark Shroom, you suffer 1d4 lightning damage but gain resistance to lightning damage for 24 hours.

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
    <roll description="Lightning Damage">1d4</roll>
  </item>
  <!-- Elemental Shroom, Spark (Lightning) -->
  <item>
    <name>Elemental Shroom, Toxic</name>
    <detail>flora, sickly green mushroom, uncommon</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <value>50.0</value>
    <text>Venom drips from this sickly green mushroom. When you consume a Toxic Shroom, you suffer 1d4 poison damage but gain resistance to poison damage for 24 hours.

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
    <roll description="Poison Damage">1d4</roll>
  </item>
  <!-- Elemental Shroom, Toxic (Poison) -->
  <item>
    <name>Luum Shroom</name>
    <detail>flora, translucent mushroom, uncommon</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <value>20.0</value>
    <text>This translucent mushroom dances with internal lights. You can use an action to shake the Luum Shroom, intensifying the light inside. Once activated in this way, the Luum Shroom sheds bright golden light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet for one hour.
	Eating the Luum Shroom instead causes the light to emit from your open mouth for 1d4 hours.

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
    <roll description="Hours">1d4</roll>
  </item>
  <!-- Luum Shroom -->
  <item>
    <name>Misty Visions Shroom</name>
    <detail>flora, lavender capped mushroom, rare</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <value>100.0</value>
    <text>Delicate mist swirls beneath the lavender cap of this mushroom. When you eat this magical mushroom, you immediately fall into a trance. While in this trance, there is a 30 percent chance that you see a glimpse of the future, and a 70 percent chance that you have an upsetting hallucination.
	If the character experiences a vision of the future, the player may ask the GM a single question concerning a specific goal, event, or activity to occur within 7 days. The character then experiences a vision of the future concerning this goal, event, or activity by way of response.
	If the character experiences a hallucination, the vivid waking nightmare drives the character to be afflicted with a random form of long-term madness (see "Madness" in chapter 8 of the DMG). This madness only lasts for 1d6 hours.

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
    <roll description="Hours">1d6</roll>
  </item>
  <!-- Misty Visions Shroom -->
  <item>
    <name>Purifying Shroom</name>
    <detail>flora, small silky azure mushrooms, uncommon</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <value>20.0</value>
    <text>These small, silky azure mushrooms grow in clumps around lakes and ponds. When ground up and sprinkled into food or water, the mushroom dissolves and purifies the consumable, rendering it free of poison and disease.

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
  </item>
  <!-- Purifying Shroom -->
  <item>
    <name>Twin Mind Shroom, Baby</name>
    <detail>flora, indigo mushroom, uncommon</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <value>50.0</value>
    <text>Two indigo mushroom caps grow from a single stalk. When two creatures both eat one of the mushroom caps within one minute of each other, they develop a telepathic connection as if linked by a telepathy spell. The duration and range of the creatures' shared telepathy varies based on the rarity, or age, of the mushroom. 

Baby: Two creatures can communicate telepathically for up to 10 minutes within 120 feet of each other.

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
  </item>
  <!-- Twin Mind Shroom, Baby -->
  <item>
    <name>Twin Mind Shroom, Mature</name>
    <detail>flora, indigo mushroom, rare</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <value>100.0</value>
    <text>Two indigo mushroom caps grow from a single stalk. When two creatures both eat one of the mushroom caps within one minute of each other, they develop a telepathic connection as if linked by a telepathy spell. The duration and range of the creatures' shared telepathy varies based on the rarity, or age, of the mushroom. 

Mature: Two creatures can communicate telepathically for up to one hour within one mile of each other.

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
  </item>
  <!-- Twin Mind Shroom, Mature -->
  <item>
    <name>Twin Mind Shroom, Aged</name>
    <detail>flora, indigo mushroom, very rare</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <value>200.0</value>
    <text>Two indigo mushroom caps grow from a single stalk. When two creatures both eat one of the mushroom caps within one minute of each other, they develop a telepathic connection as if linked by a telepathy spell. The duration and range of the creatures' shared telepathy varies based on the rarity, or age, of the mushroom. 

Aged: Two creatures can communicate telepathically for up to 24 hours, so long as they remain on the same plane of existence.

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
  </item>
  <!-- Twin Mind Shroom, Aged -->
  <item>
    <name>Wide-Eyed Shroom</name>
    <detail>flora, color-shifting mushroom, very rare</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <value>200.0</value>
    <text>This magical mushroom's color shifts between a silvery gray and a golden amber when viewed from different angles. When you eat this mushroom, your pupils dilate to a near-impossible size. For 1d4 hours you see the world around you as it truly is, as if under the effects of a True Seeing spell.
	Viewing the world through this lens can be a jarring experience, especially for first timers. For every hour that a character remains under the effects of the Wide-Eyed Shroom, they must make a DC 10 Wisdom Saving throw. At the end of the duration, a character who failed any of their saving throws is afflicted by a short-term madness (see "Madness" in chapter 8 of the DMG).

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
    <roll description="Hours">1d4</roll>
  </item>
  <!-- Wide-Eyed Shroom -->
  <item>
    <name>Zoom Shroom</name>
    <detail>flora, thin yellow and black mushroom, rare</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight>0.5</weight>
    <text>This thin yellow and black mushroom trembles with energy. When you eat a Zoom Shroom, your body begins to vibrate and the world around you appears to slow. Your speed is doubled, you gain advantage on Dexterity saving throws, and any creature that makes an opportunity attack against you has disadvantage on the attack roll for the next 1 minute.

Source:	Gloom's Shrooms v1.1 (Homebrew)</text>
  </item>
  <!-- Zoom Shroom -->
</compendium>
