<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Bard</name>
    <!-- Bard College: College of the Maestro (HB) -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bard College: College of the Maestro (HB)</name>
        <text>Music is a powerful thing. It can bolster a burning passion, inspire the meek to bravery, and sooth a cluttered mind. Wandering bards have mastered the art of creating music to shape and manipulate the thoughts and hearts of the world through song, words, and instrument. However, it is the Maestro who has learned to evoke music from the natural world around them and weave these notes with arcane skill into melodies of dynamic and potent magic.
	With but a raised hand or wand, a Maestro listens for the clang of arms on armor, the heavy footfalls of a giant, the crackle of a bolt of lightning, and catches them, crafting them into a symphony of rousing musical movements. They conduct the sounds of the battlefield like a phantom orchestra, empowering the blows of their allies, altering the minds and moods of their opponents, and changing the pace of the fray in their favor.
	The College of the Maestro calls to those who enjoy enabling their companions to become even more adept, working in unison with your sonata. It refines those of raw talent into majestic performers who can pluck the thoughts from a mind like a musical note, amplify the fears of lesser beings through sourceless, ominous tones, and seemingly stretch time by commanding the tempo of a heartbeat. Maestros become heroes who can take the chaos of the world and carve it as they see fit by controlling the vibrations of music that subtly guide the realm.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 1 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Battle Muse (College of the Maestro (HB))</name>
        <text>When you join the College of the Maestro at 3rd level, you gain one additional use of your Bardic Inspiration feature. This feature grants you another additional use of Bardic Inspiration at 6th level, and again at 14th level.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Symphony of Conflict (College of the Maestro (HB))</name>
        <text>You've been trained in the bardic art of magically manipulating the sounds of combat into a concert of powerful melodies that can alter the very battlefield around you.
	When you select this bardic school at 3rd level, you learn 2 conducting techniques of your choice, which are detailed in the "Bard (Maestro (HB)): Conducting Techniques" spell list. Al techniques require at least one free hand, baton, or wand to utilize. For these techniques to function, you must be able to see your target, and they must be able to hear you.
	You learn 1 additional conducting technique of your choice at 6th and 14th level. Each time you learn a new technique, you can also replace one technique you know with a different one.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Frenetic Crescendo (College of the Maestro (HB))</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you can harness the beat of battle, whipping it into a frenzy of drums, chants, and glory. You can use your action to expend any number of uses of your Bardic Inspiration feature. For each expended use, you can immediately grant a Bardic Inspiration die to a creature other than yourself within 60 feet that you can see. A creature can have only one Bardic Inspiration die at a time.
	Once you use this feature, you must finish a long rest before you can use it again.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Frenetic Crescendo</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>College of the Maestro (HB)</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Virtuoso of Captivation (College of the Maestro (HB))</name>
        <text>Upon reaching 14th level, you can begin conducting a mystical symphony as an action, distracting and capturing the minds of nearby creatures. For up to 10 minutes, any number of creatures you choose within 60 feet who can hear you have disadvantage on any saving throws against being charmed and against magical sleep.
	In addition, affected targets have disadvantage on Wisdom (Perception) rolls that rely on sight or sound to detect targets other than you.
	In combat, you must spend your action each turn to continue the performance or the effect ends. Once you use Virtuoso of Captivation, you must finish a short or long rest before you can use it again.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
  <feat>
    <name>Journeyman Conductor (HB)</name>
    <prerequisite>4th Level, Initiate of High Sorcery (Nuitari) Feat</prerequisite>
    <text>You have spent some time in the bardic teachings of a maestro, granting you minor command over the music of combat. You gain the following benefits.

	• You learn 2 conducting techniques of your choice from among those available to the College of the Maestro in the bard class (See the "Bard (Maestro (HB)): Conducting Techniques" spell list). If a technique you use requires your target to make a saving throw to resist the technique's effects, the saving throw DC equals 8 + proficiency bonus + your Charisma modifier.

	• If you already have Bardic Inspiration dice, you gain one more; otherwise, you have one Bardic Inspiration die, which is a d6. This die can be given to others as a bonus action (per the bard feature, Bardic Inspiration), or can be used to fuel your techniques. A Bardic Inspiration die is expended when you use it. You regain this expended bardic inspiration die when you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 3 (Homebrew)</text>
  </feat>
</compendium>
