<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <spell>
    <name>Conducting Technique: Aria of Suspense (Ansia)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Bard (Maestro (HB)): Conducting Techniques</classes>
    <text>You build an air of tension and paranoia with subtle, droning tones. As an action, you expend and roll a Bardic Inspiration die. For the next 10 minutes, any creatures of your choice within 60 feet cannot be surprised, and gain a bonus on saving throws against traps and environmental hazards equal to your Bardic Inspiration die roll.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Conducting Technique: Crash (Marcato)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Bard (Maestro (HB)): Conducting Techniques</classes>
    <text>You learn how to harness and amplify the roar of a well-placed blow into a violent explosion of sound. When a creature other than yourself within 60 feet of you hits with an attack, you can use your reaction to expend and roll a Bardic Inspiration die. The target of the triggering attack must make a Strength saving throw against your Spell save DC or take thunder damage equal to half of the number rolled and be knocked prone.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Conducting Technique: Dirge of Dread (Finale)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Bard (Maestro (HB)): Conducting Techniques</classes>
    <text>You play a terrifying dirge to accompany a deathblow, striking fear into the hearts of your nearby enemies. When an ally brings a creature within 60 feet to 0 hitpoints, you can use your reaction to expend and roll a Bardic Inspiration die. Select a number of creatures within 15 feet of the triggering ally equal to half of the number rolled (minimum 1). Each target must make a Wisdom saving throw against your Spell save DC or becomed frightened of the triggering ally until the end of that ally's next turn. After the effect ends, or the save is successful, targeted creatures are immune to Dirge of Dread for the next 24 hours.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Conducting Technique: Dissonance (Discordia)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Bard (Maestro (HB)): Conducting Techniques</classes>
    <text>Summoning a harsh, discordant tone, you muddle the mind of an opponent, lessening their defenses. When a creature within 60 feet is forced to make a saving throw, you can use your reaction to expend and roll a Bardic Inspiration die. You reduce their saving throw by half of the number rolled. You can use this feature after the creature makes its saving throw roll, but before the DM determines a success or failure.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Conducting Technique: Guiding Tone (Fermata)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Bard (Maestro (HB)): Conducting Techniques</classes>
    <text>You drag a sharp, powerful chord through the mind of a creature, forcing it to suddenly stumble in a direction you wish. As a bonus action, you expend and roll a of Bardic Inspiration die and select a creature other than yourself within 60 feet. The target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your Spell save DC or take psychic damage equal to half of the number rolled and be pushed 10 feet in a direction you choose. Atarget can fail the saving throw voluntarily.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Conducting Technique: Hasten Tempo (Accelerando)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Bard (Maestro (HB)): Conducting Techniques</classes>
    <text>Your manipulation of tempo and song can inspire others to act more quickly. You can use a Bonus action on your turn to choose one creature other than yourself within 60 feet. Expend and roll a Bardic Inspiration die, adding the number rolled to the creature's initiative and moving them up the initiative order accordingly. If this would move them higher than you, they immediately take their turn after you this round. Acreature cannot be affected by Hasten Tempo again until they've finished a short or long rest.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 3 (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Conducting Technique: Hymn of Harmony (Armonia)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Bard (Maestro (HB)): Conducting Techniques</classes>
    <text>The melodies surrounding your allies promote rapid recovery. When a creature that has a Bardic Inspiration die from you regains any hitpoints, they can expend and roll their inspiration die to regain additional hitpoints equal to the number rolled.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 3 (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Conducting Technique: Majestic Anthem (Maestoso)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Bard (Maestro (HB)): Conducting Techniques</classes>
    <text>Pulled from the chaos, you muster an uplifting melody that bolsters the resolve of your allies. You can expend and roll a Bardic Inspiration die as an action, and all other creatures you choose within 60 ft gain temporary hitpoints equal to the number rolled plus your Charisma modifier (minimum of 1). These temporary hitpoints last until the end of your next turn.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 3 (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Conducting Technique: Resonance (Risonanza)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Bard (Maestro (HB)): Conducting Techniques</classes>
    <text>You shape the harmonic vibrations of a weapon's movements into a dangerous, sonic enhancement. Using a bonus action, you can expend and roll a Bardic Inspiration die, choosimg one weapon within 60 feet of you. Until the end of your next turn, all attacks with that weapon deal additional thunder damage equal to half of number rolled (minimum of 1).

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 3 (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Conducting Technique: Sprint (Presto)</name>
    <level>0</level>
    <classes>Bard (Maestro (HB)): Conducting Techniques</classes>
    <text>The song you conjure can stir the winds, pushing along those who require expedient travel. Acreature that has a Bardic Inspiration die from you can expend and roll their inspiration to increase their speed for that turn. Aroll of 1-4 increases their speed by 10 feet, a roll of 5-8 increases their speed by 15 feet, and a roll of 9-12 increases their speed by 20 feet.

Source:	Matt Mercer - College of the Maestro v1.2 p. 3 (Homebrew)</text>
  </spell>
</compendium>
