<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<source>
  <name>Bard: College of the Maestro</name>
  <abbreviation>bard-mm</abbreviation>
  <url>https://dnd5e.wikidot.com/bard:maestro</url>
  <author>Matthew Mercer</author>
  <publisher>Matthew Mercer</publisher>
  <website>https://dnd5e.wikidot.com//</website>
  <category>Homebrew</category>
  <description>"Music is a powerful thing. It can bolster a burning passion, inspire the meek to bravery, and sooth a cluttered mind. Wandering bards have mastered the art of creating music to shape and manipulate the minds and hearts of the world through song, words, and instrument. However, it is the Maestro who has learned to evoke music from the natural world around them and weave these notes with arcane skill into melodies of dynamic and potent magic.

With but a raised hand or wand, a Maestro listens for the clang of arms on armor, the heavy footfalls of a giant, the crackle of a bolt of lightning, and catches them, crafting them into a symphony of rousing musical movements. They conduct the sounds of the battlefield like a phantom orchestra, empowering the blows of their allies, altering the minds and moods of their opponents, and changing the pace of the fray in their favor.

The College of the Maestro calls to those who enjoy enabling their companions to become even more effective and dangerous to their enemies. It refines those of raw talent into majestic performers who can pluck the thoughts from a mind like a musical note, amplify the fears of lesser beings through sourceless, ominous tones, and seemingly stretch time by commanding the tempo of a heartbeat. Maestros become heroes who can take the chaos of the world and carve it as they see if by controlling the vibrations of music that subtly guide the realm."

The College of the Maestro is a new Bardic College option to the Bard class, available at 3rd level. It plays as a more support-focused Bard, with additional utility for their Bardic Inspiration feature to alter and manipulate the battlefield in small ways. With a multitude of Conducting Techniques to choose from, you can customize your Maestro skill set to your liking. Do you wish to provide more control over battle placement and movement? Would you like to enable allies options to enhance their attacks? Perhaps you'd enjoy sutble healing and defense benefits for all around you? All of these flavors of additional playstyle options are at your disposal with the College of the Maestro.</description>
  <collection>
    <doc href="class-bard-mm.xml"/>
    <doc href="optionalfeatures-mm.xml"/>
  </collection>
</source>
