<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Artificer</name>
    <!-- Artificer Specialist: The Mad Scientist (HB) -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Artificer Specialist: The Mad Scientist (HB)</name>
        <text>"So much has been done — more, far more, will I achieve: treading in the steps already marked, I will pioneer a new way, explore unknown powers, and unfold to the world the deepest mysteries of creation...
-Dr. Victor von Frankenstein

Mad Scientists are artificers who have become deranged or certifiably insane in their pursuit of knowledge.
	Astute observers of the world and all manner of creatures in it, they always remain true to the cause of Science, uncaring of what must be done in order to acquire information, the dangers of learning forbidden secrets, or the consequences of unrestricted experimentation (particularly for creatures other than themselves).
	Although somewhat scatterbrained, and often reliant on questionable practices, these technologists possess a level of intellect unparalleled in mortal kind; having the ability to create virtually any idea that enters their mind. They are usually found inside their private laboratories, building implausible gadgetry or slightly ridiculous superweapons.
	It is not unheard of, however, for a few of those scientists to willingly go out into the world; after all, adventuring and exploration go hand in hand for providing stimulating new insights into a wide variety of fields.

Source:	The Mad Scientist by u/Camunon p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Pseudoscience Manipulation (The Mad Scientist (HB))</name>
        <text>When you adopt this specialization at 3rd level, you gain proficiency with one type of artisan's tools of your choice.
	Additionally, you have a bonus of +1 to all your Intelligence (Arcana), Intelligence (History), Intelligence (Investigation), Wisdom (Medicine) and Wisdom (Survival) ability checks. This increases to +2 when you reach 12th level.

Source:	The Mad Scientist by u/Camunon p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Mad Scientist Spells (The Mad Scientist (HB))</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you always have certain spells prepared after you reach particular levels in this class, as shown in the Mad Scientist Spells table. These spells count as artificer spells for you, but they don't count against the number of artificer spells you prepare.

Mad Scientist Spell List:
Artificer Level | Spell
3rd | identify, chaos bolt
5th | enthral, enlarge/reduce
9th | lightning bolt, thunder step
13th | summon construct, vitriolic sphere
17th | raise dead, cloudkill

Source:	The Mad Scientist by u/Camunon p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Quantitative Aptitudinal (The Mad Scientist (HB))</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you can briefly put your brain into overdrive, being able to thoroughly and completely understand the basic and complex functions of any creature you are focusing on, related to measuring the amount of matter usually estimated by spatial measurement.
	Once per long rest, you can use your action to make an Intelligence check against a DC equal to double the specified creature's CR. On a success, you may learn the attacks, immunities, features or resistances granted by the target's race or type. You must be able to see and hear the target for this feature to work, and the full breadth of what you learn is at the DM's discretion (particularly obscure monsters may reveal very little, and a hidden weapon remains hidden).
	The DC of the check becomes equal to the creature's CR when you reach 9th level, and equal to half the creature's CR when you reach 15th level.

Source:	The Mad Scientist by u/Camunon p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Crazy Contraption (The Mad Scientist (HB))</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, your unbridled genius gives you a knack for inventing the unthinkable, usually in disregard of your own safety. This may be channeled into a flash of inspiration, allowing you to build an insane gadget of unprecedented design. Using tinker's tools or smith's tools, you can spend 1 hour building the contraption in an unoccupied space on a horizontal surface within 5 feet of you.
	Have your DM roll on the Crazy Contraption table, and then describe to you the resulting creation.

Crazy Contraption:
d6 | Contraption | Properties
1 | Unstable Gadget | This item is identical in appearance to one of the other contraptions, but faulty in its design. It will explode when a creature attempts to use it, dealing 1d8 fire damage and 1d8 lightning damage to the holder and any creatures within 5 feet of them.
2 | Shock Gauntlet | You can use this item as a spellcasting focus for your artificer spells. While you are wearing the gauntlet, you may cast either Shocking Grasp or Lightning Lure as a bonus action on your turn.
3 | Laser Gun | This item functions as a one-handed firearm with a range of 30/90. When rolling for attack with this weapon, use your Intelligence modifier instead of your Dexterity. On a hit, the target takes radiant damage equal to 1d8 + your Intelligence modifier + your proficiency bonus.
4 | Electron Grenade | This single-use item can be thrown up to 30 feet away as an action, detonating when it reaches the end of its trajectory. Upon detonation, it creates a 15-foot radius sphere of whirling electricity which remains in place for 1 minute. All creatures inside the sphere when it appears, as well as any that enter or end their turn in it, take 2d8 lightning damage.
5 | Utility Gizmo | This single-use item can be used to create a dramatic or specific effect, rather than causing damage. It might blast open an impenetrable wall, steal an object carried by an enemy, reactivate a fallen construct, or any other suitably dramatic effect that the DM approves.
6 | Volatile Gadget | This item works in the same way as one of the other contraptions, but its energy cell is overcharged. Each time you use it, the DM must roll a d4. On a 1, you take 1d6 lightning damage. When you reach 9th level, this damage increases to 2d6.

Once you create a contraption, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest, or until you expend a spell slot to create one; in which case the building time is reduced to 1 minute. Only one contraption can be active at a time, and you can't create another while your current one is present. You may dismantle your current contraption during the same time spent on the creation of a new one. After 24 hours of use, your contraptions break down and become unusable.
	Starting from 9th level, you may have two contraptions active at the same time, and they last for a number of days equal to your Intelligence modifier.

Source:	The Mad Scientist by u/Camunon p. 2 (Homebrew)</text>
        <roll description="Contraption">1d6</roll>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Expanded Contraptions (The Mad Scientist (HB))</name>
        <text>If you truly wish to bring up the craziness with your character, crank it up to eleven, and blow it out of the tavern, then you may opt to use this expanded d20 list with 14 new options, instead of the usual d6 one. You may also feel free to remove or add any number of your own options, as well as mix them around in the table. The objective is to maximize the amount of fun gained when roleplaying this archetype, so the only real limit here is your imagination (and the DM's patience for your shenanigans)
	When using Omnifabrication, you may choose to build a temporary version of an item from this list, instead of picking a 3rd level feature from a different Artificer Specialization. If adhering by this optional rule, the requirement to roll a d6 each time you activate your chosen item is changed to a d8.

Expanded Crazy Contraption Table:
d20 | Contraption | Properties
6 | Telekinetic Glove | While you are wearing this item, you may cast the Mage Hand cantrip without any components, and can make the spectral hand invisible. Additionally, you can use your bonus action to telekinetically shove one creature you can see within 20 feet of you. The target must succeed on a strength saving throw or be moved 5 feet toward or away from you.
7 | Slime Lasso | This item functions in the same way as a whip, but counts as a simple weapon and deals acid damage instead. Whenever a creature is hit by it, they must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or become grappled, taking 2d4 acid damage at the start of each of their turns. They can use their action to make a DC 10 Strength or Dexterity check, freeing themselves on a success. You must use one hand to hold the lasso and maintain the grapple, otherwise the target is freed.
8 | Dart Gun | This item functions as a one-handed firearm with the ammunition and loading properties, a range of 20/60 and a total of 6 shots (2 for each dart type). On a hit, the target takes 1d4 piercing damage and must make a Constitution saving throw, suffering the dart's effect on a failed save. Sleeping Darts: the target falls unconscious for 1 minute. Toxin darts: the target becomes poisoned from 1 hour. Shock darts: the target becomes stunned until the start of their next turn.
9 | Gravity Boots | While you are wearing this item, your walking speed decreases by 10 feet, but you can move up, down, and across vertical surfaces and upside down along ceilings (while leaving your hands free). You have a climbing speed equal to your walking speed, and your movement is unaffected by difficult terrain.
10 | Mapping Radar | This item has 4 charges, and can be activated as an action on your turn. When you do so, the device will emit sound waves audible out to 200 feet, creating a simplified map of your current location or environment by extracting information from the echoes reflected in its surroundings. This process takes a total of 1 minute, and will be interrupted if the radar takes any damage. The map covers a range of 120 feet, can be viewed for 10 minutes, and appears as a static visual effect on the radar's surface.
11 | Hoverplate | This item functions as a single-person vehicle which can be controlled by standing on it. While you are riding this vehicle, your speed becomes 100 feet and your movement is unaffected by difficult terrain; but you cannot use the Dash action. Additionally, if your Dexterity score is lower than 16, you must make a dexterity (Acrobatics) check each time you use it. You lose control of the hoverplate on a failed check, tumbling down on the ground and becoming prone.
12 | Hypno Goggles | While you are wearing this item, you may cast the Friends cantrip as a bonus action on your turn without any components, and can choose a hostile creature as your target. Additionally, whenever you cast a spell from the enchantment school of magic, you don't need to maintain concentration on it as long as you and the target maintain eye contact. If the spell is of 1st level or higher, you also gain a bonus to the Spell Save DC equal to half of your Intelligence modifier (rounded down).
13 | Volatile Gadget | This item works in the same way as one of the other contraptions, but its energy cell is overcharged. Every time you take an action, bonus action or reaction which makes use of it, you must roll a d4. On a 1, you take 1d6 lightning damage. When you reach the 9th level, this damage increases to 2d6.
14 | Holo-Shield | This device has 8 charges, and may be strapped to your forearm or another limb of your choosing. It can be activated either as a bonus action or as a reaction to getting hit, generating a compact energy field which increases your AC by a number equal to your Intelligence modifier, until the start of your next turn. You cannot wield a shield while you are wearing this item.
15 | Cantrip Powerizer | You can use this item as a spellcasting focus for your artificer spells, and it may be strapped to your forearm or another limb of your choosing. When you build this contraption, choose one cantrip from the artificer spell list. While you are waring the Powerizer, you may cast that cantrip without material components. Additionally, as a bonus action on your turn, you can energize one of your cantrips known. Whenever you cast that cantrip through the Powerizer, it deals an additional damage die. This effect lasts for 1 minute or until you use it again.
16 | InfoBot | This Tiny-sized construct has an AC of 10, a speed of 15 feet, and a number of hit points equal to three times your artificer level. It is immune to psychic and necrotic damage. If it is forced to make an ability check or saving throw, treat all its ability scores as 6 (-2). If the mending spell is cast on it, it regains 2d6 hit points. It is friendly to you and your companions, and obeys your commands. You can activate the InfoBot's translation function as an action on your turn, as long as you are within 5 feet of it. Once activated, for the next minute it will be able to understand the literal meaning of any spoken language it hears, and may use its action to replicate those words in any language that its creator knows. Once this function has been used a total of 4 times, the InfoBot breaks down and becomes unusable.
17 | Zap-o-Matic | This item has 4 charges, and may be strapped to your wrist, ankle, neck or forehead. It can be activated as a bonus action on your turn, zapping one creature of your choice that you can see within 30 feet of you. If the target is an ally, they must make a DC 10 Constitution check, regaining a number of hit points equal to your Intelligence modifier on a success. If the target is a hostile creature, they must make a DC 10 Constitution saving throw with disadvantage. On a failed save, they lose concentration on any active spells or effects, and are unable to cast spells of 3rd level or higher until the end of their turn.
18 | Swingshot | This wrist-mounted gadget can be activated as an action on your turn, firing out a green energy cable from its antenna onto a target surface within 40 feet of you. Roll a d20. If the number rolled is a 10 or higher, the cable latches itself to the specified point, allowing you to swing across gaps or possibly climb steep walls. You can have the cable detach itself from a surface as a bonus action, returning it to your device. Additionally, you may choose to recall the cable without detaching it, pulling you towards the targeted surface before retracting completely. If the targeted surface is a Medium or smaller object, it is pulled towards you instead. If it is a Medium or smaller creature, they must make a Strength saving throw, being pulled towards you on a failed save and pulling you towards them on a successful one.
19 | Barely Stable Gadget | This item works in the same way as one of the other contraptions, but its functionality is unreliable. Every time you take an action or reaction which makes use of it, the DM must roll a d8. On a 1, the device malfunctions, completely losing its usability.
20 | Mustache-Inator | This terrifying weapon of evil madness can be activated as an action on your turn, zapping one creature of your choice that you can see within 60 feet of you. Make a ranged spell attack. On a hit, the target instantly grows a big, bushy mustache measuring up to twice its body size. The affected creature must then roll a d20. On a 5 or lower, it gains a bonus of +5 to any charisma ability checks it makes while having this facial hair on. The mustache lasts for 24 hours, after which it naturally falls out.

Source:	The Mad Scientist by u/Camunon p. 6 (Homebrew)</text>
        <roll description="Contraption">1d20</roll>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Crazy Contraption</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>The Mad Scientist (HB)</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Omnifabrication (The Mad Scientist (HB))</name>
        <text>At 5th level, your absolute knowledge of all forms of science gives you the power of improvisational inventing: Being able to efficiently construct any item, device or weapon you might need in an exceptionally short time, by using the existing resources in your surroundings.
	Once per long rest, you may gain the benefits of one 3rd level feature from a different Artificer Specialization of your choice. If the chosen feature requires the use of a specific type of artisan's tools, you may instead use any type of artisan's tools that you are proficient with.
	Your chosen feature lasts for 1 minute, and each time you use it, the DM must roll a d6. On a 1, the device malfunctions, losing its usability for the next round.
	In addition, you can now use your contraptions as the targets for your artificer infusions.

Source:	The Mad Scientist by u/Camunon p. 3 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Hardened by Experimentation (The Mad Scientist (HB))</name>
        <text>At 9th level, your exploits in the pursuit of science have exposed your body to consistent hazards, granting you some level of acclimation to them. You gain resistance to acid, lightning, and poison damage. When you reach 12th level, you gain immunity to the poisoned condition.

Source:	The Mad Scientist by u/Camunon p. 3 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Doomsday Device (The Mad Scientist (HB))</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you reach the stage required to finally create your crowning achievement; the ultimate tool of destruction to take over any dungeon: A Doomsday Device!
	You must expend a spell slot of 4th level or higher to build your device, choosing from the following options. You regain the ability to do this when you finish a long rest.

Killer Robot:
You can spend 1 minute building the robot in an unoccupied space within 5 feet of you. You can also choose to spend 1 hour on it instead, making it last for longer. Once created, the Killer Robot lasts for 1 hour if you spent 1 minute on it, or 8 hours if you spent 1 hour on it.
	The robot can take the form of any Large or smaller construct with a CR equal to or lower than 6. It has immunity to psychic and necrotic damage, in addition to the features given by its chosen form. It is friendly to you and your companions, and obeys your commands. During combat, it rolls its own initiative and acts on its own turn. If the Mending spell is cast on it, it regains 2d8 hit points.
	The robot breaks down and becomes unusable if reduced to 0 hit points, unable to be healed or revived afterwards.

Death Ray:
You can spend 1 minute building a high performance laser turret in an unoccupied space within 5 feet of you, which lasts for up to 1 hour.
	The turret is a Medium-sized cannon, with an AC of 20 and a number of hit points equal to five times your artificer level. It is immune to poison and psychic damage. If it is forced to make an ability check or a saving throw, treat all its ability scores as 14 (+2). If the mending spell is cast on it, it regains 2d4 hit points.
	You can activate the turret as an action on your turn, as long as you are within 5 feet of it. Once activated, it fires off a beam of searing light against a target within 60 feet of it. Make a ranged spell attack. On a hit, if the target has 80 hit points or fewer, it dies. Otherwise, it takes 5d6 radiant damage and 5d6 fire damage. The Death Ray ignores the damage threshold of objects and structures, always dealing maximum damage to them.
	You can fire off the ray a number of times equal to half your Intelligence modifier (rounded up). Once the number of shots is expended, the ray hits a living creature, or the turret is reduced to 0 hit points, the turret then completely breaks down and becomes unusable.

Bioweapon Beast:
You can spend 1 minute transforming the corpse of a Huge or smaller creature within 5 feet of you into your bioweapon. You can also choose to spend 1 hour on it instead, making it last for longer. Once created, the Bioweapon Beast lasts for 1 hour if you spent 1 minute on it, or 8 hours if you spent 1 hour on it.
	The bioweapon can be any beast of the same size as the corpse with a CR equal to or lower than 8. It has immunity to acid and poison damage, in addition to the features given by its chosen form. During combat, it rolls its own initiative and acts on its own turn. It is hostile to all creatures, including you, and will pursue and attack the nearest targets to the best of its ability.
	If the bioweapon is reduced to 0 hit points, its body breaks down into a pool of acid, unable to be healed or revived afterwards.

Explodium Bomb:
You can spend 1 minute building a Large-sized missile launch pad in a 10-foot square unoccupied space within 5 feet of you, which lasts for up to 10 minutes. It has an AC of 16 and a number of hit points equal to three times your artificer level. It is immune to poison and psychic damage. If it is forced to make an ability check or a saving throw, treat all its ability scores as 10 (+0). If the mending spell is cast on it, it regains 2d4 hit points.
	You can initiate the launching sequence as an action on your turn, as long as you are within 5 feet of it. Once activated, the structure takes one round to load the warhead, launching it to the sky at the start of your next turn. The sequence is interrupted if the launch pad takes any damage.
	Once successfully launched, one round later at the start of your following turn, the missile comes down at a point of your choice within 300 feet of you, generating an explosion of insensible proportions. Each creature in a 50-foot-radius sphere centered on the specified point must make a Dexterity saving throw. The sphere spreads around corners. A creature takes 1d4 fire damage and 1d4 lightning damage per artificer level on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. The blast damages objects in the area and ignites flammable objects that aren't being worn or carried.
	Once the Explodium Bomb is launched, or the launch pad is reduced to 0 hit points, the launch pad then completely breaks down and becomes unusable.

Source:	The Mad Scientist by u/Camunon p. 4 (Homebrew)</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
  <spell>
    <name>Identify</name>
    <classes>Artificer (Mad Scientist (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Chaos Bolt</name>
    <classes>Artificer (Mad Scientist (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Enthrall</name>
    <classes>Artificer (Mad Scientist (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Enlarge/Reduce</name>
    <classes>Artificer (Mad Scientist (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Lightning Bolt</name>
    <classes>Artificer (Mad Scientist (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Thunder Step</name>
    <classes>Artificer (Mad Scientist (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Summon Construct</name>
    <classes>Artificer (Mad Scientist (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Vitriolic Sphere</name>
    <classes>Artificer (Mad Scientist (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Raise Dead</name>
    <classes>Artificer (Mad Scientist (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Cloudkill</name>
    <classes>Artificer (Mad Scientist (HB))</classes>
  </spell>
</compendium>
