<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <race>
    <name>Revenant (UA)</name>
    <ability>Con +1</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Revenant Subrace</name>
      <text>The Revenant subrace can be applied to any race that has a subrace, and replaces that race's existing subrace options. Alternatively, you can apply this new subrace to a race without subrace options using the modification options provided below.
	Your DM might also allow you to take this subrace for a slain character. In that case, your character rises from the dead with its original subrace replaced (or with the necessary modifications made to its base traits), filled with a determination to seek vengeance or complete its mission.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Racial Adjustments</name>
      <text>For races that don't have subrace options, taking on the Revenant subrace means making changes to your character's base traits, as follows. (This playtest article provides options only for human and dragonborn characters. Any other races which do not have subrace options should not be used with these Revenant subrace rules.)

Human Revenant. If you want to play a human revenant, modify the human's Ability Score Increase trait to the following: Two different ability scores of your choice increase by 1. If you use the variant human traits, remove the Skills trait and the Feat trait.

Dragonborn Revenant. If you want to play a dragonborn revenant, modify the dragonborn's Ability Score Increase trait to the following: Your Strength score increases by 1, and your Charisma score increases by 1. Additionally, your Draconic Ancestry trait uses necrotic damage as its damage type, replacing the damage type that applies to your breath weapon and your damage resistance.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Dragonborn, Black (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Str +1, Cha +1, Con +1</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>The dragonborn walk proudly through a world that greets them with fearful incomprehension. Shaped by the dragons themselves, dragonborn originally hatched from dragon eggs as a unique race, combining the best attributes of dragons and humanoids.

Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a Revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 32,
		Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Young dragonborn grow quickly. They walk hours after hatching, attain the size and development of a 10-year-old human child by the age of 3, and reach adulthood by 15. They live to be around 80.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Dragonborn tend towards extremes, making a conscious choice for one side or the other in the cosmic war between Good and Evil (represented by Bahamut and Tiamat, respectively). More side with Bahamut than Tiamat (whose non-dragon followers are mostly kobolds), but villainous dragonborn can be quite terrible indeed. Some rare few choose to devote themselves to lesser dragon deities, such as Chronepsis (Neutral), and fewer still choose to worship Io, the Ninefold Dragon, who is all alignments at once.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Dragonborn are taller and heavier than humans, standing well over 6 feet tall and averaging almost 250 pounds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 5 feet + 6 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 175 + (2d6 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Draconic Ancestry</name>
      <text>You have draconic ancestry. Your breath weapon and damage resistance are determined by having become a revenant. Your damage type is Necrotic, and your breath weapon is 5 by 30 ft. line. (Dex. save)</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Breath Weapon</name>
      <text>You can use your action to exhale destructive energy. Your draconic ancestry determines the size, shape, and damage type of the exhalation.
	When you use your breath weapon, each creature in the area of the exhalation must make a saving throw, the type of which is determined by your draconic ancestry. The DC for this saving throw equals 8 + your Constitution modifier + your proficiency bonus. A creature takes 2d6 damage on a failed save, and half as much damage on a successful one. The damage increases to 3d6 at 6th level, 4d6 at 11th level, and 5d6 at 16th level.
	After you use your breath weapon, you can't use it again until you complete a short or long rest.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Damage Resistance</name>
      <text>You have resistance to the damage type associated with your draconic ancestry.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Draconic. Draconic is thought to be one of the oldest languages and is often used in the study of magic. The language sounds harsh to most other creatures and includes numerous hard consonants and sibilants.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Dwarf, Duergar / Gray (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>25</speed>
    <ability>Con +3, Str +1</ability>
    <weapons>battleaxe, handaxe, light hammer, warhammer</weapons>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Kingdoms rich in ancient grandeur, halls carved into the roots of mountains, the echoing of picks and hammers in deep mines and blazing forges, a commitment to clan and tradition, and a burning hatred of goblins and orcs | these common threads unite all dwarves.

Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a Revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 20,
		Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 104,
		Mordenkainen's Tome of Foes p. 77,
		Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Dwarves mature at the same rate as humans, but they're considered young until they reach the age of 50. On average, they live about 350 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Most dwarves are lawful, believing firmly in the benefits of a well-ordered society. They tend toward good as well, with a strong sense of fair play and a belief that everyone deserves to share in the benefits of a just order.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Dwarves stand around 5 feet tall and average about 150 pounds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d4
Height = 4 feet + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 115 + (2d6 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d4</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Speed</name>
      <text>Your speed is not reduced by wearing heavy armor.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Dwarven Combat Training</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with the battleaxe, handaxe, light hammer, and warhammer</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Tool Proficiency</name>
      <text>You gain proficiency with the artisan's tools of your choice: smith's tools, brewer's supplies, or mason's tools</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Stonecunning</name>
      <text>Whenever you make an Intelligence (History) check related to the origin of stonework, you are considered proficient in the History skill and add double your proficiency bonus to the check, instead of your normal proficiency bonus</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Superior Darkvision</name>
      <text>Accustomed to life underground, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 120 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Duergar Resilience</name>
      <text>You have advantage on saving throws against poison, and you have resistance against poison damage. You also have advantage on saving throws against illusions and against being charmed or paralyzed</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Duergar Magic</name>
      <text>When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the Enlarge/Reduce spell on yourself once with this trait, using only the spell's enlarge option. When you reach 5th level, you can cast the Invisibility spell on yourself once with this trait. You don't need material components for either spell, and you can't cast them while you're in direct sunlight, although sunlight has no effect on them once cast. You regain the ability to cast these spells with this trait when you finish a long rest. Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for these spells.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>You have disadvantage on attack rolls and Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight when you, the target of your attack, or whatever you are trying to perceive is in direct sunlight.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common, Dwarvish, and Undercommon</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Dwarf, Hill (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>25</speed>
    <ability>Con +3, Wis +1</ability>
    <weapons>battleaxe, handaxe, light hammer, warhammer</weapons>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Kingdoms rich in ancient grandeur, halls carved into the roots of mountains, the echoing of picks and hammers in deep mines and blazing forges, a commitment to clan and tradition, and a burning hatred of goblins and orcs | these common threads unite all dwarves.

Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a Revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 20,
		Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Dwarves mature at the same rate as humans, but they're considered young until they reach the age of 50. On average, they live about 350 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Most dwarves are lawful, believing firmly in the benefits of a well-ordered society. They tend toward good as well, with a strong sense of fair play and a belief that everyone deserves to share in the benefits of a just order.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Dwarves stand around 5 feet tall and average about 150 pounds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d4
Height = 4 feet + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 115 + (2d6 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d4</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Speed</name>
      <text>Your speed is not reduced by wearing heavy armor.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Accustomed to life underground in your race's ancient past, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>You have advantage on saving throws against poison, and you have resistance against poison damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Dwarven Combat Training</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with the battleaxe, handaxe, light hammer, and warhammer</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Tool Proficiency</name>
      <text>You gain proficiency with the artisan's tools of your choice: smith's tools, brewer's supplies, or mason's tools</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Stonecunning</name>
      <text>Whenever you make an Intelligence (History) check related to the origin of stonework, you are considered proficient in the History skill and add double your proficiency bonus to the check, instead of your normal proficiency bonus</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Dwarven Toughness</name>
      <text>Your hit point maximum increases by 1, and it increases by 1 every time you gain a level.</text>
      <modifier category="bonus">HP +1</modifier>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common, Dwarvish, and Undercommon</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Dwarf, Mountain (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>25</speed>
    <ability>Con +3, Str +2</ability>
    <armor>Light Armor, Medium Armor</armor>
    <weapons>battleaxe, handaxe, light hammer, warhammer</weapons>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Kingdoms rich in ancient grandeur, halls carved into the roots of mountains, the echoing of picks and hammers in deep mines and blazing forges, a commitment to clan and tradition, and a burning hatred of goblins and orcs | these common threads unite all dwarves.

Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a Revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 20,
		Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Dwarves mature at the same rate as humans, but they're considered young until they reach the age of 50. On average, they live about 350 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Most dwarves are lawful, believing firmly in the benefits of a well-ordered society. They tend toward good as well, with a strong sense of fair play and a belief that everyone deserves to share in the benefits of a just order.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Dwarves stand around 5 feet tall and average about 150 pounds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d4
Height = 4 feet + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 115 + (2d6 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d4</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Speed</name>
      <text>Your speed is not reduced by wearing heavy armor.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Accustomed to life underground in your race's ancient past, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>You have advantage on saving throws against poison, and you have resistance against poison damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Dwarven Combat Training</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with the battleaxe, handaxe, light hammer, and warhammer</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Tool Proficiency</name>
      <text>You gain proficiency with the artisan's tools of your choice: smith's tools, brewer's supplies, or mason's tools</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Stonecunning</name>
      <text>Whenever you make an Intelligence (History) check related to the origin of stonework, you are considered proficient in the History skill and add double your proficiency bonus to the check, instead of your normal proficiency bonus</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Dwarven Armor Training</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with light and medium armor.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common, Dwarvish, and Undercommon</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Dwarf (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>25</speed>
    <ability>Con +3</ability>
    <weapons>battleaxe, handaxe, light hammer, warhammer</weapons>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Kingdoms rich in ancient grandeur, halls carved into the roots of mountains, the echoing of picks and hammers in deep mines and blazing forges, a commitment to clan and tradition, and a burning hatred of goblins and orcs | these common threads unite all dwarves.

Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a Revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 20,
		Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Dwarves mature at the same rate as humans, but they're considered young until they reach the age of 50. On average, they live about 350 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Most dwarves are lawful, believing firmly in the benefits of a well-ordered society. They tend toward good as well, with a strong sense of fair play and a belief that everyone deserves to share in the benefits of a just order.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Dwarves stand around 5 feet tall and average about 150 pounds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d4
Height = 4 feet + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 115 + (2d6 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d4</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Speed</name>
      <text>Your speed is not reduced by wearing heavy armor.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Dwarven Combat Training</name>
      <text>You have proficiency with the battleaxe, handaxe, light hammer, and warhammer</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Tool Proficiency</name>
      <text>You gain proficiency with the artisan's tools of your choice: smith's tools, brewer's supplies, or mason's tools</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Stonecunning</name>
      <text>Whenever you make an Intelligence (History) check related to the origin of stonework, you are considered proficient in the History skill and add double your proficiency bonus to the check, instead of your normal proficiency bonus</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common, Dwarvish, and Undercommon</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Elf (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Dex +2, Con +1</ability>
    <proficiency>Perception</proficiency>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Elves are a magical people of otherworldly grace, living in places of ethereal beauty, in the midst of ancient forests or in silvery spires glittering with faerie light, where soft music drifts through the air and gentle fragrances waft on the breeze. Elves love nature and magic, art and artistry, music and poetry.

Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a Revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 23</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Although elves reach physical maturity at about the same age as humans, the elven understanding of adulthood goes beyond physical growth to encompass worldly experience. An elf typically claims adulthood and an adult name around the age of 100 and can live to be 750 years old.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Elves love freedom, variety, and self-expression, so they lean strongly toward the gentler aspects of chaos. They value and protect others' freedom as well as their own, and they are more often good than not.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Elves range from under 5 to over 6 feet tall and have slender builds. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d10
Height = 4 feet + 6 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 90 + (1d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d10</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">1d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Accustomed to twilit forests and the night sky, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Keen Senses</name>
      <text>You have proficiency in the Perception skill.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put you to sleep.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Trance</name>
      <text>Elves don't need to sleep. Instead, they meditate deeply, remaining semiconscious, for 4 hours a day. (The Common word for such meditation is "trance.") While meditating, you can dream after a fashion; such dreams are actually mental exercises that have become reflexive through years of practice. After resting in this way, you gain the same benefit that a human does from 8 hours of sleep.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Elvish. Elvish is fluid, with subtle intonations and intricate grammar. Elven literature is rich and varied, and their songs and poems are famous among other races. Many bards learn their language so they can add Elvish ballads to their repertoires.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Genasi, Air (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Con +3, Dex +1</ability>
    <spellAbility>Constitution</spellAbility>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Those who think of other planes at all consider them remote, distant realms, but planar influence can be felt throughout the world. It sometimes manifests in beings who, through an accident of birth, carry the power of the planes in their blood. The genasi are one such people, the offspring of genies and mortals.

As an air genasi, you are descended from the djinn. As changeable as the weather, your moods shift from calm to wild and violent with little warning, but these storms rarely last long.
	Air genasi typically have light blue skin, hair, and eyes. A faint but constant breeze accompanies them, tousling the hair and stirring the clothing. Some air genasi speak with breathy voices, marked by a faint echo. A few display odd patterns in their flesh or grow crystals from their scalps.

Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a Revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Elemental Evil Player's Companion p. 9,
		Princes of the Apocalypse p. 228,
		Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 170,
		Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Genasi mature at about the same rate as humans and reach adulthood in their late teens. They live somewhat longer than humans do, up to 120 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Independent and self-reliant, genasi tend toward a neutral alignment.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Genasi are as varied as their mortal parents but are generally built like humans, standing anywhere from 5 feet to over 6 feet tall. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d10
Height = 4 feet + 8 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 110 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d10</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Unending Breath</name>
      <text>You can hold your breath indefinitely while you're not incapacitated.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Mingle with the Wind</name>
      <text>You can cast the levitate spell once with this trait, requiring no material components, and you regain the ability to cast it this way when you finish a long rest. Constitution is your spellcasting ability for this spell.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Primordial. Primordial is a guttural language, filled with harsh syllables and hard consonants.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Genasi, Earth (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Con +3, Str +1</ability>
    <spellAbility>Constitution</spellAbility>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Those who think of other planes at all consider them remote, distant realms, but planar influence can be felt throughout the world. It sometimes manifests in beings who, through an accident of birth, carry the power of the planes in their blood. The genasi are one such people, the offspring of genies and mortals.

As an earth genasi, you are descended from the cruel and greedy dao, though you aren't necessarily evil. You have inherited some measure of control over earth, reveling in superior strength and solid power. You tend to avoid rash decisions, pausing long enough to consider your options before taking action.
	Elemental earth manifests differently from one individual to the next. Some earth genasi always have bits of dust falling from their bodies and mud clinging to their clothes, never getting clean no matter how often they bathe. Others are as shiny and polished as gemstones, with skin tones of deep brown or black, eyes sparkling like agates. Earth genasi can also have smooth metallic flesh, dull iron skin spotted with rust, a pebbled and rough hide, or even a coating of tiny embedded crystals. The most arresting have fissures in their flesh, from which faint light shines.

Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a Revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Elemental Evil Player's Companion p. 9,
		Princes of the Apocalypse p. 228,
		Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 170,
		Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Genasi mature at about the same rate as humans and reach adulthood in their late teens. They live somewhat longer than humans do, up to 120 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Independent and self-reliant, genasi tend toward a neutral alignment.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Genasi are as varied as their mortal parents but are generally built like humans, standing anywhere from 5 feet to over 6 feet tall. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d10
Height = 4 feet + 8 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 110 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d10</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Earth Walk</name>
      <text>You can move across difficult terrain made of earth or stone without expending extra movement.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Merge with Stone</name>
      <text>You can cast the pass without trace spell once with this trait, requiring no material components, and you regain the ability to cast it this way when you finish a long rest. Constitution is your spellcasting ability for this spell.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Primordial. Primordial is a guttural language, filled with harsh syllables and hard consonants.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Genasi, Fire (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Con +3, Int +1</ability>
    <resist>fire</resist>
    <spellAbility>Constitution</spellAbility>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Those who think of other planes at all consider them remote, distant realms, but planar influence can be felt throughout the world. It sometimes manifests in beings who, through an accident of birth, carry the power of the planes in their blood. The genasi are one such people, the offspring of genies and mortals.

As a fire genasi, you have inherited the volatile mood and keen mind of the efreet. You tend toward impatience and making snap judgments. Rather than hide your distinctive appearance, you exult in it.
	Nearly all fire genasi are feverishly hot as if burning inside, an impression reinforced by flaming red, coal- black, or ash-gray skin tones. The more human-looking have fiery red hair that writhes under extreme emotion, while more exotic specimens sport actual flames dancing on their heads. Fire genasi voices might sound like crackling flames, and their eyes flare when angered. Some are accompanied by the faint scent of brimstone.

Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a Revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Elemental Evil Player's Companion p. 9,
		Princes of the Apocalypse p. 228,
		Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 170,
		Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Genasi mature at about the same rate as humans and reach adulthood in their late teens. They live somewhat longer than humans do, up to 120 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Independent and self-reliant, genasi tend toward a neutral alignment.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Genasi are as varied as their mortal parents but are generally built like humans, standing anywhere from 5 feet to over 6 feet tall. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d10
Height = 4 feet + 8 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 110 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d10</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. Your ties to the Elemental Plane of Fire make your darkvision unusual: everything you see in darkness is in a shade of red.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Fire Resistance</name>
      <text>You have resistance to fire damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Reach to the Blaze</name>
      <text>You know the produce flame cantrip. Once you reach 3rd level, you can cast the burning hands spell once with this trait as a 1st-level spell, and you regain the ability to cast it this way when you finish a long rest. Constitution is your spellcasting ability for these spells.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Primordial. Primordial is a guttural language, filled with harsh syllables and hard consonants.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Genasi, Water (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Con +3, Wis +1</ability>
    <resist>acid</resist>
    <spellAbility>Constitution</spellAbility>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Those who think of other planes at all consider them remote, distant realms, but planar influence can be felt throughout the world. It sometimes manifests in beings who, through an accident of birth, carry the power of the planes in their blood. The genasi are one such people, the offspring of genies and mortals.

The lapping of waves, the spray of sea foam on the wind, the ocean depths—all of these things call to your heart. You wander freely and take pride in your independence, though others might consider you selfish.
	Most water genasi look as if they just finished bathing, with beads of moisture collecting on their skin and hair. They smell of fresh rain and clean water. Blue or green skin is common, and most have somewhat overlarge eyes, blue-black in color. A water genasi's hair might float freely, swaying and waving as if underwater. Some have voices with undertones reminiscent of whale song or trickling streams.

Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a Revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Elemental Evil Player's Companion p. 9,
		Princes of the Apocalypse p. 228,
		Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 170,
		Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Genasi mature at about the same rate as humans and reach adulthood in their late teens. They live somewhat longer than humans do, up to 120 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Independent and self-reliant, genasi tend toward a neutral alignment.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Genasi are as varied as their mortal parents but are generally built like humans, standing anywhere from 5 feet to over 6 feet tall. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d10
Height = 4 feet + 8 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 110 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d10</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Acid Resistance</name>
      <text>You have resistance to acid damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>You can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Swim</name>
      <text>You have a swimming speed of 30 feet.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Call to the Wave</name>
      <text>You know the shape water cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the create or destroy water spell as a 2nd-level spell once with this trait, and you regain the ability to cast it this way when you finish a long rest. Constitution is your spellcasting ability for these spells.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Primordial. Primordial is a guttural language, filled with harsh syllables and hard consonants.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Gnome (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <speed>25</speed>
    <ability>Int +2, Dex +1</ability>
    <spellAbility>Intelligence</spellAbility>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>A constant hum of busy activity pervades the warrens and neighborhoods where gnomes form their close-knit communities. Louder sounds punctuate the hum: a crunch of grinding gears here, a minor explosion there, a yelp of surprise or triumph, and especially bursts of laughter. Gnomes take delight in life, enjoying every moment of invention, exploration, investigation, creation, and play.

Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a Revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 1,
		Elemental Evil Player's Companion p. 7,
		Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 115</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Gnomes mature at the same rate humans do, and most are expected to settle down into an adult life by around age 40. They can live 350 to almost 500 years.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Gnomes are most often good. Those who tend toward law are sages, engineers, researchers, scholars, investigators, or inventors. Those who tend toward chaos are minstrels, tricksters, wanderers, or fanciful jewelers. Gnomes are good-hearted, and even the tricksters among them are more playful than vicious.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Gnomes are between 3 and 4 feet tall and average about 40 pounds. Your size is Small.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d4
Height = 2 feet + 11 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 35 + your size modifier</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Accustomed to life underground, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Gnome Cunning</name>
      <text>You have advantage on all Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws against magic.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common, Gnomish, and Undercommon. The svirfneblin dialect is more guttural than surface Gnomish, and most svirfneblin know only a little bit of Common, but those who deal with outsiders (and that includes you as an adventurer) pick up enough Common to get by in other lands.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Halfling (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <speed>25</speed>
    <ability>Dex +2, Con +1</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>The comforts of home are the goals of most halflings' lives: a place to settle in peace and quiet, far from marauding monsters and clashing armies. Others form nomadic bands that travel constantly, lured by the open road and the wide horizon to discover the wonders of new lands and peoples. Halflings work readily with others, and they are loyal to their friends, whether halfling or otherwise. They can display remarkable ferocity when their friends, families, or communities are threatened.

Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a Revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 28,
		Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>A halfling reaches adulthood at the age of 20 and generally lives into the middle of his or her second century.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Most halflings are lawful good. As a rule, they are good-hearted and kind, hate to see others in pain, and have no tolerance for oppression. They are also very orderly and traditional, leaning heavily on the support of their community and the comfort of their old ways.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Halflings average about 3 feet tall and weigh about 40 pounds. Your size is Small.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d4
Height = 2 feet + 7 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 35 + your size modifie</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Lucky</name>
      <text>When you roll a 1 on an attack roll, ability check, or saving throw, you can reroll the die and must use the new roll.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Brave</name>
      <text>You have advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Halfling Nimbleness</name>
      <text>You can move through the space of any creature that is of a size larger than yours.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Halfling. The Halfling language isn't secret, but halflings are loath to share it with others. They write very little, so they don't have a rich body of literature. Their oral tradition, however, is very strong. Almost all halflings speak Common to converse with the people in whose lands they dwell or through which they are traveling.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Human (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Str +1, Dex +1, Con +2, Int +1, Wis +1, Cha +1</ability>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>In the reckonings of most worlds, humans are the youngest of the common races, late to arrive on the world scene and short-lived in comparison to dwarves, elves, and dragons. Perhaps it is because of their shorter lives that they strive to achieve as much as they can in the years they are given. Or maybe they feel they have something to prove to the elder races, and that's why they build their mighty empires on the foundation of conquest and trade. Whatever drives them, humans are the innovators, the achievers, and the pioneers of the worlds.

Having met a cruel and undeserved end, you have returned to the realm of the living. As a Revenant, you thirst for revenge against those who wronged you in life, or seek to complete a final, critical task you left unfinished.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 29</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Humans reach adulthood in their late teens and live less than a century.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Humans tend toward no particular alignment. The best and the worst are found among them.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Humans vary widely in height and build, from barely 5 feet to well over 6 feet tall. Regardless of your position in that range, your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d10
Height = 4 feet + 8 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 110 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d10</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and one extra language of your choice. Humans typically learn the languages of other peoples they deal with, including obscure dialects. They are fond of sprinkling their speech with words borrowed from other tongues: Orc curses, Elvish musical expressions, Dwarvish military phrases, and so on.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Tiefling (Revenant (UA))</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Cha +2, Int +1, Con +1</ability>
    <resist>fire</resist>
    <spellAbility>Charisma</spellAbility>
    <trait category="description">
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>To be greeted with stares and whispers, to suffer violence and insult on the street, to see mistrust and fear in every eye: this is the lot of the tiefling. And to twist the knife, tieflings know that this is because a pact struck generations ago infused the essence of Asmodeus, overlord of the Nine Hells (and many of the other powerful devils serving under him) into their bloodline. Their appearance and their nature are not their fault but the result of an ancient sin, for which they and their children and their children's children will always be held accountable.

The tieflings connected to Nessus command the power of fire and darkness, guided by a keener than normal intellect, as befits those linked to Asmodeus himself.

Source:	Player's Handbook (2014) p. 43,
		Unearthed Arcana 11: That Old Black Magic p. 1,
		Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 1</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Tieflings mature at the same rate as humans but live a few years longer.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Tieflings might not have an innate tendency toward evil, but many of them end up there. Evil or not, an independent nature inclines many tieflings toward a chaotic alignment.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Tieflings are about the same size and build as humans. Your size is Medium.

To set your height and weight randomly, start with rolling a size modifier:

Size modifier = 2d8
Height = 4 feet + 9 inches + your size modifier in inches
Weight in pounds = 110 + (2d4 × your size modifier)</text>
      <roll description="Size Modifier">2d8</roll>
      <roll description="Weight Modifier">2d4</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>Thanks to your infernal heritage, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Hellish Resistance</name>
      <text>You have resistance to fire damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="species">
      <name>Infernal Legacy</name>
      <text>You know the Thaumaturgy cantrip. Once you reach 3rd level, you can cast the hellish rebuke spell as a 2nd-level spell; you must finish a long rest in order to cast the spell again using this trait. Once you reach 5th level, you can also cast the darkness spell; you must finish a long rest in order to cast the spell again using this trait. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait category="subspecies">
      <name>Relentless Nature</name>
      <text>Your DM assigns a goal to you—typically, one related to your character's death. The goal must be a specific task you can complete, such as slaying an enemy or liberating an area and its people. Until you fulfill that goal, you gain the following benefits:

	• If you are below half your hit point maximum at the start of your turn, you regain 1 hit point.

	• If you die, you return to life 24 hours after death. If your body is destroyed, you reform within 1 mile of the place of your death at a spot determined by the DM. If your equipment was also destroyed, you do not regain it.

	• You know the distance and direction between you and any creature involved in your goal, such as a person you seek vengeance against or someone you pledged to defend. This awareness fails if the creature is on another plane of existence.

When your goal is complete, you finally find rest. You die and cannot be restored to life.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Infernal.</text>
    </trait>
  </race>
</compendium>
