<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Cleric</name>
    <trait>
      <name>Xanathar's Guide to Everything</name>
      <text>"To become a cleric is to become a messenger of the gods. The power the divine offers is great, but it always comes with tremendous responsibility."
— Riggby the patriarch

Almost all the folk in the world who revere a deity live their lives without ever being directly touched by a divine being. As such, they can never know what it feels like to be a cleric—someone who is not only a devout worshiper, but who has also been invested with a measure of a deity's power.
	The question has long been debated: Does a mortal become a cleric as a consequence of deep devotion to one's deity, thereby attracting the god's favor? Or is it the deity who sees the potential in a person and calls that individual into service? Ultimately, perhaps, the answer doesn't matter. However clerics come into being, the world needs clerics as much as clerics and deities need each other.
	If you're playing a cleric character, the following sections offer ways to add some detail to that character's history and personality.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 17</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Temple</name>
      <text>Most clerics start their lives of service as priests in an order, then later realize that they have been blessed by their god with the qualities needed to become a cleric. To prepare for this new duty, candidates typically receive instruction from a cleric of a temple or another place of study devoted to their deity.
	Some temples are cut off from the world so that their occupants can focus on devotions, while other temples open their doors to minister to and heal the masses. What is noteworthy about the temple you studied at?

Temple:
d6 | Temple
1 | Your temple is said to be the oldest surviving structure built to honor your god.
2 | Acolytes of several like-minded deities all received instruction together in your temple.
3 | You come from a temple famed for the brewery it operates. Some say you smell like one of its ales.
4 | Your temple is a fortress and a proving ground that trains warrior-priests.
5 | Your temple is a peaceful, humble place, filled with vegetable gardens and simple priests.
6 | You served in a temple in the Outer Planes.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Keepsake</name>
      <text>Many clerics have items among their personal gear that symbolize their faith, remind them of their vows, or otherwise help to keep them on their chosen paths. Even though such an item is not imbued with divine power, it is vitally important to its owner because of what it represents.

Keepsake:
d6 | Keepsake
1 | The finger bone of a saint
2 | A metal-bound book that tells how to hunt and destroy infernal creatures
3 | A pig's whistle that reminds you of your humble and beloved mentor
4 | A braid of hair woven from the tail of a unicorn
5 | A scroll that describes how best to rid the world of necromancers
6 | A runestone said to be blessed by your god</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Secret</name>
      <text>No mortal soul is entirely free of second thoughts or doubt. Even a cleric must grapple with dark desires or the forbidden attraction of turning against the teachings of one's deity.
	If you haven't considered this aspect of your character yet, see the table entries for some possibilities, or use them for inspiration. Your deep, dark secret might involve something you did (or are doing), or it could be rooted in the way you feel about the world and your role in it.

Secret:
d6 | Secret
1 | An imp offers you counsel. You try to ignore the creature, but sometimes its advice is helpful.
2 | You believe that, in the final analysis, the gods are nothing more than ultrapowerful mortal creatures.
3 | You acknowledge the power of the gods, but you think that most events are dictated by pure chance.
4 | Even though you can work divine magic, you have never truly felt the presence of a divine essence within yourself.
5 | You are plagued by nightmares that you believe are sent by your god as punishment for some unknown transgression.
6 | In times of despair, you feel that you are but a plaything of the gods, and you resent their remoteness.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Serving a Pantheon, Philosophy, or Force</name>
      <text>The typical cleric is an ordained servant of a particular god and chooses a Divine Domain associated with that deity. The cleric's magic flows from the god or the god's sacred realm, and often the cleric bears a holy symbol that represents that divinity.
	Some clerics, especially in a world like Eberron, serve a whole pantheon, rather than a single deity. In certain campaigns, a cleric might instead serve a cosmic force, such as life or death, or a philosophy or concept, such as love, peace, or one of the nine alignments. Chapter 1 of the Dungeon Master's Guide explores options like these, in the section "Gods of Your World."
	Talk with your DM about the divine options available in your campaign, whether they're gods, pantheons, philosophies, or cosmic forces. Whatever being or thing your cleric ends up serving, choose a Divine Domain that is appropriate for it, and if it doesn't have a holy symbol, work with your DM to design one.
	The cleric's class features often refer to your deity. If you are devoted to a pantheon, cosmic force, or philosophy, your cleric features still work for you as written. Think of the references to a god as references to the divine thing you serve that gives you your magic.</text>
    </trait>
    <!-- Divine Domain: Forge Domain -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain: Forge Domain</name>
        <text>The gods of the forge are patrons of artisans who work with metal, from a humble blacksmith who keeps a village in horseshoes and plow blades to the mighty elf artisan whose diamond-tipped arrows of mithral have felled demon lords. The gods of the forge teach that, with patience and hard work, even the most intractable metal can be transformed from a lump of ore to a beautifully wrought object. Clerics of these deities search for objects lost to the forces of darkness, liberate mines overrun by orcs, and uncover rare and wondrous materials necessary to create potent magic items. Followers of these gods take great pride in their work, and they are willing to craft and use heavy armor and powerful weapons to protect them. Deities of this domain include Gond, Reorx, Onatar, Moradin, Hephaestus, and Goibhniu.

Domain Spells:
At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared. They do not count towards your limit.

Forge Domain Spells:
Cleric Level | Spells
1st | identify, searing smite
3rd | heat metal, magic weapon
5th | elemental weapon, protection from energy
7th | fabricate, wall of fire
9th | animate objects, creation

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 18</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Bonus Proficiency (Forge Domain)</name>
        <text>When you choose this domain at 1st level, you gain proficiency with heavy armor and smith's tools.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 19</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Blessing of the Forge (Forge Domain)</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you gain the ability to imbue magic into a weapon or armor. At the end of a long rest, you can touch one nonmagical object that is a suit of armor or a simple or martial weapon. Until the end of your next long rest or until you die, the object becomes a magic item, granting a +1 bonus to AC if it's armor or a +1 bonus to attack and damage rolls if it's a weapon.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 19</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Artisan's Blessing (Forge Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can use your Channel Divinity to create simple items.
	You conduct an hour-long ritual that crafts a nonmagical item that must include some metal: a simple or martial weapon, a suit of armor, ten pieces of ammunition, a set of tools, or another metal object (see chapter 5, "Equipment," in the Player's Handbook for examples of these items). The creation is completed at the end of the hour, coalescing in an unoccupied space of your choice on a surface within 5 feet of you.
	The thing you create can be something that is worth no more than 100 gp. As part of this ritual, you must lay out metal, which can include coins, with a value equal to the creation. The metal irretrievably coalesces and transforms into the creation at the ritual's end, magically forming even nonmetal parts of the creation. The ritual can create a duplicate of a nonmagical item that contains metal, such as a key, if you possess the original during the ritual.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 19</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Soul of the Forge (Forge Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, your mastery of the forge grants you special abilities:

	• You gain resistance to fire damage.

	• While wearing heavy armor, you gain a +1 bonus to AC.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 19</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Strike (Forge Domain)</name>
        <text>At 8th level, you gain the ability to infuse your weapon strikes with the fiery power of the forge. Once on each of your turns when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can cause the attack to deal an extra 1d8 fire damage to the target. When you reach 14th level, the extra damage increases to 2d8.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 19</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Saint of Forge and Fire (Forge Domain)</name>
        <text>At 17th level, your blessed affinity with fire and metal becomes more powerful:

	• You gain immunity to fire damage

	• While wearing heavy armor, you have resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage from nonmagical attacks.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 19</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Divine Domain: Grave Domain -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Domain: Grave Domain</name>
        <text>Gods of the grave watch over the line between life and death. To these deities, death and the afterlife are a foundational part of the multiverse. To desecrate the peace of the dead is an abomination. Deities of the grave include Kelemvor, Wee Jas, the ancestral spirits of the Undying Court, Hades, Anubis, and Osiris. Followers of these deities seek to put wandering spirits to rest, destroy the undead, and ease the suffering of the dying. Their magic also allows them to stave off death for a time, particularly for a person who still has some great work to accomplish in the world. This is a delay of death, not a denial of it, for death will eventually get its due.

Domain Spells:
At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared. They do not count towards your limit.

Grave Domain Spells:
Cleric Level | Spells
1st | bane, false life
3rd | gentle repose, ray of enfeeblement
5th | revivify, vampiric touch
7th | blight, death ward
9th | antilife shell, raise dead

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 19</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Circle of Mortality (Grave Domain)</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you gain the ability to manipulate the line between life and death. When you would normally roll one or more dice to restore hit points with a spell to a creature at 0 hit points, you instead use the highest number possible for each die.
	In addition, you learn the spare the dying cantrip, which doesn't count against the number of cleric cantrips you know. For you, it has a range of 30 feet, and you can cast it as a bonus action.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 20</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Eyes of the Grave (Grave Domain)</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you gain the ability to occasionally sense the presence of the undead, whose existence is an insult to the natural cycle of life. As an action, you can open your awareness to magically detect undead. Until the end of your next turn, you know the location of any undead within 60 feet of you that isn't behind total cover and that isn't protected from divination magic. This sense doesn't tell you anything about a creature's capabilities or identity.
	You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 20</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Channel Divinity: Path to the Grave (Grave Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can use your Channel Divinity to mark another creature's life force for termination.
	As an action, you choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of you, cursing it until the end of your next turn. The next time you or an ally of yours hits the cursed creature with an attack, the creature has vulnerability to all of that attack's damage, and then the curse ends.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 20</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sentinel at Death's Door (Grave Domain)</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to impede death's progress. As a reaction when you or a creature you can see within 30 feet of you suffers a critical hit, you can turn that hit into a normal hit. Any effects triggered by a critical hit are canceled.
	You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 20</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Potent Spellcasting (Grave Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 8th level, you add your Wisdom modifier to the damage you deal with any cleric cantrip.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 20</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Keeper of Souls (Grave Domain)</name>
        <text>Starting at 17th level, you can seize a trace of vitality from a parting soul and use it to heal the living. When an enemy you can see dies within 60 feet of you, you or one creature of your choice that is within 60 feet of you regains hit points equal to the enemy's number of Hit Dice. You can use this feature only if you aren't incapacitated. Once you use it, you can't do so again until the start of your next turn.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 20</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
