<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Wizard</name>
    <trait>
      <name>Xanathar's Guide to Everything</name>
      <text>"Wizardry requires understanding. The knowledge of how and why magic works, and our efforts to broaden that understanding, have brought about the key advances in civilization over the centuries."
— Gimble the illusionist

Only a select few people in the world are wielders of magic. Of all those, wizards stand at the pinnacle of the craft. Even the least of them can manipulate forces that flout the laws of nature, and the most accomplished among them can cast spells with world-shaking effects.
	The price that wizards pay for their mastery is that most valuable of commodities: time. It takes years of study, instruction, and experimentation to learn how to harness magical energy and carry spells around in one's own mind. For adventuring wizards and other spellcasters who aspire to the highest echelons of the profession, the studying never ends, nor does the quest for knowledge and power.
	If you're playing a wizard, take advantage of the opportunity to make your character more than just a stereotypical spell-slinger. Use the advice that follows to add some intriguing details to how your wizard interacts with the world.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 58</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spellbook</name>
      <text>Your wizard character's most prized possession—your spellbook—might be an innocuous-looking volume whose covers show no hint of what's inside. Or you might display some flair, as many wizards do, by carrying a spellbook of an unusual sort. If you don't own such an item already, one of your goals might be to find a spellbook that sets you apart by its appearance or its means of manufacture.

Spellbooks:
d6 | Spellbook
1 | A tome with pages that are thin sheets of metal, spells etched into them with acid
2 | Long straps of leather on which spells are written, wrapped around a staff for ease of transport
3 | A battered tome filled with pictographs that only you can understand
4 | Small stones inscribed with spells and kept in a cloth bag
5 | A scorched book, ravaged by dragon fire, with the script of your spells barely visible on its pages
6 | A tome full of black pages whose writing is visible only in dim light or darkness</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ambition</name>
      <text>Few aspiring wizards undertake the study of magic without some personal goal in mind. Many wizards use their spells as a tool to produce a tangible benefit, in material goods or in status, for themselves or their companions. For others, the theoretical aspect of magic might have a strong appeal, pushing those wizards to seek out knowledge that supports new theories of the arcane or confirms old ones.
	Beyond the obvious, why does your wizard character study magic, and what do you want to achieve? If you haven't given these questions much thought, you can do so now, and the answers you come up with will likely affect how your future unfolds.

Ambitions:
d6 | Ambition
1 | You will prove that the gods aren't as powerful as folk believe.
2 | Immortality is the end goal of your studies.
3 | If you can fully understand magic, you can unlock its use for all and usher in an era of equality.
4 | Magic is a dangerous tool. You use it to protect what you treasure.
5 | Arcane power must be taken away from those who would abuse it.
6 | You will become the greatest wizard the world has seen in generations.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Eccentricity</name>
      <text>Endless hours of solitary study and research can have a negative effect on anyone's social skills. Wizards, who are a breed apart to begin with, are no exception. An odd mannerism or two is not necessarily a drawback, though; an eccentricity of this sort is usually harmless and could provide a source of amusement or serve as a calling card of sorts.
	If your character has an eccentricity, is it a physical tic or a mental one? Are you well known in some circles because of it? Do you fight to overcome it, or do you embrace this minor claim to fame of yours?

Eccentricities:
d6 | Eccentricity
1 | You have the habit of tapping your foot incessantly, which often annoys those around you.
2 | Your memory is quite good, but you have no trouble pretending to be absentminded when it suits your purposes.
3 | You never enter a room without looking to see what's hanging from the ceiling.
4 | Your most prized possession is a dead worm that you keep inside a potion vial.
5 | When you want people to leave you alone, you start talking to yourself. That usually does the trick.
6 | Your fashion sense and grooming, or more accurately lack thereof, sometimes cause others to assume you are a beggar.</text>
    </trait>
    <!-- Arcane Tradition: War Magic -->
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Arcane Tradition: War Magic</name>
        <text>A variety of arcane colleges specialize in training wizards for war. The tradition of War Magic blends principles of evocation and abjuration, rather than specializing in either of those schools. It teaches techniques that empower a caster's spells, while also providing methods for wizards to bolster their own defenses.
	Followers of this tradition are known as war mages. They see their magic as both a weapon and armor, a resource superior to any piece of steel. War mages act fast in battle, using their spells to seize tactical control of a situation. Their spells strike hard, while their defensive skills foil their opponents' attempts to counterattack. War mages are also adept at turning other spellcasters' magical energy against them.
	In great battles, a war mage often works with evokers, abjurers, and other types of wizards. Evokers, in particular, sometimes tease war mages for splitting their attention between offense and defense. A war mage's typical response: "What good is being able to throw a mighty fireball if I die before I can cast it?"

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 59</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Arcane Deflection (War Magic)</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you have learned to weave your magic to fortify yourself against harm. When you are hit by an attack or you fail a saving throw, you can use your reaction to gain a +2 bonus to your AC against that attack or a +4 bonus to that saving throw.
	When you use this feature, you can't cast spells other than cantrips until the end of your next turn.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 59</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Tactical Wit (War Magic)</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, your keen ability to assess tactical situations allows you to act quickly in battle. You can give yourself a bonus to your initiative rolls equal to your Intelligence modifier.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 59</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Power Surge (War Magic)</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can store magical energy within yourself to later empower your damaging spells. In its stored form, this energy is called a power surge.
	You can store a maximum number of power surges equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of one). Whenever you finish a long rest, your number of power surges resets to one. Whenever you successfully end a spell with dispel magic or counterspell, you gain one power surge, as you steal magic from the spell you foiled. If you end a short rest with no power surges, you gain one power surge.
	Once per turn when you deal damage to a creature or object with a wizard spell, you can spend one power surge to deal extra force damage to that target. The extra damage equals half your wizard level.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 59</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Durable Magic (War Magic)</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, the magic you channel helps ward off harm. While you maintain concentration on a spell, you have a +2 bonus to AC and all saving throws.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 59</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Deflecting Shroud (War Magic)</name>
        <text>At 14th level, your Arcane Deflection becomes infused with deadly magic. When you use your Arcane Deflection feature, you can cause magical energy to arc from you. Up to three creatures of your choice that you can see within 60 feet of you each take force damage equal to half your wizard level.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 59</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
