<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Barbarian</name>
    <trait>
      <name>Xanathar's Guide to Everything</name>
      <text>"I have witnessed the indomitable performance of barbarians on the field of battle, and it makes me wonder what force lies at the heart of their rage."
— Seret, archwizard

The anger felt by a normal person resembles the rage of a barbarian in the same way that a gentle breeze is akin to a furious thunderstorm. The barbarian's driving force comes from a place that transcends mere emotion, making its manifestation all the more terrible. Whether the impetus for the fury comes entirely from within or from forging a link with a spirit animal, a raging barbarian becomes able to perform supernatural feats of strength and endurance. The outburst is temporary, but while it lasts, it takes over body and mind, driving the barbarian on despite peril and injury, until the last enemy falls.

It can be tempting to play a barbarian character that is a straightforward application of the classic archetype—a brute, and usually a dimwitted one at that, who rushes in where others fear to tread. But not all the barbarians in the world are cut from that cloth, so you can certainly put your own spin on things. Either way, consider adding some flourishes to make your barbarian stand out from all others; see the following sections for some ideas.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 8</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Personal Totems</name>
      <text>Barbarians tend to travel light, carrying little in the way of personal effects or other unnecessary gear. The few possessions they do carry often include small items that have special significance. A personal totem is significant because it has a mystical origin or is tied to an important moment in the character's life—perhaps a remembrance from the barbarian's past or a harbinger of what lies ahead.

A personal totem of this sort might be associated with a barbarian's spirit animal, or might actually be the totem object for the animal, but such a connection is not essential. One who has a bear totem spirit, for instance, could still carry an eagle's feather as a personal totem.

Consider creating one or more personal totems for your character—objects that hold a special link to your character's past or future. Think about how a totem might affect your character's actions.

Personal Totems:
d6 | Totem
1 | A tuft of fur from a solitary wolf that you befriended during a hunt
2 | Three eagle feathers given to you by a wise shaman, who told you they would play a role in determining your fate
3 | A necklace made from the claws of a young cave bear that you slew singlehandedly as a child
4 | A small leather pouch holding three stones that represent your ancestors
5 | A few small bones from the first beast you killed, tied together with colored wool
6 | An egg-sized stone in the shape of your spirit animal that appeared one day in your belt pouch</text>
      <roll>1d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Tattoos</name>
      <text>The members of many barbarian clans decorate their bodies with tattoos, each of which represents a significant moment in the life of the bearer or the bearer's ancestors, or which symbolizes a feeling or an attitude. As with personal totems, a barbarian's tattoos might or might not be related to an animal spirit.

Each tattoo a barbarian displays contributes to that individual's identity. If your character wears tattoos, what do they look like, and what do they represent?

Tattoos:
d6 | Tattoo
1 | The wings of an eagle are spread wide across your upper back.
2 | Etched on the backs of your hands are the paws of a cave bear.
3 | The symbols of your clan are displayed in viny patterns along your arms.
4 | The antlers of an elk are inked across your back.
5 | Images of your spirit animal are tattooed along your weapon arm and hand.
6 | The eyes of a wolf are marked on your back to help you see and ward off evil spirits.</text>
      <roll>1d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Superstitions</name>
      <text>Barbarians vary widely in how they understand life. Some follow gods and look for guidance from those deities in the cycles of nature and the animals they encounter. These barbarians believe that spirits inhabit the plants and animals of the world, and the barbarians look to them for omens and power.

Other barbarians trust only in the blood that runs in their veins and the steel they hold in their hands. They have no use for the invisible world, instead relying on their senses to hunt and survive like the wild beasts they emulate.

Both of these attitudes can give rise to superstitions. These beliefs are often passed down within a family or shared among the members of a clan or a hunting group.

If your barbarian character has any superstitions, were they ingrained in you by your family, or are they the result of personal experience?

Superstition:
d6 | Superstition
1 | If you disturb the bones of the dead, you inherit all the troubles that plagued them in life.
2 | Never trust a wizard. They're all devils in disguise, especially the friendly ones.
3 | Dwarves have lost their spirits, and are almost like the undead. That's why they live underground.
4 | Magical things bring trouble. Never sleep with a magic object within ten feet of you.
5 | When you walk through a graveyard, be sure to wear silver, or a ghost might jump into your body.
6 | If an elf looks you in the eyes, she's trying to read your thoughts.</text>
      <roll>1d6</roll>
    </trait>
    <!-- Primal Path: Path of the Ancestral Guardian -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Primal Path: Path of the Ancestral Guardian</name>
        <text>Some barbarians hail from cultures that revere their ancestors. These tribes teach that the warriors of the past linger in the world as mighty spirits, who can guide and protect the living. When a barbarian who follows this path rages, the barbarian contacts the spirit world and calls on these guardian spirits for aid.
	Barbarians who draw on their ancestral guardians can better fight to protect their tribes and their allies. In order to cement ties to their ancestral guardians, barbarians who follow this path cover themselves in elaborate tattoos that celebrate their ancestors' deeds. These tattoos tell sagas of victories against terrible monsters and other fearsome rivals.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 9</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ancestral Protectors (Path of the Ancestral Guardian)</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this path at 3rd level, spectral warriors appear when you enter your rage. While you're raging, the first creature you hit with an attack on your turn becomes the target of the warriors, which hinder its attacks. Until the start of your next turn, that target has disadvantage on any attack roll that isn't against you, and when the target hits a creature other than you with an attack, that creature has resistance to the damage dealt by the attack. The effect on the target ends early if your rage ends.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 10</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Spirit Shield (Path of the Ancestral Guardian)</name>
        <text>Beginning at 6th level, the guardian spirits that aid you can provide supernatural protection to those you defend. If you are raging and another creature you can see within 30 feet of you takes damage, you can use your reaction to reduce that damage by 2d6.
	When you reach certain levels in this class, you can reduce the damage by more: by 3d6 at 10th level and by 4d6 at 14th level.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 9</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Consult the Spirits (Path of the Ancestral Guardian)</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you gain the ability to consult with your ancestral spirits. When you do so, you cast the augury or clairvoyance spell, without using a spell slot or material components. Rather than creating a spherical sensor, this use of clairvoyance invisibly summons one of your ancestral spirits to the chosen location. Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for these spells.
	After you cast either spell in this way, you can't use this feature again until you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 10</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Consult Spirits</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
        <subclass>Path of the Ancestral Guardian</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Vengeful Ancestors (Path of the Ancestral Guardian)</name>
        <text>At 14th level, your ancestral spirits grow powerful enough to retaliate. When you use your Spirit Shield to reduce the damage of an attack, the attacker takes an amount of force damage equal to the damage that your Spirit Shield prevents.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 9</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Primal Path: Path of the Storm Herald -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Primal Path: Path of the Storm Herald</name>
        <text>All barbarians harbor a fury within. Their rage grants them superior strength, durability, and speed. Barbarians who follow the Path of the Storm Herald learn to transform that rage into a mantle of primal magic, which swirls around them. When in a fury, a barbarian of this path taps into the forces of nature to create powerful magical effects.
	Storm heralds are typically elite champions who train alongside druids, rangers, and others sworn to protect nature. Other storm heralds hone their craft in lodges in regions wracked by storms, in the frozen reaches at the world's end, or deep in the hottest deserts.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 10</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Storm Aura (Path of the Storm Herald)</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you emanate a stormy, magical aura while you rage. The aura extends 10 feet from you in every direction, but not through total cover.
	Your aura has an effect that activates when you enter your rage, and you can activate the effect again on each of your turns as a bonus action. Choose desert, sea, or tundra. Your aura's effect depends on that chosen environment, as detailed below. You can change your environment choice whenever you gain a level in this class.
	If your aura's effects require a saving throw, the DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Constitution modifier.

Desert. When this effect is activated, all other creatures in your aura take 2 fire damage each. The damage increases when you reach certain levels in this class, increasing to 3 at 5th level, 4 at 10th level, 5 at 15th level, and 6 at 20th level.

Sea. When this effect is activated, you can choose one other creature you can see in your aura. The target must make a Dexterity saving throw. The target takes 1d6 lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. The damage increases when you reach certain levels in this class, increasing to 2d6 at 10th level, 3d6 at 15th level, and 4d6 at 20th level.

Tundra. When this effect is activated, each creature of your choice in your aura gains 2 temporary hit points, as icy spirits inure it to suffering. The temporary hit points increase when you reach certain levels in this class, increasing to 3 at 5th level, 4 at 10th level, 5 at 15th level, and 6 at 20th level.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 10</text>
        <roll description="Lightning Damage" level="3">1d6</roll>
        <roll description="Lightning Damage" level="10">2d6</roll>
        <roll description="Lightning Damage" level="15">3d6</roll>
        <roll description="Lightning Damage" level="20">4d6</roll>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Storm Soul (Path of the Storm Herald)</name>
        <text>At 6th level, the storm grants you benefits even when your aura isn't active. The benefits are based on the environment you chose for your Storm Aura.

Desert. You gain resistance to fire damage, and you don't suffer the effects of extreme heat, as described in the Dungeon Master's Guide. Moreover, as an action, you can touch a flammable object that isn't being worn or carried by anyone else and set it on fire.

Sea. You gain resistance to lightning damage, and you can breathe underwater. You also gain a swimming speed of 30 feet.

Tundra. You gain resistance to cold damage, and you don't suffer the effects of extreme cold, as described in the Dungeon Master's Guide. Moreover, as an action, you can touch water and turn a 5-foot cube of it into ice, which melts after 1 minute. This action fails if a creature is in the cube.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 10</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Shielding Storm (Path of the Storm Herald)</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you learn to use your mastery of the storm to protect others. Each creature of your choice has the damage resistance you gained from the Storm Soul feature while the creature is in your Storm Aura.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 10</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Raging Storm (Path of the Storm Herald)</name>
        <text>At 14th level, the power of the storm you channel grows mightier, lashing out at your foes. The effect is based on the environment you chose for your Storm Aura.

Desert. Immediately after a creature in your aura hits you with an attack, you can use your reaction to force that creature to make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, the creature takes fire damage equal to half your barbarian level.

Sea. When you hit a creature in your aura with an attack, you can use your reaction to force that creature to make a Strength saving throw. On a failed save, the creature is knocked prone, as if struck by a wave.

Tundra. Whenever the effect of your Storm Aura is activated, you can choose one creature you can see in the aura. That creature must succeed on a Strength saving throw, or its speed is reduced to 0 until the start of your next turn, as magical frost covers it.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 10</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Primal Path: Path of the Zealot -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Primal Path: Path of the Zealot</name>
        <text>Some deities inspire their followers to pitch themselves into a ferocious battle fury. These barbarians are zealots—warriors who channel their rage into powerful displays of divine power.
	A variety of gods across the worlds of D&amp;D inspire their followers to embrace this path. Tempus from the Forgotten Realms and Hextor and Erythnul of Greyhawk are all prime examples. In general, the gods who inspire zealots are deities of combat, destruction, and violence. Not all are evil, but few are good.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 11</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Fury (Path of the Zealot)</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this path at 3rd level, you can channel divine fury into your weapon strikes. While you're raging, the first creature you hit on each of your turns with a weapon attack takes extra damage equal to 1d6 + half your barbarian level. The extra damage is necrotic or radiant; you choose the type of damage when you gain this feature.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 11</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Warrior of the Gods (Path of the Zealot)</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, your soul is marked for endless battle. If a spell, such as raise dead, has the sole effect of restoring you to life (but not undeath), the caster doesn't need material components to cast the spell on you.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Fanatical Focus (Path of the Zealot)</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, the divine power that fuels your rage can protect you. If you fail a saving throw while you're raging, you can reroll it, and you must use the new roll. You can use this ability only once per rage.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Zealous Presence (Path of the Zealot)</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you learn to channel divine power to inspire zealotry in others. As a bonus action, you unleash a battle cry infused with divine energy. Up to ten other creatures of your choice within 60 feet of you that can hear you gain advantage on attack rolls and saving throws until the start of your next turn.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 11</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Zealous Presence</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>Path of the Zealot</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Rage beyond Death (Path of the Zealot)</name>
        <text>Beginning at 14th level, the divine power that fuels your rage allows you to shrug off fatal blows.
	While you're raging, having 0 hit points doesn't knock you unconscious. You still must make death saving throws, and you suffer the normal effects of taking damage while at 0 hit points. However, if you would die due to failing death saving throws, you don't die until your rage ends, and you die then only if you still have 0 hit points.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 11</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
