<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Ranger</name>
    <trait>
      <name>Xanathar's Guide to Everything</name>
      <text>"I spend a lot of my life away from civilization, keeping to its fringes to protect it. Don't assume that because I don't bend the knee to your king that I haven't done more to protect him than all his knights put together."
— Soveliss

Rangers are free-minded wanderers and seekers who patrol the edges of civilized territory, turning back the denizens of the wild lands beyond. It is a thankless job, since their efforts are rarely understood and almost never rewarded. Yet rangers persist in their duties, never doubting that their work makes the world a safer place.
	A relationship with civilization informs every ranger's personality and history. Some rangers see themselves as enforcers of the law and bringers of justice on civilization's frontier, answering to no sovereign power. Others are survivalists who eschew civilization altogether. They vanquish monsters to keep themselves safe while they live in and travel through the perilous wild areas of the world. If their efforts also benefit the kingdoms and other civilized realms that they avoid, so be it.
	If you're creating or playing a ranger character, the following sections offer ideas for embellishing the character and enhancing your roleplaying experience.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 40</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>View of the World</name>
      <text>A ranger's view of the world begins (and sometimes ends) with that character's outlook toward civilized folk and the places they occupy. Some rangers have an attitude toward civilization that's deeply rooted in disdain, while others pity the people they have sworn to protect—though on the battlefield, it's impossible to tell the difference between one ranger and another. Indeed, to those who have seen them operate and been the beneficiaries of their prowess, it scarcely matters why rangers do what they do. That said, no two rangers are likely to express their opinions on any matter in the same way.
	If you haven't yet thought about the details of your character's worldview, consider putting a finer point on things by summarizing that viewpoint in a short statement (such as the entries on the following table). How might that feeling affect the way you conduct yourself?

View of the World:
d6 | View
1 | Towns and cities are the best places for those who can't survive on their own.
2 | The advancement of civilization is the best way to thwart chaos, but its reach must be monitored.
3 | Towns and cities are a necessary evil, but once the wilderness is purged of supernatural threats, we will need them no more.
4 | Walls are for cowards, who huddle behind them while others do the work of making the world safe.
5 | Visiting a town is not unpleasant, but after a few days I feel the irresistible call to return to the wild.
6 | Cities breed weakness by isolating folk from the harsh lessons of the wild.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Homelands</name>
      <text>All rangers, regardless of how they came to take up the profession, have a strong connection to the natural world and its various terrains. For some rangers, the wilderness is where they grew up, either as a result of being born there or moving there at a young age. For other rangers, civilization was originally home, but the wilderness became a second homeland.
	Think of your character's backstory and decide what terrain feels most like home, whether or not you were born there. What does that terrain say about your personality? Does it influence which spells you choose to learn? Have your experiences there shaped who your favored enemies are?

Homelands:
d6 | Homeland
1 | You patrolled an ancient forest, darkened and corrupted by several crossings to the Shadowfell.
2 | As part of a group of nomads, you acquired the skills for surviving in the desert.
3 | Your early life in the Underdark prepared you for the challenges of combating its denizens.
4 | You dwelled on the edge of a swamp, in an area imperiled by land creatures as well as aquatic ones.
5 | Because you grew up among the peaks, finding the best path through the mountains is second nature to you.
6 | You wandered the far north, learning how to protect yourself and prosper in a realm overrun by ice.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Sworn Enemy</name>
      <text>Every ranger begins with a favored enemy (or two). The determination of a favored enemy might be tied to a specific event in the character's early life, or it might be entirely a matter of choice.
	What spurred your character to select a particular enemy? Was the choice made because of tradition or curiosity, or do you have a grudge to settle?

Sworn Enemies:
d6 | Enemy
1 | You seek revenge on nature's behalf for the great transgressions your foe has committed.
2 | Your forebears or predecessors fought these creatures, and so shall you.
3 | You bear no enmity toward your foe. You stalk such creatures as a hunter tracks down a wild animal.
4 | You find your foe fascinating, and you collect books of tales and history concerning it.
5 | You collect tokens of your fallen enemies to remind you of each kill.
6 | You respect your chosen enemy, and you see your battles as a test of respective skills.</text>
    </trait>
    <!-- Ranger Archetype: Gloom Stalker -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ranger Archetype: Gloom Stalker</name>
        <text>Gloom Stalkers are at home in the darkest places: deep under the earth, in gloomy alleyways, in primeval forests, and wherever else the light dims. Most folk enter such places with trepidation, but a Gloom Stalker ventures boldly into the darkness, seeking to ambush threats before they can reach the broader world. Such rangers are often found in the Underdark, but they will go any place where evil lurks in the shadows.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Gloom Stalker Magic (Gloom Stalker)</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Gloom Stalker Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.

Gloom Stalker Spells:
Ranger Level | Spells
3rd | disguise self
5th | rope trick
9th | fear
13th | greater invisibility
17th | seeming

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Dread Ambusher (Gloom Stalker)</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you master the art of the ambush. You can give yourself a bonus to your initiative rolls equal to your Wisdom modifier.
	At the start of your first turn of each combat, your walking speed increases by 10 feet, which lasts until the end of that turn. If you take the Attack action on that turn, you can make one additional weapon attack as part of that action. If that attack hits, the target takes an extra 1d8 damage of the weapon's damage type.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Umbral Sight (Gloom Stalker)</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain darkvision out to a range of 60 feet. If you already have darkvision from your race, its range increases by 30 feet.
	You are also adept at evading creatures that rely on darkvision. While in darkness, you are invisible to any creature that relies on darkvision to see you in that darkness.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Iron Mind (Gloom Stalker)</name>
        <text>By 7th level, you have honed your ability to resist the mind-altering powers of your prey. You gain proficiency in Wisdom saving throws. If you already have this proficiency, you instead gain proficiency in Intelligence or Charisma saving throws (your choice).

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        <proficiency>Wisdom</proficiency>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Stalker's Flurry (Gloom Stalker)</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you learn to attack with such unexpected speed that you can turn a miss into another strike. Once on each of your turns when you miss with a weapon attack, you can make another weapon attack as part of the same action.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Shadowy Dodge (Gloom Stalker)</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, you can dodge in unforeseen ways, with wisps of supernatural shadow around you. Whenever a creature makes an attack roll against you and doesn't have advantage on the roll, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on it. You must use this feature before you know the outcome of the attack roll.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Ranger Archetype: Horizon Walker -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ranger Archetype: Horizon Walker</name>
        <text>Horizon Walkers guard the world against threats that originate from other planes or that seek to ravage the mortal realm with otherworldly magic. They seek out planar portals and keep watch over them, venturing to the Inner Planes and the Outer Planes as needed to pursue their foes. These rangers are also friends to any forces in the multiverse—especially benevolent dragons, fey, and elementals—that work to preserve life and the order of the planes.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Horizon Walker Magic (Horizon Walker)</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Horizon Walker Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.

Horizon Walker Spells:
Ranger Level | Spells
3rd | protection from evil and good
5th | misty step
9th | haste
13th | banishment
17th | teleportation circle

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Detect Portal (Horizon Walker)</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain the ability to magically sense the presence of a planar portal. As an action, you detect the distance and direction to the closest planar portal within 1 mile of you.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.
	See the "Planar Travel" section in chapter 2 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for examples of planar portals.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Planar Warrior (Horizon Walker)</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn to draw on the energy of the multiverse to augment your attacks.
	As a bonus action, choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of you. The next time you hit that creature on this turn with a weapon attack, all damage dealt by the attack becomes force damage, and the creature takes an extra 1d8 force damage from the attack. When you reach 11th level in this class, the extra damage increases to 2d8.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Detect Portal</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
        <subclass>Horizon Walker</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ethereal Step (Horizon Walker)</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn to step through the Ethereal Plane. As a bonus action, you can cast the etherealness spell with this feature, without expending a spell slot, but the spell ends at the end of the current turn.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Ethereal Step</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
        <subclass>Horizon Walker</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Distant Strike (Horizon Walker)</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to pass between the planes in the blink of an eye. When you take the Attack action, you can teleport up to 10 feet before each attack to an unoccupied space you can see.
	If you attack at least two different creatures with the action, you can make one additional attack with it against a third creature.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Spectral Defense (Horizon Walker)</name>
        <text>At 15th level, your ability to move between planes enables you to slip through the planar boundaries to lessen the harm done to you during battle. When you take damage from an attack, you can use your reaction to give yourself resistance to all of that attack's damage on this turn.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Ranger Archetype: Monster Slayer -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ranger Archetype: Monster Slayer</name>
        <text>You have dedicated yourself to hunting down creatures of the night and wielders of grim magic. A Monster Slayer seeks out vampires, dragons, evil fey, fiends, and other magical threats. Trained in supernatural techniques to overcome such monsters, slayers are experts at unearthing and defeating mighty, mystical foes.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Monster Slayer Magic (Monster Slayer)</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Monster Slayer Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.

Monster Slayer Spells:
Ranger Level | Spells
3rd | protection from evil and good
5th | zone of truth
9th | magic circle
13th | banishment
17th | hold monster

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Hunter's Sense (Monster Slayer)</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain the ability to peer at a creature and magically discern how best to hurt it. As an action, choose one creature you can see within 60 feet of you. You immediately learn whether the creature has any damage immunities, resistances, or vulnerabilities and what they are. If the creature is hidden from divination magic, you sense that it has no damage immunities, resistances, or vulnerabilities.
	You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once). You regain all expended uses of it when you finish a long rest.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Slayer's Prey (Monster Slayer)</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you can focus your ire on one foe, increasing the harm you inflict on it. As a bonus action, you designate one creature you can see within 60 feet of you as the target of this feature. The first time each turn that you hit that target with a weapon attack, it takes an extra 1d6 damage from the weapon.
	This benefit lasts until you finish a short or long rest. It ends early if you designate a different creature.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Supernatural Defense (Monster Slayer)</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain extra resilience against your prey's assaults on your mind and body. Whenever the target of your Slayer's Prey forces you to make a saving throw and whenever you make an ability check to escape that target's grapple, add 1d6 to your roll.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Magic-User's Nemesis (Monster Slayer)</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to thwart someone else's magic. When you see a creature casting a spell or teleporting within 60 feet of you, you can use your reaction to try to magically foil it. The creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC, or its spell or teleport fails and is wasted.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Magic-User's Nemesis</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
        <subclass>Monster Slayer</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Slayer's Counter (Monster Slayer)</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you gain the ability to counterattack when your prey tries to sabotage you. If the target of your Slayer's Prey forces you to make a saving throw, you can use your reaction to make one weapon attack against the quarry. You make this attack immediately before making the saving throw. If your attack hits, your save automatically succeeds, in addition to the attack's normal effects.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
