<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Sorcerer</name>
    <trait>
      <name>Xanathar's Guide to Everything</name>
      <text>"Practice and study are for amateurs. True power is a birthright."
— Hennet, scion of Tiamat

When it comes to drawing forth their abilities in times of need, sorcerers have it easy compared to other characters. Their power not only rests within them, but it likely takes some effort to keep it at bay. Every sorcerer is born to the role, or stumbles into it through cosmic chance. Unlike other characters, who must actively learn, embrace, and pursue their talents, sorcerers have their power thrust upon them.
	Because the idea of an innately magical being traveling among them does not sit well with many folk, sorcerers tend to breed mistrust and suspicion in others they come across. Nonetheless, many sorcerers succeed in overcoming that prejudice through deeds that benefit their less magically gifted contemporaries.
	Sorcerers are often defined by the events surrounding the manifestation of their power. For those who receive it as an expected birthright, its appearance is a cause for celebration. Other sorcerers are treated as outcasts, banished from their homes after the sudden, terrifying arrival of their abilities.
	Playing a sorcerer character can be as rewarding as it is challenging. The sections below offer suggestions on how to flesh out and personalize your persona.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 48</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Arcane Origins</name>
      <text>Some sorcerers understand where their power came from, based on how their abilities manifested. Others can only speculate, since their powers came to them in a way that suggests no particular cause.
	Does your character know the source of your magical power? Does it tie back to some distant relative, a cosmic event, or blind chance? If your sorcerer doesn't know where their power arose from, your DM can use this table (or select an origin) and reveal it to you when the information plays a role in the campaign.

Arcane Origins:
d6 | Origin
1 | Your power arises from your family's bloodline. You are related to some powerful creature, or you inherited a blessing or a curse.
2 | You are the reincarnation of a being from another plane of existence.
3 | A powerful entity entered the world. Its magic changed you.
4 | Your birth was prophesied in an ancient text, and you are foretold to use your power for terrible ends.
5 | You are the product of generations of careful, selective breeding.
6 | You were made in a vat by an alchemist.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Reaction</name>
      <text>When a new sorcerer enters the world, either at birth or later when one's power becomes evident, the consequences of that event depend greatly on how its witnesses react to what they have seen.
	When your sorcerer's powers appeared, how did the world around you respond? Were other people supportive, fearful, or somewhere in between?

Reactions:
d6 | Reaction
1 | Your powers are seen as a great blessing by those around you, and you are expected to use them in service to your community.
2 | Your powers caused destruction and even a death when they became evident, and you were treated as a criminal.
3 | Your neighbors hate and fear your power, causing them to shun you.
4 | You came to the attention of a sinister cult that plans on exploiting your abilities.
5 | People around you believe that your powers are a curse levied on your family for a past transgression.
6 | Your powers are believed to be tied to an ancient line of mad kings that supposedly ended in a bloody revolt over a century ago.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Supernatural Mark</name>
      <text>A sorcerer at rest is almost indistinguishable from a normal person; it's only when their magic flies forth that sorcerers reveal their true nature. Even so, many sorcerers have a subtle but telling physical trait that sets them apart from other folk.
	If your sorcerer has a supernatural mark, it might be one that's easily concealed, or it could be a source of pride that you keep on constant display.

Supernatural Marks:
d6 | Mark
1 | Your eyes are an unusual color, such as red.
2 | You have an extra toe on one foot.
3 | One of your ears is noticeably larger than the other.
4 | Your hair grows at a prodigious rate.
5 | You wrinkle your nose repeatedly while you are chewing.
6 | A red splotch appears on your neck once a day, then vanishes after an hour.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Signs of Sorcery</name>
      <text>As the world well knows, some sorcerers are better than others at controlling their spellcasting. Sometimes a wild display of magic gone awry emanates from a sorcerer who casts a spell. But even when one's magic goes off as planned, the act of casting is often accompanied by a telltale sign that makes it clear where that magical energy came from.
	When your sorcerer character casts a spell, does the effort reveal itself in a sign of sorcery? Is this sign tied to your origin or some other aspect of who you are, or is it a seemingly random phenomenon?

Signs of Sorcery:
d6 | Sign
1 | You deliver the verbal components of your spells in the booming voice of a titan.
2 | For a moment after you cast a spell, the area around you grows dark and gloomy.
3 | You sweat profusely while casting a spell and for a few seconds thereafter.
4 | Your hair and garments are briefly buffeted about, as if by a breeze, whenever you call forth a spell.
5 | If you are standing when you cast a spell, you rise six inches into the air and gently float back down.
6 | Illusory blue flames wreathe your head as you begin your casting, then abruptly disappear.</text>
    </trait>
    <!-- Sorcerous Origin: Divine Soul -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sorcerous Origin: Divine Soul</name>
        <text>Sometimes the spark of magic that fuels a sorcerer comes from a divine source that glimmers within the soul. Having such a blessed soul is a sign that your innate magic might come from a distant but powerful familial connection to a divine being. Perhaps your ancestor was an angel, transformed into a mortal and sent to fight in a god's name.
	Or your birth might align with an ancient prophecy, marking you as a servant of the gods or a chosen vessel of divine magic.
	A Divine Soul, with a natural magnetism, is seen as a threat by some religious hierarchies. As an outsider who commands sacred power, a Divine Soul can undermine an existing order by claiming a direct tie to the divine.
	In some cultures, only those who can claim the power of a Divine Soul may command religious power. In these lands, ecclesiastical positions are dominated by a few bloodlines and preserved over generations.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Divine Magic (Divine Soul)</name>
        <text>Your link to the divine allows you to learn spells from the cleric class. When your Spellcasting feature lets you learn or replace a sorcerer cantrip or a sorcerer spell of 1st level or higher, you can choose the new spell from the cleric spell list or the sorcerer spell list. You must otherwise obey all the restrictions for selecting the spell, and it becomes a sorcerer spell for you.
	In addition, choose an affinity for the source of your divine power: good, evil, law, chaos, or neutrality. You learn an additional spell based on that affinity, as shown below. It is a sorcerer spell for you, but it doesn't count against your number of sorcerer spells known. If you later replace this spell, you must replace it with a spell from the cleric spell list.

Divine Soul Spells:
Affinity | Spell
Good | cure wounds
Evil | inflict wounds
Law | bless
Chaos | bane
Neutrality | protection from evil and good

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Favored by the Gods (Divine Soul)</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, divine power guards your destiny. If you fail a saving throw or miss with an attack roll, you can roll 2d4 and add it to the total, possibly changing the outcome. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Favored by Gods</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
        <subclass>Divine Soul</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Empowered Healing (Divine Soul)</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, the divine energy coursing through you can empower healing spells. Whenever you or an ally within 5 feet of you rolls dice to determine the number of hit points a spell restores, you can spend 1 sorcery point to reroll any number of those dice once, provided you aren't incapacitated. You can use this feature only once per turn.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Otherworldly Wings (Divine Soul)</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, you can use a bonus action to manifest a pair of spectral wings from your back. While the wings are present, you have a flying speed of 30 feet. The wings last until you're incapacitated, you die, or you dismiss them as a bonus action.
	The affinity you chose for your Divine Magic feature determines the appearance of the spectral wings: eagle wings for good or law, bat wings for evil or chaos, and dragonfly wings for neutrality.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Unearthly Recovery (Divine Soul)</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain the ability to overcome grievous injuries. As a bonus action when you have fewer than half of your hit points remaining, you can regain a number of hit points equal to half your hit point maximum.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Unearthly Recovery</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>Divine Soul</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Sorcerous Origin: Shadow Magic -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sorcerous Origin: Shadow Magic</name>
        <text>You are a creature of shadow, for your innate magic comes from the Shadowfell itself. You might trace your lineage to an entity from that place, or perhaps you were exposed to its fell energy and transformed by it.
	The power of shadow magic casts a strange pall over your physical presence. The spark of life that sustains you is muffled, as if it struggles to remain viable against the dark energy that imbues your soul. At your option, you can pick from or roll on the Shadow Sorcerer Quirks table to create a quirk for your character.

Shadow Sorcerer Quirks:
d6 | Quirk
1 | You are always icy cold to the touch.
2 | When you are asleep, you don't appear to breathe (though you must still breathe to survive).
3 | You barely bleed, even when badly injured.
4 | Your heart beats once per minute. This event sometimes surprises you.
5 | You have trouble remembering that living creatures and corpses should be treated differently.
6 | You blinked. Once. Last week.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
        <roll description="Quirk">1d6</roll>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Eyes of the Dark (Shadow Magic)</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, you have darkvision with a range of 120 feet.
	When you reach 3rd level in this class, you learn the darkness spell, which doesn't count against your number of sorcerer spells known. In addition, you can cast it by spending 2 sorcery points or by expending a spell slot. If you cast it with sorcery points, you can see through the darkness created by the spell.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Strength of the Grave (Shadow Magic)</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, your existence in a twilight state between life and death makes you difficult to defeat. When damage reduces you to 0 hit points, you can make a Charisma saving throw (DC 5 + the damage taken). On a success, you instead drop to 1 hit point. You can't use this feature if you are reduced to 0 hit points by radiant damage or by a critical hit.
	After the saving throw succeeds, you can't use this feature again until you finish a long rest.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Hound of Ill Omen (Shadow Magic)</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to call forth a howling creature of darkness to harass your foes. As a bonus action, you can spend 3 sorcery points to magically summon a hound of ill omen to target one creature you can see within 120 feet of you. The hound uses the dire wolf's statistics (see the Monster Manual or appendix C in the Player's Handbook), with the following changes:

	• The hound is size Medium, not Large, and it counts as a monstrosity, not a beast.

	• It appears with a number of temporary hit points equal to half your sorcerer level.

	• It can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. The hound takes 5 force damage if it ends its turn inside an object.

	• At the start of its turn, the hound automatically knows its target's location. If the target was hidden, it is no longer hidden from the hound.

The hound appears in an unoccupied space of your choice within 30 feet of the target. Roll initiative for the hound. On its turn, it can move only toward its target by the most direct route, and it can use its action only to attack its target. The hound can make opportunity attacks, but only against its target. Additionally, while the hound is within 5 feet of the target, the target has disadvantage on saving throws against any spell you cast. The hound disappears if it is reduced to 0 hit points, if its target is reduced to 0 hit points, or after 5 minutes.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Shadow Walk (Shadow Magic)</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain the ability to step from one shadow into another. When you are in dim light or darkness, as a bonus action, you can magically teleport up to 120 feet to an unoccupied space you can see that is also in dim light or darkness.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Umbral Form (Shadow Magic)</name>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, you can spend 6 sorcery points as a bonus action to magically transform yourself into a shadowy form. In this form, you have resistance to all damage except force and radiant damage, and you can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. You take 5 force damage if you end your turn inside an object.
	You remain in this form for 1 minute. It ends early if you are incapacitated, if you die, or if you dismiss it as a bonus action.

Source:	Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Sorcerous Origin: Storm Sorcery -->
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sorcerous Origin: Storm Sorcery</name>
        <text>Your innate magic comes from the power of elemental air. Many with this power can trace their magic back to a near-death experience caused by the Great Rain, but perhaps you were born during a howling gale so powerful that folk still tell stories of it, or your lineage might include the influence of potent air creatures such as djinn. Whatever the case, the magic of the storm permeates your being.
	Storm sorcerers are invaluable members of a ship's crew. Their magic allows them to exert control over wind and weather in their immediate area. Their abilities also prove useful in repelling attacks by sahuagin, pirates, and other waterborne threats.

Source:	Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137,
		Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Tempestuous Magic (Storm Sorcery)</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, you can use a bonus action on your turn to cause whirling gusts of elemental air to briefly surround you, immediately before or after you cast a spell of 1st level or higher. Doing so allows you to fly up to 10 feet without provoking opportunity attacks.

Source:	Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137,
		Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Wind Speaker (Storm Sorcery)</name>
        <text>The arcane magic you command is infused with elemental air. You can speak, read, and write Primordial. Knowing this language allows you to understand and be understood by those who speak its dialects: Aquan, Auran, Ignan, and Terran.

Source:	Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137,
		Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Heart of the Storm (Storm Sorcery)</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain resistance to lightning and thunder damage. In addition, whenever you start casting a spell of 1st level or higher that deals lightning or thunder damage, stormy magic erupts from you. This eruption causes creatures of your choice that you can see within 10 feet of you to take lightning or thunder damage (choose each time this ability activates) equal to half your sorcerer level.

Source:	Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137,
		Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Storm Guide (Storm Sorcery)</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to subtly control the weather around you.
	If it is raining, you can use an action to cause the rain to stop falling in a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on you. You can end this effect as a bonus action.
	If it is windy, you can use a bonus action each round to choose the direction that the wind blows in a 100-foot-radius sphere centered on you. The wind blows in that direction until the end of your next turn. This feature doesn't alter the speed of the wind.

Source:	Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137,
		Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Storm's Fury (Storm Sorcery)</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, when you are hit by a melee attack, you can use your reaction to deal lightning damage to the attacker. The damage equals your sorcerer level. The attacker must also make a Strength saving throw against your sorcerer spell save DC. On a failed save, the attacker is pushed in a straight line up to 20 feet away from you.

Source:	Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137,
		Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Wind Soul (Storm Sorcery)</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain immunity to lightning and thunder damage.
	You also gain a magical flying speed of 60 feet. As an action, you can reduce your flying speed to 30 feet for 1 hour and choose a number of creatures within 30 feet of you equal to 3 + your Charisma modifier. The chosen creatures gain a magical flying speed of 30 feet for 1 hour. Once you reduce your flying speed in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.

Source:	Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137,
		Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Wind Soul</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
        <subclass>Storm Sorcery</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
